Evolution wasn't ready for us to age, and
so we have no intrinsic program to prevent
us from aging.
So I think of it as kind of a systems
failure,
as things start to fall apart, because
they're not built to last.
>> Does that mean that these people that
are pursuing the fountain of youth,
they're looking for immortality are going
to get there?
Because if it's a disease can you treat
it?
Can you stop the aging process?
Doctor Tom Rando is a professor of
Neurology at Stanford where he is
the director of the Glenn Laboratories For
The Biology Of Aging.
He's also director of the rehabilitation,
research and development center
of excellence, at the veterans' affairs
Palo Alto health care system.
And the deputy director of the Stanford
Center on Longevity.
Research in the Rando laboratory focuses
on tissue-specific stem cells in
aging and disease.
He's the recipient of numerous awards,
including the prestigious NIH director's
pioneer award for his groundbreaking
research in stem cell biology.
His work has broad implications for
the fields of regenetive medicine and stem
cell transplantation.
For those reasons and many more, it is an
honor to be here today with Dr.
Tom Rando with an expert interview in
aging.
Thank you for taking the time to be with
us Tom.
>> My pleasure.
>> So I had to shorten your biography
substantially for the interest of time.
But the bottom line is that you're highly
accomplished.
And you're the director of essentially
everything that related to aging
in this area, and you have a very
productive lab.
What inspires you to work so hard in the
field of aging?
>> Our work in aging really emerged from
our work in actually studying diseases.
Because, we're, we study in the lab a lot
of muscle degernative diseases,
muscular dystrophies.
And, there are a lot of changes that occur
in those diseases
that are degenerative and progressive And,
we've always been interested in
this kind of relationship between these
changes and what happens as we age.
Now, they're, they're not the same,
they're different kinds of changes.
And yet, there are some similarities.
And really what we've been interested in
as we look for treatments for diseases.
Are there actually treatments hidden in
there for the changes that occur in aging.
And muscle, that's really muscle loss.
I mean, there are a lot of biochemical
and,
and morphological changes underlie that.
It's really, as we know, we lose muscle
when we get older.
We get weaker as a result.
That leads to disability.
People can't get out of the chair, they
can't get out of the bed.
The further disability kind of spirals
downward.
So, we became interested in muscle aging
from that perspective.
And then that's what brodened our
insterest in aging Other tissues and
people and organisms in a broad sense.
>> And does that mean that aging is
disease?
>> That's a great question.
So, I used to always answer that question
no.
I've changed my mind.
I mean, I've changed my mind in the sense
that I wouldn't say aging is disease.
But I have come to the conclusion which I
will now state firmly that it is now
on the spec, its on the spectrum.
And that, and I think a perfect example of
that, for example is bone loss
going from an, a property of aging to
becoming a disease, osteoporosis.
I think muscle loss may soon reach that
same plateau of
being elevated to becoming a disease,
sarcopenia.
As soon as there's a treatment for it, it
will not be called a disease.
And so I've really come to this thinking
that there are these changes that.
It's almost like a spectrum where you go
from changes that are minor and
relatively insignificant physiologically
like skin wrinkles to changes that
are truly life threatening.
And I think that if you break it down,
it's very hard to put a, a firm line
between aging and disease.
So, I wouldn't say aging is a disease but
I would just call this a, a broad
spectrum.
>> Does that mean that these people that
are pursuing the fountain of youth and
looking for immortality are going to get
there?
Because, if it's a disease, can you treat
it?
Can you stop the aging process?
>> Well, I, I would.
I mean, we study exactly this kind of
question.
And from everything that I know and
everything that I see in,
in across evolutionary time, across
phylogenetic spectra.
Aging is a fairly, but not completely,
universal property of life.
At least, metazoic life, multicellular
life, and
the idea of stopping aging is almost tenth
my stopping biology.
So I'll leave at that to say I think there
are interventions that
can reduce the burden of age related
disease or age related changes.
And that that will give the appearance of
slowing of aging, but
nothing we've seen in any organism stops
the aging process.
So I, I think we're stuck with aging.
>> Hm.
Interesting.
So, if we're stuck with aging why, why is
it that we even age at all?
I mean we, we put this huge effort into
creating life and
then, why can't we just maintain it?
>> Well that's one of the fundamental
evolutionary theory questions,
is why do we age?
And so the, the, the answer to that is, is
kind of an evolutionary question.
Is, is how is it that over time
as organisms evolved did we not evolve to
become immortal.
And the answer is sort of, it's, it's sort
of a nuance of how organisms I think,
are selected during evolutionary time.
The fundamental answer is that over
evolutionary time, aging did not exist.
That is, organisms live long enough to
reproduce, and were barely able to
produce enough adults to produce enough
offspring to propagate the species.
And that's the sort of history of
evolution.
So, aging was an afterthought of
And so there was never any, if you want to
consider it sort of
evolutionary investment in the maintenance
of an organism, post reproductive age.
So, whatever happened after that was sort
of fine, but it didn't matter.
It didn't lead to a survival of the
species.
So, I kind of consider aging to be an
experiment of civilization.
It really is since the civilization, well,
the development of the evolution of large
mammals.
But, really, if we look at humans,
civilization changed humans from being a,
a species that lived long enough to
reproduce.
To a species that lived long enough to
become old.
So, we're stuck with an evolutionary
makeup that allows us to grow,
mature, reproduce, and that's it.
[LAUGH] [CROSSTALK] So I consider it
sort of it's, it's almost an experiment.
>> It's an artifact.
>> It's an artifact of, of the, the fact
that we can live longer by
building houses and staying warm and
getting, you know, growing food.
And then, much more as we become
civilized, treating diseases.
And so, evolution wasn't ready for us to
age.
So, we have no intrinsic program to
prevent us from aging.
So I think of it as kind of a systems
failure.
The system is designed to get to a certain
point allow [UNKNOWN] to be produced,
And that's it.
And then however further we go is fine
with evolution, but didn't matter.
And then things start to fall apart
because they're not built to last.
>> That's really interesting.
We could talk philosophy for a long time.
But let's sort of get back to the concrete
work in your lab which is very compelling.
So tell us what research you're doing in
your lab right now.
Well, where to begin?
>> [LAUGH]
>> So, so, I guess the, the research that
we do that's most relevant to
the questions we're talking about today.
Are we study how cells age and in
particular how stem cells age.
And how that relates to how tissues age.
So, pick a tissue.
Skin.
Skin has lots of stem cells its always
producing new skin and
those are coming from stem cells in the
skin.
And yet over time skin changes with age.
And our question is, is that because the
stem cells themselves are aging.
Or is it because the cells that producing
the stem cells are in
this environment that makes the tissue
older?
So it's kind of a dichotomy.
But that's the kind of question we ask.
What are the driving mechanisms that make
stem cells produce tissues that are,
in a sense, morphologically older than
young tissues.
And we study this at the level of
genetics.
And we call it epigenetics.
And I think the, the interesting results
that have come from the lab.
Probably the most fundamental issue when
it comes to aging is that the behavior
of an old stem cell can be rejuvenated to
behave like a young stem cell.
And that sounds of course magical,
fountain of youth.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Like you're saying.
And there's some truth to that.
But also there's, yoiu know, it's not that
simple.
But the observations that you can take a
tissue, and we do this mostly in mice.
And by treatments either pharmacologicaly
or
genetically, we can make an old mouse
tissue appear younger in many ways.
Biochemically, histologically, and, and
that seems to be true the more we look
across tissues.
Now the, the challenge is, is there a down
side to that?
And we would argue there probably is, we
haven't really observed it.
But we think that if we're imposing these
conditions that
allow an old stem cell to become young
again.
Or to make young tissue,
you're also predisposing that cell
Potentially, to producing cancer.
In a way we think of the suppression of
activity that occurs with
age that leads to a diminished activity is
in a way a protective mechanism.
So, you might be able to, and this is how
we think of this therapeutically,
enhance the stem cell activity in the
tissue to repair it.
So you want to repair a skin wound.
We want to repair a bone fracture or a
muscle injury.
You might want to do that better in an old
person.
That would be great if you could, but if
you could do that in a very spatially and
temporally restrictive way.
You could repair that tissue without
imposing, I think,
this risk of generating a lot of young
stem cells in an old person.
Young stem cells that might proliferate
too much.
And who knows what bad might, might
happen.
These cells probably have acquired a lot
of mutations over a life span.
So they're probably not the cells you want
proliferating a lot in an old person.
>> Wow, that sounds amazing.
Like, it has huge implications for disease
states and older adults.
But, what about athletes?
. . .
So athletes, so
older athletes, it might be very relevant.
So, younger athletes, I'm not so sure, in
the sense that we haven't really seen but,
we haven't really tried, to ask.
Can we make a young tissue repair better
but, that's, of course, that would
be phenomenal for athletes, for people who
are trying to recover from an injury.
But we have seen old tissues repair like
young tissues.
So, we don't know if young tissue repair
is at a maximum.
If it's not, maybe it could be enhanced.
>> Mm-hm.
>> As you suggest.
But what we really looked at is the
spectrum between young tissue repair and
old tissue repair.
And asked can we drive old tissue repair
toward that kind of
younger [UNKNOWN] type.
And that's we've been able to do.
And many people have subsequently kind of
done this in other systems and
it seems to be quite a robust phenomenon.
And we do this, if I can just tell you one
experiment.
>> Oh, please.
>> You know,
that kind of highlights the way we can
modify this.
We use a technique called parabiosis in
which two animals are actually joined
surgically.
So they become essentially conjoined
twins.
And, and then they had a single shared
circulatory system.
So, what's circulating in the blood of one
animal is now circulating in the blood of
the other animal.
And that is done surgically and
it takes a couple of weeks to develop this
true shared circulatory system.
So, what happens if you pair a young
animal with an old animal?
That was kind of our experimental
question.
And we had reasons to think that there
might be factors in the young animal that
are kind of promoting youthfulness.
And factors in the blood of old animals
that are actually promoting aging, or
maintaining aging.
And indeed, when we do this parabiosis,
young to old.
We find that in pretty much every tissue
we've looked at, the tissues and
the cells of the old animal adopt a more
youthful phenotype.
A more youthful biochemical appearance and
morphologic appearance.
Now, there, there's no free lunch.
The ti, the cells and tissues of the young
animal adopt an older phenotype.
Okay so they seem to be kind of moving
toward the mean.
That's good for the old animal, maybe not
so good for the young animal.
And and so that's, that's really what the,
that's really what is the kind of
fundamental observation, from which we've
gone on to ask How does this work?
Why does this work?
What are the factors?
Not a factor probably.
In fact, we've found some and
other people have found many contributing
to different tissues.
So you have many different factors Blood's
[?] a complicated tissue.
>> So I'm an exercise physiologist so I
have to ask.
What does physical activity and
exercise do to these factors that you've
identified?
Uh-huh.
So, we just started to actually ask this
question.
So, we actually have a new NIH Grant
called The Transformative [UNKNOWN].
Because it's kind of a little bit of a
wild idea.
But, but we have the hypothesis that.
So, one thing is known, which you know
well,
is that exercise is kind of good for
everything.
It's good for everything.
Almost every parameter you look at
physiologically exercise improves that.
And one of the things we've been very
interested in is that exercise improves
neurogenesis.
So new neuron formation in the brain.
As well as improves cognitive function.
So this is in collaboration with a Tony
[INAUDIBLE] Stanford.
We have the hypothesis that exercise
actually leads to the production of
factors in muscle that are secreted into
the blood.
That travel around the body and that are,
is good for what ails you.
So, and these are, this is a field,
well the field of these kind of secretory
factors is called myokines.
And that's kind of In in opposition to a
dipicons.
Factors secreted from fat that are very
pro flammatory and not very good for you.
So we think there might be this balance
between midicons and
dipicons generally as we get older.
And midicons might be enchaned by
exercise.
So that's kind of our current working
hypothesis.
We had a lot of mice Running on treadmills
and actually, we have some studies for
people to, for [UNKNOWN] humans to look at
myokinds in the blood.
Ask if they are secreted.
because myokinds don't all have to come
from muscles,
they can also come from other tissues.
But as, actually,
exercise induces the expressions of these
pro-longevity, if you will.
Pro-health factors from muscle, that are
secreted into the blood, and
that can have wide ranging physiologic
effects.
>> And are these the usual suspects, like
the growth factors, IGF 1,
BDNF those types of things?
>> That's what, we're looking at those for
sure and then we're looking for novel
molecules that aren't yet identified.
Those are obviously high on our list as
candidates and and the we're testing them.
And so one of our long term experiences as
we
began to see what changes as we exercise.
What goes on in the blood.
What comes from muscle.
And then ask what if we knock out that
gene,
we block that gene only in muscle, could
we block the effects of exercise?
I mean that would essentially prove the
hypothesis that exercise,
through its' effects on muscle,
physiology, leads to improved physiology
elsewhere, through secreted factors.
>> So, you're an athlete yourself.
You're a marathon runner, and you're doing
work in aging and exercise.
And so how has all this information that
you've gathered impacted your
ideas on training and competition and
Motivation.
>> So, yeah, I think about these things
all the time.
Because a lot of what, when I'm training,
obviously I'm always dealing with
sore muscles and injuries and that sort of
thing.
And it's all about repair, you know, at
that point.
And I would say practically the research
that we do in
the lab hasn't translated in a new
training program.
>> No magic training programs to share?
[CROSSTALK]
>> I don't have anything
unfortunate no stem cells in the freezer
that I checked in when I get home,
which I would love to do.
But but it, but it, but it's just, it,
it, I think it informs my thinking about
my own physiology, and,
and in fact, if anything I would say I
spend more time resting than training.
As a result as a, really thinking that you
know,
that time is important for the training
process and recovery.
I mean, this is what trainers will tell
you to do, but most people ignore it and
they think, I'm going to go out and run
anyway and then I'm sore.
But, I think I listen more to my body.
Thinking about what's happening.
>> That's because you have pictures in
your brain that was actually going
on a little micro [CROSSTALK].
>> But I would that's probably the aspect
of the work.
That if anything kind of changes my
training its the notion of recovery and
the importance of recovery in training.
again, that's not, you know, that's well
known but I think it,
it kind of it resonates when I think about
the work we do.
>> > And does that apply to young people
and older people?
>> > I think so and I think young people
recover faster but absolutely.
I think it applies to younger people and
the, the interesting thing is
when we first published these results, And
it was, we, we found these improvements
of repair in old animals, in these
parabiotic pairs, looking at muscle.
But we looked at other tissues.
We looked at liver, we looked at brain, we
looked at skin, we looked at blood.
But we focused on muscle because that's
what my lab mostly focuses on.
Yeah there was a lot interest in, in this.
And, I have to say there was a lot of
interest from the academic community.
But, the main interest in terms of the
number of phone calls and
e-mails I received after I first published
this.
These findings on how to improve muscle
repair were from men's health magazines.
>> [LAUGH]
>> That was by far and away kind of the
greatest, you know, what have you got?
What are you hiding?
What are you not telling us?
And, you know, they're looking for the,
the factors of the drugs.
And indeed, you know, I think there's a, a
good likelihood that, that these can be,
and they are being developed into
therapeutics.
But that I would, I would just come back
to something you said before.
For me, this therapeutics for repair.
It's not therapeutics for becoming
younger.
You know, the, the, I don't think there's
going to be any easy road to slow or
stop kind of tissue aging.
But I'd really like to think that there
will be therapeutics developed to help
repair injuries in older people for enough
time when they weigh.
Bu, help them recover function more
quickly.
>> Yeah, or other people, I'm sure other
people are working on,
taking the very factors right now, had GNC
contacted you?
And,
>> They have not,
I mean cause most of the, most that
factors that we and
others have found are proteins.
So those are you know, not easy to
administer.
Not easy to get from you know, a bottle
into your system.
And so small molecules are the key.
And, and we and others are looking at
that.
If these proteins that we identify, that,
you know, that increase with age,
maybe you want to suppress.
Because maybe they're promoting aging.
Or they decrease with age, and you want to
increase them.
If instead of modifying those proteins.
If we could use small molecules that could
do the same thing, and
that's a pill you could take.
So we haven't gotten there yet.
So, we haven't, you know,
so no one's contacted me about licensing
the the compounds.
But people have certainly been interested
in licensing the concepts, and
then it's trying to find the small
molecules.
So what else is going on in the field that
you're just keeping an eye on.
So not just in your lab but like the,
a major finding in the last couple years
that you're very excited about.
>> In, in aging?
>> In aging.
>> hm, good question.
You know, there's so many aspects of aging
that are still really unknown.
And, I think I, I would say there's not a,
I guess the area that I'm most interested
in.
Or the area that I think is ripe for
changing the way we
think about aging is this I used the word
previously, epigenetics.
Now, epigenetics is a, kind of of a vague
word, because it kind of.
You can use it mean almost anything other
than the gene sequence.
So it loses meaning in some ways.
Having said that I think and, and this is
kind of the area we work in.
If you look at old tissues and you ask why
they're old, or an old cell,
the one of our holy grails is to be able
to take a cell and say how old is it.
You know, someone give you a cell, we
don't know where it comes from.
Can we tell how old that, or really, how
old the person, or
the mouse, from which that cell came.
How old was that?
And we think that's going to be possible.
>> So not chronologically, but
functionally, essentially.
because everybody, just as you.
>> Well, let's say, let's, let's come
back.
Let's say chronologically.
Is this from a one year old mouse or a two
year old mouse.
And there's no two year-old mouse in the
same strain,
that looks like a, however differently
they age.
And there's no 90 year old that,
that is like a 40 year old, in the absence
of disease, right.
So, so, you're right that there's going to
be a variation one 40 year old to another,
one 90 year old.
But, if you really talk about across the
lifespan, there's no, you know,
pathologists who couldn't tell you a 90
year old liver from a 40 year
old liver in otherwise healthy people.
So if you take a cell, you can see that
under the microscope,
you can clearly tell, you take one cell.
And you ask what is it about that cell
that makes it old?
Is there a, you know, is there a clock in
there somehow or something like that?
Is there some marker that tells you how
old that cell is?
So we are looking at this,
and we're hypothesizing that there will be
an epigenetic signature.
That is when we know what to measure,
which is what we're looking to find out.
We will be able to tell you out how old
that cell is, or
that how old the person from whom that
cell came is.
So what we're really interested in is what
aging means.
To a cell.
And we think that will be at the level for
what we call this epi-genetic signature.
And that's, that has to do with
modifications of DNA.
Proteins that bind to DNA that change with
age.
And there are many other ways to think
epi-genetics.
But we try and reduce it to things that we
can measure and
characterize and look for this kind of
epi-genetic signature of aging.
Is that how the influence, the environment
is influencing the genome?
Is through these genetics and changes?
>> That's exactly what we hypothesized,
and we have evidence that that's true.
So if you look at these epigenetic
patterns,
let's say, the way proteins bind to DNA.
A lot of these proteins that bind to DNA
and
warp DNA in this structure called
chromatin.
And if you look at old cells they have
very different chromatic patterns
than young cells.
And if we rejuvenate the cells by these
parabodic experiments or
other ways, now are we to do this.
As in do they then adopt the young
epigenetic profile?
And that's exactly what we're looking for
and I feel confident that's going to be
True and I will then be entered to see how
much, if its true,
that actually is kind of causal of what's
happening in epigenetics.
So right now its at a correlation but
if we can drive that epigenetic process
directly.
Can we rejuvenate cells by changing those
epigenetic states rather than by,
you know, connecting them to other
animals.
But as for humans [LAUGH] we're not
actually proposing that we will
rejuvenate humans or rejuvenate tissues
from humans that way.
So we're looking for these kind of more
biochemically tractable and
definable parameters that might define.
It really comes down to definig what is
aging?
For a cell, what is aging?
It is the passage of time, but it's a,
it's a fairly predictable, reproducible
series of changes in the cell.
And, can we begin to understand what that
is, and, and
why these apparent rejuvenation processes
are reversing, apparently reversing aging?
>> Yeah, it's amazing,.
As someone who is getting somewhat older
to experiencing these changes that you
read about.
And you research and then you think it'll
never happen to you.
And then [LAUGH] [CROSSTALK]
>> I know.
The, the immortality of youth.
[LAUGH]
>> It's amazing.
>> Quickly disappears.
>> Well, what you're talking about is so
interesting that I could go on and
on but we should probably think about
wrapping up.
So towards the end here.
What advice would you give to students who
are watching who might want to
go into the field of aging research?
>> That's a great question, and
I think, I get that all, because I get
students who come in.
Actually, I get a lot of people, students
and post-docs who come from
other fields because they, they come to my
lab because they want to work on aging.
And I kind of read these papers and it's
all very intriguing.
And they, but they have usually fairly
ill-formed concepts of what they
really want to study.
They want to study aging and of course
that becomes far too broad to study.
So my, my advice would be to, to focus on
a,
a, what I've called a tractable question.
Don't, don't go out to seek, don't seek a
way of stopping the aging process.
Look at what you can do and find a kind of
mechanism and
a system in which you can study this.
Something that really can be studied to
understand kind of a cause and
effect relationship.
Because the, the history of aging research
has been so largely correlative.
You know, you take a young animal home and
see what's different between them.
And, but really the question is what are
the driving mechanisms?
And I think in these rejuvenation
experiments, we have, you know, finally
a kind of experimental intervention that
allows us to do more than correlate.
So, so I think that's the real challenge
in aging research,
is finding Aspects that are that are truly
mechanistic.
And, and they can really tell us why cells
age and, and are there ways that,
when we delay it or slow it, that we can
understand the mechanism.
The other thing I guess I would, I would
advise, and
this maybe a little bit off of what people
would want to study is.
I would say become very firmly entrenched
in evolutionary theory.
Because evolution theory has absolutely
changed the way I
think about aging completely.
And you know there's a, there's a famous
evolutionist theorist
Dobzhansky who said nothing makes sense
except in the light of, in Biology.
Nothing makes sense except in the light of
evolution.
And I think nothing could be more true
than in aging that if you
think about how and why we age and you
don't look at evolutionary history.
You'll get the wrong idea, and I'll just
use one example.
There had been a theory of aging for many,
many decades and
people still think this is true.
That we age so that old people die, on
purpose, you know for
some evolutionary plan to get rid of them,
so there's more food for young people.
And this comes back to what we were
talking about at the beginning,
it's That can't be true.
Because over evolutionary time there were
no old people.
So, so even though it kind of makes some
sense when you have a society and
limited resources, that's a very, very
modern phenomenon.
So I think it's very, very important to
couch the questions in terms of
the evolutionary theory of how and why we
age.
>> That's creative huh [LAUGH]?
And do you have any last take home message
that you want to share on life,
on research, on whatever?
>> Well, so I guess you know,
one of the things that comes up all the
time when we talk about aging is
is really this investment in aging
research.
That the NIH is making, and foundations
are making, and Google is now in the game.
Whats the goal?
And I think that if I have a thought to
share its that we for sure and many people
like most the people I know who study
aging, are not looking to extend lifespan.
I know that's what we all want and in some
sense we all want to extend lifespan, but
of course we all want to extend lifespan.
Healthy and young.
Young.
so, really what the focus of aging
research really is,
is health span extension.
How do we, as we age, maintain our health,
maintain our physical function,
our mental function, and and reach old age
as healthy as possible.
So, I think in the public press and you
know, in popular.
>> In the websites online.
[CROSSTALK]
>> It's all about living, you know,
living to 150 and that's all well and good
in terms of thinking about.
But that's not what the research is about.
It will for sure increase the number of
people who are living to very,
very old age.
You know, centenarians and super
centenarians past 110.
But really, the focus of the research in
most labs is,
is really ultimately directed to healthy
aging.
And, and so I think, you know, we think of
that, in that sort of therapeutic way.
Of what are we doing that can really help,
with the kinds of changes that occur with
age and diseases that occur with age.
>> Well, thank you so much for talking
with us.
And thank you for all the great work that
you're doing.
It's helping us all.
>> My pleasure, I hope that it can help me
too.
Great.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[BLANK_AUDIO].