[MUSIC]
We have the honor today of being with Joe
Coughlin,
who is the director of the age lab.
His research exams have the disruptive
demographics of an aging society, social
trends and technology will shape future
innovations in business and government.
Coughlin teaches policy and
systems innovation in MIT"s engineering
systems division.
Dr. Coughlin has advised numerous
governments, the world economic forum and
the council on foreign relations, and
is a fellow of Swizterland's world
demographics and aging forum.
He was appointed by president George W.
Bush ,to serve on the White House advisory
committee on aging,
and has testified before Congress.
The National Transportation Safety Board
and
addressed the National Governors
Association.
His research and collaboration with
industry has earned him recognition as one
of Fast Company Magazine's a 100 most
creative peoples in business.
A fine line between a bio and eulogy but,
thank you.
[LAUGH]
>> So
you use that term, disruptive demographics
quite frequently.
> Mm-hm.
>> Can you tell us what you mean by that?
>> Well, we all know from the very very
fine work of Clay Christensen and
others that ,disruptive innovation comes
often from technology.
Technology comes and changes the game.
Here at the age lab we believe that,
that's not incorrect but it is incomplete.
That the new generation of older adults,
with greater numbers, greater
expectations, are set to converge with
that technology to demand not just to live
longer, but to live better.
>> So ,that idea that struck a demographic
is what caused you to found this.
because you were here at MIT before and
how long ago did you start the age lab?
>> Started the lab on paper in about 99,
and then physcial space around 2001.
But really was to solve what I see as the,
the longevity paradox.
Life expectancy is about 30 to 40 years
longer than it was 100 years ago.
But we have yet to invent what we are
going to do.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To fill that time in.
It's gotta be better than golf, rocking
chairs, and cruise ships.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And so,
beginning whether it's the car, shopping,
finances, frankly even having fun.
>> Mm-hm.
>> We hope to
invent how you live tomorrow.
I, I get to, talk about it but the
students, the staff that I work with,
and faculty.
They're the great minds, and, and the fact
is that what we're really trying to do,
is to really cast a new definition around
aging.
A sense of optimism and living longer is
an opportunity to invent how we live,
not a problem that governments, families,
and communities should be depressed about.
In fact, one of the real precepts of the
lab ,is that hopefully nothing that we
develop in here is for old people by
themselves.
>> Mm-hm.
>> As we've learned from the auto industry
and almost anything else, if you build an
old man's car, a young man won't buy it,
or a young woman, but neither will an old
man.
So as we reinvent life tomorrow being
safer, easier, more fun,
20 year old's don't complain about that
either.
So really, the aging population is an
opportunity to reinvent how we all live,
albeit longer.
>> So that sort of touches on the breadth
of the age lab, and you collaborate with
industry, and academics, and students and,
>> Right.
>> So how do those all fit together?
That's a very unique model that you're
working under.
>> Well, we're based in the engineering
systems division, so
the, the notion here at MIT is that,
integrated thinking across disciplines,
whether it's exercise physiology,
psychology, indeed engineering.
Medical.
But also if you think about how we age and
how we live.
It's not that any one is wrong and
we're only focusing on one domain, but
it's how we pull those things together.
So age lab really wants to replicate the
consumer facing experience of how we
use technology ,how we navigate every day
and how we spend those 30 to 40 years.
>> And that seems to be really your
target, the consumers.
You don't do basic science research here.
You really try and apply that to the real
world.
>> As is, the school of engineering where
we hope to develop here as in,
in Asia lab in particular is new methods,
new insights, new technologies, and
to ignite what is that vision of how we
will live.
>> Uh-huh.
And can you give an example of some of the
projects that you have going on right now?
>> Sure, we've worked extensively with the
auto industry to rethink the interface of
the car that is getting increasingly
autonomous,
hence Miss Daisy sitting in the middle of
the room.
And the question here is not how old is an
older driver, but
how does a driver at any age adopt, trust
and eventually use new technology?
What's better?
Shall we use voice commands.
Well, voice commands are interesting but
given that 90% of the population over age
50, particularly men, have a hearing
hearing deficit, is a problem.
Should it be touch command?
Well, that leads to a lot of other issues
in terms of arthritis and
physical factors as well as distraction
factors and so one of the innovations that
we've come out with here is that, in fact,
it might have to be a blended answer.
That, in fact, it's not any one interface
But its personalization, and
personalization does a number of things,
one it allows you to make it work for
your capability, but secondly when its
personalized, its not about age,
its about being cool.
>> Uh-hm.
And we're here specifically to look at the
Agnes suit and
so
>> Right.
>> With that, we've earlier that it,
it provides a certain amount of empathy,
>> Sure.
>> That may also create that opportunity.
>> Yup.
>> Everyone realizes that they are in
fact going to get to a stage where they
going to have this impairments Then I'm
sure that people will jump on and try and
re-create the products that we have.
>> Absolutely.
And AGNES is one of the tools that we
developed because we
realized that the current set of tools do
a very bad job at giving you
insights into what the future may hold.
And so AGNES really gives that aha moment
for a design engineer or
a planner, frankly a policy maker, or even
a corporate marketer.
Of what it feels like to have a difficult
time opening a box, reaching for
a shelf, getting in and out of a vehicle.
>> Certainly for middle age or
younger people, talking about health later
on is not the stimulus that they need.
>> Yeah.
>> It's really Has to,
has to focus on something right now.
>> Tangible, yeah.
>> Like, it's going to give you more
energy right now.
>> Yeah.
>> It's going to
reduce that pain right now.
This idea that someday, way in the future,
>> Way in the future, yeah.
>> You're going to have osteoporosis, or
you're going to not be able to get off the
toilet, and
that's, actually it doesn't really
motivate us.
>> Exactly.
Because, you know, by the time you're
about 50, ,if you've made it that far
you're pretty confident that you'll make
it the next ,uh, rest of the marathon so.
>> Haha.
>> So this is AGNES,
age gain now empathy system, and basically
what AGNES is,
is a tool that we developed for students
and for companies we work with to
give that aha moment of what it's like to
do the simple things we take for
granted, getting in and out of the car
Going shopping, opening a bottle or a box.
And so ,we've got a variety of things that
my colleagues here in the lab of design to
replicate that tightening of neck that
happens, unfortunately, in our 30s and
40s if we don't stay as sharp as we once
did.
The ,uh, yellowing of lenses of the eyes
as well as contrast sensitivity.
For instance You know, most people would
like to think he's aging 15,
20 years older than themselves, but with
respect to vision, you
need 20 times more light to see as well to
drive at night as you did at age 40.
So aging starts a lot sooner than we
think.
But the suit goes through.
We've got various straps and harnesses and
the like to replicate the feeling of
stiffening joints around arthritis ,but
this is not destiny.
One of the teachable moments we've learned
about AGNES, was that,
while we were using it as a tool to give
the approximation of a 75,
80 year old woman behaving badly with
diabetes and osteoarthritis.
This is also a teachable moment that with
behaving well,
eating well, exercising, that you can push
off what may be considered the,
the destiny of various cormorbidiities.
And so AGNES became a great design tool.
That only later, frankly, through the eyes
of Dr.
Oz, of all folks, that, that had used
AGNES,
was understanding that this was something
that you could teach Baby Boomers, Gen X,
Gen Y, whatever generation number you're
up, letter we're up to, that how well you
live tomorrow, in your old age, is how
well you treat yourself today.
Miss Daisy is actually more that just a,
you know, a million dollar video game
simulator.
It actually, the color and
the beatles is a symbol of fun and
[UNKNOWN].
[MUSIC]