Thanks for coming back to part two.
Let's move on with our introduction to
aging,.
There's so much good stuff to talk about,
79 years old can look very different.
You can be like Cory, pictured here in the
Agnes suit or worse, in a nursing home,
dependent on others for most of your
activities of daily living.
Or you could look more like Bill Caspari,
who you saw in the intro video,
as a very fast 79 year old sprinter.
Or like Joan Calmay picking up a new sport
at age 85.
Who would you rather be like at age 79?
Stupid question, right?
I bring it up because you have control
over which way you go.
There are always exceptions and situations
beyond your control.
There are genetic differences, injuries,
bad luck, and
some diseases we can't influence.
And there really is no way to stop aging
at this point.
But, the bottom line is that we all have
some control over
the trajectory our lives will take in
regards to health and aging.
Even small lifestyle changes can make a
big difference in that
trajectory over time.
Let's look at what we have these days to
manipulate either longevity or
healthy lifespan.
Unfortunately, there aren't to many
options right now.
Theres caloric restriction.
This isn't just cutting back on your
sweets.
This is caloric restriction in the range
of 25 to 50% decrement below what
would keep you weight stable for life.
This technique has consistently been shown
in species from worms, to mice,
to monkeys to affectively reduce the risk
for disease and prolong maximum life span.
In humans, it's hard to study because we
live so long, but
there's no reason to think it doesn't work
for us as well.
In fact, there are a group of people out
there doing it right now.
You can probably spot them because they're
hungry and cranky and cold.
But they're probably also pretty healthy.
I expect that most people wouldn't think
it's worth it.
We'll talk a bit more about caloric
restriction in Module nine.
Genetic and stem cell manipulation.
We talked about this already in the C
elegans experiment by Cynthia Kenyon.
Change in particular gene made the worm
live twice as long.
This genetic manipulations to be done in
other animal models as well, but
it's far more complex in human, and we are
ways off from making this work for us.
A more likely possibility, in the short
term, is stem cell manipulation.
Stem cells can repair and become new
healthy tissues in our bodies, but
they become less responsive and active as
we age.
Scientists are now working on making old
stem cells behave more
like young stem cells, but the capacity to
repair tissues more readily.
There's a lot of exciting, award winning
research going on in this area right now.
The next option is my personal favorite.
Drink red wine.
There's a compound they have isolated in
red wine and
other dark berries called Resveratrol.
And it seems to have some anti-aging
properties similar to caloric restriction.
One small problem though.
You need a lot of it.
In fact, if you look at the mice studies,
for their size,
they were getting the equivalent of
between 50 and 300 glasses per day.
I'm still giving it a try though.
In fact, I'm about 2 3rds the way through
my 50 glass allotment today.
I'm still feeling pretty good.
You probably didn't even notice, right?
Okay, I'm really not drinking that much.
You can actually buy concentrated res,
Resveratrol supplements in the drug store,
but it's unclear, at this point, whether
they actually work.
So that leaves us with lifestyle behaviors
like eating a healthy diet and
regular physical activity.
As an exercise physiologist, I'm a big fan
of this option.
It's hard to separate out aging from
sedentary lifestyle because there's
a lot of overlap in what happens in
response to the two.
For example, common elements include
sarcopenia, which is muscle wasting or
loss, increased fat mass, and
atherosclerosis, which is plaque formation
in the arteries.
WIth aging per se, there's def, there are
definitely things that happen.
You slow down.
You become less resistant to disease and
your body structures become less
resilient.
Underlying a lot of the changes you see
with aging,
that you have less robust repair
mechanisms.
This gets back to the quote by George
Williams.
Why can't we just maintain what we already
have?
Younger people also experience damage to
their body systems at the macro and
micro level, but they're much better and
faster at repairing that damage.
It's almost as if our bodies give up after
a certain point.
Interestingly, new data coming out
suggests that physical activity may even
enhance the repair mechanisms as we age,
especially in the critical mitochondria,
which are the powerhouses of the cell that
sustain a lot of damage over time.
There is no doubt that functional
capacity, or your ability to
do physical work, goes down with age
because of a combination of aging and
per se and inactivity.
But most of what people thing of as aging,
slowing down, losing strength,
getting sick, can at least be slowed with
good health behaviors.
The figure to my right is a typical
depiction in the literature of what
happens to physical function with aging.
This particular one was modified from a
paper by Nair, et al from 2004.
It suggests that aging leads to muscle
weakness,
decreased endurance capacity and muscle
wasting.
That, in turn, causes a decrease in
physical activity.
The fall in physical activity then
increases diseases and risk factors such
as high blood pressure, abnormal lipo,
lipids, and type two diabetes.
And finally, those problems can lead to
cardiovascular disease.
Genetics and obesity can play a role in
the process as well.
Wow.
That seems pretty depressing.
But I actually look at this figure with a
great deal of optimism.
Because right in the middle of the whole
shebang is physical activity.
By reversing that one arrow, you can
reverse all the others.
Let's take a look.
Here we go.
Flip all those babies the other direction.
With increased phys, physical activity,
you slow the decrement in
muscle weakness and wasting, you increase
endurance capacity and
lower the disease risk factors for type
two diabetes and cardiovascular disease.
Because physical activity modulates so
many different systems in your body,
you have control of a powerful way to
impact your aging.
And it doesn't just stop at your body.
Physical activity can improve brain
function as well, through direct and
indirect mechanisms that we will talk
about in a later module.
We'll look more closely at all of the
individual elements in this figure,
as we move through the upcoming modules.
Hopefully, module two helped lay the
foundation for
the upcoming sections, by discussing why
we age.
In the upcoming modules, we will focus
more on how we age and
what happens to our bodies, brains, and
functional capacity.
Is it all inevitable?
Or can we do something about it?
Let's find out.
See you soon.