This short bonus module is on the common
cold, or
otherwise known as upper respiratory tract
infections.
On average, adults in the US get between
two to five colds per year,
resulting in about 250 million days of
restricted activity.
Colds remain the leading cause of doctor
visits and missed work days.
By the way, this is an actual sneeze
that's been back lit.
So the next time someone sneezes in your
direction duck.
[LAUGH]
Your immune system is very sophisticated
and complex.
What's behind me is just part of what's
going on with your immune
system right now.
You have innate elements that have been
with you to protect you since birth.
They include anatomical barriers not
listed here, like skin and
mucus membranes.
As well as the cell-mediated killers like
macro phages and
natural killer cells, the NK cells.
You also have the Adaptive component that
includes the lymphocytes with
the T cells and the B cells that find
foreign invaders, and
not only neutralize them, but then they
stick around as antibodies in
order to attack the future invaders more
quickly.
That's how the flu shot works.
You get an injection of weakened or dead
viruses,
your body mounts an immune response and
produces antibodies to that virus.
If you get infected with the real thing
later, your body's already set to fight.
Your immune system is amazing, built in
protection and
you didn't even have to pay extra for it.
Wow!
What happens to immune function with
exercise is as complex as
the system itself.
However, there seems to be a general
pattern in which most people agree,
call the Open Window Hypothesis,
illustrated to my right.
With moderate exercise, there's a boost in
activity of
your natural killer cells in the blood, so
the blue line.
The levels then return back to normal
within a matter of
hours following exercise.
However, in the case of intense exercise,
there's an initial boost in immune cell
activity, but then a fall below base line
levels for a period of hours, up to a day.
So if exercise is prolonged or intense,
there's a period following exercise when
an athlete is at greater risk of illness,
the open window as it were.
If you string many workouts together with
chronic training,
moderate exercise can lead to enhanced
immune function.
An illustration of this came from a
classic study by David Neiman in which he
compared upper respiratory track
infections in middle aged women who were
either put on a 15 week brisk walking
program or who remained sedentary.
By the end of the study, walkers showed a
40 to 50% reduction in
days with upper respiratory tract
infections.
In contrast, severe exercise training can
lead to suppressed immune function,
elevated cortisol, pro-inflammatory
responses and
micro damage in the tissues with intense
training is thought to
impair immune function and redirect
Towards tissue repair.
Thus, non exercisers are at an average
risk, moderate exercisers at reduced risk,
and then intense exercisers are at
exaggerated risk.
The concept referred to as the J curve,
illustrated to my right.
So what's an athlete to do?
You don't have the option of training
moderately.
In order to be competitive,
you need to go through phases of intense
training and competition.
There are some things you can do to reduce
the risk of illness.
Again, none of this is rocket science.
First, train smarter,
not necessarily harder, making sure that
you have adequate periods of rest.
Don't increase your training load by more
than 10% per week and monitor signs of
deterioration in performance which may be
an indication of over training.
Add variety to your training to limit
staleness.
Second, immune function is impacted by
cummulative stress.
So try to keep other life stresses to a
minimum.
Avoid excessive travel and unnecessarily
stressful events.
You know, like if your girlfriend or
boyfriend wants to break up with you, tell
them to wait til the end of the season.
[LAUGH] Assure optimal nutrition,
especially adequate carbohydrate while
training and competing.
For example, Neeman and others have shown
that
given a carbohydrate during a marathon
race can reduce cortisol levels.
Thus reducing the suppression of immune
function and reducing subsequent colds.
There are a lot of supplements out there
that claim to boost immune function in
athletes, but most of them are not
supported by scientific evidence.
A 2011 review article by Walsh [UNKNOWN],
sorts through the scientific evidence on
supplements and does not recommend any of
the usual suspects like vitamin C,
vitamin E, ecanacia, glutamine, multi
vitamins etc.
But there are a couple interesting
exceptions.
If you'd like to look at the data on
these, the Walsh review paper is
sited in the resource section, under the
title maintaining immune function.
Actually, maintaining immune health.
[LAUGH] Fourth, contrary to what many
people believe, you won't increase
your risk of getting a cold by exercising
in the cold or hot environments.
Go ahead, walk around in the cold with wet
hair.
[LAUGH] However, certain scientists argue
that increased movement of cold,
dry air in and out of the lungs during
heavy exercise in
the cold can damage the sensitive
respiratory membranes and
make them more susceptible to infection by
colds.
In addition at altitude, there may be a
slight suppression of
cell mediated immunity as your body tries
to cope with the additional stress.
Adequate sleep is important, but not
necessarily in the short term.
Studies of up to three days of sleep
deprivation suggest little impact on
immune function.
However, long term chronic sub-optimal
sleep quantity and
quality, may lead to increased risk of
illness.
But the data is pretty scarce on that
topic.
Finally, getting the flu shot can help and
my personal favorite, avoid sick people.
[LAUGH] I realize that the last one's kind
of ridiculous, but just keep it in mind.
For example, if you've just completed a
long,
intense run outside, you may not want to
do your cool down on
a treadmill in the gym next to the guy
who's hacking up a lung.
Just a thought.
I've presented information so far on
preventing infections, but
what happens if you already have a cold.
Is it safe to exercise?
To answer that, physicians generally apply
the above the neck rule.
Meaning, if your symptoms are all in your
head.
So, stuffy nose, headaches,
scratchy throat, then it's probably okay
to exercise if you feel like it.
Keep the exercise below 65% of your
maximum though, so
you're in the immune boosting, rather than
immune suppression range.
Keep in mind that certain cough and cold
medicines can increase your heart rate.
So be careful with your intensity.
However if an illness feels systemic.
Meaning you have fever, muscle aches,
chest congestion, or
especially a bad sore throat.
Which can indicate strep throat, you
should definitely take time off to rest.
A few days of missed training won't impact
your performance as much as
perpetuating the flu, bronchitis, or
worse, for weeks.
Some common wisdom about colds is true,
get lots of rest,
drink lots of fluid, avoid getting overly
stressed, both physically and emotionally.
Your body will need energy to fight the
cold, so
if you're exhausted from other causes, you
will prolong the illness.
That's it.
That's all I've got for this module.
Stay healthy.