Welcome back.
Get ready to maintain your brain.
In this category, exercise is huge.
And, I'm not just talking about mental
exercise,
like doing the New York Times crossword
puzzle.
I'm also talking about physical exercise.
In fact, when I was working at the
Stanford Center on longevity.
We brought in a panel of brain and
cognition experts to
evaluate whether online brain games worked
to improve cognition.
There were varied opinions on that topic.
But the one thing that they all agreed on
was that physical activity was,
without a doubt, beneficial to brain
health.
So rather than playing an online training
game,
use that 30 minutes to go out for a walk.
Hmm.
Now I'm feeling guilty about asking you to
sit inside watching this video online.
Oh well, I'm over it.
Let's look at how your brain changes with
age and why physical activity can help.
Okay folks, I've got some bad news for
you.
Size does matter.
For the majority of you out there, your
brain is shrinking.
In general, if you're a young adult it's
shrinking about .12% per year.
If you're over 50, it's disappearing at a
rate about three times that per year.
Some regions are relatively stable, but
others like your hippocampus, which
plays a major role in memory formation,
can shrink more than 1% per year after 50.
Bummer.
You can't see your brain shrinking unless
you have an MRI scanner in your garage.
But if you're over 40, you've probably
noticed that you just can't
problem solve or remember as well as you
used to.
My friends and I joke about this all of
the time.
Let me describe a scenario for your, you
and see if it sounds familiar.
You want to go to the store, but you need
to get your grocery list from the kitchen.
You pick up your keys and walk into the
kitchen to get the list.
By the time you make it from the living
room to the kitchen,
you can't remember why you're in, in the
kitchen to begin with.
However, you see the mail on the table, so
you put your keys down and
pick up the mail, you sort through some
mail, but
then remember you're on your way to the
store.
You put the mail down on top of your keys,
you leave the kitchen.
Now you're back in the living room, you
still don't have your list,
you can't find your car keys, and you're
no closer to getting to the store.
If you're over 40, you're probably nodding
and chuckling.
If you're under 40, you probably have no
idea what I'm talking about.
But you will eventually.
Trust me.
Most of the time,
these charming characteristics are a
normal part of aging.
Elements of cognitive function, like
executive control,
which includes tasks like scheduling and
planning .
.
.or your working memory, or
controlled functioning, which keeps you on
task,
without getting distracted by a pile of
mail, all decline slowly with age.
But, the rate of decline and function,
even the structural changes in the brain,
can be impacted by a variety of behavioral
factors.
Most scientists agree that three lifestyle
factors in
particular can slow the rate of cognitive
decline and prevent dementia.
The first of the big three is to be
socially active and engaged.
So interact with your friends, have a
social support network, and
don't isolate yourself away from the
world.
Second is to engage in cognitive leisure
activities like learning to
play an instrument, learning a new
language, building something new for fun.
Some types of employment work can help
too, but
there needs to be a creative and
constantly changing component to it.
Basically, you want your brain to be
learning new things and
the more different those things are, the
better.
The final one on the list is to perform
regular physical activity.
At this time, physical activity has the
most support of
anything as a means to combat age
associated cognitive decline.
There was a nice review paper by Hillman
et al that came out in
Nature Neuroscience Reviews in 2008.
The authors reviewed the scientific
literature looking for rigorous studies
investigating the effects of physical
activity on brain function in adults.
Data from their summary are presented to
my right.
The effect size is how much better the
different task got in response to
the intervention.
The bar suggest there is a small effect on
cognitive function just from being in
the control group of the studies.
Probably resulting from increase practice
on the task over the course of
the studies.
On the other hand, there was a medium to
large effect of
the exercise interventions on cognitive
performance.
The biggest improvement came in the
Executive Function Task category, so
being able to plan and deal with the
unknown.
This review study is supported by many
other, more recent studies,
that show benefits of physical activity on
brain structures and function.
By the way, physical activity and
fitness doesn't just improve cognitive
health in older adults.
It is correlated with academic performance
like reading and math in children as well.
Enhanced metabolic activity in the regions
of the brain responsible for
those academic skills can be seen with
exercise in children.
And data shows that a single bout of 20
minutes of
walking right before a test can improve
children's test scores.
Also, fitter kids, even within identical
twins have bigger
hippocampal and basoganglia regions of the
brain, and higher test scores
even when socioeconomic Body composition
and other factors are controlled.
So its ironic that in order to improve
standardized test scores in kids, physical
education is being cut out of schedules to
make room for more academic time.
In reality, it may be making scores worse,
just some food for thought.
[NOISE]
As an exercise physiologist, I sort of
ignored the brain for a while.
I was focused more on the body and
the brain was this separate thing way up
in your head.
However, I've changed my thinking over the
years because of the obvious and
strong connections between body and brain.
Even Plato, back around 400 B.C. could see
the relationship and
is quoted as saying, in order for man to
succeed in life,
God provided him with two means: education
and physical activity.
Not separately, one for the soul and
the other for the body, but for the two
together.
With these two means man can attain
perfection.
That was my Plato voice.
Clearly, the bidirectional connection
between body and
brain has been generally understood for a
long time.
The brain impacts the body in terms of
health, well-being, and physical
performance, and the body impacts the
brain in terms of its size and function.
However, it's only more recently with the
new brain imaging techniques that we've
been able to investigate the mechanisms of
the connection.
It's not really a surprise, but
it turns out that many of the same things
that improve the health of
our bodies with exercise also improve the
health of our brains.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Physical activity has been shown in
animals and
some human studies to directly affect the
biological properties of the brain.
Exercise causes the release of important
growth factors, such as, IGF1 and
VegF and brain derived nuerotropic factor
BDNF.
Together these factors increase the
formation of new blood vessels so
angiogenesis and new neurons; neurogenesis
the former supplies more nutrients
to the brain and the ladder creates more
circuitry in the brain that facilitates or
makes learning easier.
The BDNF is reduced with age, Parkinson's,
Alzheimer's, depression,
anorexia, but as I just mentioned,
exercise increases it.
Also, exercise reduces low grade,
background inflammation in our bodies
which is
good because inflammation inhibits the
activity of those growth factors.
Growth factors lead to better brain
circuitry and
even preservation of brain mass, the
amount of brain you have, over time.
One of the first studies to support this
idea was a 2003 study by Colcombe et al.
It demonstrated that higher cardiovascular
fitness was associated with
reduced loss of gray and white matter.
In various regions of the brain in older
adults.
There also indirect mechanisms that
connect physical activity in
cognitive functions.
For example increased cardiovascular
fitness improves cardiac output and
vascularization, excuse me to the brain.
Increased energy expenditure can reduce
the risk of obesity,
cardiovascular disease.
type 2 diabetes, high blood pressure and
again, inflammation.
Those together reduce vascular disease and
increase blood flow and
nutrients to the brain, to allow some
serious power thinking.
In addition, there may be indirect effects
because of the improved sleep,
increased sense of well being, self
efficacy, and
decreased stress associated with regular
physical activity.
We've established that physical activity
can maintain your brain, but
what happens if you already have some mild
cognitive impairment?
Can it still help?
Apparently, yes.
The loss of cognitive function can be
slowed even
in people who already have symptoms of
mild cognitive impairments.
And perhaps even more extraordinary,
is the observation that cardiovascular
fitness is associated with
better cognition in brain size even in
early stage Alzheimers patients.
So the protective affect is indeed
powerful.
Another important benefit of physical
activity is a rediction in depression.
A recent review of the literature suggests
that both aerobic and resistance exercise
can improve depressive symptoms as
affectively as either drug psychotherapy.
The higher the intensity of exercise, the
better the outcome.
Further, if exercise is continued for the
long term, it's more effective at
preventing a relapse in symptoms in either
of the other two.
It's amazing.
Information on which activities are the
best for
these benefits is hard to come by.
We do know that aerobic or
endurance training consistently shows
benefits in terms of cognitive function,
whereas resistance training shows less
reliable beneficial effects.
Unfortunately, how much, how long, and
how often you need to exercise is not
fully understood.
More comparison studies are currently
underway, so,
hopefully, we'll have some more answers
for you soon.
And, finally, exercising, in groups, has
the added benefit of social interaction,
one of the big three we talked about.
But, research has shown that exercising,
at home, and
on your own, can also be effective.
Before we move on,
I'd like to remind you of something
important about aging and the brain.
It's easy to get caught up in the negative
aspects of the physiology of aging.
But we can't forget about the good side of
aging too.
We talked about brain shrinkage, memory
impairments,
how your brain becomes less nimble and
adaptable to new situations as you age.
But, at the same time, you gain more
experience and
knowledge on a wide variety of topics.
As a result, older adults frequently make
better decisions.
Show better judgement and have better
social skills.
Further, psychological studies have shown
that older adults, between 60 and
80, are more emotionally balanced.
Demonstrating better understanding of
their feelings.
Developing strategies to regulate their
emotions and
showing a higher degree of emotional
control than their younger counterparts.
And finally, counter to what many people
believe,
research suggests older adults are
actually happier than younger people.
Young people have that pressure of all
that ambiguity about the life, their life.
What will they do, who will their life
partner be, will they succeed?
The human brain doesn't like the unknown.
Studies out of Lora Carsinson's lab out of
Stanford have show as people's time
horizon shorten, meaning they get closer
to death, they focus more on the positive,
they live in the moment, they savor life,
and as a result, are happier.
I don't have time here to go into the
details of these studies, but
they're quite compelling.
There's an interesting 10 minute Ted talk
on the topic by Dr. Carstensen,
who's the director of the Stanford Center
of Longevity,
that is linked in the resources at the end
of this section.
Take a look if you have the time and the
interest.
So anyway, the bottom line is that aging
is not easy in many ways.
But there are good things that come with
it as well.
These positive changes related to
experience and
emotion are not insignificant.
Experience does pay off.
That's all for now.
Before you move onto module 7 on aging
disease and
physical activity go boost your brain
power by running around with a group of
friends while learning a new activity.
See you in a bit thanks.