Many people don't want to age at all and
certainly don't want to die prematurely.
The anti-aging, aging market is estimated
to be $50 billion annually.
People are looking for a quick fix that
doesn't require any behavioral changes,
which are too much work.
In a sense we're all already part of a
huge anti-aging network.
We have medicines that people take
regularly to combat diabetes,
high blood pressure, cardiovascular
disease and high cholesterol.
All of which are conditions that are known
to be associated with aging and
to shorten healthy lifespan.
But consumers, and thus drug companies,
are looking behind standard medicines for
a magic bullet that doesn't just treat the
diseases associated with aging, but
targets the aging process itself.
Anti-aging clinics and therapies abound.
The clinics range from well-meaning
physicians promoting what they believe,
through research or personal experience,
will help their patients, to opportunistic
snake oil salesmen, who only wish to
profit from people's fears and vanities.
Many of the popular treatments at clinics
involve hormone therapy such as
human growth hormone, testosterone, and a
sex steroid hormone precursor DHEA.
These hormones are anabolic or
growth-promoting and normally decline with
age, making it hard for us to maintain our
strength function and vitality.
Although each of these hormones I just
listed have been associated research
studies with positive benefits such as
increased strength, libido, bone density
and more, there are also many studies that
show minimal benefit, negative side
effects and a substantially increased risk
for diseases, including cancer.
If you think about it,
if you give a growth promoting agent to
cells that may have
accumulated damage over your lifetime, you
do risk stimulating tumor growth.
The anti-aging properties of these
hormones remain debatable.
In fact, debatable, unconfirmed, needs
further study, are phrases frequently
associated with drugs, hormones,
interventions in the anti-aging field.
What follows in this module is information
on what we do know so far.
I've spent eight previous modules talking
about
the benefits of physical activity on
healthy aging.
I think you get the idea.
So on this slide I just want to give a
couple of
examples that quantify the information for
you.
A 2008 study by Khaw et al demonstrated
that combined positive behaviors,
regular physical activity, lots of fruits
and
vegetables, moderate to low alcohol
consumption and
not smoking, made people functionally
equivalent to 14 years younger.
Think about that a moment, 14 years.
So if you're currently 74, it would be
more like you're 60.
If you're currently 60, you could feel
like you're 46.
Those are big difference and could mean a
lot more play time with your grandkids.
In another example,
a 2011 report by Wenitall on over 400,000
Taiwanese adults suggested that as little
15 minutes a day of activity could
increase life expectancy by three years.
Do you have a spare 15 minutes today to
lengthen your life?
On this slide, I say proven and doable.
I didn't say proven and easy.
Because long-term behavior change is not
easy for most of us but it is possible.
With physical activity, ideally you should
meet the recommended minimum guidelines of
30 minutes per day, five days a week, of
moderate intensity activity.
I've posted the full American College of
Sports Medicine guidelines in
the Resource section.
But if you're not active at all right now
and
that seems overly ambitious, just start
doing something.
Any small amount, even that 15
minutes-a-day walk, can help.
Oh, and limit your prolonged sitting
whenever possible.
I have good nutrition on the slide as
well.
In the context of healthy aging, good
nutrition is simple.
Lots of fruits and vegetables, whole
grains and
healthy fats, real non-processed foods,
lean protein sources and
minimal saturated fats and simple sugars.
Pretty standard stuff that you hear about
over and over again.
Not complicated but not necessarily easy
either.
Moderate alcohol consumption for
this study was considered between one and
14 drinks per day.
I mean, no [LAUGH] I mean during, per
week, not per day.
And no smoking is, well, no smoking.
In addition to physical activity improving
healthy lifespan,
there's also some indication it may impact
the aging process itself.
Telomeres are the little protective caps
on the ends of our
chromosomes within our cells.
They're involved with the cell replication
process and get shorter over time.
The length of telomeres is thought to be
an indication of cell age and
once they get too short the cell dies.
Although the relationship between telomere
length and
aging may be more nuanced than originally
thought, it is generally agreed that
longer telomeres are better in terms of
health and aging.
Observations have been made that people
who exercise regularly have
longer telomeres than those who don't,
even within identical twins, so
the same genetic make up.
Further, a recent 2013 pilot study
published in Lancet demonstrated that
five years of healthy behaviors that
included regular walking exercise,
a plant-based diet, relaxation techniques
and social support groups
actually lengthened telomeres in a group
of men with early stage prostate cancer.
In contrast, the telomeres in a control
group continued to shorten over that time.
Larger studies will need to be completed,
but
information on this topic looks promising.
Another factor involved with aging is
accumulative damage in the mitochondria.
Throughout much of our lives we have
mechanisms that repair this damage, but
the repair mechanisms start to weaken over
time.
A study comparing muscle of sedentary and
resistance trained old and
young men showed that with resistance
training both the appearance of
the mitochondria and the transcription
signatures, sort of the gene activity,
in older men looked more like those of
younger men.
This suggests that resistance training not
only increases strength but
may have a rejuvenating affect on muscle
structure as well.
A more recent study investigated the
effects of endurance exercise on mice that
were genetically designed to lack the
mitochondrial repair mechanisms.
These knockout mice age twice as fast as
the normal mice.
However, half of them were put on a
regular running routine which
essentially eliminated the premature
aging.
It's amazing.
Here's a picture of two of the mice from
that knockout study.
The mouse on your right didn't exercise.
The mouse on the left did.
They're both the same chronological age.
The group of mice that didn't exercise had
all sorts of problems,
including increased disease risk,
oxidative stress damage,
body composition change, enlarged heart,
even gray and thinning hair.
In contrast, the running mice appeared
much more normal for their age.
Keep in mind that these mice are not a
perfect model for
aging, because it's so extreme.
Still, it does suggest that physical
activity may improve that key element of
cellular repair.
So if the previous lifestyle factors were
doable but difficult,
this next one is actually really
difficult, [LAUGH] caloric restriction.
Caloric restriction, as I mentioned
earlier,
refers to a 30 to 60% reduction from
normal weight-stable caloric intake.
But without malnutrition, so meaning you
get all your micro nutrients and vitamins.
Caloric restriction has been shown to
reduce age associated diseases,
median lifespan and
maximal lifespan in many species from
worms all the way up to monkeys.
However, a recent 2012 long-term primate
studies showed that
caloric restriction didn't extend lifespan
in that group of monkeys.
So now people are confused as to whether
it will actually work in humans.
Even so, a lot of work has been done to
figure out why this works in so
many different species.
One possible explanation is that
under-eating causes metabolic rate to
slow which in turn causes reduction in the
mechanism of living and
a reduction in oxidative stress, which can
cause cellular damage.
Another theory suggests that a little low
grade stress brought on by
caloric restriction actually strengthens
an organism's defenses,
a phenomenon referred to as hormesis.
There's also an important new finding that
the reduction in insulin that
comes from caloric restriction leads to
increased activity in the FoxO pathway,
that then improves repair mechanisms
within the cell.
Incidentally, the insulin FoxO pathway is
also involved in that original gene
experiment by Cynthia Kenyon that
doubled the lifespan of worms that I
mentioned way back in Module Two.
[SOUND] Seems like a long time ago.
And finally, there are a number of
signalling molecules that seem to
be altered either up or down in the cell
in response to caloric restriction,
like the sirtuins, AMPK, and TOR.
Those signaling molecules are important
because they have led to a better
understanding of why substances like
resveratrol and rapamycin can mimic some
of the effects of caloric restriction, in
terms of longevity and disease prevention.
Since it is so hard to maintain caloric
restriction throughout one's lifetime,
these mimetics may end up being our best
possibilities to improve health and
longevity, although we don't have any
definitive answers yet.
Incidentally, resveratrol first gained
attention as
the first possible explanation to the
French paradox.
A little shout-out to all of you watching
from France.
The French paradox describes the
unexpected finding of the French
population's good health and vitality,
despite drinking lots of wine and eating
foods that aren't considered optimally
healthy such as lots of bread and cheese.
It was thought that perhaps the
resveratrol found in grape skins, and
thus wine, was counteracting the negative
effects of an unhealthy diet.
However, as I mentioned earlier in Module
Two, it would take a lot of wine for
it to have such a beneficial effect.
So maybe it's all of that walking, slow
food, as opposed to our fast food here,
and good genes that actually explains the
good health in France.
The last thing I'd like to talk about is
the possibility of
increasing our repair mechanisms
especially in muscle.
As I've said before, part of the loss of
function and increased recovery time that
we experience with age is due to poor
repair mechanisms in our cells.
For example, when we damage muscle tissue
during exercise, stem or
satellite cells will jump into action to
repair the damage and or
replace destroyed cells with new ones.
This is true whether the injury is big,
like a muscle tear, or
small, like micro damage that results in
delayed onset muscles soreness, or
DOMS, that we feel 24 to 48 hours after
vigorous or unusual activity.
Older tissue has stem cells like younger
tissue, but
they're not as responsive as the stem
cells in younger tissue.
Are they worn out?
Are they damaged?
What's going on?
How can we get them to perk back up?
Well, it turns out that the stem cells are
actually in pretty good shape.
It's the surrounding environment that's a
bit problematic.
Tom Rando, who we interview at the end of
this section by the way, and
others in the field have found that if you
put old stem cells in
young tissue environments, they start to
behave like young stem cells.
Dr. Rando first discovered this by
connecting the circulations of
two mice together that had damaged
muscles.
One was young and one was old.
What they found was that the older mouse
recovered faster than other mice it's
age and ended up with less scar tissue in
it's repaired muscle.
The experiment showed that there was
something circulating in
the blood of younger animals that could
make older stem cells behave younger.
His lab and others have since identified
several substances involved with aging and
stem cell regulation.
This is potentially huge.
It means that maybe down the road we can
use those substances to regenerate old or
damaged tissue in a way that resembles
young, healthy tissue.
Master's athletes, muscle wasting with
aging,
disease states like muscle dystrophy, even
young athletes facing a major
injury could all derive huge benefits from
this type of research, very exciting.
Watch Tom Rando's interview at the end of
this section for
more details on his exciting aging
research.
Wow, you did it.
[LAUGH]
If your watching this, you made it through
the monster aging section.
There is the one bonus module on exercise
and
the common cold at the end, but that's an
optional bit of information.
There's no quiz questions on it, but
I think you'll find it as relevent and
interesting.
So check it out.
But of course, I think all of this
physiology is relevant and interesting, so
I'm a bit biased.
Anyway, thank you for sticking with it.
I really hope you learn things that will
help you as you move forward in your life,
no matter how old or how active you are
right now.
Next week, you get the physiology of
stress.
We have a big surprise for you in that
one, so stayed tuned.
Thank you.