Hello everyone.
Here in module seven we'll touch on a huge
topic.
Aging and chronic disease.
I say touch on the topic because there's
no way I can do it justice in
one short module.
So again, because of my exercise
physiology background I will focus on
the benefits of physical activity, on the
diseases associated with aging.
But even that will be just a taste of the
topic.
There's a lot of other information out
there and
I'll provide a few review references in
the resources at the end of this section,
if you'd like to read more.
If you think aging is a slow progression
of disease,
physical activity can definitely help.
It is the ultimate healthy aging pill.
Many doctors and researchers have
commented that if it were in
pill form it would be the biggest selling
drug of all time.
It has beneficial effects on most of the
physiologic systems within the body.
One important target of physical activity
is excess body fat and obesity.
As you can see by the Center for Disease
Control graph to my right,
obesity rates have increased over the past
30 years.
Estimates from 2010 were that 33% of U.S.
adults were overweight, 36% were obese,
and 6% were extremely obese, for a total
of three quarters of the U.S. population.
Although other estimates are closer to two
thirds, its still quite stunning.
So what?
Why should we care about obesity rates?
Excess body fat is associated with 30
serious medical conditions and
chronic diseases associated with aging.
The financial and qualitative costs on
both an individual and
societal level are huge.
I could could go on and
on about this, but I suspect you're
already aware of the issues on this topic.
Excess body weight is a problem on many
levels.
Why are we facing this crisis?
Clearly our body weight is a balance
between the calories that go in,
versus the calories that we expend.
Both sides of the equation have been
effected over the last 30 years.
In the U.S. and
many countries we're eating more, and what
we're eating is getting worse.
So more simple processed carbohydrates,
sugars, and high fructose corn syrup.
But that's only part of the problem.
Our energy expenditure has gone down as
well.
Not so much our exercise, like going out
for a jog, but our daily activity level.
We have so many devices that make our
lives more convenient that we
have essentially engineered activity out
of out lives.
Again, I'm speaking from a U.S.
perspective, but now we drive everywhere,
spend most of our leisure and
work time in front of screens, and send
emails instead of visiting people.
In the academic world we have printers at
our desks and
access all the information we need
electronically.
Way back when I was in grad school, if I
wanted a paper I'd have to go to
the library, search through these big
stacks of books to
get these huge bound books of journal,
carry the big books back to the copy room,
pay to copy the pages and then go back in
the stacks to get more books.
Now, I just look online and never leave my
desk.
These changes may not seem like a big
deal, but add it all together,
they can make a significant difference in
energy expenditure.
A study by Lanningham and Foster showed
that just changing a few things in
a person's daily routine, such as washing
the dishes by hand, taking the stairs
whenever available, and walking instead of
driving to work, an average of 0.8 miles,
resulted in an increased daily energy
expenditure of 111 calories.
That amount, or
more every day, thrown in with keeping an
eye on your diet, can really add up.
Physical activity, whether it be
recreational exercise or
activity within daily life, can help.
First, it can help with weight loss.
It's hard to lose weight from exercise
alone, so
you have to be paying attention to intake
as well, but
physical activity can help tip the balance
towards fat use rather than storage.
Second, exercise can selectively cause the
loss of visceral fat.
For example, a weight loss of 5% can
result in visceral fat loss of 25%.
Visceral fat is the fat that is stored
around the organs in your stomach region,
and is considered especially bad in the
terms of disease risk.
Fat is not just a passive storage site,
it is metabolically active tissue that
releases proteins and hormones called
adipokines that impact your health,
especially your sensitivity to insulin.
So a reduction in visceral fat can reduce
your risk for
type two diabetes and a whole host of
other illnesses,
like cardiovascular disease, high blood
pressure, etc.
Third, if you stay active you protect your
lean mass as you age.
That will maintain better physical
function for
you, as we've discussed, but will also
keep your metabolic rate higher.
Your body is well adapted to maintain its
weight, which is good for survival in
times of starvation, but not so good if
you're trying to drop a little body fat.
As you cut calories, if you're not
remaining active,
your body will slow its metabolic rate to
protect your body mass.
Exercise both raises metabolic rate
directly and
gives you more metabolically active muscle
tissue so you're burning calories 24/7.
Finally, physical activity, integrated
into daily life, can reduce sitting time.
Sitting has emerged as an independent risk
factor for disease.
Meaning, even if you get your recommended
30 minutes a day, five days a week of
activity, but you sit the rest of the
time, you're putting yourself at risk.
So anything you can do to reduce the time
in a car, sitting at work, or
in front of a TV could help.
It's hypothesized that even if you don't
reduce your total sitting time but you
interrupt your sitting with short standing
or walking periods, it could help.
I hear crickets every 50 minutes or so at
work because my coworkers down stairs have
set their phones to chirp as a reminder to
get up regularly and move around.
Whenever I walk down stairs in those
periods they're stretching and marching.
It's very inspiring, and it's a great
idea.
Physical activity isn't just beneficial as
a weight management program,
it impacts a whole bunch of diseases.
To my right are some examples.
Arthritis, cancer, osteoporosis, type two
diabetes, and many more.
The diseases on the list have been well
researched and
we know now, not only the physic, that
physical activity does work, but
we know the mechanism of how it works as
well.
Sometimes it is mediated through body fat
loss, but
there are many other mechanisms
independent of body weight.
And, a bonus, unlike many drugs that tre,
treat just the symptoms of disease,
physical activity can treat the underlying
causes.
For example, as I mention on the last
slide, exercise can reduce visceral fat.
It releases adipokines that can cause
insulin resistance that is at the root of
type two diabetes.
The second bonus is that you can get some
benefit from exercise in
terms of reducing di, disease risk, even
if you start later in life.
To my right is a typical graph
illustrating average function over
the lifespan.
You could put in muscle strength,
cognitive function, bone density, VO2 max,
whatever, on the Y-axis.
For the adult lifespan, you could label
the graph with health as well.
The general pattern is that things go up
for a while, and
then they go down for a while.
[LAUGH] If you exercise for your whole
life, then your peaks will be higher,
the fall off both in adulthood and old age
will be less steep.
Thus, you will hopefully avoid that
threshold of disability in
your later years.
You're essentially changing the trajectory
of your own
aging through physical activity.
You can even get a bump up if you start
exercising in mid or later life.
For example, the diba, the diabetes
prevention program, which was a large,
multi-center trial, showed that people
over 60 who started a program of diet and
exercise, could reduce their risk of type
two diabetes by more than 70%.
So get out there and start doing it.
I've talked about lifestyle activity and
small changes that can add up throughout
the day, and you may be wondering, does
that really make a difference?
Well the good news is that some of the
biggest gains can be obtained at
the low end of the spectrum.
Meaning, that there's a lot of room for
improvement if you haven't been doing any
exercises at all.
For example, on the fitness scale, panel A
above, unfit people may be able to
improve their aerobic capacity by 30% if
they start a new,
well planned exercise program.
In contrast, elite athletes may train and
train and only improve aerobic capacity by
2%.
Because they've reached the high end of
their genetic potential and
are on the flat part of the upper curve.
That's often when they consider
performance enhancing drugs,
to sort of bump themselves up off that
flat curve.
But that's a whole other discussion.
Anyway, in curve B, getting the least fit
people a little bit
more active can cause the greatest disease
risk and all cause mortality.
It doesn't mean that over most of the
spectrum, more isn't better, but
there is a law of diminishing returns.
And some data even suggests at the really,
really high,
ultra endurance level curve B may even tip
up a little in terms of cardiac health
at the end, meaning there may be some long
term problems.
But don't panic if that applies to you,
it's still being investigated.
Although I didn't have time to talk about
data that support the benefits of
physical activity on disease risk I assure
you, it does work.
Just remember physical activity is truly
the healthy aging pill.
If your doctor offered you a drug that
could reduce your risk of
cardiovascular disease by 50%, reduce bad
cholesterol by 67% and
had the side effects of reducing risk for
type two diabetes in cancer,
lowering blood pressure, enhancing weight
loss, improving mood and
cognitive function, lowering rates of
depression, improving strength,
increasing functional capacity, and
perhaps even increasing longevity.
Would you take it?
Of course you would.
You'd probably even pay a lot for it.
So in summary, physical activity won't
solve the obesity epidemic but
it can help directly by assisting with
weight loss, or
indirectly by reducing symptoms and risks
associated with obesity.
Second, physical activity can reduce the
risk of
many age-associated chronic diseases by
targeting the underlying causes of risk.
Third, physical activity can be started at
any time and
produce some amount of benefit.
And four, in people who are very unfit to
start with even small amounts can
help with health and fitness.
By the way, I was going to discuss how
exercise interacts with immune function in
terms of the common cold in this module.
But it was getting too long.
For those of you who want to learn whether
exercises make you sick or
healthier, and whether you should exercise
if you already have a cold,
check the short bonus topic video at the
end of this section.
Thanks for your attention.
Next up in module eight, unique
considerations for
the masters athletes, [SOUND] fun.