Welcome back.
Did you move?
I hope so, I did.
I went out and got a bit of fresh air, and
now my head is back in the game, and
I'm ready to push forward.
Speaking of pushing forward, when you're
muscles move you forward,
they need to pull on something.
That would be your bones and joints.
Nice transition, eh?
The density of your bones is a major
contributor to their strength, and
it's pretty easy to measure bone density
non-invasively these days.
Thus, it is frequently used as an
indicator for your risk of fracture.
To my right is a normal pattern of bone
gained and lost throughout life.
Peak bone mass is usually reached in the
late 20's.
It is higher for men than women because of
larger body sizes mean more muscle and
weight pulling on the bones and
higher testosterone which enhances bone
size and density.
In the graph you can see that both men and
women lose bone throughout adulthood.
But women experience an accelerated loss
around menopause,
when the protective effect of estrogen is
lost.
The accelerated period of loss can last
ten years for some women.
This pattern puts women more at risk of
osteoporosis in their later years.
The word osteoporosis literally means
porous bones.
It occurs when bone loses an excessive
amount of their protein, mineral content,
particularly calcium resulting in a
decrease in bone strength.
As a result bones become fragile and break
easily with a fall or
sometimes as little as a sneeze or
vigorous handshake.
Osteoporosis is five times more prevalent
in women than in men, and Asian and
Caucasian women of small stature are most
at risk.
During menopause, bone loss is more
associated with
the trabecular bone pictured here, than
the harder cortical bone.
Trabecular bone fills the vertebral bodies
of the spine, your hips and
wrists, which are all major osteoperotic
fracture sites, and
you can see from its appearance why it's
called spongy bone.
The panel on the left is normal trabecular
bone, and
the panel on the right is osteoporotic
bone.
A lot of surface area of trabecular bone
to mine for minerals, and
you can see what happens when that mining
gets out of balance.
The trabecula on the right are thinner,
and in some cases, gone altogether.
If you were going to build something
strong you
would definitely pick the substance on the
left.
The loss of those supporting structures
over time causes compression fractures in
the spine that you can see in the next
picture.
See how all those vertebr- vertebrae in
the center of the picture are crushed and
jagged and the whole spine is bent over?
That compression is what leads to the
hunched look that some older adults have
when they get osteoporosis, like the woman
pictured here.
What causes the loss of bone throughout
our lives?
Just like everything else in our bodies
its a balance between synthesis and
breakdown we have a series of bone
remodeling units that
are made up of osteoclasts and
osteoblasts.
In response to nutrient needs, or
to fix a micro-fracture, the osteoclasts
will become active and
resorb the bone, thus releasing minerals
that be used by your body in other places.
Then the osteoblasts come in to build a
new bone,
to fill in the little hole that was made.
Unfortunately, that process is never 100%
efficient, so
you lose a little bit of bone at each of
the sites.
Over time, the losses add up.
Estrogen suppresses osteoclast activity.
So during menopause, when estrogen falls,
bone resorption rates increase,
throwing the system out of balance and
accelerating bone loss.
As I mentioned, your bone remodeling units
respond to micro-damage,
nutrient needs and the changes in loading
pattern.
In the table to my right are a series of
intrinsic and
extrinsic factors that also can impact the
balance of the modeling units.
The intrinsic ones you can't do much
about.
But the extrinsic, extrinsic ones you can
control.
Notice our friend, physical activity is
again on the list?
As the muscles pull on the bone,
the bone cells called osteocytes send
signals to the remodeling units.
In this way, bone will adapt to
accommodate the stress that is
placed upon it by up regulating osteoblast
activity.
Human studies show that regular exercise
training programs can reduce bone loss by
one percent per year in the spine and hip
in pre and post menopausal women.
Two important ways to optimize your bone
density is to maximize peak bone mass and
minimize age and menopausal related loss.
Regular weight bearing exercise and good
nutrition including calcium and
Vitamin D through childhood are critical
to optimizing your peak bone mass.
Also, aminerial which is a delay or
interruption of normalmenices can sup
press the development of peak bone mass by
increasing absorption.
Many young, elite athletes that are
dependent on high training loads and or
caloric restriction for
success are at risk for disrupting normal
estrogen cycles.
With reduced estrogen levels, bone can be
negatively impacted at
that critical growth phase, which many not
be repairable later on.
If you or your children are amenorrheic,
you should seek medical assistance to
address this situation.
There are a variety of recommendation to
my right,
on the slide, to minimize age associated
loss.
There are also more detailed
recommendations and
explanations on the Mayo Clinic and
National Institute of Aging website.
Especially if you are female and have a
history of osteoporosis in the family,
it is worth taking a look at these
recommendations.
Moving on to joints.
With age, joints become stiffer and less
flexible.
The fluid that keeps everything springy
and lubricated starts to decrease.
Their joints start to rub together in a
road.
Degenerative changes like the loss of
joint cartilage begin to
occur especially in the hip and knees.
Overall, the result is stiffer and more
painful movements of the joints.
Why do we become less flexible?
As our bodies slowly dehydrate, the
tissues become less elastic.
Also, increases in calcium deposits,
adhesions and
cross-links cause structural changes to
the cartilage.
Finally, some of our normally stretchy
muscle fibers begin to
be replaced with scar tissues like
collagen fibers.
We also may stretch less, either
intentionally, or
by changing our normal activities that
require stretching.
You may remember in the story video, Bill
told his friend every night that he
twisted around to look over his shoulder
to maintain his flexibility.
And she said, no, I don't do that.
Well, stretching as you get older can be
very useful thing to maintain your
range of motion for normal activities like
reaching up to a high shelf or driving.
And although stretching doesn't
necessarily reduce injuries as
many people think, it does stimulate the
production of
lubricants between connective tissue
fibers.
It also increases the range of motion by
decreasing the formation of
adhesions within the connective tissue.
If you are over 50 you are likely starting
to experience some type of minor or
major joint pain, aches, stiffness,
clicking in your joints.
It's true that some of that is inevitable
part of aging.
But it also could be the start of
arthritis.
There are many forms of arthritis but most
common kind in the over 50 crowd is
osteoarthritis, a degenerative disease
known as the wear and tear disease.
As we get older the rubbery cartilage that
serves as a shock absorber in our joint
becomes stiff, losses its elasticity, and
becomes more susceptible to damage.
As the cartilage wears away, we can get
bone on bone rubbing.
Bone spurs can form in the joint space and
tendons and
ligaments stretch all causing pain.
It occur, it can occur in almost any joint
in the body.
But most commonly in the fingers, hips,
knees and spine.
There are a number of things that you can
do to limit the severity and
impact of osteoarthritis.
Some are listed in this slide, and I'm
just going to highlight a few.
Maintain a healthy weight is important
because it decreases the loading on
the joint, but it also because it
decreases systemic inflammation and
has been shown to increase the progression
of osteoarthritis.
Also, despite the discomfort that exercise
can cause when you have osteoarthritis,
it is important to keep doing it.
It will maintain muscle strength stabilize
the joint and
again reduce systemic inflammation.
Assistive devices can help with particular
joint problems for
example jar openers can be a life saver if
you have impaired hand function.
Also there are new commercially available
shoes that
unload certain portions of the knee while
walking to minimize the pain and
decrease wear on susceptible parts of the
joint.
Oh, one more thing on osteoarthritis.
Despite what many people believe, running
does not cause osteoarthritis.
Several studies of long-term runners
support this.
However, if problems already exist that
have started this cycle of degeneration,
then repetitive loading exercises can make
it worse.
These problems include previous injuries
such as ACL tears, biomechanical issues,
loose joints, uneven loading, etc.
Once the degeneration has started,
alternative and
varied forms of physical activity are
recommended.
Congratulations!
We did it.
We went through the major body system
changes as they relate to
exercise capacity.
The cardiovascular system, muscles, bones
and joints.
Now we get to see how good physical
activity can be for your brain.
Stay tuned for module six.