Today we are interviewing Bill Kaspari,
who is our expert in aging.
Or I should say our expert in healthy
aging.
Bill is 79 years old, has a running form
and speed that
would put people decades younger to shame,
and I include myself in that category.
And he's an international sprint
competitor.
He's been active for most of his life, but
didn't start sprinting until age 72.
Recently, he's come in first in the 100
meter and
second in the 200 meter sprint at the bay
area senior games, and
he came in third in the 400 meter at the
world championships in Sydney in 2009.
Bill, thank you for
agreeing to join us today, and share your
wisdom with our students.
>> You're welcome.
>> It's a pleasure to be here today with
you.
>> Thank you.
>> So
I'm going to start perhaps with a most
obvious question, and that is that
sprinting seems like a pretty aggressive
sport for someone who's almost 80.
What got you into sprinting, and what
drives you to continue?
>> I ask myself that same question in
terms of
sprinting because I didn't have any
background.
I didn't sprint when I was younger,
I didn't even compete in any kind of team
sports.
What I did do, my dad made me work all the
time, which kept me fit.
And then When I was 14, I started smoking.
One of the, you know, one of the guys.
And I told myself, I'll never get hooked
on this, and about 20 years later,
I was still smoking a cigarette.
And I remember the day well because I was
sitting in front of my TV,
watching the 1968 Olympics.
And I had a cigarette in one hand and a
beer in the other and
I'm watching all these outstanding
athletes and I just, I got mad at myself.
And so I put the cigarette out and I
crumpled up the pack and
threw' em away and I told myself, okay,
you're going to go down to the track.
I lived by the San Carlos High School
track at the time.
And you're going to go down there every
day for two weeks.
You're going to make yourself run four
laps.
And at the end of that two weeks you can
quit.
And I did that and I, I never stopped.
And so for the next 37 years or so I did a
lot of trail running and
a lot of road running, but I always had
this love of the sprints.
I don't know, I don't quite understand it.
So one day I came down to Stanford track
here,
and I was doing what I thought was kind of
a sprint workout, and
this young lady came flying by me, like,
wow, she was really fast; and
then she stopped me and she said are you
going to be in the senior games?
I said, me, a senior?
You know?
>> [LAUGH]
>> And.
And I said, no, I don't know anything
about it and
she said, well they're having the senior
games in a few weeks and I said, oh,
I'm not, I'm not, you know, anywheres near
that kind of shape.
She said, no, I was watching you, you, you
look like you're in pretty good shape.
So I came down and I watched those senior
games.
I got to know a few of the guys, just
talking to people and
it was one of the most relaxed, you know,
competitive ar, atmospheres I'd ever seen.
And so I came down a couple of days later
to the track again and
there was Joy with all these little kids.
And what she calls her jack rabbits track
team.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, I went over and I said, do you ever
coach old guys?
And she said, well, okay.
And so she started coaching me and I told
her what I want to do.
That I love sprinting and, that's, you
know, the rest is sort of history.
>> huh.
>> By the end of that year.
So, that was I was 71 at the time, and
right after I turned 72 I went to the
Huntsman's Senior Games.
Surprised myself, I was 3rd in the 100 and
4th in the 200 and that was a pretty
competitive meet.
And by the end of that year, I was in
Italy, leading off the 4 by 100, U.S.A.
4 by 100 relay team, and it was just like,
that was a dream come true,
and it really was.
>> So some people will hear that story,
and think that you have a genetic
predisposition to be an athlete, and that,
you know, they couldn't do the same thing,
and it wouldn't necessarily have a
positive impact on their health.
Do you agree with that statement?
>> No, not, not, not exactly.
I mean the, the, there clearly are, some
people that have you know,
are predisposed to certain diseases and
that sort of thing.
And you can't expect them to go out and do
some vigorous sport like track and field.
But, what everybody can do is find
something that works for them.
It might be swimming, it may just be going
for
a walk every evening if you can do that,
you know?
But it's it's up to the individual to find
something that works for them.
To me it's, it's, the difficult part is
how you think about it.
And what your mental attitude is about it.
>> And you have other people in you family
who aren't as active and
have had different histories?
>> Oh boy, I'm may get into trouble for
this one.
I have a younger brother and
an older brother and my younger brother
started jogging around the same time I did
my older brother just thought it was
ridiculous.
And the years went by and I said some day
we'll find out and my
older brother ended up having a quadruple
bypass and to his credit he changed.
You know, he quit the smoking, he starts,
he walks every day, he's a better,
eater than I am now, he's a virtual vegan,
so you know, vegan - vagen [LAUGH].
And so from a genetic standpoint, you
know,
we have pretty close to the same genetics.
So I think that's an indication that
there's more to it than just genetics.
>> Um-hm.
So he started pretty late then,
and have you seen a change in his health
since he's started exercising?
>> Oh, definitely.
He's,
he been, yeah, he's been healthier and you
know, obviously quitting smoking,
that's not good for you but, just the, I
can, I can tell.
I was just went back to his 80th birthday
a month ago or something and.
He's out walking now and he just looks
better and
he, you know, to me, he's just healthier
than I've seen him for a long time.
And its all the change in diet, change in
attitude, and.
>> They say its the ultimate healthy aging
pill and it will give you 14 years back.
So someone who is 74 functionally can be
60 years old if
they have healthy diet and exercise.
But getting back to your training.
So what's your current training regimen
like?
So what do you to, to be some of the,
the best sprinter in the world of your age
group?
>> Well I'm, I'm trying to get to be one
of the best.
[LAUGH] I, I work out regularly.
I do still have Coach Joy as my coach.
And I have her give me work outs,
which typically are maybe two days on the
track sometimes three.
A couple of speed workouts where I'm doing
some really fast stuff.
Another day might be some more endurance
training where I'm doing what we
call [UNKNOWN] 500, 400, 300 meter kind of
intervals.
On the weekend I'll do like an easy jog.
And then, fill in work, I'll go to the gym
and do some workouts, you know?
Especially if I have like, an injury of
some kind or other.
Then I'll go down to the gym, and get on
the exercise bike, or that sort of thing.
But even without I go to the gym anyway
because
if having a strong core is important and
you know and having it you know.
Your entire body should be fit not just
your legs.
>> And have you found that the strength
training you do in
the gym contributes to other activities of
daily living,
that makes things easier compared to other
people your age?
Yeah I think so especially if you just to
the general public.
Yeah no, the other thing that I do, and
this is a personal thing with me, is.
One of the things that, that I've noticed
as I've gotten older is that
people seen to think that easier is
better.
And they'll go out and
they'll buy this machine to do something
that they could do, you know.
I still, when, if I want to dig a ditch, I
don't go get a machine.
I'll get out my pick and shovel.
I still cut up my own firewood and I do
that, because I,
I actually enjoy it, It makes me feel
good, you know.
When I'm finished, I get to go in and have
a cold beer or something.
>> [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] You know.
But it's, it's, that's the attitude part
of it, I think.
You know.
Some people just maybe aren't willing to
do that.
I don't know why.
>> Yeah.
And if you cut those things out of your
life, you lose that physical ability and
you sort of watch it deteriorate and it
becomes a rapid slope.
So pushing that envelope and keeping that
intensity up
over time may very effective in
maintaining your functional capacity.
>> Right.
I, I and a lot of people and I hear it all
the time.
They think oh, they'll say well you know I
just turned 65, so I,
you know, I can't do that anymore.
Well but I know guys that are 80 that are
doing it.
So I don't think the number has anything
to do with it.
I think it's what you do yourself.
You know I'm just talking about some
fairly simple things like I can't jog to
the corner or something and back.
They just, they just develop bad habits.
[COUGH]
>> I know there a lot of people out there
who would like to be as active as you are,
and they just can't get themselves to do
it.
So they wake up in the morning, they say
today is going to be the day and
another day goes by and they don't do
anything about it.
So, how do you do it?
How do you make yourself stay active,
whether it's chopping wood or
coming to the track.
>> Well, part of it is I know that if I
get in shape and if I
train the way I know I should train, then
I'll do well when I go to a competition.
And, I want to do well, and, and, and that
makes it easier.
It does require a certain amount of self
discipline.
But, but just having a goal, I guess, you
know,
something that you want to accomplish,
make,
you know, I want to do this, so this is
what I have to do to get to my goal.
>> And that goal, that goal can be playing
with your grandchildren, or.
>> It can be anything [CROSSTALK]
>> Going on a trip to Europe, something
like that.
>> Exactly, it's, it's finding something
that you enjoy doing.
You know, now a lot of people might say,
well I enjoy watching TV.
Well, so maybe I should say, enjoying
some,
finding something you enjoy doing that's
good for you, that's healthy, you know.
It's okay to watch TV, but you should do
something besides that.
>> Yeah, pick up that tennis racket you
haven't played in a long time.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> And get back out on the court.
I, I, I don't want people to think that
oh, if you don't go out and, and
get involved in some, you know, world
competition or
something, that's no, not many people can
do that.
People can't even afford it, you know,
many people.
But if you just go out and do something
that you find that you enjoy doing,
that keeps your heart pumping, you know.
One of the things that I had to do that,
nutrition wise,
my wife would give me a piece of apple pie
and
say, wait a minute Bill, I'm going to get
the ice cream.
And I finally told her, I said, wait a
minute.
I'm not allowed to have two desserts at
the same time anymore, you know?
Just the pie and I'll have the ice cream
tomorrow.
>> Mm-hm.
So how has your training changed as you've
gotten older?
Have you had to give up some things?
Have you had to have longer recovery
times?
>> I haven't had to give anything up, but
I definitely have longer recovery times.
You know, and I have to be careful.
I can't, I can't get out there in, in the
heat and beat myself to death.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Because I get lightheaded, that sort of
thing.
But at the same time it's important to
maintain conditioning just because it's
painful, if you get out of shape,
you have to work harder to get back in
shape and I don't like that.
So I try to stay in shape just to, you
know, just to maintain good conditioning.
And earlier you were talking about how you
were forming a relay team with some of
your friends, some of the best sprinters
around, and so what are some of the social
aspects of athletics, and being part of a
team, and playing in the Senior Games?
>> That's the best part of it.
I've met some really nice people since
I've been involved in this, I mean,
just coming down to the track here, or
someplace else.
You run into people like,
you know who have the same kind of common
interest and you become friends with them.
And you find there's some very, very nice
people and, and when I've gone to
some of the, you know lucky enough to go
to a couple of international track meets,
I now have friends there's a guy in
Australia that's regularly emails me and
tells me what he's doing.
He just turned 80.
He's breaking records over there, you
know.
And so, it, you make not just new friends
but
new friends who understand the importance
of being healthy.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And that you can be healthy.
So it's, you know, it's an attitude again.
>> Yeah.
And they, we know that exercise increases
cognitive function so it keeps
the brain fresh and keeps people on task
and improves executive task functioning.
Oh, do you feel that that has an impact on
your brain function as well,
what do you do to keep yourself sharp and
alive in daily activities?
>> Probably the most fun thing I do is
spend time with my grand kids.
Spend a lot of time with them, and they
keep me hopping.
I've got in fact result of the track
thing,
is my grand, my older granddaughter who's
12 went out for
track this past season, and I got to help
coach that team, you know?
And that was just a lot of fun, and
I got closer to her, and she kind of
opened up with grandpa.
And that sort of thing.
And the same with the younger her younger
sister and
my other daughter has a little boy that,
we go down the creek.
We hike up and down the cr, we just do
those things.
That I would say, that's, that's the best
thing for, for Grandpa, you know.
But also, I just wrote a book and it's
very stimulating.
I, something that was important to me.
I decided to write a book about it.
And now I'm getting involved in a very
steep learning curve again on not just,
you know, I got it published.
Now I have to figure out how to promote it
and, and get involved in that.
But it does give me something to do every
day that I enjoy.
>> So this was just as in this past year,
when you?
>> Yes, it was just published in April.
>> Wow, congratulations.
>> Yeah, well thank you.
And it's, it's exciting.
And I'm getting a lot of good feedback.
And the result from this particular book
is, is what I was hoping I would get.
You know, I'm starting to hear back from
people.
And I started a website.
You talk about a learning curve.
Oh, man.
[LAUGH]
>> But, your grandkids can help with that
as well.
>> Well, I'm sure, yeah.
Well, actually, my oldest boy put it
together and
so, you know, working with him.
And, again, there's another positive.
Just you know, it's better than sitting
around doing nothing.
>> So, what did you do in real life?
What were you doing before you were out
running every day?
For work.
>> Well I'm an engineer in business
background.
You know, electrical engineer.
Did a little graduate work at Stanford
here but never completed it.
And I ended up.
Well, I lost my first son and
I ended up deciding I wanted to get into
the medical product business, and
so I came out with one of the first
automated blood pressure machines.
And set up a company.
Was very lucky to get a couple of people
here to, to, you know,
put up some money for it.
And I really enjoyed going out and
setting up distribution and that sort of
thing.
But again, so now you're traveling, but
you don't want to get out of shape.
I would get up in the morning and try to
find a place to go run if nothing else
they might have a gym in the hotel, just
something to keep me active.
And when I came home, it was the same
thing.
Sure, you're very busy, but there's always
time in the day for, if nothing else,
a ten minute run, you know, you can always
find 10 or 20 minutes.
>> So, if you had one take home message
for
our students, and the students could be
college age students, they could
just be middle aged people, living their
lives, or they could be masters, athletes,
what would you want them to understand
about aging and health, and exercise.
>> I think the biggest thing for me is to
is,
when I realized that the reason I wanted
to keep doing it was it became enjoyable.
I no longer viewed it as oh I've got to go
out and do this work out.
It was that, boy if I get in shape I'm
going to go to this track meet, and
I'm going to do well, and I'm going to be
with some good guys you know,
some good people, ladies and guys.
And.
It's turned out that I look forward to it,
like I'm going to the U.S.
Championships, and I know that my friends
are there, and I know we're going to
put together some relays, and we'll go
out, and we'll have a nice dinner.
So that's, it's a fun thing, it can be a
very, very positive thing, and
it requires a positive attitude toward it,
you know you've got to think about it as
something good, not something you have to
do, but as something you like to do.
Do you think you'll ever stop?
>> I hope not.
>> How many more age categories do you get
to jump into?
>> There's no limit.
I am getting close to the next one, where
I get to be the young guy again.
>> So you're saying they're five year
increments.
>> Yeah.
75-79.
Getting close to the, another year, and
then I get to be the young guy again.
And, I already know guys in that age group
that are pretty fast.
You know, and their friends and it's, it's
just something that keeps you going.
And I asked myself, you know,
is it worth all this workout, and the
answer clearly is yes.
Because if I, if I have to stop once in
awhile, I start feeling kind of sluggish.
I prefer feeling good.
And you do feel good all the time, and you
know, you don't have trouble walking.
One of the, one of the things that I do
now regularly is I do a lot of stretching.
I was telling Corey earlier this is the
part where I,
where I think of it as thinking old.
For example I was talking to a lady in an
insurance office and
she was telling me how, yeah, she'd backed
her car into this pole a couple of times.
And she said because I, I can't turn she
says.
It's just hard for me to turn.
Well, I, I know she wasn't close to my age
and so I said to her, I said well.
You know, every evening I just do this
back twisting.
I said, it takes me five or ten seconds,
that's all.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Just, just a little bit like that, and
she kind of looked at me all,
I don't do that stuff, and all I could
think was, keep backing into the pole.
[LAUGH] You know, I didn't know what else
to say.
Or you know it's, it's, it's the attitude.
It's, not giving yourself a chance or,
yesterday a friend of mine introduced me a
guy.
Told him I, you know, I'm still sprinting.
And this guy was really excited.
He said oh, yeah, he, I ran a 9-700, yards
in high school.
I said that's great, you would, why don't
you come out for
track, that's real, that's fast, you know.
You'd, you know, I have to lose 60 or 80
pounds.
I said, well why not?
So he continued to tell me how he did in
high school.
You know, I don't know.
Hopefully he'll go home and think about it
and think, maybe I can do that.
That's what I hope happens from your
class.
That people will realize, you know, I can
make myself feel better and
I can enjoy life more.
As a, as a result that not to mention that
you are not going to get diabetes as
easily in all the rest of the health parts
of it.
>> Great.
So one question going back to the training
what have you learned about your
body being a high end athlete as you are?
>> You have to be smart.
You better you're better in,
in terms of the workouts, you better make
sure you're warmed up, you're stretching.
You know.
And I do a stretching before and after the
workout.
And that sort of thing, and I learned that
from my coach and
from other, you know, competitors.
That's just very important.
The other think one incident that happened
was that after running that 400 meters.
I was warming up for the 200 and my legs
started spasming and I found out later
that was due to me not putting the right
kind of nutrients into my body.
You know, I had a blood test and they said
oh you're low on biotin and
you're low on these vitamin B6 and so,
they gave me a better diet, you know,
eat more vegetables, and that sort of
thing, and
also, you know, eat, go ahead and eat more
meat if you want, you know?
But make sure that you learn how to take
care of your body and
you're smart about it.
You know, how to, how to take care of your
body also.
>> How to read the changes in your body,
>> Yes.
>> So you sense a problem coming up before
it actually turns into something serious.
>> Sure, and the other thing that's hard
for somebody like me is so
you've got a minor injury, but you want to
get to that competition, you got to
listen to your body and say guess what,
you have to stop today, you can't.
If you, if you continue, you're going to
injure yourself worse so, you know,
you, you learn a lot of things like that.
>> I've got news for you, that's not just
older athletes, that's everybody.
It's, it's hard to get off the track, or
wherever, with a, with slight injury.
>> That's right yeah, right, right.
No, I mean, that again to the point is,
people say well yeah you're older so
you're going to get injured.
Well, there's an awful lot of Olympic
athletes that get injured and
have all the same problems, so it's not
just an age thing.
It's all.
It's all attitude.
>> So, how old do you feel?
>> [LAUGH] About 79.
[LAUGH] No, it's again it's like I don't
think of it as old.
It's like I like when I started learning,
I learned a couple of European languages,
and they don't say, how old are you?
They say, how many years do you have now?
And I thought that was really interesting.
Again, it's a different way to think about
it, you know?
We think, oh, you're, I'm old now, because
of this or that, and
we put a number on it.
My dad was when he turned 65, he was
designing a power plant in Korea and
they walked up to him on his birthday 65th
and
said sorry John, we have to take you off
the project.
You're too old now.
And he, what do you mean?
Yesterday, I wasn't, today I am.
And it's that, that's,
that's that whole attitude, I think that's
part of what should change in our culture.
Is that attitude that old is, means you
can't do anything anymore.
>> I think that's a perfect place to stop.
Thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
>> For your wisdom and your thoughts.
Thank you for giving me an opportunity.