Welcome back ,the first physical component
we will investigate is
cardiovascular fitness ,your
cardiovascular fitness can contribute to
how well you do on certain biking and
running races but it can also determine
how fast you can work up the flight of
stairs in your neighbors house and how
winded you are when you get to the top.
We'll see in this module how staying above
a certain critical level of cardiovascular
fitness can mean the difference between
taking care of yourself, or
being dependent on others for many of your
care needs.
In this unit, we will also talk about
amazing accomplishments of
physical performance done by athletes in
their later years, so keep watching.
If we're talking about cardiovascular
fitness, we've got to start with VO2 max.
You probably remember from the cold
section that VO2 max is
the gold standard for cardiovascular
fitness.
It takes into account your ability to move
air, into and out of your lungs, so
ventilation, to move oxygen from your
lungs into your blood, to move blood
through your heart and into your body, and
to extract and use oxygen in your tissues.
The higher your VO2 max,
the higher the intensity of exercise that
you can sustain.
So, we care about this both as a marker of
overall health, and of fitness.
Let's look at a variety of conditions that
impact VO2 max to
put the aging effect in context.
First, training.
Not surprisingly, VO2 max goes up with
training.
A variety of adaptations that help oxygen
delivery and extraction in the tissues
will increase your work capacity and your
maximal oxygen consumption.
In contrast, altitude, or low oxygen
pressure, environment will
reduce the delivery of oxygen in your
tissues, and thus, decrease VO2max.
And finally, your VO2 max will also down
with aging.
Where it falls in relation to altitude
line and
your baseline line depends on how old you
are, how high you are and how fit you are.
In the next few slides ,we'll tease apart
how much your
oxygen consumption will fall with age and
why it falls.
The figure to my right comes from a paper
that was published by Tanaka and
Seals in the Journal of Applied Physiology
in 2003.
It shows VO2 max values for
endurance-trained women,
the black dots, and sedentary woman, the
open squares, from age 20 to 75.
The dat, data gives us a good sense of
what happens to VO2 max as we age.
There are several key points here.
First, there's a lot of variability at
every age, but
the values in both groups clearly decline
with age.
On average, it is estimated that aerobic
capacity will decline about 1% per year,
after your mid-20's.
Second, regardless of age, for
the most part, the trained women have
higher VO2 maxes than the untrained women.
For example, that one seven year old woman
to the right of the graph has
a VO2 max that is almost twice that of
some of those 30 year old sedentary women.
So age plays a role in determining aerobic
capacity, but
is certainly not the only factor.
The third thing to notice is that there
seems to be a convergence of the lines.
Meaning the trained folks seemed to be
losing at a faster rate and
the lines are getting closer together.
Can you think about why that might be?
Well, there was more than just aging
physiology going on there.
As many of you out there may have
experienced,
it is really hard to train like you used
to when you were young.
Between the reduced time availability, the
increased recovery time, and
the decreased motivation to train in many
cases,
it's very difficult to put in the same
number of hours and intensity of training.
I'll show a, show you a bit more about
detraining in the next slide, but
you get the idea for now.
Let's say you're going through life,
getting older, you're fit and
training hard, but your friend is
completely sedentary.
Which one of you will notice first the
change over time in VO2 max?
Well, you probably will.
As an athlete who has trained hard, you
will notice pretty early that you
can't quite keep up with that old race
time and
that high end effort gets harder to
sustain.
That can be frustrating, but the problem
for
you friend is that, she may not notice the
fall in her capacity until it's too late.
There's a critical thresh hold of
disability around 18 mils per kilogram,
per minute, below which it is really hard
to do your activities of daily living.
Those open dots below the red dashed line
have
crossed that thresh hold of disability.
We've tested older women in my lab who
have had VO2 maxes in the range of 14.
That's equivalent to walking very slowly
on a treadmill with no grade.
And it is, and that's their maximum, so it
can't be sustained for very long.
What happens if those women want to carry
their groceries or
get out of the way of a bus?
It's important to think about this
throughout your life, so you can be one of
those black dots and not one of those open
dots below the threshold of disability.
Ha, freaked you out.
I'm on the other side of the slide now and
you didn't even see me move.
Faster than a speeding bullet.
Just thought I'd be wild and crazy and mix
it up a bit.
Okay, let's tease apart the influence of
training on age and VO2max.
To my left is a graph of VO2max versus age
for three different groups.
The lowest line, blue, is the untrained
group, green is the fitness range,
recreational athletes, and black
represents competitive runners who can't
keep up their earlier lev, earlier level
of training Similar to the previous graph,
you got a convergence of those lines.
However, if those elite runners were able
to train as hard as they did when they
were younger, the VO2 max would still fall
off but no faster than the other groups.
In contrast, if they were to stop training
in their early 30's and never train again,
They would lose a lot of that base that
they had built up in their youth.
So the expression, use it or lose it, is
definitely true.
What about gender differences?
To my, left is a representative line of
VO2 max versus age for men.
Let's add women onto the graph.
As you can see,
there's nothing physiologic that causes
women to lose aerobic capacity faster than
men if they were to keep up their training
as much as the men.
However, there can be some accelerated
muscle loss, circulatory adjustments and
body composition changes around the time
of menopause.
The problem, is more that on average,
women tend to
start with low aerobic capacity, and live
longer than men, therefore they
run a greater risk of dropping below that
critical threshold of disability.
Unfortunately, that results in more women
needing care in their later years and
ending up in nursing homes.
A 2005 paper by Gewirtz in the Journal of
Women's Health reported that
among residents of US nursing homes,
age 75 to 84, for every 100 men there were
246 women.
And among those greater than 85, for every
100 men there were 425 women.
That ratio's almost twice as much as the
same age groups in the general population.
You have to remember though, that these
are average values, and
it is not necessarily destiny.
I was giving a talk on this topic to a
group of older adults.
And when I got to this slide, I asked the
question, who is more at risk,
men or women?
One woman spoke up and said,
men are definitely more at risk because
they sit at home all day eating chips and
watching football, while the women are out
cooking and cleaning and doing errands.
It was obviously not the answer that I was
expecting, and everyone sort of chuckled.
But I thought about it more and
I realized that there was a lot of truth
in that comment, meaning,
that no matter what the graphs or the data
say you have some control over your aging.
In their house, if what she said is true,
she will probably be healthier than her
husband in the long run.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here we are ,back at the Fick Equation.
What better way to figure out why VO2 max
declines with age than to
tease apart the components that actually
determine VO2 max.
As you look at this equation ,which
factors do you think decline with age?
Is it heart rate ,Stroke volume, the
amount of oxygen in the arterial blood,
the amount of oxygen that the body's
extracting, well the answer is,
drum roll please, yes.
Yes.
All of the above.
Everything goes down, let's look more
closely.
You probably already know that max heart
rate declines with age,
even if you've never really thought about
it.
Have you heard of the formula that your
max heart rate is 220 minus your age?
That's based on estimates that your heart
rate goes down about one beat per year.
It turns out that,
that formula underestimates heart rate max
for older adults.
A new and improved formula is listed on
the slide to my right.
It is based on a large data set of people
over wide ranging ages.
The reason for the fallen heart rate over
time is still unclear, but
it seems to be a combination of the
decrease of the intrinsic rhythm of
the heart as well as decreased
responsiveness of
the heart to stimulation, in this case
beta Adrenergic stimulation to be precise.
The fallen, the fallen max heart rate is
independent of gender or fitness.
Stroke volume, the other component of
cardiac output is the amount of
blood pumped from the heart per beat.
It declines with age for the reasons
listed on the slide to my right.
Basically, the heart becomes less elastic,
beats less hard, and has more resistance
to emptying over time thus reducing the
amount of blood it can expel per beat.
The amount of oxygen your tissues extract
during max exercise also declines.
First ,there's less oxygen delivery to the
tissues due to
less blood flow to active tissues and less
hemoglobin to carry the oxygen.
And second, there's less removal of oxygen
that does arrive in the working
muscles because an older adult There are
fewer mitochondria to use the oxygen.
Finally, the ventilatory reserve that you
started out with in your youth will start
to wane as you damage the surfaces of your
lungs over time, especially if you smoke.
Various other changes to the lungs also
take place that make sustained,
high rates of ventilation more difficult.
But here's the thing, all of the age
related changes I
just described except maximum heart rate,
can be at least slowed,
if not stopped, with a lifetime of
regular, sustained endurance training.
Basically, from the heart to the lungs to
the blood to the tissues, it's all good,
and can slow the trajectory of aging.
However, because of the decline in max
heart rate, that is
not impacted by training, there will be a
fall off in maximum aerobic capacity,
even if you are able to train hard enough
to arrest some of the other changes.
Sorry.
But at least now you can answer one of the
corey questions about what is inevitable,
and what can be improved by regular
endurance training.
In the category of aerobic capacity, max
heart rate is the one stubborn outlier.
So the bad news is that, even if you were
training as hard as you were
when you were young, you still will lose
some aerobic capacity.
And, because the recovery time issues and
the poor repair mechanisms,
it also will be hard for you to fully
maintain your training.
But, the good news is that whenever you
are, whether you're a casual exerciser, or
an elite athlete, regular physical
activity will help you maintain your
functional capacity and performance as you
age.
Even with the age related decrements that
we've been talking about,
older adults are capable of amazing
accomplishments.
For example, let's look at the Hawaii iron
man.
This is the ultimate triathlon prize, and
requires swimming 2.4 miles in the ocean,
riding a bike for 112 miles, and then
running a marathon, so
26.2 miles, across the hot lava fields on
a big island of Hawaii,
all that in average temperatures 86
degrees Fahrenheit, and 70% humidity.
The cutoff for finishing is 17 hours.
Can you imagine doing that kind of
strenuous activity for 17 hours straight?
Actually, probably some of you ,folks out
there have done it and more but, for
the rest of us that is tough stuff.
Anyway, guess the age of the oldest man
and woman to complete the race.
Lew Hollander, at age 81, completed it
with 14 minutes to spare in 2011.
Amazing, 81.
Lew claims his secret is to go anaerobic
every day, meaning he pushes his upper
limit of intensity every day to prevent a
slow decline in capacity as he ages.
And then, there is Sister Madonna Buder,
the flying nun.
She started running in her 50's and has
been competing in races ever since.
She became the oldest woman to complete
the Hawaii Iron man at age 75, and
then beat her own record at age 76.
She also completed the Canada Iron Man at
age 82 in 2012 now
making her the oldest person to have
completed any Iron Man.
You go sister.
Let's go over the key points from this
module.
VOx max declines on average about 1% per
year after a peak value in your 20's.
Many factors contribute to the decline in
aerobic capacity like maximum heart rate,
heart elasticity and oxygen transport.
Values for trained and
untrained people decline about the same
right, rate if training is continued.
But it is very hard to keep up those
training levels.
Men and women decline at the same rate,
but women start lower and
live longer, so they're more at risk for
long term disability.
And, physical activity is critical to
maintaining optimal aerobic
function throughout our lifespan.
Okay, that's it for module three.
Complete the check for understanding
questions and move on to module four to
find out how your muscles fare during the
aging process.
Thank you for your continued interest.