Alright?
>> Alright.
>> Take her away.
>> Oky doky.
In this module, we're going to look at how
your muscles change with age and
what strength training can do for you in
your later years.
One point of clarification before I start.
I will use weight training, resistance
training and
strength training interchangeably in this
section.
When I do, I mean the same thing.
Muscle training against some type of
resistance such as free weights,
machines, stretchy bands, or the wall in
order to increase our strength.
Strength is the force your muscles can
generate.
On average, there is about an 8% decrease
in strength per decade starting at
around 45 years old.
The 8% can vary depending on where you
start in terms of strength,
whether you remain active, you genes, and
I'm not talking about your Levis, and
whether you are measuring your upper or
lower body strength.
As you might expect, lower body strength
is maintained better because you
tend to use your legs moving about more in
everyday life.
The losses will accelerate in later years
as well.
As you get older, you experience
Sarcopenia, or muscle loss,
that comes both from a decrease in muscle
fiber size, and a decrease in fiber and
motor unit number.
Do you remember what a motor unit is?
It is a grouping of muscle fibers that is
innervated by a single nerve,
the alpha motor neuron.
The loss of fiber number is called
Hypoplasia.
It frequently happens with your type two
muscle fibers that you tend to
under use as you get older.
Remember that your type two fibers are
your big high intensity strength fibers.
Throughout your life, they are denervated
and
then renervated to keep that neuron fresh.
If you don't use them as you age, your
body won't bother to renovate them and
that process and they will eventually fade
away from lack of recruitment or use.
Doing high resistance strength training,
training to fatigue, or things like
spring training will help maintain those
bigger, stronger Type II fibers.
To my right, is a sample graph of what
knee extension strength might typically
look like in untrained men, versus men who
weight trained throughout their lives.
Weight trained men, represented by the
blue line, are stronger to begin with.
They start to decline in strength later,
and
they do not fall off as rapidly as
untrained men.
Again, there could be a lot of variability
in these curves for
different people, but you get the general
idea.
Muscle power becomes an issue as we get
older as well.
Aging muscle has decreased velocity of
shortening.
That means we can't contract our muscles
as quickly,
because of a variety of neural factors
such as Decreased neural drive,
poor fiber recruitment, and slowed nerve
firing rates.
Power is equal to force times velocity, or
in other words, a combination of force and
speed.
So small reductions in both force and
velocity, can result in larger losses of
power.
We need power for many of our activities
of daily living, like climbing stairs.
Standing up out of a chair, or catching
yourself to prevent falls.
Some researchers and health care
providers,
argue that power training should be added
to regular strength training to
older adults, to help maintain optimum
muscle recruitment and faster firing race.
Power training in older adults consist of
lifting lighter weights at a faster speed.
People should work up to power training
program, though,
to reduce the risk of injuries.
For more information on power training,
see the resource unit at the end of the
section.
There's a saying that on average, a 20
year old uses 20% of his or
her strength to get out of a chair, and an
80 year old uses 80% of their strength.
But that is on average.
That means that some 80 year olds will
take 60% of their strength, and
some will take 100%.
You definitely want to be on the good side
of that average,
because if it takes you 100% or more of
your strength to get out of a chair, or
off of the toilet for example, you're
going to,
you're not going to be able to get up
without someone else helping you.
That obviously would be a major blow to
your independence and qulaity of life.
The good news is that, in the case of
muscle, all of the decrements and function
can be improved with regular physical
activity, especially resistance training.
Even so, regular activity is not going to
make an 80 year old look 20.
There's too much water under the bridge,
so to speak.
Hormones change over time, so there are
lower concentrations of those anabolic, or
growth promoting hormones, in both men and
women.
Stem cells that normally repair damage in
the young get less responsive as we age,
we'll talk about that in the last module
some more,
scientists are trying to whip those old
tired stem cells into shape.
And there's also cumulative damage to the
tissues, organs and
muscles that start to add up over time
resulting in less than optimal function.
Of course, it's better if you exercise
throughout your life, but
you're never too old to start.
I could give lots of examples here on how
exercise benefits aging muscle.
But this study published in 1990 has the
oldest mean age of participants that I
could find.
Investigators put frail, elderly men and
women, ranging in age from 87 to 96,
on eight weeks of high-intensity
resistance training.
After that time, their thigh muscles, the
thigh muscle strength and
thigh cross sectional area had increased
by 174 and 9% respectively.
The trainee showed increased gait speed,
stair climbing power, and
improved balance.
Also, they got a bonus of increase
spontaneous aerobic activity levels.
So more walking and moving around.
You frequently see this when frail people
start to, a resistance training program.
They get a little stronger,
they have more confidence, they feel
better about themselves, and
so they are more interested in
participating in other activities.
In this way, you can get a spiraling up of
activity and fitness.
Unfortunately, the opposite is also true.
If someone has a fall or they stop
exercising and start to lose strength it
can be harder and harder for them to get
back into their normal movement routines.
Anyway, the bottom line is that you are
never too old to benefit from exercise.
And that nothing so
far is as effective at reversing muscle
loss as resistance training.
It used to be that people thought that
exercise was only for the young and
after a certain point, why bother really?
But now we know the critical importance it
plays in maintaning our health and
well being.
We see from studies like the last one I
just showed you,
that really substantial and important
benefits can be obtained at any age.
There is no doubt that it gets harder both
psychologically and
physically to maintain a program of
activity as you get older.
Doing what, doing whatever you can is
better than nothing.
For example, if you have mobility issues,
join a chair aerobics class.
If you're overweight and
have joint pain, try swimming or joining a
water movement class.
There are options out there that can work
for you.
Time to take a mini-break.
Wake up, grab some coffee or better yet,
move, stretch, jump up and down.
In fact, why don't you put your computer
on something higher and
watch Module five standing up.
Give those legs a little something more to
do and
start your process of healthy aging.
Just an idea.
See you in a bit.