Welcome to the Physiology of Aging
section.
We've put this into the Environmental
Physiology class because you're
really looking at the effects of time on
our bodies.
Which is kind of environmental.
It's also such an important and relevant
topic that we couldn't resist.
It affects every one of us, every day.
Although we may not notice dramatic
changes for years at a time, we gradually
start to notice that it's harder for us to
do things that we used to do easily.
We start to feel a little more vulnerable,
a little less willing to take that leap
with our kids to the next rock or
less excited about taking the god kids on
the spiny ride at the fair.
Or maybe we succumb to an illness or
an acute injury from which it takes us a
long time to recover.
Are these changes inevitable?
Can we just push through them?
What's causing these changes?
My father used to get together with his
friends, and
go through what he called the organ
recital.
Inevitably, they would start discussing
what was going wrong with
their different body parts, used to drive
me crazy.
I never really understood it until the
other day I found myself with a group of
my close friends doing exactly the same
thing, and
all the kids in the room were rolling
their eyes.
I just started laughing.
You have to appreciate the irony in the
cycle of life.
So let's explore some of these issues
together in this section on aging.
Here are the questions that we're going to
ponder through this section.
Like in the previous sections we'll
include from the end of
the Corey MIT Agnes video.
What causes the impairments associated
with aging?
How does exercise keep Bill from
experiencing Agnes deficits?
Which aging deficits are improved with
diet and exercise and which are fixed?
We'll also discuss issues related to
healthy aging,
diseases, cognitive function and special
concerns for Masters Athletes.
Now keep in mind, as we go through the
material in this section that
I am an exercise physiologist by training.
So, a lot of the information you will
receive today will have a physical
activity flavor to it.
We'll look both at how aging can impact
exercise performance, but
also the reverse, how physical activity
can affect aging.
Fortunately, physical activity is the
ultimate healthy aging pill.
So there's a lot to talk about on this
subject.
This section is going to be a little
different than previous ones in
that the both the practical tips and the
answers to Cory's questions will be
woven throughout the material rather than
having their separate modules at the end.
I hope that we'll keep things moving along
through this massive topic that is
the Physiology of Aging.
Let's get started with module two.
Here we'll be discussing the basics of
aging, and healthy aging.
Before we get started though,
I want to explain the face that you see in
the center of this slide.
This is Danielle.
Its original format is a five minute video
by filmmaker, Anthony Cerniello.
We set out to emulate the aging process by
creating a person.
What we wanted to mimic was an image that
changes, but
you can't quite see it change.
You can only sense it, like aging itself.
We've had to speed it up just a little bit
to fit it into this module, but
the full link is in the resources at the
end of this session if you'd like to
watch it online as well.
Cerniello created Danielle as a composite
person.
A meticulously combined sequence of
related multi-generational family
members who were all photographed at more
or less the same time.
While I'm talking you will see her get old
without actually seeing her change,
so keep watching.
So what is aging?
Aging is the process of how things change
over time in an organism.
The Merriam Webster Dictionary definition
is pretty grim.
Gradual change in an organism,
that leads to increased risk of weakness,
disease and death.
It takes place in a cell, an organ or
the total organism over the entire adult
lifespan of any living thing.
There's a decline in biological functions
and
an ability to adapt to metabolic stress.
Yikes.
That sounds pretty depressing, and
unfortunately, much of it is true.
You see it all around you with your
parents,
your grandparents, you, the old woman in
the grocery store.
They are clearly decrements that occur
over time however, that
doesn't mean there's nothing we can do to
minimize the negative aspects of aging.
Healthy aging or successful aging is when
individuals work throughout their life to
be free of disease, to function at a high
physical and
cognitive level and to be socially engaged
and productive,.
I use the term work because it does take
work there is no easy fix and
we are not always successful but there are
many thing we can do to
get closer to get closer to that goal
aging vs longevity.
These two terms are often confused in both
the popular press and
the scientific literature.
Where's aging is a process, longevity is a
measure of how long we live.
Aging is actually quite hard to quantify.
For longevity, death is the end point, but
it doesn't say how well we've lived.
Why do we age?
On the philosophical side of the
discussion,
this is one of the great mysteries of
biology.
An often cited quote from the mid-century
evolutionary theorist, George Williams,
is written on the side to my far right.
He said, it is remarkable that after a
seemingly miraculous feat of
morphogenesis, a complex metazoan, which
is just a multi-celled animal.
Should be unable to perform the much
simpler task of
merely maintaining what is already formed.
In other words, it should be a lot harder
to create something from scratch than to
simply maintain it.
So why don't we maintain it?
As we move on with our discussion, we're
going to leave Danielle behind.
Bye Danielle.
[LAUGH] It's an amazing work of art.
I want to thank Corey for finding it
online and Anthony for letting us use it.
Biologically speaking, there are two
general theories on why we age.
The first is Age by Design, the idea that
we are preprogrammed to age after
reproduction to make room for the new
generation, so resources don't run out.
At a certain point we just stop repairing
the ongoing damage that happens to
our minds and bodies.
Support for this theory came from a
landmark study in 1993 in
which Cynthia Kenyon from the University
of California, San Francisco,
was able to double the life span of a sea
elegan's worm by mutating a single gene.
The Sea Elegans worm is frequently used as
a model for aging.
Before that everyone thought that aging
wasn't very interesting,
that we just kind of wore out.
Since then, many others have been able to
manipulate lifespans in a variety of
organisms by altering gene expression.
On the other hand, we also know that aging
can be manipulated by the environment.
Which brings us to the accumulated damage
theory of aging.
This theory suggests that through a series
of different onslaughts to our systems,
we slowly damage various cell
compartments, DNA, proteins, etc.,
as the signs of aging become more and more
apparent.
Within this unifying theory, there are
many hypotheses about what is
actually causing the damage, and some of
those are listed to my right.
The citation for a review paper with a
description of these different mechanisms
is listed at the end of this section if
you're interested in reading more.
Support for
theory two comes from studies of caloric
restriction in which both maximal and
average lifespan can be prolonged in many
species by dietary manipulation.
Suggesting that genetic control of aging
is not absolute.
The answer to why we age is probably a
little bit of both theories.
In most things, we are a combination of
our environment and
our genes and there is no reason to expect
that aging is any different.
This slide is for a point of
clarification.
Life expectancy, or average lifespan, is
not the same as maximal lifespan.
Life expectancy is the age where it is
expected that 50% of
the population will still be alive.
In the graph to my right you can see that
the average lifespan has
changed dramatically in the past 100
years.
The graph isn't exactly to scale, but
the life expectancy of a child born in
1900 was between 45 and 49 years old.
In the US, for
a child born in 2000, the life expectancy
is 77 for males and 80 for females.
In Japan, the new life expectancy as high
as 83.
We've accomplished this amazing expansion
of life span by reducing child mortality,
creating better vaccines, better health
care, better living conditions and
better nutrition.
You can see the influence of the better
child health by
comparing the initial shape of the 1900
curve compared to that of 2000.
There are many fewer deaths at younger
ages these days.
Curves for
animals in the wild look more like the
shape of the red curve on the graph.
In contrast to life expectancy, maximal
lifespan is anecdotal.
It changes every time we find someone that
lives longer.
Right now, the official documented record
is held by a Frenchwoman named
Jean Calmet, who lived from 1875 to 1997.
A total of 122 years and 164 days.
She was apparently quite a character and
very lively until she died.
She took up fencing at age 85, rode her
bike until 100, and claimed that
she maintained her health by using lots of
olive oil, drinking port regularly, eating
a kilogram or 2.2 pounds of chocolate per
week, and quitting smoking, at age 117.
[LAUGH] She was also very funny.
For example, at one of her later birthday
parties somebody left by saying,
until next year perhaps.
She looked at him and responded, I don't
see why not, you don't look so bad to me.
[LAUGH] Good for her.
In honor of Jeanne Calment's lively
attitude we're going to take
a mini break here so that I don't rattle
on too long.
I hope part one set a good foundation for
explaining why we age.
When you come back we'll talk about
strategies that
may slow the aging process.
Not things that are advertised on
late-night TV, but
things that are actually worked in the
lab.
See you soon.