Welcome to module eight.
I hope you are all still with me.
I realize this is a long section, but
there's so much to talk about when it
comes to aging.
Only a couple more module's to go and this
should be a good one for
all you athletes out there.
Used to be that when an older adult came
into a sports medicine physician office
complaining about a problem, the physician
would just tell them to stop competing and
just take time to rest.
But they can't do that anymore.
There's currently a much greater
understanding of the benefits of
physical activity on the mind and body for
people of all ages.
In addition, there's been an explosion of
participation by masters athletes who
train for competition or just for fun and
health.
For example, in 1987, there were 500
participants in the World Senior Games,
which requires people to be over 50.
That event had grown to 9000 participants
in 2007, and in 2013,
the national senior games, which draws the
top senior athletes from
around the country had almost 12,000
athletes.
In those games they had to create an 80+
basketball division, and
records were falling like dominoes in the
new 100+ age categories.
It's estimated now that 50% of all
endurance athletes competing in the US.
are in their middle age.
Woo hoo, let's hear it for middle age.
[LAUGH] There is no denying that amazing
feats are being accomplished by
older athletes all the time.
We talked in an earlier module about
Sister Madonna Buder,
who completed an Ironman at age 82.
In addition we have Olga Kotelko, who is
94 and
has 700 track and field gold medals and 26
world records.
Her favorite event is the hammer throw.
There's a link to a very sweet video about
her in the resources section.
There are also a lot of middle age
athletes who are competing on par with
younger athletes in open age categories.
Dara Torres, winning an Olympic silver
medal in swimming at 41.
Professional baseball players playing into
their late 40s, and many other examples.
Having said that though, there's
definitely something going on with aging
even in people who train as hard as they
possibly can throughout their life.
Exercise is the healthy aging pill, but
it's not magic.
An elite 50 or
70 year old athlete is not going to
compete like an elite 30 year old athlete.
So what's normal?
What is an inevitable decline, and
is there a point where physical activity
can't compensate anymore for aging?
Well, a good way to answer those questions
is by looking at the changes in
world record times across the lifespan.
People who, in theory, aren't detraining
from lack of effort.
To my right are two graphs that show the
change in world record times with age.
The top panel is for 10 kilometer running
times for men and women.
You can see that initially, values are
pretty stable: 20s, 30s, 40s pretty flat.
50s, 60s, starting to fall off a bit.
70, 80s, start to get an exponential
increase in the time that
it takes to finish the 10k.
A similar type of thing happens in the
lower graph, representing the swim world
record times for men and women in the 500
meter and the 1500 meter.
Values gradually fall off until 70 years
old, when times increase dramatically.
The fall off seems to happen a bit later
in swimming than the running graph,
probably because of fewer muscular
skeletal injuries in
swimming compared to running.
So what does this mean?
It means that exercise is pretty good at
compensating for
aging until around 60 or 70 years old.
This applies to strength events like
Olympic weightlifting as well.
But even in these elite older athletes
it's hard to know what is true biology and
what is behavior.
For example, also at that time.
Self chosen walk pace declines in humans.
And it's not just humans.
There's also a reduction in spontaneous
physical activity in
other species like insects and rodents at
that equivalent age range.
So maybe it's that masters athletes just
don't want to
push themselves as hard anymore.
It's just not worth it.
The good news is that, life long activity
seems to
push that decline in spontaneous activity
to an older age, at least in rats.
So why will performance go down even if
you're trying to train as hard as
you did when you were younger?
As we talked about earlier, there are
several reasons.
First, your maximum heart rate will
decline no matter what.
So even if you're training hard enough to
keep most other things relatively
constant, cardiac output,
which is the amount of blood pumped from
your heart per minute, will fall.
And we know from the Fick equation
earlier, that the fallen cardiac
output will result in the a lower maximum
capacity of the O2 max.
Muscle mass will be maintained better in
masters athletes than
their sedentary counterparts, but it's
still not possible for
an older adult to keep the same amount of
muscle as a younger person.
Hormones like testosterone, estrogen,
growth hormone, fall with age, so
the internal environment is less anabolic
or growth promoting.
Next, reaction time and your speed to
develop peak force declines, so
younger people beat you off the mark and
to the ball.
Your flexibility declines as well because
little cross bridges start to
form in your connective tissue, which
tighten up the tendons.
The loss of flexibility can reduce your
economy of movement.
For example, older sprinters take smaller
steps.
Steps.
Both because of reduced power and
reduced joint range of motion, causing him
to slow down.
Sorry, but things that increase with age
aren't so good either.
You're more likely to get injured acutely
because connective tissue gets stiffer and
decreases in tensile strength.
Therefore, when you pull on it abruptly,
it's more likely to rupture.
I know this from personal experience
because I had a full rupture of my
Achilles tendon a couple years ago,
doing a movement that I had done a 1000
times before.
It was not a pleasant experience.
But I'm fully recovered now, just in case
you're interested.
Overuse injuries become a bigger problem
as well because A,
you've been using that muscle or tendon or
joint for
many years and B, your repair mechanisms
are not as effective as they used to be.
So small problems that would go away
quickly in a young person linger for
longer and get aggravated masters
athletes.
Talk briefly about why repair mechanisms
are slowed in
older tissue in the next module.
It's fascinating stuff and they're working
on some good solutions.
Anyway, as a result, you need more
recovery time between exercise bouts.
So even if you really really want to train
as much as when you were 20,
your body probably won't cooperate.
If you're a masters athlete you can expect
to do really well at any age and
you can expect to be much better off than
your couch potato uncle,
who only watches sports instead of
participating himself.
But you can't expect to be as fast as you
were 20 years ago.
Estimates vary and individuals can prove
general estimates wrong, but
what I've listed here are just a few
examples of expected rates of decline.
For example, although master's Ironman
triathletes have been getting faster in
general over the past 25 years, there's
still a decline in performance of about
13% per decade for men, and 15% per decade
in women up to age 70.
With running over a range of distances,
things remain pretty good
through the 40's, but then start to
decline about 1.7% per year after age 50,
and then more like 7% per year after age
70.
Interestingly, biking performance is
thought to stay more stable than running.
It has to due with the mechanical
advantage of the bike and
the reduction of repetitive loading
injuries.
Also when biking you use mainly concentric
contractions, or shortening contractions,
in contrast, running relies more heavily
than biking on eccentric or
lengthening contractions, which decline
more rapidly with age.
A combination of these factors helps
maintain biking performance into
later years.
Good for all you cyclists out there, eh?
And finally, weightlifting generally
decreases more
rapidly than others on the list after age
45.
Let's talk about some special
considerations for masters athletes.
Whereas regular physical activity has
clear benefits on cardiac function.
Those that have underlying cardiac disease
can be of greater risk of
a cardiac incident during unaccustomed or
sudden high intensity exercise.
In general the benefits greatly outweigh
the risks but
before starting a new exercise program,
it's recommended that masters athletes
have a pre-participation evaluation.
Osteoarthritis is common and can make
movements of the joints painful.
Although exercise doesn't cause
osteoarthritis, high impact act,
act, activities can make it worse than if
already exists.
Alternative, lower impact forms of
training may need to
be incorporated in to your routines.
Medications of various kinds can interfere
with performance.
There are too many to get list them all,
but here are a couple of common examples.
Beta blockers, taken to lower heart rate
and blood pressure do just that,
lower heart rate and blood pressure, which
is not good for high intensity activities.
Statins that are very common medication in
the US for high cholesterol may cause
muscle pain, muscle damage and impaired
muscle performance in some athletes.
A review article on this topic is linked
in the resources for those,
for those of that, you that are currently
taking statins.
Rather dilators like Calcium channel
blockers can lower blood
pressure too far if exercise is stopped
suddenly.
Next issue is hydration.
Hydration status needs to be monitored
more closely in
masters athletes because they have a less
robust thirst mechanism and
dehydration can interact negatively with
many medications.
Injuries.
In one study,
89% of athletes over 50 reported having
injuries of various degrees.
Injury is the most common reason athletes
stop competing, so they will happen, but
most of the time they will heal.
But the injuries can't be ignored, and
they need to be given time to repair.
As a result of the considerations
described, it's wise for masters athletes
to consider a pre-participation screen
evaluation if they are taking medications,
have an ongoing injury, or have any
disease risk factors.
The last thing on the list is team sports.
Now this is an interesting category
because you're not just competing against
the clock, now you're battling younger
players.
Although it's changing a little bit, it's
rare for
athletes to compete in team sports at
elite levels past 40.
Those athletes that do experience more
contraction induce injuries and
are at a greater risk of injuries during
collisions because of less elastic fibers.
Also, with fewer power type II muscle
fibers,
older athletes experience more eccentric,
those lengthening contractions, and
they're overpowered by younger, stronger
athletes.
One way to help with this is to integrate
more plyometric training into
your routine.
Plyometric training involves explosive
movements like jumping down from a box and
then quickly up again.
But work up to it slowly, so no injuries
occur while doing the training.
This slide gives a great example of what
happens in team sports with
older athletes.
For those who don't follow U.S.
basketball, and
I actually include myself in that category
Kareem Abdul Jabbar, Charles Barkley and
Michael Jordan are three very famous
players that remained in
the league until their early 40's.
The graph to my left has two measures
expressed as a percentage of
peak performance.
The line with the solid circles shows the
free-throw percentage for
the three athletes over time.
Free-throws are uncontested attempts to
get the ball in the hoop from
a particular spot on the court, so no one
is interfering with the shot.
The graph line for those number is
essentially flat.
However, the open circles show the points
per game that they were able to score.
In this case, points per game falls off
dramatically as they got older.
A reasonable conclusion, therefore, is
that accuracy is not lost but
the ability to shoot when being guarded by
ever younger players falls off by
more than 50%, as it becomes harder for
them to become open.
Dang, those pesky young athletes always
getting in the way.
Based on what we've discussed in this
module,
here are some general recommendations for
training as a master's athlete.
These are not sports specific, but they
can be tailored for
many different activities and individuals.
In the end, you need to do what works for
you and or your coach.
These are just a few things to keep in
mind.
First, working on flexibility becomes more
important with age,
because things really start to tighten up
and we start to lose our range of motion,
that can limit our performance.
Doing slow, lengthening contractions
across joints can
help break up the cross bridges and
connective tissue.
An example of this would be to put your
toes on the edge of
a stair Lift yourself up with both feet on
to your tip toes and
then slowly lower your heel down as far as
it will go.
So with one foot.
Then use both feet to push yourself up to
your toes again, and
then lower yourself down, as far as you
can go, with one foot.
That action is thought to break up cross
bridges and
re-align collagen fibers in your Achilles
in a more optimal pattern.
Now keep in mind that too much flexibility
can be bad for performance.
For example, in running, those that are
more flexible are actually less
efficient in their running stride because
they have to overcome all that elasticity.
Trying to find that sweet spot right in
the middle of flexible enough to maintain
range of motion, but not too flexible to
impair performance, can be challenging.
Before an event or training do a sport
specific dynamic warm up that involves
slowly doing the movements of the event,
but through an extended range of motion.
This method of functional stretching will
increase blood flow to
the relevant muscles as well as loosen up
tight tissues.
Avoid traditional static stretches like
sit and reach before an event.
This type of stretching has been shown to
decrease measures of performance like
vertical jump and power for after an hour
after the stretch.
Some athletes, such as gymnasts require
additional flexibility that is enhanced
with static stretching, but the current
consensus is that most sports don't derive
much benefit in terms of performance or
injury prevention from static stretching.
Aerobic conditioning.
In order to keep your aerobic capacity,
it's important to maintain your high level
training.
As you age, you can train smarter by
cutting your amount of training but
continue with some intensity intervals.
Short bouts of High Intensity Interval
Training for
HIIT, have been shown to sustain aerobic
capacity and
even cause changes in the muscle, like
increased mitochondria that were
traditionally associated with high volume,
low intensity endurance training.
HIIT also recruits your type II muscle
fibers that may not get a lot of
action as you get older.
Use them or lose them baby.
Strength, masters athletes should focus on
multi-joint compound movements that build
functional strength.
Cross-training will allow higher training
loads while reducing the risk of
repetitive use injuries.
Maintaining core strength can improve
performance and reduce risk of injuries.
Then of course, listen to your body and
give it the recovery and rest time that it
needs.
Remember, your body will not heal as
quickly as it did at age 20.
So your performance will actually better,
if you give yourself the necessary time to
recover.
That's all I have time for right now.
I know that this is probably a popular
topic, so I've included some additional
links and references in the resource
section for your viewing pleasure.
Huh, that was a fun trip to Boston.
It's a picture of us in the sculpture on
the MIT campus.
Anyway, congratulations.
You can check off another module.
Next up is a short one on general tips for
healthy aging, but
I might throw in a couple science nuggets
about color restrictions, stem cells, and
new strategies to manipulate aging.
You know, just to make things interesting.