Welcome to the Physiology of Altitude
section.
This is one of my personal favorites, both
because I love being in the mountains and
because I spent several years doing high
altitude physiology research.
So it's near and dear to my heart.
As I mentioned in the introductory video,
there are so many fascinating things that
happen when our bodies are exposed to low
oxygen environments.
It's amazing how adaptable we really are.
A fun illustration of this concept comes
from the book Into Thin Air,
by John Krakauer, about the 1996 Everest
expedition where things went
terribly wrong and many people lost their
lives.
Early on in the book, when the author is
flying in Nepal,
in the Airbus 300, he describes a moment
of panic.
He looks out the window and
sees the unmistakable outline of Mount
Everest at eye level with the plane.
The wind is howling off the top creating a
long train of ice crystals.
His palms suddenly get sweaty because he
realizes that if
the plane were to depressurize at that
moment he would likely pass out or die.
Yet, in 6 to 8 weeks, he was planning to
be standing on top of that mountain.
Now, he climbed the mountain with
supplemental oxygen, as most people do.
But there are a handful of people who have
been able to climb Mount Everest
without supplemental oxygen.
A feat that many people thought was beyond
capability,
until it was actually accomplished in 1978
by Reinhold Messner.
So through this process of going up a
little and then down a little up a little
more and back down, our bodies slowly
acclimatize to allow spectacular feats
of physical performance that push the
limits of human capabilities.
Among other things this section will
explain how our bodies adapt to
allow such accomplishments.
So here are a list of questions to ponder
for
this section as you go through the
material.
First we will address Corey's questions
from the story video.
How did Corey compensate for the lower O2
availability at attitude?
What stop Corey at a lower work load
during exercise at altitude.
And did Corey do better or worse than the
predicted change for 10,000 feet?
We'll also talk about why we care about
altitude research, and
how we actually study it.
What are the challenges we face at high
altitude?
How our bodies adapt over time to high
What are the high altitude illnesses we
need to worry about, and what causes them?
What are the ways to decrease our risk of
illnesses and
increase performance at altitude?
And, finally, how do we train at altitude
and will it help our performance?
Over to my right is an outline of how the
overall sections is laid out.
We will work through the topics that will
help address the questions that you
had on the last slide.
You can also see in Module four, we have a
bonus story video for you.
Corey and I, and the camera crew, went up
to the summit of Pikes Peak to
illustrate what it was like to start the
acclimatization process at 14,000 feet.
I have to say that it was particularly fun
to watch our
hypoxic camera crew weaving about trying
to film the video.
We're going to talk about the challenges
you face at altitude in this module.
And, believe me there are a lot of them.
High altitude really does provide a
strong, systemic stimulus to the body.
Low O2 availability impacts your heart
rate and blood pressure,
you have cardiovascular and endocrine
changes, falls in performance, and
you could even experience symptoms of
acute mountain sickness.
But if your an athlete there are good
things that happen to
like increase red blood cells and
hemadocrit.
Before talk, we talk about the details,
let's put all that information in context.
Why do we even care about high altitude
physiology?
As the slide to my right says,
35 million people travel per year to
altitude of greater than 8,000 feet.
They do so, do so for
a variety of reasons that include
recreation, military service, and work.
Populations reside permanently at high
altitudes in the Rocky Mountains of
North and Central America, the Andes of
South America,
the East African highlands and the Asian
Himalayan plateau.
But what you may not realize is that even
if you have not been to the mountains
recently, you may have experienced a
moderate altitude stimulus simply by
flying in a commercial jet.
You see, it takes a lot of fuel to
pressurize the cabin.
So as it compromised to save on fuel, they
only pressurize the cabin to between 5 and
8000 feet.
Therefore, on those long, international
flights,
feelings of jet lag may actually be mild
symptoms of acute mountain sickness.
There's also clinical relevance to
studying the body's response to
hypoxic conditions.
For example, people which chronic
obstructive pulmonary disease and
heart disease experience varying degrees
of hypoxia.
Fetal development is also on the list,
because under normal conditions,
developing fetus, in utero, exists in
high, in a hypoxic environment.
Fetal arterial oxygen tension,
is about one quarter of a healthy adult,
so 25 versus 100 tore respectively.
That is equivalent to the blood oxygen of
a person on the summit of Mount Everest.
This work is particularly relevant to
pregnancies in which hypoxia is
exacerbated such as in fetuses or
women who smoke, have heart or lung
disease, or anemic or malnourished, or
from mothers who engage in strenuous
physical activity or heavy work.
Some theorize that we are able to adapt so
effectively to high altitude because we
spent the first nine months of our lives
in a hypoxic environment of the womb.
Also on the list, tumor treatments.
Researchers and physicians are working on
depriving tumors of their blood supplies,
and thus oxygen and nutrients to prevent
further growth.
Understanding how our tissues respond to
hypoxic environments is critical to
such advancements.
And finally because hypoxia is a whole
body stressor it helps us
understand the integration of the body
systems.
We apply a stress to the system, see how
it responds and
it gives a stronger understanding of basic
physiology.
So how do we study humans in a high
altitude environment?
There are several ways, first we can use a
high altitude chamber,
like the one you saw in the Corey's Story
video at the start of this section.
The USARIEM chamber we visitied provided a
hypobaric hypoxia stimulus,
meaning it lowers the total pressure in
the chamber to achieve hypoxia.
This type of stimulus is similar to what
happens when you actually travel to
the mountains.
Studies that are done in these chambers
are both short term,
like the one we did with Corey, and long
term,
where participants are asked to stay in
the chamber for days or even weeks.
As we mentioned in the story video, one of
the most famous of
these long term studies was Operation
Everest Two, which was conducted in 1985.
This study simulated a climb by eight
volunteers to
the summit of Mount Everest about 29,000
feet over the course of 40 days.
During that time, an international group
of 23 military and civilian scientists
conducted a series of experiments at
escalating climatization plateaus.
They collected data to determine the
relative importance of
various psychological, physiologic, and
biochemical responses to low oxygen.
Can you imagine volunteering to be trapped
and
watched, 24/7, a little metal box for 40
days?
To this day, it remains one of the
landmark studies in the field,
from which we attained a huge amount of
valuable information.
Unfortunately, there are not many of this
chambers around.
They're expensive, and complicated to
build, run and
maintain For example, can you envision
what would happen if you
flushed a normal toilet in an altitude
chamber where the plumbing on
the outside was significantly higher
pressure than the plumbing inside?
Kaplue.
There would be a lot of nasty stuff on the
walls of the chamber.
So many things have to be redesigned
within the chamber.
Hypoxic gas can also be used to mimic
altitude for both research and
training purposes.
The gas can be administered through masks,
tents, cubes, hotels, and
even horses snouts.
The stimulus in this case is normobaric
hypoxia, meaning the pressure remain,
remains s at ambient levels, but the
environment is
made hypoxic by reducing the percentage of
oxygen in the air.
Although originally considered as been
equivalent to hypobaric hypoxia, there
are some minor but critical differences
emerging that require further research.
We'll talk about a couple of these later.
But as you can see from the slide people
use the technology in gyms to train, in
labs to do research, and in the bedroom to
improve subsequent exercise performance.
And finally there's the real thing.
Now this is the best gig if you can get
it.
Being able to do field work is a fantastic
way to earn a living.
It allows us to study participants in a
more realistic environment and for
longer periods of time.
The picture to my right is a view of Pikes
Peak from the lower part of
the road that goes up to the top.
There is a Usarium Altitude Research
Station at the top where I
have spent several summers studying the
acclimatization process with my
co-investigators, the Army Dudes, as we
fondly called them.
You met Chuck and Steve from that group in
the Usarium Chamber story video.
Later in this section you will get a first
hand view of the research station as
Corey and I head up there for a few days
for the Chronic Altitude story video.
Before we get started,
I thought I should define some of the
altitude ranges for you.
As you can see on the slide, I have the
elevations both in meters and in feet.
I will try to get both units throughout
the section, but I may jump back and
forth a bit.
I apologize in advance for that.
It's a bad habit on my part but
I will tend to relay the information as
it's presented in the literature.
However, you can see that I have the
conversion down at the bottom of
the slide, as well.
So that will help you cross over to your
preferred units if needed.
Low altitude includes cit, cities like
Denver.
When you head up to Colorado Springs
you're in the moderate altitude range.
Also several stages of the Tour de France
and
Giro d'Italia climb up into that range.
But things really start to get dicey, when
you reach the high altitude and,
of course, extreme altitude ranges.
These include Pikes Peak and Mt Everest
respectively.
So, we will spend most of our time talking
about the impact of high altitude.
So now to the good stuff.
The primary physiologic challenge at
altitude is the low oxygen pressure.
As you can see from the numbers on my
right, as you go up in elevation,
the percentage of the oxygen in the
surrounding air stays at 20.93, but
the barometric pressure falls.
Therefore, the partial pressure of oxygen
falls also.
If you trace the numbers in the partial
pressure of oxygen row,
second from the bottom, you will see that
the pressure of oxygen on the summit of
Everest is about 1 3rd that of sea level.
As the barometric pressure falls, the air
expands to take up a larger volume.
You may have experienced a classic
illustration of this when you were
in the mountains.
Increased farting.
The gas in your gut expands, and wants
out.
Anyhow, the lower pressure also means,
there are fewer molecules of oxygen and
air in a given space which causes the
temperature to fall.
Typical temperatures are listed in the
last row of the table,
from 59 degrees Fahrenheit in Miami to
minus 46 on Everest.
In my experience with Miami, the
temperature is more like 90.
But either way, it is quite a range.
The falling oxygen pressure is felt
throughout the whole body and
can greatly affect your physical and
cognitive performance.
On my right is a graph of oxygen transport
cascade for three different elevations.
The graph starts where the previous table
left off,
at the oxygen pressure of the surrounding
or inspired air.
What happens next?
The air that you breathe into your lungs,
first mixes with the water vapor and
the carbon dioxide coming from metabolism
that is already in your lungs.
So by the time, that oxygen gets into the
alveolar spaces, which are the gas
exchanging areas of the lungs, it is now a
smaller percentage of the total air mix.
So like, with the altitude tense, the
partial pressure of oxygen is less because
it makes up a smaller portion of their
overall gas If you're confused by
partial pressures, it is explained more
fully in the glossary.
Looking at the purple sea level line on
the graph,
you can see that the alveolar gas has an
oxygen partial pressure of about 105.
From there the gas diffuses into the
arterial blood rather efficiently so
there's not much loss of pressure there.
Gasses move from high pressure to low
pressure and the higher the pressure
the more the driving force is to send that
gas to the other compartments.
The arterial blood then circulates around
the body to the tissues
where the oxygen is extracted as needed.
Whatever oxygen is not extracted returns
to the lungs and
the mixed venous blood is illustrated on
the graph.
Now look at the blue line which represents
an altitude of 4300 meters, or
equivalent to Pike's Peak.
You can see that the whole cascade is
impacted.
You start lower with the inspired air.
Therefore, when the oxygen mixes with the
water and
the carbon dioxide, it is again lower.
You get good transfer still into the
arterial blood, but your levels are so
much lower to start, that there is much
less oxygen available for
your tissues to extract.
When you look at the green Everest line,
it is even flatter,
meaning there is almost no oxygen
available for your tissues to extract.
We all know that our tissues can't
survive,
much less exercise, without oxygen.
Here is our friendly Fick equation
describing the components of
the oxygen consumption.
The volume of oxygen consumed is equal to
cardiac output, Q,bBlood pumped
from the heart per minute times the
arterial venous oxygen difference.
With acute exposure, it is the a component
of the equation that is most impacted.
As the arterial oxygen pressure gets lower
and
lower, the a minus v O2 difference
approaches 0.
So that on the summit of Mount Everest,
even if your heart is racing you can't get
enough oxygen to the tissues.
Without acclimatization, you would die.
The result of this decreasing oxygen
cascade is that your
maximum work capacity, your VO2 max,
falls.
There is some variability, but the general
rule is that VO2max will fall off 1% for
each 100 meters over 1500 meters.
So on the summit of Pike's Peak,
that means a fall off in maximum oxygen
consumption of about 27%.
On Everest, 75%, which means someone with
a VO2 max
of 60 which is quite good at sea level
would fall to less then 15 on Everest.
That is equivalent to walking slowly on
the flat with a light pack,
can you imagine trying to climb with
Everest with that kind of work capacity.
From descriptions by climbers and
scientific studies from the 60s,
we know that in order to move in that
situation, you need to take about six to
eight breaths per step and you still need
to rest every 20-30 yards.
Which is why most people use supplemental
oxygen when they climb Everest.
The limited oxygen availability doesn't
just affect maximum performance, but
affects sub-maximum performance as well.
Let's give Corey a hypothetical challenge
at 4,500 meters where he tries to
exercise to maximum and compare it to sea
level.
His VO2 max falls about 30 percent.
But now, a set task, say riding the bike
at 125 watts, which is depicted
in the red on the graph, represents a
higher percentage of his maximum.
Therefore, everything he does will seem
harder at altitude.
Climbing, making camp, competing in a
cycling event will all be harder, and
he won't be able to sustain that same
absolute workload as long at altitude.
Since we spend most of our time performing
sub-maximal tasks,
the sub-maximal impact will be more
noticeable decrement in performance.
It is logical that being more fit should
help you do better at altitude, and
it certainly does in some ways.
It requires great strength and stamina to
climb mountains.
But, interestingly, some of the advantage
that fit people have at sea level,
relative to less fit people, is lost at
altitude.
Because the fall in VO2 max is a
percentage.
So a recreational athlete with a VO2 max
of 45 at sea level will drop to
about 12 on Everest.
Similarly, a much fitter guy with a C
level VO2 max of 60 will drop to 15.
So there's a convergence of these values
at altitude.
Why is that?
It has to do with the concept of transit
time.
Transit time is the amount of time that
blood is in contact with
the exchanging tissues.
In this case, the lungs.
Highly fit people have very high cardiac
outputs, meaning that their
hearts are pumping larger volumes of blood
in very rapid rate to the heart and lungs.
So the blood has less time to fully
saturate with oxygen as it
passes through the lungs.
Remember how I said earlier that the
higher the gas pressure the greater
the driving force of movement for that
gas.
Therefore at sea level, the high cardiac
output in athletes is less problematic.
Because the gas diffuses into the blood
more rapidly with the higher pressures.
However, at altitude, the diffusion rate
slows, so the arterial oxygen
saturation falls as cardiac output
increases at the higher workloads.
Thus, the O2 max declines to a greater
extent in fit versus unfit people.
In summary, more fit equals higher Q,
equals lower transit time.
Shorter transit time in fit means less
oxygen in the blood at
higher workloads and greater falloff is
VO2 max.
The bad news is that we are challenged to
perform at altitude,
even if we are highly fit.
However, the good news is that our bodies
respond to
the low oxygen right away to try to help
us cope.
We've spent this last, rather extended
module talking about the challenges to
performance at high altitude.
Next we'll move on to what our bodies
actually do about it.
Congratulations you survived Module 2.
Take the practice quiz for this module and
then go on to Module 3 to
learn about the initial physiological
responses to altitude and
see how Corey actually performed in the
chamber relative to what was expected.
Thank you.