Pike's peak.
We had some kind of fun on the mountain
during filming.
Reminds of those summers I used to spend
up there working my tush off with
the research team.
Actually, to be honest, it wasn't all that
pleasant this last visit,
because we didn't have much time to
acclimatize.
After spending whole summers up there,
I had forgotten that the first couple days
are not so fun.
Right when Corey and I started feeling
good again, it was time for us to leave.
Oh well, it was worth it just to watch
Carlos and Wes getting all queasy and
hypoxic behind the cameras.
So let's find out what was going on up
there.
In module three, we talked about the
changes that occur in the first few hours.
Now we are going to move onto chronic
adaptations to altitude.
In this picture Corey is looking not too
happy, but
definitely less stressed than in the acute
changes module.
Right away in the first 48 hours, several
things occurred to make him feel, and
perform slightly better at altitude.
Again, an early priority is to get more
oxygen into the blood.
A reduction in plasma volume within the
first 48 hours hemoconcentrates the blood,
so there are more red cells per unit
blood.
As a result, hematocrit, or the percent of
red blood cells, will be higher, and
the blood will carry more oxygen.
However, a negative consequence of the
plasma volume loss is a reduction in
cardiac output.
There is a relationship between plasma
volume and stroke volume.
If you decrease plasma volume, there is
less blood returning to
the heart; therefore, less blood leaving
the heart at every beat.
Also, within the first 48 hours, there
will be a spike in Epo,
which will start the production of new red
blood cells.
You probably have heard of Epo in the
context of blood doping,
especially cycling.
Athletes take it to increase red blood
cell production so
they can carry more oxygen to their
tissues during competition Effective, but
dangerous, and a banned activity.
Also in the process of getting rid of
plasma volume,
you excrete some bicarbonate from your
blood buffering system.
The bicarbonate buffering equation is
explained in the glossary.
But essentially, you just need to know
that by having less bicarbonate in
your system more CO2 is available in your
blood and your blood remains more acidic.
We know from our previous discussions that
more CO2 and
more acidity means up regulation of
ventilation.
And up regulation of ventilation will get
more oxygen into the lungs and blood.
The added acidity will also help to
correct the oxyhemoglobin dissociation
curve back to the right which will
facilitate the unloading of oxygen in
the tissues 2,3 DPG a metabolism byproduct
is released
from the red blood cells to further shift
that curve back to the right.
Another way to get more blood to the
tissues is to further increase blood
pressure, to help perfusion and diffusion.
The adaptations that have occurred up to
this point combine to
reduce the stress associated with
altitude.
It's getting easier compared to the acute
exposure.
So, resting at submaximal heart rate will
fall relative to acute.
Interestingly max heart rate will also
fall at this stage and
continue to fall slightly over a prolonged
stay at altitude.
Perhaps it is a protective mechanism
dating back to our days in
the hypoxic utero when we were protecting
ourselves from low oxygen availability.
Don't squirm too much because there's not
enough oxygen to go around.
Okay.
So a couple of days pass, Corey and
I are just starting to feel good.
If we'd stayed longer,
some of the big time adaptations would
have started to kick in.
The long term adaptations require protein
or structural changes that are slow to
happen, but they stick around longer when
they do.
For example, the blood changes continue.
But after three to four weeks instead of a
quick fix of decreasing plasma volume
the new red blood cells have started to be
released making it a more stable change.
A typical response pattern in hematocrit
the percent
of red blood cells in the blood Can be
seen in the graph on your left.
Hematocrit may start around 43 in a young
man at sea level.
After a couple of days on the peak with
the loss of plasma volume,
maybe it'll jump up to 45.
Then, after four weeks,
it gets even higher as more red blood
cells are formed and released.
However, the degree of response varies
from person to person, and
that variability may help explain why some
people benefit from altitude training, and
others do not.
More on that later.
Finally, as you stay longer in altitude,
your body will work to minimize the
diffusion distance in the tissues.
In this way, oxygen will not have to
travel as far within the cell to
get where it needs to go.
This is accomplished in several ways.
First, by increasing levels of myoglobin
within the muscle cell.
Myoglobin is similar to its cousin
hemoglobin, in that it transports oxygen.
But instead of being in the blood, it
works in a cellular environment.
It also serves as a cell storage for
oxygen when it is not being used.
Second, there may be an increase in
mitochondrial density and
aerobic capacity.
That is controversial.
You might think it seems strange that you
would increase mitochondria,
your powerhouse organelles where you use
oxygen.
What is really oxygen delivery, and not
use that is limiting at altitude.
You have plenty of mitochondria at sea
level to use,
the even greater amount of oxygen that is
available.
But there is some indication that the low
oxygen levels in the cell at altitude,
may be sensed by your metabolic pathways
as a training stimulus.
Your cells are saying, make more energy
now.
And one of the best ways to do that,
in the long term, is to increase your
mitochondrial density.
The increased density also decreases the
diffusion distance,
because there is more machinery around to
access.
The data are mixed on this issue.
A synthesis of the literature suggests the
following.
If you are exercising at moderate
elevations,
there seems to be an increase in
mitochondrial density.
On the other hand, if you are sedentary at
moderate elevations, there doesn't seem to
be enough stimulus to start the
mitochondrial bio genesis process.
And finally, if you are at extreme
elevations,
there is plenty of stimulus but you're in
a too much of
a catabolic state to be able to respond by
creating much of anything new.
You're breaking down tissues instead.
The last thing on the list is increased
vascularity which creates more vessels per
unit of muscle.
We definitely see this in high altitude
natives or in situations where animals,
like chicks are raised experimentally in
low oxygen environments.
Hypoxia stimulates angiogenesis or the
formation of new vessels.
However, with lowlanders going to altitude
it may be that there is a loss of
muscle mass which increases the capillary
to fiber ratio.
Independent of actually forming new
vessels.
So all these adaptations get us to the
ultimate prize, Mount Everest.
We started off talking about John Krakauer
in his plane flying to Nepal and
realizing that he would die if his plane
depressurized at that elevation of
Mount Everest.
And now we've arrived at the point where
we can discuss people climbing that
same mountain without supplemental oxygen.
Now Everest is too high to just go and
hang out until you climatize.
It is up in the death zone, where as it
sounds, if you stay too long,
you will not survive.
but, climbers have devised a way to go up
for a while, and
come back down to recover.
Go up again, and come back down.
So on, and so forth.
As many of you know, the first pair to
successfully climb the mountain and
make it back down was Hillary & Tensing in
1953.
You can see in the figure to my right that
the successful climb was
more than 30 years after the first group
that we know of tried to climb it.
Oxygen was first used in an attempt in
1922.
Over the years researchers had done the
calculations and determined that it
was not hu, humanly possible to climb the
mountain without supplemental oxygen.
Meaning that the arterial saturation value
in the thick equation would be too low for
anyone to actually be able to survive up
there.
So surprise, surprise when Reinhold
Messner did it in 1978,
people didn't believe him.
They thought that he'd been sucking oxygen
out of the emergency bottles.
But lo and behold, he went back up again
in 1980, not only proving he didn't
need oxygen, but also accomplishing the
first solo ascent of the mountain.
Well it turns out that, that original
estimate of barometric pressure on
the top of Everest was low by about 17
millimeters of mercury.
Apparently, the proximity of the mountain
to the equator had not been
taken into account.
Which increases the pressure slightly.
And that little difference was sufficient
to drive just enough oxygen into
the system to make the climb possible.
Even so, it is right on the limits of
human performance and
very few people are capable of doing it.
The use of oxygen to climb Everest has
always been controversial.
At first it was thought to be cheating and
unpure.
For awhile, it became a mute point when it
was thought that the mountain couldn't be
climbed without it.
The controversy is now back in the
forefront because the sheer numbers of
people attempting to climb the mountain
and
the number of people that are dying
because of it.
Many argue that the oxygen allows people
to attempt the climb even...
Though they have no business being on such
a treacherous and challenging mountain.
These days, if you have the cash, you can
find someone to take you up.
And too often, that ends in tragedy.
Just a little side note for those that
are, don't know the mountain lore.
On the slide, I've listed Mallory and
Irving in 1924 with a question mark.
To this day we don't know whether they
made it to the top.
They were last seen through binoculars on
the final pitch before the summit.
But they never came back down.
People were convinced that they had
actually summoned the mountain.
In 1999 an expedition went back to try to
recover the bodies and
find some clues like an old camera that
might put the speculation to rest.
They did find the bodies at 27,000 feet,
but no camera and
no indication from where they fell.
I guess we will never know.
Fascinating.
That is it for the adaptation modules.
Next we will get to apply what we learned,
to Cory's data.
Also we will discuss how the altitude
impacted his exercise performance.
Feeling of well being.
Sleeping.
Oh, and the peeing and farting.
Thank you.