Welcome back to the Physiology of
Altitude.
I hope you enjoyed your break.
Let's get right to it.
What is the primary challenge at high
altitude?
No real surprises here.
The primary physiologic challenge at
altitude is the low oxygen pressure.
But it's what our bodies do in response to
the low oxygen that's so interesting.
As you can see from the numbers on my
right, as you go up an elevation,
the percentage of oxygen in the
surrounding air stays the same at 20.93%.
But the barometric pressure falls,
therefore the partial pressure of oxygen
falls too.
If you trace the numbers in the pressure
of Oxygen row on the bottom of the slide,
you'll see the pressure of oxygen on the
summit of Everest is
about one third that of sea level.
As the barometric pressure falls, the air
expands to take up a larger volume.
You may have experienced a classic
illustration of this when
you're in the mountains.
Increased farting?
[LAUGH] The gas in your gut expands and
wants out.
Anyhow, the lower pressure also means that
there are fewer molecules of oxygen and
air, in a given space, which causes the
temperature to fall.
Typical temperatures can range from well
above 100 degrees Fahrenheit at
sea level to as low as 76 below zero
Fahrenheit on Mount Everest,
obviously dependent on time of year,
weather, et cetera.
The falling oxygen pressure is felt
throughout the whole body and
can greatly affect your physical and
cognitive performance.
On my right is a graph of oxygen transport
cascade for three different elevations.
The graph starts where the previous table
left off,
at the oxygen pressure of the surrounding
or inspired air.
What happens next?
The air that you breathe into your lungs,
first mixes with the water vapor and
the carbon dioxide, coming from
metabolism, that is already in your lungs.
So by the time the, that oxygen gets into
the alveolar spaces, which are the gas
exchanging areas of the lungs, it is now a
smaller percentage of the total air mix.
So like with the altitude tents, the
partial pressure of oxygen is less,
because it makes up a smaller portion of
their overall gas.
If you're confused by partial pressures,
that is explained more fully in the
glossary.
Looking at the purple sea level line on
the graph,
you can see that the alveolar gas has an
oxygen partial pressure of about 105.
From there, the gas diffuses into the
arterial blood rather efficiently,
so there's not much loss of pressure
there.
Gases move from high pressure to low
pressure, and the higher the pressure,
the more the driving force is to send that
gas to the other compartments.
The arterial blood that circulates around
the body to the tissues where
the oxygen extract, is extracted as
needed.
Whatever oxygen is not extracted returns
to
the lungs in the mixed venous blood as
illustrated on the graph.
Now look at the blue line, which
represents an altitude of 4300 meters, or
equivalent to Pikes Peak, you can see that
the whole cascade is impacted.
You start lower with the inspired air,
therefore when
the oxygen mixes with the water and the
carbon dioxide, it is again lower.
You get good transfer still into the
arterial blood, but your levels are so
much lower to start that there is much
less oxygen available for
your tissues to extract.
When you look at the green Everest line,
it is even flatter,
meaning there is almost no oxygen
available for your tissues to extract.
We all know that our tissues can't
survive,
much less exercise, without oxygen.
Here is our friendly Fick equation
describing the components of
the oxygen consumption.
The volume of oxygen consumed equal the
cardio output, Q, blood pumped
from the heart per minute times the
arterial venus oxygen difference.
With acute exposure, it is the a component
of the equation that is most impacted.
As the arterial oxygen pressure gets lower
and
lower, the a minus v O2 difference
approaches 0.
So that on the summit of Mount Everest,
even if your heart is racing, you can't
get enough oxygen to the tissues.
Without acclimatization, you would die.
The result of this decreasing oxygen
cascade is that your
maximum work capacity, your VO2 max,
falls.
There's some variability, but the general
rule is that VO2 max will fall off 1% for
each 100 meters over 1500 meters.
So on the summit of Pikes Peak,
that means a falloff in maximum oxygen
consumption of about 27%.
On Everest, 75%, which means someone with
a VO2 max of 60,
which is quite good at sea level, would
fall to less than 15 on Everest.
That is equivalent to walking slowly on
the flat with a light pack.
Can you imagine trying to climb Everest
with that kind of work capacity?
From descriptions by climbers and
scientific studies from the 60s,
we know that in order to move in that
situation,
you need to take about six to eight
breaths per step.
And you still need to rest every 20 to 30
yards,
which is why most people use supplemental
oxygen when they climb Everest.
The limited oxygen availability doesn't
just affect maximum performance, but
affects sub-maximum performance as well.
Let's give Corey a hypothetical challenge
at 4500 meters,
where he tries to exercise to maximum and
compare it to sea level.
His VO2 max falls about 30%.
But now, a set task, say riding the bike
at 125 watts, which is depicted
in the red on the graph, represents a
higher percentage of his maximum.
Therefore, everything he does will seem
harder at altitude.
Climbing, making camp, competing in a
cycling event will all be harder and
it won't be able to sustain that same
absolute workload as long at altitude.
Since we spend most of our time performing
sub-maximal tasks,
the sub-maximal impact will be more
noticeable decrement in performance.
It is logical that being more fit should
help you do better at altitude.
And it's certainly does in some ways,
requires great strength and
stamina to climb mountains.
But interestingly, some of the advantage
that fit people have at
sea level relative to less fit people is
lost at altitude,
because the fall in VO2 max is a
percentage.
So a recreational athlete with a VO2 max
of 45 at
sea level will drop to about 12 on
Everest.
Similarly, a much fitter guy with a sea
level VO2 max of 60 will drop to 15.
So there's a convergence of these values
at altitude.
Why is that?
It has to do with the concept of transit
time.
Transit time is the amount of time that
blood is in contact with
the exchanging tissues.
In this case, the lungs.
Highly fit people have very high cardiac
outputs,
meaning that their hearts are pumping
larger volumes of blood at
a very rapid rate through the heart and
lungs.
So the blood has less time to fully
saturate with oxygen as it
passes through the lungs.
Remember how I said earlier that the
higher the gas pressure,
the greater the driving force of movement
for that gas?
Therefore, at sea level, the high cardiac
output in athletes is less problematic,
because the gas diffuses into the blood
more rapidly with the higher pressures.
However at altitude, the diffusion rate
slows, so the arterial
oxygen saturation falls as cardiac output
increases at the higher work loads.
Thus, VO2 max declines to a greater extent
in fit versus unfit people.
In summary, more fit equals higher Q
equals lower transit time.
Shorter transit time in fit means less
oxygen in the blood at
higher workloads and greater falloff in
VO2 max.
The bad news is that we are challenged to
perform at altitude,
even if we are highly fit.
However, the good news is that our bodies
respond to
the low oxygen right away to try to help
us cope.
We've spent this last rather extended
module talking about the challenges to
performance at high altitude.
Next we'll move on to what our bodies
actually do about it.
Congratulations.
You survived Module 2.
Take the practice quiz for this module,
and
then go on to Module 3 to learn about the
initial physiologic responses to altitude,
and see how Corey actually performed in
the chamber relative to what was expected.
Thank you.