Welcome to Module 6.
All about Corey, his questions, his bodily
functions and his data.
We're going to apply some of what we
learned in
general about acclimatization to Corey's
experience on the peak.
First, just a reminder of the questions we
left you with at the end of
the Pike's Peak story video.
Why did Corey sleep so badly on the first
night?
Why did Corey's submaximal performance
improve?
Why didn't his maximum performance
Sleeping, peeing, and farting, oh my!
Let's start with sleep.
There are several things that can
interfere with sleep at altitude.
First, symptoms of acute mountain sickness
like headache,
frequently are present in the early days
at altitude.
Both Corey and I had a splitting headache
that first day.
Second, people experience periodic
breathing at attitude,
referred to as Cheyne Stokes breathing.
This condition happens quite frequently,
but
it is not associated with altitude illness
per se.
Results from a conflict within the body
over a control of breathing during sleep.
We talked about this before, oxygen
sensors in the body tell the brain to
increase ventilation which causes the
lungs to blow off CO2.
But CO2 sensors in the body then tell the
brain to slow breathing,
as a result, breathing then stops for
up to 10 to 12 seconds, until the oxygen
sensors take over again.
The first large breath after the pause
will sometimes wake the person up with
a feeling of breathlessness or
suffocation.
Also generally when you sleep, your
metabolic rate declines which
further slows breathing and can exacerbate
low oxygen levels in the blood.
Third, you may recall from the video that
Corey got up four times to
pee in the night.
It's hard to sleep when you have to pee.
So why the frequent urination?
Well, reason one is hydrate, hydrate,
hydrate.
That is the advice that people are given
when they go to altitude.
The dryer air, increased ventilation, and
high energy outputs with rapid evaporation
of sweat accelerate fluid losses.
To prevent dehydration it is wise to up
your fluid intake.
Reason 2, is it's actually part of the
acclimatization process.
Can you think back to module 5 and
remember what I might be talking about.
Loss of plasma volume.
In an attempt to hemo concentrate the
blood,
people excrete excess plasma volume in the
form of urine.
Throw the excreted bi-carbon there and you
get lots of frothy urine.
Believe me I know this because we did
urine collections in
one of our experiments on the peak and we
all rotated processing those collections.
Not my favorite part of the experience,
but all for the good of science aye.
If we're just going to get rid of our
plasma volume anyway why are we advised to
hydrate at altitude.
It has to do with where the water is
coming from.
If you lose too much fluid before your
body sends the proper hormonal signals to
reduce your plasma volume, the water will
be drawn from other cells and
compartments like your brain.
Basically, you want your body to make the
change at it's own pace and
not force it into a dehydrated state.
Okay.
You've all experienced it.
Flatus expulsion.
Corey in the video team started to notice
it on the way up the mountain on
the first day.
During my Pike's Peak research tenure, I
remember some pretty fragrant mornings,
walking to the participant dorm room with
10, not so clean, gaseous young men.
As I mentioned in one of the first slides
it is a simple matter of physics.
As the pressure of altitude decreases the
volume of
the gas in your gut increases and wants
out.
In addition you are frequently eating an
unfamiliar diet when you
are trekking in the mountains, like lots
of nuts and dried fruit.
So that can make the problem worse.
Let's move onto the serious questions,
shall we?
Why did Corey's Submax performance improve
by day three?
To my right is a table of Corey's data
during the treadmill test at sea level
within the first two hours of arrival on
the peak and then 48 hours later.
The data posted is from stage five which
is the same absolute work load in
each case.
Therefore, as row one indicates, Corey
required essentially the same amount of
oxygen to do the same amount of work under
each of the three conditions.
Rather than walk you through each of the
numbers, just pause the video and
take a moment to look through the pattern
of the numbers with the following
thoughts in mind.
Do the numbers continue to change over
time, or
do some revert back closer to sea level?
Is the pattern what you would expect given
the adaptations we have discussed so
far in this section?
Figure it all out?
Good.
Now, what are the adaptations that cause
these numbers to behave the way they do?
I can read it right off the slide.
Increased hematocrit and increased
ventilation means more oxygen per
unit blood, resulting in a higher oxygen
saturation on day three.
Therefore, epinephrin and heart rate can
be lower for a given work load.
Overall the work load felt less stressful
for Corey, was easier to accomplish, and
it was closer to his steady state.
So now the tricky question,
why didn't Corey's maximum performance
improve on day three relative to day one?
This question is about maximum
performance.
So, you will note in the table that he
went three stages farther at
sea level than at altitude.
His VO2 max was also much higher at sea
level and you may remember it
is also much higher than his maximum value
on the bicycle 65 versus 50.
Except for trained cyclists, a person's
VO2 max is
usually about 15% higher on a treadmill
test than on a bicycle test.
Non-cyclists experience localized leg
fatigue before they
maxed out their cardiovascular systems on
the bike.
Also, running uses more muscle mass to
consume the oxygen and
represents a more familiar movement to
most people.
In Corey's case, the difference is even
greater because our buddy Corey is
clearly a track athlete, not a cyclist.
Anyway, again pause the video as long as
you like and investigate the data.
Are the numbers what you would expect?
Do they give you any clues to the ans, to
answer the question?
Take a look.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Did you find any clues?
Let me put up the thick equation as a
reminder.
Some things are definitely getting better,
like the arterial oxygen saturation and
ventilation, but max heart rate is going
down.
That is going to negatively impact the VO2
max.
Interestingly, VO2 max does not usually
improve substantially at altitude.
Is because you get helpful adaptations
like increased hermatocrit,
red blood cells and saturation.
But on the other side of the equation
there are negative factors in terms of
maximum performance such as decreased
plasma volume, stroke volume, and
maxed heart rate.
Also the increased viscosity of the blood
and
increased blood pressure combine to
elevate after load.
Afterload is the pressure that the heart
has to fight against when emptying.
A higher afterload can impair cardiac
output further.
The fall and max heart rate may be a way
for
us to protect ourselves against the
potential risk of damaging tissue
hypoxia as a result of doing too much high
intensity work at altitude.
Well, that was fun!
But I'm sorry to say it is not all fun and
games at altitude.
Take the practice quiz and I will see you
in the next module.
Thank you.