Welcome to the Physiology of Altitude
Module 7, Risks, Consequences, and
Practical Tips.
As the title implies, we have several
different areas to cover, and
so an outline is more useful for this
particular module.
You can see on my right that we will be
talking about the impact of
altitude on your cognitive function, and
then the causes and
symptoms of altitude-related illnesses.
We will then move on to
strategies to make your time in the
mountains healthy and happy.
Finally, we will address topics related to
altitude competition and training.
If low oxygen availability impacts your
body so
profoundly, it only makes sense that it'll
impact your brain as well.
Sure enough, on the right is a summary of
years of research investigating
the cognitive function deficits that occur
with increasing elevation.
Light sensitivity is the first to be
impaired.
Then visual acuity.
Postural stability, meaning balance.
Cognition, coding, reaction time.
All of these critical functions are
impacted at the time when you are in
highly risky situations and really need to
be thinking clearly.
For example, when climbing Everest,
impaired cognition makes even simple math
like how much time do I have left before
my oxygen runs out, nearly impossible.
So you need to be prepared for that and
make as many decisions as possible, prior
to reaching the higher elevations.
Remember, you're not at the top of your
game when you're at the top of a mountain.
There are some other goodies you need to
worry about when heading to high altitude.
And those include the altitude related
illnesses of acute mountain sickness.
High altitude pulmonary edema and high
altitude cerebral edema.
We will stat with AMS.
On my right are a series of locations of
increasing elevation.
The upper limit of permanent residence is
thought to be around 17,000 feet.
Above that your body can never quite adapt
and you remain in a catabolic state where
you're essentially breaking yourself down
and getting weaker and sicker.
Apparently, some gold miners in Chile
lived above 19,000 feet for
about two years in the mid 80s.
Although they were never officially
studied, John West,
an altitude researcher, described them as
a little bit blue.
So that didn't sound very promising.
Anyway, the symptoms of AMS start as mild
and get worse and worse as you go up.
Risk of AMS is thought to start, for most
people, at around 9,000 feet.
But even at that, even at the elevation of
Denver,
some people can experience lightheadedness
and headache.
As you go higher you might experience more
discomfort that includes
the digestive tract, the lungs and sleep
patterns, then problems breathing,
anorexia or lack of appetite and G.I.
issues.
As you approach upper limit of permanent
residence, you may feel weak and
tired and above that you only have limited
time to survive.
Let's take a look at how many people get
AMS, and
when it usually develops, to see how big
of a problem it really is.
First of all, it takes about six to 12
hours to kick in.
When I was involved with the Pikes Peak
studies, we used to fly people from
Stanford out to Colorado, the night before
taking them to the peak.
They would sleep in Colorado Springs in
our apartments breathing supplemental
oxygen.
So it still felt like they were at sea
level.
Then we'd drive them up the mountain at
5:00 am the next morning when they
arrived on the peak we would take off
their oxygen masks and
boom sea level to 4300 meters
instantaneously.
It's funny because all the participants
would do the same thing.
They take a couple deep breaths [SOUND]
and
then say, this isn't so bad, I think I'm
going to be okay.
We'd all nod and say well hope so, and
then 12 hours later quarter of them or
so would be pretty uncomfortable, which
brings us to the percentages,
above 2500 meters about 25% will
experience AMS.
Between 4500 meters and 5500 meters 50 to
85% will be impacted.
Above 5500 meters pretty much everyone
will have some type of symptoms with
mild and moderate AMS that usually takes
one to three days to resolve.
In our story videos we gave Corey a
questionnaire to monitor his AMS symptoms.
Of course, in the chamber his exposure was
too short to develop any symptoms.
But, on the peak he did have some minor
symptoms listed on the slide.
He did pretty well, though.
What are the risk factors for developing
AMS?
How come some people get it and others
don't?
And are you at risk?
Well, here are the risk factors outlined
by Bartsch & Swenson
in the recent New England Journal of
Medicine article.
First.
A previous history of AMS.
If you've had it before you are more
likely to get it again because it's
an indication that you are less able to
buffer the normal brain swelling that
occurs at altitude.
Interestingly younger than 46 is a risk
factor.
This is one of the few physical things
that I know of
that actually gets better with age.
Maybe it's behavioral, for example
climbing less rapidly and aggressively.
Maybe it's wisdom, making smarter choices.
Or maybe it's physical.
Some have theorized that the slight brain
shrinkage that occurs with
age allows more room in the skull for the
brain edema that occurs at altitude,
thus reducing pressure on the brain and
reducing symptoms of AMS.
At this time, the reason is unclear, but
they are still looking for reasons.
History of migraines also disposes people
to AMS.
And as with many things,
there is thought to be a genetic component
that makes some people more susceptible.
Scientists are doing gene array
experiments to try to
figure out whether they can predict who
will get AMS, but it is not clear-cut.
One test that has been somewhat successful
is the Hypoxic Ventilatory Response.
In this test a person breathes gases of
lower and
lower oxygen levels and their ventilatory
response is measured.
The point at which they start increasing
the ventilation tells us how they
will probably respond at altitude.
Those people in the upper percentages who
start increasing their
breathing right away, were probably would
not be as susceptible to AMS at altitude.
Those people are not very responsive to
the low oxygen, will likely do poorly.
The problem is, that there's this whole
middle range, where most people fall, and
the test is not predictive.
What's next?
Women are more at risk than men.
It is unclear why but women are also more
susceptible to migraines.
So perhaps there's some type of
neurological connection there.
And finally it has been well established
that fitness is not protective.
That is not to say that fitness isn't
important.
Being fitter will definitely help you get
up the mountain, but
it won't protect you from AMS.
There are behavioral risk factors as well.
Essentially, anything that lowers the
oxygen content of
your blood will increase the risk.
For example, a rapid rate of ascent.
The faster you go, the less time you have
to acclimatize No pre-acclimatization and
early hard exercise can lower arterial
oxygen levels.
In Cory's data, we showed that he dropped
his
saturations into the 60s during that first
day one exercise test.
The cause of AMS related to brain
swelling.
In response to low oxygen, the linings of
the blood vessels release signalling
molecules that cause the blood vessels to
expand within the brain.
The permeability of those vessels and
brain blood pressure also increases,
causing leakage of fluid into the
surrounding tissue.
Brain swelling is a universal response to
altitude.
So it is the degree of swelling, and how
the body deals with that swelling,
that differentiates Someone with AMS.
AMS may be just the lower end of a
continuum that leads to
a high altitude cerebral edema in the
unfortunate.
High altitude cerebral edema takes your
swollen head to the next step.
The first indication is a headache that
does not respond to typical painkillers.
Other symptoms include, mental confusion,
ataxia, or
uncoordinated movements, and poor
cognition, cognition decision making.
For example, not making sense, removing
gloves when it's freezing out,
passing up food, taking excessive risks,
etcetera.
If untreated it could very rapidly lead to
unconsciousness and death.
High altitude pul, pulmonary edema has a
similar pathology but
involves the lungs rather than the brain.
Symptoms usually appear between days two
and four of exposure and
are proceeded by pulmonary hypertension
and patchy vasoconstriction in the lungs.
Symptoms are listed on the slide but
coughing, labored breathing, gurgling,
turning blue or cyanosis are classic
indications.
Both HACE and
HAPE occur much less frequently than AMS
but they are much more deadly.
Let's move on to some practical
information.
Perhaps you would like to climb Mt
Kilimanjaro for
your 50th birthday, but you are afraid of
getting altitude illness.
How should you prepare?
First you want to make sure you are in
optimal physical shape, not because it
will protect you from AMS but because it
will help you reach the top successfully.
Independent of illness.
So keep training.
What about the illness part?
If you have some flexibility, consider the
following.
Figure out a way to get some prior
exposure.
Ideally, stay a week between 2,000 and
3,000 meters prior to any higher ascent.
While there, take day hikes to higher
elevations.
If you can't stay up at altitude,
take intermittent trips above 3000 meters
in the weeks or
months leading up to the trip .The 3000
meter is start on the slide as a caveat.
Recent research by scientists at Usarum
have shown that normal baric hypoxia
may not help the acclimatization process
the same way as hyperbaric hypoxia.
This is important for two reasons.
First using altitude tents in your bedroom
is not a good way to prepare for
your climb.
And second, there may be bigger
differences in
the two modalities than we had originally
thought and
more research is needed to determine the
foundation of those differences.
Ascent slowly if you want to reduce your
risk of illness.
It is recommended that if you are climbing
above 3,000 meters that you do not exceed
300 to 500 meters per day and that you
take a rest day every three to four days.
Those two things alone can reduce your
risk of AMS by 50%.
Especially at the beginning take it easy.
As we've discussed,
the higher your intensity the lower your
blood oxygen saturation.
Make sure you are getting enough fluid and
calories especially carbohydrate to match
your higher rate of energy expenditure.
You will be burning extra calories not
just from exercise, but
from the elevated basal metabolic rate
that occurs as altitude as well.
About 200 k cho's per day at 4300 meters.
Also, you can't make new red blood cells
without iron.
So, make sure your ferritin stores are
sufficient.
Based on your previous experience in the
mountains, and
the prior list in this module, you can
determine whether you're at high risk.
If so consider talking with your physician
about getting Acetazolamide,
brand named Diamox, to start taking before
you go.
Diamox is well established prophylactic
for altitude illness.
There are some minor risks such as tingly
fingers, bad tasting carbonated beverages,
reduced exercise performance, and nausea.
So it's best to test the drug in dosing at
sea level before you go to
make sure you can tolerate it.
If your elaborate preparation doesn't work
and
you end up with some degree of altitude
illness, you have several options.
Over the counter pain medications can help
reduce your headache from AMS.
For a temporary fix, you can try breathing
supplemental oxygen,
which could reduce the severity of your
AMS symptoms and
may, in some cases, stop and reverse the
progression of HAPE.
Various drug options that reduce
inflammation, lower blood pressure, or
reduce pulmonary pressure can be taken
either as prevention or treatment.
However without symptom amelioration
Pressurization in
a portable hyperbaric chamber, and descent
as soon as possible is required.
Enough about illnesses.
Let's talk about competition at altitude.
The second bit of practical information is
which track and
field events would be most affected when
competing at moderate altitude?
If you think about it, it makes sense that
those events that are dependent on
oxygen based fuel sources would be most
negatively impacted.
Long distance and
dirt events are the ones that use oxygen
based fuel sources the most.
your oxygen based fuel sources are not the
quickest source of energy.
But they represent a large reserve of
energy within your body that can
sustain you for prolonged events.
In contrast, events that are performed at
high intensities for
a short period of time rely on non
oxidative energy sources.
These events like sprinting, may actually
benefit from the lower air
density altitude which lowers the air
resistance to forward movement.
Throwing events are mixed.
Those events that require air buoyancy
like the discus are negatively impacted.
Whereas those that overcome air resistance
like the shot-put are improved
at altitude.
A great illustration of this difference is
the comparison in results between
the Mexico City Olympics in 1968 versus
the Tokyo Olympics four years earlier.
Runners in all distances shorter than 800
meters did better in Mexico City than in
Tokyo four years earlier.
In contrast, runners in all distances of
1500 meters and
up did worse than in previous Olympics.
In Tokyo.
Mexico City turned out to be a personal
best for many sprinters.
So if you're a sprinter and you want to
break your own record, go up.
Practical information three,
does altitude training improve performance
at A, altitude or B, sea level.
The first part is easy.
Yes, unless you stay too high or too long
so that you can't train hard enough and
you start to de-train over time.
The second part is not as easy.
It depends on a lot of factors.
Whose doing it?
How hard you're training?
How high?
How long?
What type?
Et cetera.
Let's explore these mixed results a bit
further.
There are two basic types of altitude
training,
classic which is when you go to a moderate
altitude, stay and train at that altitude.
The US olympic training center in colorado
springs has been using this strategy to
train its athletes for more than a decade.
The other more recent strategy is the live
high, train low paradigm.
As the name implies, the stimulus is
intermittent.
With sometimes spent living at altitude,
but
with the training under normal sea-level
conditions.
There are certain environments where that
that is possible in the field, but
the usual method for this type of training
is done with altitude tents or chambers.
The ladder strategy is supposed to
overcome some of the drawbacks of
the classic altitude training.
We will discuss in a moment.
Let's talk first about classic altitude
training and
sea level performance, there are some
great things about it,
most people experience and increase in red
blood cells, hematocrit, hemoglobin Maybe
even an increased vascularization,
although that probably takes too long.
On the other hand, we talked about how
plasma volume,
cardiac output, buffering capacity all
decrease.
And the increased blood viscosity that
occurs with the elevated hematocrit,
means that the heart has to work harder to
move the blood around your system.
In fact it can be quite dangerous to
undergo altitude training if you
are then going to be competing in a hot
environment where dehydration is a risk.
On occasion cyclists have died during long
races from cardiac issues that may have
been compounded by excessive blood doping
and dehydration.
And the ugly.
As we talked about before, there is an
increase in relative intensity in
altitude, meaning every sub-maximum work
load feels harder.
Therefore you can't train as hard.
Although, some think that the relative
intensity is more important than
the absolute intensity for training, there
are likely some high-end neurological and
metabolic pathways that are not optimally
used.
Overall then, it's kind of a mixed bag.
The good and the bad balance out
differently in different people.
So what about live high, train low?
Well, this method overcomes some of the
drawbacks of classic training.
You can train at your normal intensity,
and
there will be less of a negative response
in plasma volume because you
spend some of every day in a normoxic
state.
The bad part is it is not nearly as strong
of a stimulus.
Much debate still exists on how long of an
exposure is needed to be effective.
Although there is a great deal of
variability in noise and
the data, a recent meta analysis suggests
that approximately nine and
a half hours per day, and between 2500 and
3500 meters For at least two weeks, is
required for Optimal performance benefit.
However, it should also be noted, that a
followup commentary on that same paper.
Suggested that a far greater exposure is
needed on the order of 20 hours per day,
at 2,000 to 2,500 meters for no less than
28 days.
Links to both of those papers are provided
in the glossaries and
resource section, if you'd like to read
more details on that topic.
As you can tell from the last few
sentences on the previous slide,
the debate on altitude training continues
after decades of study.
And it's not just how much exposure is
needed, but whether it works at all.
Some argue that any improvement that is
seen in response to
altitude training is actually a placebo or
training camp affect.
The studies pick these athletes,
put them in a very motivating, isolated
camps with expert trainers and
of course they're going to do better when
they come back down.
Only one study thus far has actually been
controlled with
a comparable sea level training camp.
But, even that control is not enough to
resolve that issue.
Because, just believing it works, ie, the
placebo effect, may be enough.
Another thing to consider though,
is that many studies don't show us
statistically significant improvement.
But sports performance does not rely on
statistics.
The difference between a gold medal and an
also ran may only be 0.5%,
a concept known as the smallest worthwhile
change.
The problem is when looking at differences
that small, there's a lot of noise in
the data collection so it's hard to make
any definitive statement.
One consistent thing that comes up is all
the papers,
in all the papers is individual
variability.
In every study, some people do better,
some people do worse.
And, some people stay the same.
When I asked the Stanford athletes in my
class who've gone to an Olympic training
center, whether they thought it worked for
them, I'd get answers across the board.
It may be that those people who have a
strong EPO response, and
that's an increase in red blood cells,
benefit and the others do not.
Whatever the mechanism, physiologic,
placebo or
other, if it works for you, go for it.
We hope you enjoyed this high-altitude
section and
found the information useful and relevant.
Remember, treat the mountains with respect
because they are a powerful force to
be reckoned with.
And we didn't even talk about the extreme
weather and variable conditions.
Be careful out there.
Thank you.