Hello everyone.
We're here at USARIEM, the U.S.
Army Research Institute of Environmental
Medicine.
And that's right outside Boston and
Natick, Massachusetts.
I have the pleasure of talking right now
with Steve Muza,
who is the Acting Chief of the Thermal
Mountain Medicine Division.
And Chuck Fulco, who is a Researcher
Emeritus.
And between the two of them,
they have over 60 years of high altitude
research experience in this unit.
So they, they know everything there is to
know about research,
altitude research in this facility.
So Steve, starting with you,
can you tell us a little bit about what
you do at this facility.
>> Thank you for that introduction.
>> [LAUGH] You're welcome.
>> Everything that you need to know, I
don't know.
Well, the Army Research Institute of
Environmental Medicine
is here to understand, research, and
determine the effects of the environment
and the occupations, occupational work,
that war fighters do, that soldiers,
sailors, airmen,
Marines when they conduct both peacetime,
wartime, and training activities.
Most of the military's activities take
place outdoors.
Therefore, they're exposed to the extreme
environments of heat, cold, high altitude,
even water immersion.
And our job is to identify what risks
those pose to the war fighter and
how we can mitigate those risks or reduce
them by either acclimating them
through physiological processes or
improving their nutrition or
pharmacological interventions that could
sustain and optimize their performance.
>> Mm-Hm.
And so do the studies that you do, do they
come from the top down or
do they come from the field up.
Like, needs in the field that generate the
ideas for the research.
>> It's actually an interaction of both.
There are needs that are identified by the
folks in the field.
We call those requirements.
They then send up through their chain of
command, and across through, and
usually through what we call the Training
and Doctrine Command, TRADOC.
They, they send those over across to the
acquisition research logistics command,
and which comes down to us.
>> Mm hm.
>> But,
we also are required and really, we're
looking for what are the state of the art,
new emerging technology's knowledge, that
we can leverage to improve performance.
So I would say, it's a mix.
Maybe 60% in fact may come from us.
>> Mm hm.
>> Because we see how things are moving
along and where there's potential for
making major leaps and capabilities, and
then there's those folks who tell us we
got a problem, what can we do about it?
>> Um-hm.
As a researcher myself,
I suspect that you have more ideas than
you have time to research.
>> Absolutely.
>> There's a lot of stuff going on.
Great.
>> There, there is.
And, and we in fact frequently will tell
other people.
Hey, why don't you try this study.
>> Uh-huh.
>> It's not for us to do everything.
Part of our job is to know what is already
being done in academic laboratories,
private laboratories, foundations, bring
that, disseminate that information into
the military but then also say, gee, this
looks like a promising area of research.
We don't have the funding or the
capability to do it.
Why not you, you know.
>> Uh-huh.
>> You suggest to
somebody else that they do it.
>> Yeah, because you have such a unique
setting here with all these chambers and
devices that you must be well setup to do
things that no one else can do,
in the world probably.
>> Well, we like to think that.
>> [LAUGH]
>> There's several things about,
about the capabilities.
One, we do have as you just witnessed.
A hyperbaric chamber that's not just a low
pressure chamber but
it's also an environmental chamber in
terms of both the range of
temperatures from 25 degrees below
freezing, to 125 degrees above.
Yeah.
you know, humidity's running from 10% to
85%.
We've used that chamber to simulate a
cold, dark, damp submerged, submarine.
>> [LAUGH] That's lovely.
>> We've used that chamber to simulate a
cold,
damp winter day or a hot dry summer day.
In addition, we have water immersion
facilities, we have thermal facilities to
study the war fighter human function in,
in these extreme environments.
We also have a regular basic performance
laboratory.
We can outfit it with virtually any type
of ogometer,
treadmill, cyclergometer, rowing machine.
We can run a wide range of both
noninvasive and invasive studies.
And then on top of that,
we have our Pike's Peak facility at the
summit of Pike's Peak, Colorado.
That we've had the pleasure of working
together at, and 114.
[LAUGH] 114,000 feet!
>> 114,000, I'm, I'm really going over the
top there.
>> Yeah.
>> But as you know, we can do,
use that facility to study long duration
acclimatization.
>> Yeah.
Then a lot of your studies have to do with
stressing an individual.
Do you find, you have trouble recruiting
subjects, or
are people jumping at the opportunity to
participate in these fabulous studies?
>> We really have not had a problem
recruiting test volunteers.
We recruit from both military and
civilian.
We find that the military are very
interested in knowing and
pushing their limits and understanding
both their own personal performance,
whether it's altitude again heat or cold.
And we find that there's,
there's a population of civilians, who as
we all know, I enjoy the outdoors.
Many people enjoy the outdoors.
We have a rich community,
of academic community here in the Boston
metropolitan area.
Many universities with outdoor clubs, with
athletes who
really want to see what it's like to work
either in a high altitude environment or
a heat, or a cold environment.
>> Yeah.
>> There's also,
there's also a deep sense of wanting to do
something for
their fellow soldiers as well.
That's what motivates a lot of the
soldiers to put up with a lot of the,
the ill feelings that you might get.
>> Uh-huh.
>> In high altitude.
And how difficult it is.
>> Yeah.
>> So.
>> Yeah, speaking of that,
you were involved some time ago, in
operation Everest two.
Which is an amazing study.
>> Yeah.
>> And why don't you tell us a little bit
about that?
because, that must really required some
real dedication on the part of
the subjects.
>> Well, well it was an international
study.
We had probably 50, 60 scientists here
from all over the world.
And because it was such a unique study.
Unique being that we were going to
simulate a trek up Mt Everest.
So, we had eight volunteers go in that
chamber for 42 days.
And because of the uniqueness of that
study it seemed like,
every, every scientist wanted to, to
collect every bit of data, every day.
It was a massive study.
We did everything invasive that you could
imagine.
We took lots of blood.
We did muscle biopsies.
We did Swan-Ganz arterial sticks.
>> And explain what that is.
>> Oh.
We went up through the femoral artery up
into the heart.
And where we can look at pressures in the
heart.
[INAUDIBLE] pressures and so forth.
To see exactly what happens over a period
of 42 days of a climatization.
We did cardiac output studies, respiratory
studies, sleeping studies.
It was absolutely amazing.
And how did the subject survive that?
So 42 days, in a little box, being watched
24/7.
>> They
>> Must have been challenging.
>> Well, they were specifically recruited
by the principal investigator,
which was Charlie Houston.
So, with the idea that they could get
along with each other.
He went through 65 volunteers, and
actually chose ten.
Eight started the study and after 20,000
feet, two dropped out.
And we ended up with six.
But they, they seemed to all get along,
they didn't have much time at altitude to
do anything other than participate in
studies.
But it was, it was a great study,
absolutely great study.
>> So, when you got up to the very high
altitudes, 29,000 feet.
What would happen if an investigator
didn't have the oxygen?
Are there any examples.
>> Well, we actually found out,
unfortunately.
It wasn't quite 29,000 feet, but
we were up at about 27,000 feet, if I
remember correctly.
And we were doing an experiment, and
somebody stepped on
someone else's oxygen hose and actually
pulled it out of the wall.
And within about 30 seconds or so, that
investigator was on the floor.
So, we plugged him back in,
[LAUGH] and the investigator got up, and
continued his experiment.
>> Now, you guys are some fun loving guys,
are you sure that wasn't intentional?
Like, let's just see what happens, how
long it takes?
How to hit the floor?
>> No, it would have been to another
investigator if it was intentional.
>> Yeah [LAUGH] Yeah, I mean that, one of
the things that I learned working with
both of you on Pike's Peak is that it is,
it is really such a bonding experience.
Because there is so much going on in that
little brief period.
And you're working so hard.
And you're exhausted but
you're all sort of working as a team
toward this common goal.
And it's, a really rewarding way to do
research, as opposed to,
you know, working in your own little lab,
doing your own thing.
Just to have this team of people, that are
helping each other out, and
investigating such interesting questions.
So, I'm sure, in that situation, where it
was brutal, but
you were I'm sure you had some life-long
friendships that were made from that.
>> Absolutely, yeah, absolutely.
>> And many of them stayed here.
With you in the facility, and you've
worked with him for almost 30 years.
For both of you, and that's a pretty
unique experience.
It seems like when people come here, they
stay.
>> Yep.
>> Because it doesn't get much better than
this.
>> No, it doesn't.
It really doesn't.
>> It was, I have to tell you that going
back to my graduate career program, I was
looking at an interest in high altitude
physiology and environmental physiology.
And originally I wanted to be an Air Force
aerospace physiologist.
>> Mm-Hm.
>> That didn't quite work out,
but I knew of this lab and I, I said this
is a great opportunity and
when I went to look for a job,
I sought out individuals who were here
and, and that was the beginning of it all.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, and 1980,
it's actually 30 years ago this month that
I said yes, I'd come here to this.
>> Uh-huh.
>> To this research institute.
>> That's amazing.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, what's the biggest change, if you
had to pick one change over that period
that you've noticed, over the 30 years.
>> He retired.
>> [LAUGH] I would, I would have to say,
and I think it's probably true of all
facilities of, of this type, all research
facilities, that the regulatory.
>> Yeah.
>> [LAUGH] Has changed quite a bit,
quite a bit.
I don't know that we could've done
Operation Everest two in,
in these times any more.
>> Mm-hm.
Especially with the very invasive studies
that we've, we had done.
Yeah.
>> And, and
the amount of blood that we took from
those fellas,.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I'm not sure that we
could do that again.
And that's a direct reflection of the, the
regulatory environment that we're in.
>> Yeah.
So, what is the next thing,
what are you working on right now, for
this year?
Well this year is really a continuation of
the last several years,
what really came out of the last dozen
years,
was a poor understanding of how bad these
extreme environments are.
And, things have gotten much more
quantitative,
it's like we know if you go to high
altitude you slow down.
Chuck showed that in 1998.
He, you know, put together a meta-analysis
and showed how the impact of
altitude affects the ability to perform
certain long duration activities.
But what's really been, and we all know
that,
you go to altitude you get the potential
for acute mountain sickness.
But it's really become more quantitative.
What is the percent?
Much like the, when you look at community
flu models.
Mm-hm.
>> You want to know that in this
community,
because it maybe have an elderly
population more of,
more of preschool population, what's the
probability of flu.
>> Mm-hm.
>> With you know, and how I'm going to
deal with it to mitigate or
minimize it, the same thing that goes with
altitude.
How big of a probability and, and also
risk of altitude sickness is.
>> Mm-hm.
>> If I do a mission for
12 hours at 12,000 feet.
>> And that has some planned personnel so
if 30% are going to be out,
then you need to know that.
>> [CROSSTALK] Or in some cases, they
don't even realize it,
just because you're going to 14,000 feet,
if you're doing it for
only four hours, the chances of there
being acute mountain sickness is rare.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And so now we're producing these
models, these dynamic models that
include both time at altitude, the
altitude, plus a lot of other factors.
We're doing the same with work performance
largely based on the initial models that
Chuck developed, as I said back in the
90s.
An interesting thing is that the math is
proving out what he saw back in 1998.
So, you know, validating [LAUGH] Chuck's
original observation.
>> [LAUGH]
>> so.
>> Told you so.
>> [LAUGH] The area of the climatization,
you know,
we knew that sleep high, you know, climb
high, sleep low.
How many days, how many hours, how fast
should you ascend?
There's been general guidance.
>> Mm-hm.
>> For decades.
In fact, Charlie Houston published some of
the first guidance, particularly for
climbing above 12, 14,000 feet.
But it still was very general, very broad
based.
Now we're actually dev, devised, we
actually have a mathematical model for
altitude acclimatization.
Which will then, you know.
We looked at that as a cost benefit
analysis.
>> Mm hmm.
>> What's the, you know, and much more
quantitative.
Where we're going and then, beyond that,
I think we're moving in the area of more
molecular physiology.
We're really involved now.
We're looking at biomarkers that could be
looked at
to assess an individual's susceptibility.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To both work impairments at altitude,
altitude illness, or even the degree of
acclimatization.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I really think that in a few years, we
may have something as simple as
spit on a stick or pee on a stick, much
like a urine pregnancy test where
she says you are acclimated for either
altitude or heat.
Uh-huh.
>> Or you're not.
>> Uh-huh. Uh-huh. >> And
then that will help leaders and unit
commanders devise ways of identifying
not only the best personnel but, personnel
that maybe need more training.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And, and need more time.
Yeah.
So, besides the gene issues which are now
just emerging about who's susceptible.
You know, you, you two.
You are the guys about acclimatization and
getting adapted.
So, if you were going to recommend
something that someone could do if
they were going to 14,000 feet.
To minimize their risk of AMS.
>> Mm-hm.
>> What would that be?
What do you recommend?
>> Well, it's funny you should ask we, we
did a study not to long ago.
Where we took folks from here, brought
them to the Air Force Academy,
then again we do a lot of collaborations
with outside groups.
We welcome it.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And we were at roughly 7,000 feet.
And we stayed there for six days before we
went up to Pike's Peak.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Of course, previous to that we had,
had other volunteers going directly from
sea level directly up Pike's Peak, so
that was sort of our control group.
And what we found was that acute mountain
sickness with just six days being
at 7,000 feet before 14,000.
Was reduced 70, 80% if I remember
correctly.
Uh-hm.
>> And perhaps more surprisingly is that
exercise performance was actually
improved by above 40 to 50% as well.
>> Uh-hm.
>> So it, its, it, it's a great way to go
people don't get sick,
at 7,000 feet are not anything worse than
about a mild headache.
>> Mm-hm.
>> For example.
But yet this tremendous acclimatization
that goes on.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
that can really benefit people before they
go up to high altitude.
>> But, but not everyone has six days.
Like, if you're an athlete and you have a
job.
>> That, that's right [CROSSTALK]
>> And you want to, you, you going to go
up and climb a mountain.
You don't have the six days.
So, what are some things people can do in
the short term?
Well, one of the things that we're looking
at this year is that prior to going out to
Pike's Peak we have several groups that
are going to different altitudes for
two days, before they go up to Pike's
Peak.
So we, we know that long term
acclimatization works,
we know that shorter term acclimatization,
six or seven days works very well.
So, now we're looking at two days.
And I think the preliminary data indicate
that it does work.
Doesn't work as well as seven days, but it
certainly, certainly is a benefit.
>> Other things that you can do, is if you
don't have the benefit of acclimization,
this laboratory was one of many back in
the 1970's and 80's
that established diomox or cedazolymyde
for prevention of acute mountain sickness.
>> This lab has also just ten years ago
and jointly with you,
as you recall [LAUGH] Chuck established
the fact that in unacclimatized individual
supplementing, you know, their, their,
their hydration with carbohydrate,
improved their performance acutely at
altitude.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Yep.
>> So, we've been
strongly suggesting that, you know, munch
as you go as a way of
sustaining your physical activity at least
at altitude.
>> Mm-hm.
>> It may not have an impact on
acute mountain sickness, but it certainly
allows you to increase your performance.
I certainly have learned two things.
You know, keep hydrated and keep eating
carbs.
>> Mm-hm.
>> and, and just keep, you know.
You can move out.
So, those are some things that can be
done.
I was going to say that sometimes what you
learned is what doesn't work.
And we've done a number of studies in the
last dozen years where we've
tested what we thought may be beneficial
and
it resolved it in no real substantial
improvement.
We've published work earlier on that Luke
Utrinin's have been,
were thought to be involved in acute
mountain sickness.
These were inflammatory in, inflammatory
biochemical processes.
When we block them, they didn't, that
didn't prevent acute mountain sickness.
So, that sort of went down the tubes.
>> Antioxidants.
>> Antioxidants, we tested together.
>> Down the tubes.
>> That went down the tubes.
>> [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] At the carbohydrate.
We've looked at the use of these
artificial altitude tents,
these normal baric hypoxic tents, or
altitude tents, or
chambers, that you can purchase
commercially.
They're widely used by some athletes,
they're said to simulate altitude.
We said, okay, let's see if we can use
those here at low altitude, have either
our test volunteers exercise or, or spend
hours in them, or even sleep in them.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And what we found was some very
interesting physiological adaptations that
you would expect within the hypoxia room,
but then when you went to
the actual true altitude environment,
whether in the hyperbaric chamber or
on Pike's Peak, there's little or no
carryover effect.
He essentially had minimal to negligible
acclimatization value.
>> And is that in performance or in acute
mountain sickness?
>> Both.
>> Really.
>> Yeah.
>> And so there's something
about the hypobaria per se,
the low pressure that's impacting that
>> Yes.
Yes.
And that has driven
a whole new area of research.
In your research.
>> Mm-hm.
>> How is hyperbaria, per se you know,
impacting our, our, our, our where is it?
What's the receptor for it?
What's the molecular pathways which are
adapting to the hyperbaria?
And there's some interesting work that's
coming out of that.
Not just from this lab, but other
laboratories,
showing that body fluid regulation is
different between the two environments.
>> Mm-hm.
>> For example.
We are currently looking with jointly with
our college from
Mas General Hospital Neuroscience Group,
we're now currently looking at changes in
cerebral blood flow regulation between the
normal barric and
the hypobarric [INAUDIBLE] environments.
>> Hm.
So,
if you were going to put together a list,
I'm going to 14,000 feet tomorrow, don't
bother to get in the altitude tent.
But stay hydrated.
Mm-hm.
>> Have carbohydrates,
maybe back off on the exercise a little
bit on the first couple days.
>> Absolutely.
>> And, and how many days do you need
before you can start going at full,
do you know full intensity?
>> Well, I would add,
if you're going straight to 14,000 feet,
probably some moderate dose of, of diamox.
Diamox.
Okay.
>> Especially if you know that you're
susceptible, but
I would think Diamox is probably
beneficial for
anybody above 3,000 meters to 3500 meters
or 14,000 feet.
And you probably want to stay on the
Diamox for two or
three days, and you can generally over the
course, if, if you're, you know,
you gotta [INAUDIBLE] look at it, if your
symptoms permit you to increase your
physical activity, increase your physical
activity, increase your physical activity.
If you feel the headache coming on and,
and the light headedness and
particularly the nausea.
You need to back off.
It can be adjusted.
>> And does the Diamox impact exercise
performance at all?
>> Yup, it can.
These men are, are studied not by us but
ironically, at,
at approximately the same altitude as
Pike's Peak.
>> Mm-hm.
>> When they gave it at sea level and
looked at endurance, there was about a 20
or 25% reduction in endurance performance.
And they took the same folks up to
approximately 14,000 feet.
And they again found about a 14, I'm
sorry, about a 20,
25% reduction endurance performance.
So, in some situations and some MOS's in
the Army it's,
it's a wonderful thing in terms of it'll
help a lot of people not to get sick.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
also it will help them sleep a little bit
better.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Perhaps.
But in terms of exercise performance not
so good.
Nothing, nothing is really as good as, as
natural acclimatization.
>> Yeah.
>> That's, that's the key thing.
>> The one thing that's always confused me
and, and then we can sort of wrap up but
why do you want to hydrate so much when
you go to altitude when one of the first
adaptations that generally occurs is that
you lose your plasma volume.
Well, I would, first of all, I would
caution, say hydrate too much.
I, when we say maintain hydration
depending upon the situation you're in,
remember, you, you you are correct in that
you do
generally urinate out a good chunk of your
body fluid, but there are other ways.
You know, you tend to sweat more and it
evaporates faster at altitude.
You also lose fluid through exhaled air.
But it's really relative to maybe a,
a modest 5 or 10% increase in hydration,
because that's about all you.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Really are losing.
I, I caution that overhydration has, you
know, shown no benefit.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To preventing altitude illness or, or
improving performance.
You need to just maintain adequate
hydration.
Probably 5 or 10% over what you normally
do under the conditions.
so, but, but, but if, you, you, you do,
you're right,
you're going to lose that plasma volume as
you well know, but you do still main,
you need, need to maintain adequate,
adequate tissue hydration.
Also, coupled with the diuresis that comes
with altitude is the bicarbonate loss.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> Losing bicarbonate through the kidney
is an important
adaptive function for ventilation.
Because you're basically, as you know,
when you go to altitude you create and,
and hyperventilation, that causes a
respiratory alkolosis,
driving the pH up slightly.
In order for the body to readjust the pH
back down towards normal,
you have to get rid of bicarbonate.
You get rid of bicarbonate largely by,
through the kidney.
And so is not going to leave the kidney if
you don't have enough water to
flush it out.
>> To flush it out.
>> Anything else you'd like to add?
>> No.
>> There's no one single discipline that.
That's right.
>> You know, is appropriate for
a mountain of medicine.
I mean, I came from a neurophysiological
discipline of control breathing.
Chuck is an exercise physiologist.
We've worked with people who are metabolic
and endroconologists.
Cardiovascular people.
So, you can come from a wide range of
disciplines and
still make your career mark in mount
medicine or high altitude medicine.
But I, I echo what Chuck said, and that is
especially if you're going to be
doing human studies you've gotta be
willing to get out of the lab.
You've gotta be willing to work, you know,
some cases 24 hours a day
>> Yep.
>> Because once you go into that altitude
environment, you're, you're,
you're typically stuck up in there along
with your test volunteers.
>> Um-hm.
>> That's the other aspect of it,
we get exposed to the same stresses that
we expose our test volunteers to.
And, you know, and, and, and
so unlike many research studies where the
investigator is,
is in a cocoon, you know, or protected
from that, that's not the case.
Yeah.
>> With mountain medicine.
>> No.
That's very true.
>> It makes it exciting, too.
>> Yeah.
And, and
further reason why people come all these
different disciplines is because
hypoxia is such a strong stress.
>> That's right.
>> And impacts so
many systems in the body.
>> Yeah.
Mm-hm.
>> Good.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Are.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> It's a powerful stressor.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah.
>> Yes, it is.
>> [LAUGH] Well,
thank you both so much for your time.
>> Well, thank you.
This
really wonderful.
It's been a pleasure, Ann.
Oh, it's always a pleasure.
It really has.
Good to see you.
Good to see you
also.
I'll see
you on the peak
>> Yay!
>> Absolutely.
Great.
Thank you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]