Welcome to the Physiology of Altitude
section.
This is one of my personal favourites.
Both, because I love being in the
mountains and
because I spent several years doing
High-altitude Physiology research, so
it's near and dear to my heart.
As I mentioned in the introductory story
video, there are so many fascinating
things that happen when our bodies are
exposed to a low Oxygen environment.
It's amazing how adaptable we really are.
A fun illustration of this concept comes
from the book,
Into Thin Air, by Jon Krakauer, about the
1996 Everest expedition,
where things went terribly wrong, and many
people lost their lives.
Early on in the book, when the author is
flying to Nepal in the Airbus 300,
he describes a moment of panic.
He looks out the window and
sees the unmistakable outline of Mount
Everest, at eye level with the plane.
The wind is howling off the top creating a
long train of ice crystals.
His palms suddenly gets sweaty because he
realizes that if the plane were
to depressurize at that moment, he would
likely pass out or die.
Yet in six to eight weeks he was planning
to be standing on the top of
that mountain.
Now he climbed the mountain with
supplemental oxygen, as most people do.
But there are a handful of people who have
been able to climb Mount Everest
without supplemental oxygen.
A feat that many people thought was beyond
human capability until it was actually
accomplished in 1978 by Reinhold Messner
and his climbing partner Peter Habeler.
So through a process of going up a little
bit and then back down and
then up a little bit higher and back down.
Our bodies slowly acclimatize to allow
spectacular feats of physical performance.
That push the limits of human
capabilities.
Among other things this section will
explain how our
bodies adapt to allow such a
accomplishments.
So here are your questions to ponder for
this section as you go through the
material.
First we will address Corey's questions
from the story video.
We'll also talk about why we care about
altitude research and
how we actually study it.
What are the challenges we face at high
altitude and
how our bodies adapt to high altitude.
What are the high altitude illnesses we
need to worry about, and what causes them?
What are ways to decrease our risk to the
illnesses and
increase performance in altitude?
And finally, how do we train at altitude,
and
will it help our performance both at
altitude and sea level.
Over to my right is an outline of how the
overall section is laid out.
We will work through the topics that will
help address the questions that you had on
the previous slide.
There are two parts to Module Two because
it was getting a little long, and
I wanted to give you at least a mental
break.
The first part will provide background on
why we care about altitude research and
how we study it.
The second part will focus more on
the challenge our bodies experience at
altitude.
You can also see that in module four we
have a bonus story video for you.
Cory and I and the camera crew went up to
the summit of Pike's Peak to
illustrate what it was like to start the
climatization process at 14,000 feet.
I have to say that it was particularly fun
to watch our hypoxic camera crew
weaving about trying to film this video.
We're going to talk about the challenges
you face at altitude in this module,
and believe me, there are a lot of them.
High altitude really does provide a strong
systemic stimulus to the body.
The low O2 availability impacts your heart
rate and blood pressure.
You have cardiovascular and
endocrine changes, falls in performance,
and you could experience symptoms of AMS.
But, if you're an athlete there are good
things that happen too,
like increased red blood cells and
hematocrit.
But before we talk about the details,
let's put the information in context.
Why do we even care about altitude
physiology?
As the slide to my right says,
35 million people travel per year to
altitude of greater than 8,000 feet.
They do so for
a variety of reasons that include
recreation, military service and work.
Populations reside permanently at high
altitudes in the Rocky Mountains of North
and Central America, the Andes of South
America, the East African Highlands and
the Asian Himalayan Plateau.
But what you may not realize is that even
if you have
not been to the mountains recently, you
may have
experienced a moderate altitude stimulus
simply by flying in a commercial jet.
You see, it takes a lot of fuel to
pressurize the cabin, so as a compromise
to save on fuel, they only pressurize the
cabin to between five and 8,000 feet.
Therefore on those long international
flights, people feeling they get
feelings of jet lag may actually be having
mild symptoms of acute mountain sickness.
There's also clinical relevance to
studying the body's response to hypoxic
conditions for example, people with
chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and
heart disease, experience varying degrees
of hypoxia.
Fetal development is also on the list
because under normal conditions,
the developing fetus en utero exists in a
hypoxic environment.
Fetal arterial Oxygen tension is about one
quarter of a healthy adult.
So, 25 versus a 100 Torr respectively.
That is equivalent to the blood-Oxygen of
a person on the summit of Mount Everest.
This fork is particularly relevant to
pregnancies in which
hypoxia is exacerbated.
Such as, in foetuses of women who smoke,
have heart or lung disease, or anaemic or
malnourished, or for mothers who engage in
strenuous physical activity or heavy work.
Some theorize that we are able to adapt so
effectively to high altitude because we
spent the first nine months of our lives
in the hypoctic environment of the womb.
Also on the list, tumor treatments.
Researchers and physicians are working on
depriving tumors of their blood supply and
that's oxygen and nutrients to prevent
further growth.
Understanding how our tissues respond to
the hypoxic environments is
critical to such advancements.
And finally, because hypoxia is a whole
body stressor,
it helps us understand the integration of
the whole body systems.
We apply a stress to the system, see how
it responds, and
it gives us a stronger understanding of
basic physiology.
So how do we study humans in high altitude
environments?
There are several ways.
First we can use the high altitude chamber
like the one you
say in the Cory story video at the start
of this section.
The Usariem Chamber provides a hypobaric
hypoxias stimulus.
Meaning it lowers the total pressure in
the chamber to achieve hypoxia.
This type of stimulus is similar to what
happens when you actually are,
travel to the mountains.
Studies that are done in these chambers
are both short term,
like the one we did with Cory, or long
term,
where participants are asked to stay in
the chamber for days or even weeks.
As we mentioned in the story video, one of
the most famous of
these long-term studies was Operation
Everest 2, which was conducted in 1985.
This study simulated a climb by eight
volunteers to the summit of Mount Everest,
about 29,000 feet over the course of 40
days.
During that time an international group of
23 military and civilian scientists,
conducted a series of experiments at
escalating acclimatization plateaus.
They collected data to determine the
relative importance of various
physiological, biochemical and
physiological responses to the low oxygen.
Can you imagine volunteering to be trapped
and
watched 24-7 in a little metal box for 40
days?
To this day, it remains one of the
landmark studies in
the field from which we obtained a huge
amount of valuable information.
Unfortunately, there are not many of these
chambers around.
They're expensive and complicated to
build, run, and maintain.
For example, can you envision what would
happen if you flushed a normal toilet in
an altitude chamber, where the plumbing on
the outside was at
a significantly higher pressure than the
plumbing inside?
Ka-plooey!
Ha [LAUGH] there would be a lot of nasty
stuff on the walls of the chamber.
So many things have to be redesigned
within the chamber.
Hypoxic gas can also be used to mimic
altitude for
both research and training purposes.
The gas can be administered through masks,
tents, cubes, hotels, and
even horses' snouts.
The stimulus in this case is normobaric
hypoxia.
Meaning the pressure remains at ambient
levels but the environment is
made hypoxic by reducing the percentage of
Oxygen in the air.
Although originally considered as being
equivalent to hypobaric hypoxia,
there are some minor but
critical differences emerging that will
require further research.
We'll talk about a couple of these later.
But as you can see from the slide, people
use the technology in gyms to train, in
labs to do research, and in the bedroom to
improve subsequent exercise performance.
And finally, there's the real thing.
Now this is the best gig if you can get
it.
Being able to do fieldwork is a fantastic
way to earn a living.
It allows us also to study participants in
more realistic environments and
for longer periods of time.
The picture to my right is a view of Pikes
Peak from the lower part of
the road that goes to the top.
There is a Usariem altitude research
station on the top where I've spent man,
many summers studying the acclimatization
process with my co-investigators.
The army dudes, as we fondly call them.
You met Chuck and Steve from that group in
the Usariem chamber story video.
Later in this section, you'll get a first
hand view of the research station as
Cory and I head up there for a few days
for the chronic altitude story video.
Before we get started,
I thought I should define some of the
altitude ranges for you.
As you can see to my right, I have the
elevations both in meters and in feet.
I try to give both units through out the
section but I may jump back and
forth a bit.
I also have the conversion down at the
bottom of the slide, so
that will help you crossover to your
preferred units if needed.
Low altitude includes cities like Denver,
when you head up to Colorado spring,
springs you're in the moderate altitude
range.
Also, several stages of the Tour de France
and
Giro d'Italia climb up into that range.
Things really start to get dicey when you
reach the high altitude, and
of course extreme altitude ranges.
These include Pikes Peak and Everest
respectively.
We'll spend most of our time talking about
the impact of high altitude.
That's it for the background information.
Let's take a mini break before we get into
the big question.
Why is it so challenging at altitude?
Take a moment to stand up, jump around and
then come back for some more.
See you soon.