Welcome back.
In this module, you will learn about the
initial things that take place within
the first few hours of altitude exposure.
Imagine you drive or fly to the top of a
mountain, or
you get sealed into an altitude chamber
like Corey did at 10,000 feet.
Your body would say, ack, what happened to
all the oxygen?
You would experience a stress response
whether you liked it or
not, and in this case that is a good
thing,
because it is going to help to get more
oxygen to your tissues.
The first thing your body will do in
response to low oxygen is try to
get more oxygen into your arterial blood.
The easiest way to do that is to breathe
more.
So you're resting and submax ventilation
goes up.
This is good because it keeps in your
alveoli higher.
As the oxygen gets pulled into the
arterial blood, if you are ventilating
more it is quickly replaced with new air
that has more oxygen in it.
However, there are some problems with the
increased ventilation rate as well.
As you breathe more the carbon dioxide
that is in your lungs gets blown off and
that draws CO2 out of the blood.
A decrease of CO2 in the blood is a signal
to slow breathing.
Thus it is a negative feedback on
ventilation which is counter
productive and can result in blood oxygen
levels that are less than optimal.
This can increase the risk of acute
mountain sickness or AMS.
Ventilation is stimulated by both low O2
and high CO2 levels in the blood.
So those people who respond more to the O2
levels and
less to the CO2 levels, are at a lower
risk of getting AMS.
Blowing off more CO2 can also make the
blood more alkalotic or
basic, the opposite of acidic.
This will shift the oxyhemoglobin curve to
the left,
which inhibits the unloading of oxygen in
the tissues.
Although, it is a small effect,
you don't want to compromise an already
limited oxygen delivery.
Your body also responds by trying to get
more oxygen to the tissues,
by increasing blood flow.
If you look at our friendly Fick equation
at the bottom of the slide, you can see
that oxygen consumption can be impacted
both by putting more oxygen in the A, or
arteriole blood, or by sending more blood
around to the tissues.
So resting and submaximal exercise heart
rate increases.
Blood pressure also increases to send more
blood to the tissues, lung, and brain.
This improves profusion or
the distribution of blood into the
tissues, but it also puts you at risk for
high altitude pulmonary edema and high
altitude cerebral edema.
We'll talk more about HAPE and HACE in one
of the later modules.
What I've already described is part of the
stress response.
But the stress response is mediated by the
sympathetic nervous system,
which is responsible for the fight or
flight reaction.
Stimulation of the SNS results in the
release of the Catecholamine hormones,
epinephrine and nor-epinephrine.
Otherwise called adrenaline and
nor-adrenaline.
Catecholamines help increase heart rate,
blood pressure and ventilation.
In addition, they cause you to use more
carbohydrate,
abbreviated as CHO on the slide, as fuel.
That is good because you get more energy
per unit oxygen for
carbohydrate than other fuels.
But it is bad because carbohydrate supply
is limited in your body.
Also, as part of the increase breakdown of
carbohydrate,
more lactate will accumulate in the blood
for a given workload.
The concept is illustrated with a little
diagram at the bottom of the slide.
When you are rapidly breaking down your
two forms of carbohydrate in the body,
glycogen and your glucose, not all of the
pyruvate form can be used, so
some spins off in the form of lactate.
Although lactate is not the bad apple many
people think, it is an indicator of
non-steady-state conditions, or a
disruption of homeostasis.
People who reside in high-altitude regions
know that
a little sympathetic stimulation is good
for altitude acclimatization.
That's why when you get off the plane in
La Paz,
Bolivia, at about 4,000 meters, they give
you cocoa leaf tea.
It is a stimulant like caffeine, that is
supposed to jump start
the acclimatization process and reduce the
risk of AMS.
The bottom line is that the responses I
just described will help compensate during
rest and submaximal exercise, but
you will reach your maximum capacity at a
lower work level.
If you think about it, that makes sense,
right?
You have an upper limit to your heart
rate.
If at it, if it is elevated at each work
load,
you won't be able to go as hard before you
reach your maximum heart rate.
Let's look at how all of this impacted
Corey in the chamber.
Fortunately for us, Corey was a textbook
case.
Nice work, Cory.
[LAUGH] The data I am about to discuss
compares his sea level
bike test with his 10,000 foot simulated
altitude bike test in the chamber.
First look right above my head, at his
maximum work and oxygen consumption.
At sea level,
he reached 325 watts on the bike with a
VO2 with 50 mills per kilogram per minute.
At altitude, he only reached 275 watts
with a VO2 of
45 mills per kilogram per minute.
So, a fall of ten percent.
Now look at his ventilation data in the
top graph.
Just what we would expect.
For a given work load, which is displayed
on the x or horizontal axis.
And all the way up to the point of fatigue
his ventilation was noticeably higher.
His arterial oxygen saturation displayed
in the lower graph was significantly
higher at sea level and stayed essentially
stable throughout exercise as expected.
In contrast his altitude saturation was
lower at the start, and
then fell off even more as exercise
intensity increased.
The fall off during the higher intensity
has to do with the decreasing transit time
of the blood in the lungs as cardiac
output increases.
Remember in the earlier module, we talked
about how the lower driving force of
the gas at altitude means slower diffusion
through the lungs and
thus greater desaturation of the blood,
blood as it moves faster.
Like ventilation, both heart rate and
perceived exertion, so, how hard he
felt he was working, were both elevated
for a given work load at altitude.
Now you should have enough information to
answer the questions we left you
with at the end of the story video.
How did Corey compensate for the lower O2
availability at altitude?
What stopped Corey at a lower workload
during exercise at altitude?
And did Corey do better or worse than
predicted change for 10,000 feet?
You'll see a couple of these questions on
the practice quiz and
maybe the other a little later.
So make sure you can answer all of them
After the quiz,
we have a special treat for you, another
Corey video.
This one is up on Pikes Peak and there is
farting and peeing involved, so
you wont want to miss it.
It will be the talk of the discussion
sections, no doubt.
Enjoy.