As you are taking this class, one thing to
remember is that sometimes students may
feel unmotivated or discouraged during an
online course.
This might be due to a feeling that you
are anonymous and
not really connected to a group.
We know that participants of this course
come from every ethnic, religious, and
educational background possible.
We want you to know, that no matter which
of these groups you belong to,
you're now part of a single course
community.
Our community.
Even though it's simple, you might find
your learning is helped if you
notice whether you're feeling like an
outsider or like a member of the class.
One way you can practice feeling more like
a member is to actively participate.
By watching the videos and answering the
online questions you will be sharing
a learning experience with thousands of
other people from around the world.
The best way to connect with other
participants is to share your thoughts and
comments online through the discussion
forums.
Having a shared experience with social
interaction can become the glue that
allows people to learn together.
We believe that you belong in our
community.
And we couldn't be more excited to have
you here.