[MAN SHIVERING INTENSELY]
>> Vic, let's get you out of there.
>> Welcome to our expert interview on
cold.
Today we're here with Dr. Thomas Nuckton,
who is a specialist in pulmonary and
critical care medicine with Sutter Health,
and
an Associate Clinical Professor of
Medicine in the UCSF Medical School.
He primarily focuses on studying survival
prognoses for
patients in intensive care wards, which is
led to the exploration of a wide range of
interests from sleep to hypothermia.
His research aims to better inform
physicians caring for
critically ill patients in intensive care
units.
Dr. Nuckton was involved in designing and
implementing the Alcatraz swim study.
Where Dr. Nuckton and his colleagues
explored questions related to hypothermia,
an after drop in the ann, in the annual
San Francisco Bay Race.
As a member of the Dolphin Club and the
Polar Bear Club himself, Dr. Nuckton
bridges the experiential and research
perspective on what it means to be cold.
For those reasons and many others, it's a
pleasure to be here with you today.
Thank you so much for agreeing to talk
with us.
>> Thank you.
>> So, you are normally in pulmonary and
critically care med,
critical care medicine, so how did you
come to cold research and
being a cold swim yourself, which came
first?
>> Well I grew up swimming and playing
water polo and
the water always seemed to be cold but I
did my fellowship in pulmonary and
critical care medicine at UC San
Francisco, and I got involved in
critical care outcomes research where we
examined physiologic variables to
see if we can predict how intensive care
unit patients are going to do over time.
And, the methods that we use for that the
regression models and
the statistics lend themselves very well
to hypothermia research.
And it just so happens that the San
Francisco Bay is and
was home to a really large group of cold
water swimmers folks that
swim year round without wetsuits in the
bay.
And you can go down there on any given
day, it's at aquatic park near
Fisherman's Wharf it's really nice setting
right below Ghirardelli Square and,
near the high street pier historic ships
and you can see folks swimming back and
forth without wetsuits.
So we approached those swimmers and asked,
hey would you be willing to participate in
physiology research where we are examining
emergent hypothermia, and they said yes.
They were incredibly supportive and
enthusiastic about helping us.
>> Great.
And was that before or after you started
swimming with them?
I would occasionally go down there to swim
with folks I knew.
I knew people in the club and I think I
became a club member in 2005 or 2006.
So the study, you can, you can swim just
as a guest there or day use.
But I didn't join the club until about
five or
six years after we had published our first
study.
>> And how cold is the water in the bay?
>> The bay right now is about 60 degrees
but
in the winter it will go down to about 48
degrees, or 50 somewhere in that range.
Well this last winter it was a very cold
winter, we had several days below 50.
>> And how long can a normal person
survive in that temperature water?
>> It depends on the size of the
individual but it depends on whether or
not they're wearing a life jacket.
If they're not a good swimmer and
you fall in a 48 degree water, you're
survival time is estimated in minutes.
But if you have a life jacket on and
you're protected at
least from that initial cold shock
response you need two or
three hours of total survival if, if
you're a good sized individual.
>> And what does the life jacket have to
do with the survival?
>> If you get in really cold water at the
beginning,
you really don't even have time to get
hypothermic.
You'll have this cold shock response,
where you'll,
you'll increase your ventilatory rate,
hyperventilate, become tachycardic,
your blood pressure will go up, you'll
have muscle weakness and extremity pain.
And most folks while they're in this cold
shock will drown.
Most people don't die of hypothermia, they
don't have time to get hypothermic, so
they'll die with this cold shock response
and so that's the life jacket.
If you're wearing a life jacket that cold
shock is uncomfortable, but
most people survive it.
>> Interesting.
So you've done a number of studies now
with the club.
>> Yeah.
>> And,
what were some of your major findings and
discoveries?
>> I think they kind of get put into two
different categories.
One are, are studies that have
applications to true core hypothermia,
cooling and survival, and others that are
more geared toward sports medicine,
and, and, and the health implications of
swimming in cold water.
For true core hypothermia and
survival we go back to our first study,
which was published in 2000.
And in that study, we studied the New
Year's Day Alcatraz swimmers.
They swim from new, from Alcatraz to shore
distance of about a mile and
a half on New Year's day, one of the
coldest days of the year without wetsuits.
And we had just one simple question.
Do these swimmers become medically
hypothermic?
They have all sorts of ways of describing,
oh it was cold, it was freezing, it was.
All of these things, but
we want to know do they, do they mean a
medical definition of hypothermia?
And to determine that we asked these
swimmers to have rectal temperature
measurements.
We measured their core temperature after
they got out of the water, and we found
that five out of 11 subjects did reach a
medical definition of mild hypothermia.
These swimmers also had a phenomena,
underwent something called after drop, and
after drop refers to continued core
cooling after removal from cold a stress,
so after you get out of the water.
And just about every one of the swimmers
had this, and that, that's to be expected.
What we didn't expect was it, it was very
dramatic in certain individuals,
the drop in temperature was precipitous
in, in some of the subjects.
So applying that research in terms of
other swimming events
folks are at risk for hypothermia if they
participate without wetsuits.
And then you can anticipate this
afterdrop.
So keeping an eye on folks after the
event, we think is a good idea.
In terms of, of, of rescuing immersion
victims it's,
it's a reminder, that look as the rescuer
once you get your victim out of the water
your job is not done, they're still having
a core temperature decrease and
that's something you need to pay attention
to.
>> Yeah that can be really scary,
your drop's not done once they're out of
the water, clearly.
>> Right, that's right.
>> And we did see that in Cory's video
where we put him in a,
in a cold water tank and took then took
him out and had him walk on
the treadmill and he got colder while he
was walking on the treadmill.
It seems a little bit different in that
case than what your swimmers experience,
because your swimmers were swimming then
they came out and rested.
He was sitting in cold water and then came
out and exercise.
>> And exercise, yeah.
>> Are the mechanisms different there?
>> They're similar, but exercise in some
studies has been shown to
worsen afterdrop, basically get that core
blood,
that's warm pumping down into the
extremities which are very cold, and
then that cold blood comes back to the
core so exercise can worsen that.
And that's why in some treatment protocols
when folks are rescued when victims
are rescued, they're advised to lie still,
and not exercise it depends on how severe
the hypothermia is but, but in some cases
exercise can worsen that after drop.
>> Yeah, it's something to definitely keep
in mind.
>> Yeah.
>> So
these swimmers that you're studying are in
and out of the water a lot.
So they do this recreationally.
>> Sure.
>> Are they experiencing hypothermia every
time they go for a recreational swim and
is that bad for someone over time to be
hypothermic, normal, hypothermic, normal?
Certainly we haven't seen any, you know,
adverse events in, in,
in the long term, but there aren't a lot
of longitudinal studies, so I don't know.
And they probably do get mildly
hypothermic, they probably feel it less,
because they're acclimatized.
We also have warm showers and saunas that
are readily available.
So alotta that, you know you come out of
the water and
they go straight into a nice warm shower,
and some folks make the shower lukewarm to
begin and kind of, and then go into the
sauna afterwards.
So, my hunch is that most folks are not
getting hypothermic on
a daily basis because of the showers and,
and the saunas that are there.
>> And I asked on the detrimental side but
I've heard many cold water swimmers
claim that it's actually beneficial for
them to be cold periodically.
Do you agree with that?
>> Yeah.
>> Is that a possibility?
>> I don't know, and I'm a little bit
skeptical on, on, on certain aspects.
There are studies, preliminary studies
that have
suggested that frequent immersion in cold
water improves the immune system,
increases your, your T-cell count
increases beneficial cytokines increases
antioxidants it helps improve mood and,
and
can be used as a treatment for depression
and fibromyalgia and asthma and.
There's all sorts of preliminary studies
out there but
they're not any really good longitudinal
studies, so we really don't know.
And, and I think they're interesting
there's some
interesting hypotheses out there, but I
think a lot more work needs to be done.
>> And I've heard you mention brown
adipose tissue before and
we talked about it in our learning
modules.
>> Right.
>> And
some people claim that any beneficial
effect may be partially related to
the brown adipose tissue.
Can you talk about that and where the
research is going?
>> Sure, sure.
So what is brown fat?
Brown fat is, is fat that has increased
mitochondria count.
So there's a higher density of
mitochondria and
it actually produces energy.
And it's found primarily in hibernating
animals and in babies.
But it is also seen in adults especially
after cold exposure.
It gets activated after cold exposure.
So there's a theory that these swimmers
that swim routinely in cold water,
either increase their total amount of
brown fat or
the brown fat they have is charged and is
activated.
Because this fat is metabolic,
it's often referred to as the good fat as
opposed to the bad white fat.
In all, and there's been some speculation
that having more brown fat is good for
you, it improves your metabolism and
it can have all sorts of health benefits,
I honestly don't know.
It's a interesting theory, I'm a little
bit skeptical because the swimmers
even though they are acclimatized, they
cool at more or
less the same rate I was expect anyone to
cool.
So if their brown fat were really hi, I'm
a, and, and
it was working I would expect them to cool
a bit slower or substantially slower rate.
But I don't know.
I haven't measured brown fat in any of the
swimmers and you know,
I think it's interesting theory but just
more research needs to be done.
>> Yeah I think that's a, a safe way to
end that.
I mean, it's, it's sort of gone beyond
cold water swimming now, and
people are trying to take cold showers,
and roll in the snow.
>> Right, right.
>> To increase their fat,
with the hope of losing weight.
>> Pharmaceutically hoping to improve
their brown fat.
>> Right. Right. Indeed.
>> But
I think the jury's still out on that.
>> Yeah.
>> A lot of work needs to be done.
>> It's going to be a major target, and
a lot of money's going to go into that in
the next five years or so.
>> We'll have to see, yeah.
>> So we talked a little bit about
survival briefly when
we touched on the life preservers, and
because of your experience you've
taught survival skills in cold water, so
what else can you share with people about
what to do if you're in a situation where
you're exposed to cold water?
>> Well there's two or three things that,
that come to mind, and the first one is.
To get out of the water, and
I'm not being cute there you lose heat to
water some 25 times compared to air.
And I think most of us know that
intuitively if you go jogging in 53 degree
air wearing shorts and a t-shirt, most
people are reasonably comfortable.
If you go swimming in 53 degree water,
you'll feel it.
That cold water can just suck the heat
right out of you.
So if you find yourself in a situation
where you're ending up in cold water,
if there's anything you can do to get out,
pull yourself up on a raft or
on, onto some debris that kind of kind of
thing.
There have been survival accounts of
people that have survived in
really cold water by getting up on some of
the wreckage and
getting themselves outta the water.
The next thing would be the life jackets
again you know,
it's gets hammered home by the coastguard
all the time and that's for good reason.
If you are in a life jacket, your survival
time is just exponentially increased if,
if you, if you don't have that life
jacket,
there's a good chance you won't even have
a chance, have time to become hypothermic,
you'll, you'll drown in this cold, with
this cold shock phenomena contributing.
So wear that life jacket, it's going to
increase your survival time and then.
Also survival suits since legislation has
been passed in Alaska for
example, the fishing vessels are now
required to have
survival suits the fatality rate amongst
fishermen is decreased.
So survival suits and life jackets and
getting out of the water are the things
that I really recommend.
>> What is a survival suit?
>> Survival suit is a, there's a
different,
different types out there but, the common
one it's a,
it's a neoprene suit that, that folks get
into before they get into cold water.
It's often called the gumby suit because
you look like gumby in it.
And it basically allows a lot of you to
stay dry in the parts that aren't dry
to be insulated so it increases, it
decreases your core cooling dramatically.
So wearing that suit is going to increase
your odds of survival.
>> And you're supposed to wear it around
the boat in case it capsizes or
just if like boat is going down?
>> If the boat is going down.
>> And that, that's problematic too you
know, they, they're trying to
increase training so people can get into
these suits so rapidly, and, and
inspect the suits to make sure there's no
leaks in them, and that kind of thing.
>> Yeah I've tried to get into a wetsuit
when I've been a little damp.
>> Right.
>> And it's very challenging,
to get the neoprene on.
>> It is.
>> Good.
So that's that's survival.
What about performance in cold water?
>> Yeah performance is always a tough
issue, It's a tough issue in any sport,
tough issue in running, how much you know
is, the VO2 max versus training regimen,
diet, all of those things kind of you
know,
it's a pretty complex interplay of
factors.
And in cold water swimming, it's the same.
The things most people talk to me about,
you know what can I do to get used to this
cold shock?
And if you get in the water every single
day,
these cold shock reflexes get blunted.
So if you have never been in cold water
before, and
you just go down to the bay and hop in on
a daywards 48 degrees, you will
hyperventilate, you'll become tachycardic,
you'll have extremity weakness and
pain, you might feel nauseous but if you
get in every single day,
you get in every single day for a week
you'll do much better by the end of it.
So, climatizing is, is something that can
be very helpful.
The problem with that though is even
though you feel better,
your core temperature is probably still
going down.
So you feel fine, you're out there
swimming, or you feel better,
you're out there swimming, but you can
still run into trouble.
And that has happened to some of the
swimmers down there.
They'll say, I was swimming along, I felt
fine but
then, things weren't quite working out
well and they were becoming hypothermic.
>> So there's not, a threshold below which
they start to feel this same?
They, that, that benefit continues down
even into the hypothermic range,
acclimatization benefit?
>> Right, right, so most of the cold shock
response is in the first five to ten
minutes, so you get through that and then
you start swimming and you feel okay and
most people wouldn't even be in the water,
because they would've of you know,
they would've had that cold shock and just
said no I'm not going any further.
These swimmers get through that, and then
they keep swimming but they're still
swimming in cold water and their
temperature, they're still losing heat.
>> So what's the first sign, for
them to recognize that they're starting to
get into the danger zone?
>> It can be different for, for, for
different people.
I have one of the swimmers down there
practices his times tables.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And when he can't do them, then he
thinks he needs to go out.
And, and other people have different
tricks that they try, but
I've never seen anything that you can
really hang your hat on.
I think, you know, it's a judgement call
and
before you go swimming, look at the water
temperature and
say, you know what, I'm only going to swim
for 15 minutes today,
the water is really cold, I'm not going to
push it for a couple of hours.
>> I noticed with the dolphin club they
frequently have a boat nearby, do you swim
with groups and with people monitoring so,
in case someone get's hypothermic?
>> So the rules at the, at the Dolphin
Club are that you
can swim inside the cove on your own as
much as you like.
But you can't go outside the cove unless
you have a pilot.
And we have several sanctioned events
every, every year.
The Alcatraz swim, The Golden Gate swim,
Pier 39 swim.
In, excuse me, in those swims they, they
have a whole group of pilots
that are out there in rowboats, it's a
rowing club as well I should add, so.
They have these, this great fleet of
historic wooden row boats.
That, that folks are out there as well as
kayakers to make sure that the events are,
are as safe as possible.
So, outside the cove, you have to have a
pilot.
>> Makes sense.
>> Yeah.
>> So, what about these extreme characters
that you see written up
swimming the English Channel, swimming in
Antarctica, you the iceman.
Is there something different about their
physiology that makes them capable of
doing this?
>> I think.
Yes and no.
In terms of the English Channel that's,
that's a great example.
If you look at some of the older survival
tables, the average survival time for
an aviator, or a mariner, would be about
six hours in the English Channel.
But people that swim the English Channel
they take twice that long, some of them.
You know, I know somebody that just spent
12 hours in the Channel.
And an, an elite swimmer can generate
heat.
So if you can generate heat consistently,
and
some elite swimmers can swim at 80% of
their maximum workload.
So you can overcome you know, these
survival tables.
But that can be really hard to do when the
water's 50 degrees.
The channel's usually 60, give or take,
when most folks do their attempt.
If the channel were 48 degrees, I think it
would be a different story.
In people that swim in really cold water,
I think there's some common
characteristics.
One, they're in usually in phenomenal
shape.
So they're in really good physical shape.
two, they limit the amount of time they go
in.
They study very carefully, you know, how
long you're going to be in the water.
Some of these polar swims only last about
20 minutes.
And then, many of them gain weight, before
they get in the water.
So they have an increased layer of fat, or
size, because it's not just fat, it's
overall, overall size, overall volume.
Smaller surface to volume ratio things of
that nature.
So they're good at generating heat, they
also have increased fat layer, and
they're careful about monitoring how long
they're going to be in the water.
>> And, they can tolerate pain.
>> And, they are acclimatized [LAUGH] I
won't take that away from them.
They are acclimatized and, and
in that sense they are different than
someone walking down the street.
They've been, They've been in cold water
repeatedly preparing for the event.
>> How do you do it?
How do you get over the pain?
>> I just, you just go down there and hop
in and sort of how I do it.
I have to coax myself into the water.
Some of the swimmers, it's a spiritual
experience.
And, you know, I kind of grew up with it.
It's a little bit of a chore for me, I
have my good days, I like it.
But for me it's a workout and I don't
really enjoy working out personally.
But you know if, if you skip a week you're
going to feel it.
You're not going to be as acclimatized, so
that's also the incentive to keep it up
once you start swimming.
Keep going back in or you're going to have
a problem after taking time off, so.
>> So it's type two fun as they say.
It's more fun when you get out not when
you're actually doing it.
>> For me, definitely, but
I think everybody has their own reasons
for doing it.
>> Good.
So getting back to the research on cold.
So what, what's next for you and
what do you see, where do you see the
field going now?
>> I think you know we talked about brown
fat, that's obviously a hot topic.
Other things with these cytokines and,
sort of,
what are the health implications of
swimming in cold water?
And I think longitudinal studies.
We have a database ongoing where we've,
you know, gathering data continually in
these swimmers longet, lon, longevity, and
does this help?
We have some, some octogenarians that swim
three times a week down at the club.
All of those things I think need to be
studied over time,
and so that's where I sort of see some of
the future with this.
There's also some mathematical modeling
work that can still be done.
How much this whole interplay between how
much heat can you
generate versus that heat being sucked out
of you.
At what temperatures is it feasible.
At what temperatures isn't it, it, isn't
it feasible.
Things of that nature.
And then in terms of survival it doesn't
sound as glamourous.
And it just sounds like a broken record
but the lifejackets, how do you
increase use of lifejackets and folks and,
you know, if it's just in the boat and
you fall in the water and you can't get to
it, it doesn't do much good.
How do you get people to actually wear
their life jackets and,
and get into their survival suits quickly
when the,
when their, when their vessel is sinking,
those kinds of things.
>> Great.
And we have a lot of students out there
who're watching this probably, and
many of them may be interested in code
research.
Do you have any suggestions for them or
tips for
them on how to get involved in the field?
>> You know, I think.
Pretty much, the, the resear,
the advice I would give to a researcher in
general would be
probably something they've heard, things
that they've heard many times, you know.
Do you homework first.
Really learn basic physiology first.
and, and really study the physiology
around what your,
what your going to be doing research in.
Also learn as much statistics as you can,
so that you can take a really rigorous
statistical approach.
When you're, when you're doing a research
project.
All of those things.
On a personal level I would have two
things that I would recommend.
One, first and foremost, don't discount
the older studies.
There are some fantastic studies from the
1960s, 70s, and 80s.
And you'll go and look up that study from
1965 on cold shock, and, and
really read it carefully.
And a lot of times, you'll find that some
of the questions that you're having have
already been answered.
If you just take the time to go back, and
look at some of these older studies.
So, don't discount them.
By the same token, some of these
investigators are still around.
Give em a call, talk to some of the senior
guys.
Their just remarkable resource.
you, my on, I on, example that comes to
mind I.
A few months back, I met with Dr. Martin
Nemeroff.
Who's a retired coast guard physician who
did a lot of pioneer work in
resuscitating children who had been under
the ice, for say half an hour.
And just meeting him, with him was just
fascinating.
You know, hearing his story, hearing his
approach.
I mean I probably learned more from him,
it would've taken me hours to go to try
and different journals and, and
text to try and you know, tease some of
those things out.
So you know, talk to the older folks.
And then I think also moving forward in
terms of a research career
with funding cuts being what they are,
you're going to have to be I think both
flexible and resourceful.
Not only in your career but also in the
research itself.
So you know, any academic position is a
combination between teaching,
administration and research and
in some years it's going to be more of one
and other years more of the other, and
I think you know, new graduates should be
aware of that.
And then also same with the studies.
Can you do a study with less funding?
Quite frankly.
Can you do a non-funded study?
Can you, you know can you, can you work
through various aspects of the study using
mathematical modeling instead, and is that
going to work or is it not going to work?
So those kind of things.
So talking to the older folks, and looking
at the older studies, and then,
also Being flexible and resourceful as you
move forward with your career.
>> That's great advice.
So it's interesting about the older
studies in this field in
particular is it because the technology
that we use to measure cold has
not changed that much over the years.
because in a lot of the newer fields you
know,
if it's older than ten years, people
discount it.
So what, what allows you to go back into
the 60s and get that great data?
some, some of that's true I think, you
know, temperature measurement is
temperature measurement thermometers are
not dramatically different.
But I think you know, for a while,
physiology was sort of king, and
there was a lot of work being done in
physiology and
now things are a little bit more
molecular.
And I think with some of the younger
students I've
met there's just a tendency to discount
some of those older studies.
Not that there aren't good studies being
done now but
you just want to make sure you're not
trying to reinvent the wheel,
when it's already been examined very
carefully by some very bright individuals.
>> I think that's a great place to end it,
thank you so much.
>> Sure.
>> Really, really interesting information.
>> Great, thank you.
[MAN SHIVERING INTENSELY]
>> Vic,
let's get you
out of there.