Welcome back to the Physiology of Cold,
Module 7 -
Risks, Consequences and Practical Tips.
You can see some of the risks in the
pictures to my right.
Missing toes.
Sailors with hypothermia rescued at sea by
the US Navy.
There are a lot of things to consider and
prepare for when you're out in the cold.
Let's start with hypothermia.
Hypothermia is when your core temperature
drops below normal, but
there are various degrees of hypothermia.
A two degree drop in core temperature is
considered mild hypothermia, and
that is where you get maximal shivering,
which is just about where Cory was at the
end of his experience in the cold room.
Do you remember this?
>> Yay, victory!
Okay, click!
>> You deserve a warm blanket for that.
>> Yeah.
>> Are we done?
>> Yeah, we're done.
Let's get him warmed up.
>> It's so cold but the background.
There's no heat in the shoe, so you can't
freak that your hands are so cold.
>> Your hands are just [LAUGH].
>> [NOISE]
>> Yeah, let's get me out of here.
>> Anyway, you get the idea.
That is some serious shivering.
A four degree centigrade drop in core
temperature is
considered moderate hypothermia.
At that stage you can expect to see apathy
and ataxia.
That means uncoordinated movements.
You also start to make bad decisions
because you're not thinking clearly.
Then with a six degree drop you get severe
hypothermia which can lead
to unconsciousness.
A drop greater than six degrees can lead
to abnormal heart rhythms,
decreased brain blood flow and death.
A core temperature between 23 and
25 degrees is usually fatal, with some
exceptions.
To get hypothermia, it doesn't need to be
frostbite cold.
You can get hypothermic whenever the heat
loss is greater than the amount of
heat your body is producing.
That can even be during exercise despite
the high metabolic rate.
I remember some distinct times back in my
youth before performance fabrics when I
made myself hypothermic even in Marin
County,
California in the summer, which is not
that cold.
I would ride my mountain bike up Mount Tam
in the afternoon sun,
get all sweaty in my cotton t-shirt and
then head down the shady side of the
mountain as the sun was setting.
Again, not that cold out, but between the
hypoglycemia, which is low blood sugar,
the shade, the windchill from riding down
and the sweat, I was so cold and shaking
so uncontrollably hard on my bike, that I
had to get off and walk down the mountain.
The thing about hypothermia is that it can
get bad fast.
When you depress the central nervous
system,
shivering actually stops when you need it
the most.
You also may run out of the energy needed
to do the shivering.
Plus you get confused, so
you start making poor decisions that can
make a bad situation worse quickly.
Because of the depression of the central
nervous system and
the slowed reaction rates in your body,
your heart may beat one to
five times per minute right before you die
of hypothermia.
In that condition, you're not actually
dead yet,
just in a sort of suspended animation.
Some people have been revived from such a
condition as they warm up.
You've probably all heard about children
who have been pulled from frozen lakes
after 30 minutes and survived, even though
they looked dead initially.
It happens more often in children because
of their small body size.
Means they lose heat faster, so
they go into suspended animation more
quickly before they get brain damage.
So a good rule of thumb is that you're not
dead until you're actually warm and dead.
Keep that in mind if you find someone out
in the snow who is non-responsive.
Here's some practical advice on avoiding
and treating hypothermia.
Most of it's common sense, but we'll go
quickly through it anyway.
For prevention, cover up in layers that
you can remove during exercise and
quickly put back on afterwards.
Stay dry and avoid overexertion, both
because the sweat will make you wet, and
if you deplete your energy reserves, it'll
be harder to stay warm.
If someone is hypothermic, you can do the
following.
Remove their wet clothes, and insulate
them from the cold ground.
Get the person lying down flat, and warm
them with blankets or
whatever you have available.
If the person is not shivering,
then moderate external warmth like body
heat or heating pads can be helpful.
You've all seen scenes in movies where two
people have to get naked in
a sleeping bag to recover from
hypothermia.
It usually leads to no good in the movies,
but
it can be an effective way to warm someone
up.
However, if someone is still shivering,
they'll warm faster if you just dry them
off, insulate them and let them shiver.
The moderate external heat can suppress
shivering and
won't warm them up any faster.
By the way, the best place for warm
heating pads, hot water bottles or
whatever you have available is the neck,
face, groin, and
armpits where the capillary beds are close
to the surface.
Whether to warm the periphery is
controversial at this point.
Some say it will help rewarming.
Others fear it will increase the risk of
afterdrop in cases of moderate to
severe hypothermia.
The experimental warming devices we used
in the Cory Warms Up
video may circumvent this problem by
selecting the less muscular arms for
rewarming, rather than the legs that are
greater cold sinks.
It's also designed to send rapidly warmed
blood back to the core,
but more research is needed to determine
whether it is effective and safe in
cases of more severe hypothermia than Cory
experienced in our demonstration.
If conscious, give warm beverages and
easily digestible calories to
treat dehydration and hypoglycemia, which
frequently accompanies hypothermia.
Don't use hot water or apply direct heat
that can cause damage to the tissues.
And finally, with moderate or severe
hypothermia, seek medical treatment.
Warm intravenous fluids can be given, or
in extreme cases blood can
actually be removed from the body by
machine like a dialysis unit, warmed, and
then re-circulated back into the patient.
Overall, remember to be gentle when
handling someone with hypothermia.
The cold can make the electrical activity
of the heart unstable, so jarring or
aggressive movements could lead to cardiac
arrest.
Also, watch rescued victims closely, even
if they seem okay initially,
because frequently core temperature will
get worse before it starts getting better,
and they could experience post rescue
collapse.
Frostbite usually affects smaller exposed
areas of skin like fingers,
toes, noses, ears, chins and cheeks.
It occurs when the skin and the tissue
right underneath it freezes.
First, your skin becomes very cold, then
numb, hard, and pale.
Frostnip, the first stage of frostbite,
irritates the skin but
doesn't cause permanent damage.
Severe frostbite, on the other hand, can
damage skin, tissue, muscle, and
even bones, leading to complications,
complications such as infection, gangrene,
and nerve damage.
Gangrene is death and subsequent decay of
the tissues, as above, and
frequently requires amputation of the
affected areas.
You can get frostbite both by fall in core
temperature accompanied by
prolonged interruption of warm blood
supply to the peripheral tissues or
from direct contact with a freezing
surface.
If you are trying to give first aid for
frostbite, slowly rewarm the tissues in
moderate temperatures, and don't rub.
Direct heat, hot temperatures and
rubbing can damage the tissues that are
frozen and numb.
Also, if there is a chance that the
tissues are going to refreeze,
don't try to thaw them until you are all
out of danger.
If it doesn't look like the affected areas
are getting better,
seek medical attention.
A variety of different strategies can be
applied such as sterile dressings,
pain killers, debridement, which is the
removal of dead or
damaged tissue, antibiotics, hydrotherapy,
or surgery.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
When things go bad, continued.
Paradoxical undressing.
20 to 50% of people who experience
moderate to
severe hypothermia undergo a phase of
disorientation, confusion, and
combativeness that ends in their taking
off all their clothes.
That in turn increases heat loss and
accelerates their hypothermia and demise.
Although rescue workers are trained to
expect it, the nakedness of
the victims has sometimes led to the
mistaken assumption of sexual assault.
When I asked my Stanford class why they
thought this might happen,
I got some interesting responses ranging
from delirium and
confusion, which does probably play a
role,
to nerve endings that can't feel cold any
more,which is a reasonable explanation,
to, if I'm going to die I may as well go
out in a dramatic fashion.
Okay, whatever.
To, I'd rather look good than feel good.
Cute.
Anyway, the mechanism is unclear.
As you can imagine, it is a hard research
study to do, but one theory is
that the severe cold disrupts the
hypothalamus that is responsible for
the body temperature regulation.
My favorite theory is that as you get
exhausted, cold, and
hypoglycemic, you lose the ability to keep
your peripheral vessels constricted.
Therefore, you get a sudden flush of
warmer blood from the core to
the cold peripheral tissues.
You suddenly feel very warm and
flushed and your, in your confused state,
you take off all of your clothes.
Wait.
What was that?
Terminal burrowing is something else that
occurs in end stages of hypothermia and
is often associated with paradoxical
undressing.
It is a preservation behavior where an
individual tries to squeeze into
tight spaces like under desks, in the
holes of trees or under beds to stay warm.
Okay.
I'm not trying to depress you or anything,
but
some of this information could come in
useful sometime.
I hope not, but you never know.
So, when things go bad.
Final.
Cold water immersion.
Let's say you're out sailing in the winter
in the ocean, and your boat capsizes.
Yikes!
If the water temperature is very cold,
you're at risk from the initial cold shock
response.
You probably have experienced it.
You jump off of a rope swing into a lake
that is much colder than you expect, and
it knocks the breath out of you.
Your first response is to gasp, and
if you're underwater at the time, that can
be deadly.
Hyperventilation is also common, and
in some cases it can lead to cardiac
arrest if the shock is great enough.
The key is to try not to panic, which will
make the cold response worse.
If you survive the first minute, you need
to start to worry about hypothermia.
As we talked about earlier in the cold
section,
water draws heat away from your body much
faster than air.
The numbers at the bottom of the slide
give an indication of how long
a person can survive in water of varying
temperatures.
You can see that there are pretty wide
ranges, but if you are in water that
is just above freezing, the survival time
is only between 30 and 90 minutes.
You may be tempted to swim for
shore, but keep in mind that it will make
it harder for someone to find you.
If you're away from your boat, your head
will look like a basketball in the ocean.
Also in the long run, swimming will make
you colder by increasing the movement of
water across your limbs, sending blood to
the periphery and
depleting important energy reserves.
Few people can swim a mile in 50 degree
water.
If you find yourself in such a situation,
and
I hope you don't, the general advice is as
follows.
Swim only if you are close to shore.
Otherwise, stay with the boat, which will
be the most visible thing in the water,
and wait for rescue.
Try to get out of the water by climbing
onto debris.
If you are with others, huddle together
face-first to reduce heat loss.
Try to trap air in your clothing to make
yourself more buoyant, so
you don't have to tread water which will
waste energy and increase heat loss.
Signal rescue with whatever you have,
flairs, mirrors, flashlights, whatever.
Congratulations for finishing the
Physiology of Cold Section.
We hope you will never have to use the
information in the last modules on risk,
but we tried to provide you with some
practical tips, nonetheless.
To get credit for this section, please
take the final quiz.
The next section is the Physiology of
Heat,
so get ready to see Cory get hot.
[LAUGH]
Thanks for watching.