Hello everyone.
We only have a couple of cold modules left
in this section.
Now we're going to talk about chronic
adaptations to cold.
Unfortunately for
us humans, there is not a lot we can do in
the cold, physiologically speaking.
We are tropical animals,
which means we can do more to adapt to the
heat than to the cold.
Our main adaptations are behavioral, such
as putting on clothes, seeking shelter or
lighting a fire.
When it comes to cold, we mainly just get
used to it.
However, there are a few things that our
bodies can do, to relieve cold stress.
One thing that we do, is release hormones
like norepinephrine and thyroxine.
Norepi, norepinephrine,
is a catecholamine released by the
sympathetic nervous system.
Thyroxine, is the predominant hormone
released from the thyroid gland.
Together norepinephrine and
thyroxine increase metabolic rate through
a variety of mechanisms.
One mechanism of interest is the
uncoupling of oxidative phosphorylation.
As I mentioned earlier in this section,
oxidative phosphorylation is the normally
tightly coupled process in
the body where oxygen is used to form the
body's energy currency, known as ATP.
When the process is uncoupled, energy is
used but
ATP is not being produced, which results
in excess heat generation.
Again, the common analogy is revving your
engine at
the stop light with the clutch in.
A tissue that is particularly good at
uncoupling oxidative phosphorylation is
brown adipose tissue, or BAT.
Unlike white adipose tissue, brown adipose
has a lot of mitochondria and more blood
vessels, which makes it metabolically
active and gives it its brownish color.
Brown adipose is common in rodents,
hibernating animals, and babies.
If you put a rat in the fridge, it'll
uncouple its brown adipose tissue,
generate more heat, and be happy as a
clam.
If you think about it, if you were an
animal who was at risk of being pray,
being able to generate heat without
shivering, is definitely a good thing.
You'd be able to hide better, and sleep
better for that matter.
Human babies have brown adipose along
their spines and
upper backs, which is also a good thing.
They don't shiver, either, and they can't
regulate their own body temperature,
temperature simply by getting up and
getting a blanket or going for a jog.
For many years, it was believed that
adults didn't have brown adipose tissue,
but it turns out that we do.
We just didn't have the right tools to
find it.
Some adults have more than others, and
those that have more, tend to be leaner,
than those with less of it.
Therefore, people are now discussing brown
adipose tissue as a possible target for
weight loss.
Brown fat seems to be up regulated in
colder climates.
So there's this movement of sorts out
there by people who are trying to
induce the formation of more brown adipose
in themselves, by making themselves cold,
taking frigid showers in the morning,
rolling naked in the snow,
all sorts of fun stuff.
Exercise also may up regulate brown
adipose,
and now there is a brown fat revolution
diet.
It is too soon to tell whether brown
adipose will emerge as an important
contributor to weight balance in humans,
but it is an interesting issue to watch.
Other things that we
can do to acclimatize include intermittent
peripheral vasodilation.
Sometimes referred to as the hunter's
response.
About five to ten minutes after initial
constriction of the hand,
vasodilation occurs resulting in a warm
pulse of blood to the periphery.
Then the vessels constrict down again.
The response is more pronounced in people
that have lived or
worked in the cold for long periods of
time, thus the name hunters response.
It was thought that the response protected
the hands and
feet from cold injury, but now the
benefits are less clear.
Second, long time residents of cold
climates have
adapted by increasing the insulating layer
of subcutaneous body fat.
And finally, people in cold climates seem
to get used to the discomfort.
Cold becomes less disruptive.
I actually think it is this latter element
that allows the students from
cold cultures to walk around campus in the
winter wearing shorts.
It just doesn't feel like cold to them,
it's a habituation to discomfort.
So that's it.
That is all we do acclimatize to the cold.
A short and sweet list.
Now on to the brutal stuff, risks and
consequences.
Thank you.