Welcome back.
I hope you enjoyed watching Corey warm
back up.
A number of people have asked why we
didn't put some clothes on him to
warm him up.
We probably should have, but
we were curious about whether the avacore
devices would warm him up sufficiently.
Anyway, I bring it up so you would
understand there's no physiologic reason
why we didn't put clothes back on him to
warm him up, okay?
Good.
In this module, we're going to talk about
exercise in the cold,
which is a topic that we didn't address in
the Corey get's Cold video but
is an important one nonetheless.
Whether you are climbing in the mountains,
running in the snow, or
hauling wood back to your cabin in Homer,
Alaska, it is important to
know what you can expect from your body
under these conditions?
So we'll discuss your maximum aerobic
capacity, or VO2 max, your endurance, and
your muscle activity.
Before we talk about how the cold impacts
VO2 max, I thought I should
explain what VO2 max actually is, and why
it is an important measure of fitness?
We'll be referring to it regard,
regularly throughout this environmental
physiology class.
So it's important to make sure all of you
understand it now.
VO2 is the volume of oxygen that your body
consumes at any particular time.
And VO2 max is the maximum amount of
oxygen your body can consume.
Is also called your maximal aerobic
capacity.
As you can see in the graph to my right,
VO2 is linearly related to work output.
The more work you do the more oxygen is
required to sustain that activity.
An appropriate training stimulus of high
enough intensity will increase your
VO2 max.
It's illustrated by the new line in red on
the graph.
For a given sub maximum work load after
training,
you will still need about the same amount
of oxygen.
The difference will be, that you will be
able to do more work, and
consume more total oxygen, at maximum
capacity.
The little plateau at the end of each
line, is the theoretical point,
where any additional work that you do,
is supported by non-oxydative sources of
metabolism, like fast glycolosis.
The picture that just appeared shows one
method of measuring VO2.
It was taken in the army research lab at
the top of Pikes Peak at 14,000 feet.
The participant is breathing from one way
valve that move air from the room into his
lungs, back out through the mouthpiece and
down into the analyzer.
The analyzer measures the oxygen consumed
and the CO2 produced.
V02 max is considered the gold standard
for cardiovascular fitness, because it
requires successful integration of so many
components of your cardiovascular system.
You have to breathe the air into your
lungs, which is dependent on ventilation.
Then the oxygen in the air has to diffuse
through the lung tissue into
the arterial blood, where it's picked up
by the hemoglobin in the red blood cells.
The bound oxygen then circulates through
the left side of the heart,
out through the arteries, and down into
the tissues.
Then your tissues extract the oxygen and
use it in their mytochondria to
power metabolism and sustain the high
energy outputs of exercise.
Thus VO2max is dependent on the health of
many elements of your cardiovascular and
muscle, muscle system.
For example, if your arteries are plugged
up or you have, or
are anemic your VO2max will be reduced.
On the other hand,
if you're an elite athlete who trains
regularly at high intensity endurance
activities, all those components of the
system will be optimized.
Mathematically and conceptually, V02 can
be defined by the Fick Equation,
which says that V02 is equal to Q,
which is cardiac output, times a minus v
02 difference.
Cardiac output is the amount of blood that
leaves the heart per minute, and is equal
to the heart rate, beats per minute, times
stroke volume, blood ejected per beat.
The arteriovenous O2 difference is the
amount of oxygen in the arterio blood or
little a minus the amount of oxygen in the
venous blood or v.
In other words the amount of blood
extracted by the tissues.
Together the components of the equation
tell you how much oxygen your
body is using per minute.
Okay then.
That was a long preamble to, what happens
to VO2 max in the cold?
Well, after all that, the answer is, it's
hard to say.
It depends on how cold it is outside, and
how cold you are inside.
Because of the heat that you generate
during exercise,
core temperature can go up, even if it is
very cold out.
If your core stays relatively stable,
VO2max can actually go up in the cold,
because the cooler temperatures cause
peripheral skin and
tissue vessels, to remain constricted,
which would increase central blood volume.
Higher central blood volume means more
blood would return to the heart,
increasing stroke volume, and thus cardiac
output.
The Fick equation says that higher cardiac
output means higher VO2max.
On the other hand, if core and
muscle temperatures are lower, then
maximum capacity would be impaired.
Nerve signaling would be slowed,
muscle function would be compromised,
blood would get more viscous, and
even max heart rate would decline as core
temperature went down.
So as you can see, it is critical for peak
performance to keep body and
muscle temperature in an optimal range.
An aerobic exercise that is performed for
a long period of
time at a sub-maximal workload is
considered an endurance activity.
Endurance exercise is compromised by fall
in core and or muscle temperature.
First, there is the higher metabolic cost
for a given workload, because more,
less-efficient fibers may be needed to do
the work.
Also contraction of agonist, antagonist
muscle pairs during shivering,
waste energy.
Second the constriction of peripheral
vessel means less blood flows to
subcutaneous adipose or
fat tissue, so less of that abundant long
term fuel sources available.
Therefore, there is an increased
dependence on carbohydrate fuels that
are limited in supply and can cause an
increase in lactate concentrations.
In the orange box below, it says that
bonking, or hitting the wall,
is what happens when you run out of
carbohydrate, especially glycogen.
Even if there is still fat around when
that happens,
fats burn in the fire of carbohydrate.
It's a complicated biochemical process but
essentially what it
means is you need some amount of
carbohydrate around to use your fat.
So you can't keep exercising if you've run
out of carbohydrate.
Cold muscle and
core temperatures may also change the
hemoglobin binding characteristics,
making it harder for your red blood cells
to release oxygen in the tissues.
Now, muscle activity.
Interestingly, muscle fatigue has been
shown to actually improve by some but
not all studies when the muscles are kept
slightly cool.
The mechanism of improvement is unknown,
although some scientists hypothesize that
it relates to signal processing and
central control by the brain.
Maybe the brain is thinking, hey, the
muscle isn't hot, it must not be tired.
As opposed to cool muscles, cold muscles
fatigue faster because of the slowed nerve
conduction velocity, altered recruitment
patterns, and the Q10 effect.
Peak power and strength also declines for
those same reasons.
Manual dexterity goes down for the reasons
we talked about in the previous module.
Just as a FYI, I put the tension versus
recruitment graph back up, for
you as a reminder.
So when it comes to exercise is not only
about the ambient temperature, but
how cold you are inside.
The bottomline if you're cold in the cold
is that, slightly cold can be good for
both muscle fatigue and VO2 max.
But very cold is bad for fatigue, VO2 max,
endurance and muscle strength and power.
If you're going to exercise, in serious
cold,
here are some things to keep in mind.
Make sure to dress appropriately, in
comfortable layers, that won't accumulate
sweat, and that can be removed or added as
needed to modulate temperature.
Avoid cotton, and wear a wicking layer
like polypropylene, close to your skin.
Avoid the temptation to over dress, but be
sure to at least carry a hat.
Because your head is one of the main
sources of heat loss.
Even if there is no weather generated
wind, remember that you may be moving at
a rapid pace through cold air, which
generates its own wind chill.
Also, head into the wind on the way out
and have the wind at
your back on the way in to avoid the wind
chill against sweat saturated clothing.
Proper warm-up.
Optimal performance requires the elevation
of muscle temperature before competition,
especially in events requiring strength
and power.
Heavier clothing, exercising more
intensely, and
or longer, and continuing the warm-up
until immediately before the competition,
may be required in cold conditions.
In severe cold, avoid exposing delicate
skin areas like ears, nose and fingers.
They are susceptible to frost bite.
Since the tissue would go numb first, and
there will be no sensation of pain,
check regularly, to sure that the tissues
are not turning white.
Once you stop exercising, core temperature
can fall rapidly,
because heat production slows, but heat
loss remains high.
Put on clothing layers rapidly and
to, and move to a warmer environment soon
to prevent post-exercise hypothermia.
Congratulations.
You've completed another one!
[LAUGH] Now complete the check for
understanding questions and
move on to module six to find out how our
bodies adapt to cold.
Something's gotta be going on.
Because my students from cold climates all
show up in class in
shorts in the middle of winter.
While the rest of us Californians are
freezing.
I guess we'll find out in the next module.
See you then, thank you.