Welcome back to the Physiology of Cold,
Module 3- Corey's Data.
In this module, we will take a closer look
at Corey's temperature data,
from his time in the cold room and answer
the pending questions we left you with.
Just a reminder, here are the questions.
Why didn't Corey's core temperature drop
much in the cold water bath?
Why did his temperature drop rapidly on
the treadmill?
And why was it harder for him to control
his hands and
legs in order to throw the ball and walk
on the treadmill?
To my right is a graph of Corey's Core
Temperature data as measured by
the esophageal probe.
Initially he went through an equilibration
period during which time he was
constricting down his peripheral vessels,
and
the probe was stabilizing in temperature.
Then he entered the cold bath.
During that time you can see some small
fluctuations in temperature, but
overall his temperature remained
relatively stable.
Can you think back to the previous model?
What was allowing him to keep his core
temperature stable,
even though he was sitting in a cold bath
of slowly circulating water.
Well, all those responses we talked about,
vasoconstriction, you can see that
illustrated in the color of his hands as
viewed through the infrared heat camera.
He was also shivering off and on.
His core temperature would drop a little
and
he'd start shivering, his temperature
would rebound up again and
then he'd stop shivering, then down more
shivering, then up.
The shivering cycle is what gives the
data,
that undulating line that I just
highlighted in orange.
But then what?
He gets out of the tank, starts walking on
the treadmill, and
his core temperature plummets.
Why on earth does that happen?
I thought exercise was supposed to keep
you warm.
Well, Corey's cooled limbs were behaving
as a cold sink.
He was sitting in the water with all of
his peripheral vessels constricted down.
He was successfully keeping the warm blood
in his core, but his legs and
lower body were getting colder and colder.
If we'd had temperature probes on his
lower body, even right inside the surface
of his muscles, they would have been
measuring close to the water temperature.
Then Corey got up and started walking on
the treadmill.
In order for him to use his leg muscles
for
walking, he had to send blood down into
the area.
So his warm blood passed through the cold
tissues, and
brought all that coolness back to the
core.
There you have it.
Something called after drop.
And hypothermia ensued.
In Corey's case, you can see that he had
started to turn the corner right
about the time that we stopped.
He had reached the point of maximal
shivering, but exercise was starting to
generate more heat, and his temperature
was starting to creep back up.
He probably wouldn't have gotten much
colder.
However, you can imagine that after drop
could be quite dangerous for
someone stranded in severe cold.
They're huddled in the cold for a long
time, and
then suddenly get up to run after a rescue
plane or some scenario like that.
Their core temperature could get
dangerously low.
The after drop phenomenon is also, it also
plays a cautionary role in
hypothermia first aid, but we will talk
more about that later.
The previous slide covered two of our
questions.
How did Corey keep his temperature stable
in the bath and
why did his temperature fall on the
treadmill?
Now let's address the third question.
Why did Corey have trouble controlling his
hands and feet?
Remember in the video, he struggled with
his shoelaces, he was staggering a bit on
the treadmill, and he actually threw the
ball into the water tank by accident?
When your nerves are cold, they don't work
as well,
in either direction, sensory or motor.
So part of the reason for
diminished manual dexterity is that you
can't feel your fingers and hands as well.
So limited sensory input.
You can make up for
it somewhat visually, but if you really
want a challenge, you should
try tying your shoes when your hands are
really cold with your eyes closed.
Also, motor nerve signals going from your
brain to your
muscles are slowed by the cold,
compromising reaction time.
The slowed nerve signals combined with the
tissue Q10 effect will
force an awkward change in your patterns
of movement.
The Q10 effect describes the way your body
enzymes behave in
response to temperature changes.
In our bodies, we have a Q10 of about two.
That means for
every change of ten degrees Celsius up,
our enzymes work twice as fast.
On the other hand, for
every ten degrees Celsius down our enzymes
work half as fast.
The enzymes in Corey's cold legs were
struggling to
keep up causing each muscle fiber to
produce less force.
Therefore he had to recruit more muscle
fibers to do the same work.
And here's the thing.
You have different types of muscle fibers,
Type I and Type II,
and they are good at doing different types
of activities.
Your Type I muscle fibers are what we call
slow oxidative fibers.
They are used for lower intensity work,
are well equipped to do prolonged
exercise, and are fatigue resistant.
A motor unit consists of an alpha motor
neuron and
the muscle fibers it innervates.
Muscle fibers innervated in a motor unit
range in number from under 10
to into the thousands.
Type I motor units are smaller with fewer
innervated fibers per neuron.
This allows you to do more precise
movements.
In contrast, your Type II fibers are your
power and strength fibers.
They're a form of more explosive heavier
work but they fatigue more rapidly.
They are larger motor units having more
fibers associated with each nerve.
When you are cold, you don't get as much
force out of
your smaller type one fibers as you
normally do.
So you need to switch over to your larger
type two fibers at a lower tension.
That is fine except that is harder to do
fine motor movements with your
big power fibers.
So the movement becomes jerky and
uncoordinated.
You'll also fatigue more rapidly.
What is that smell?
Smells like body odor.
Anyway, this next figure to my right
illustrates the size principle that
we were just talking about indirectly.
Under normal conditions, your body
recruits more and
more fibers as needed, for increasing
muscle tension or force.
You start off with your smaller Type I
motor units and
then move up to your larger Type II motor
units.
Thus the name, the Size Principle.
In the cold, for reasons we just
discussed, the curve shifts down and
to the right.
So, for a given muscle tension,
you are forced to use more of your bigger,
less precise fibers.
So that's why Corey had trouble, walking
on the treadmill,
throwing the ball, and tying his laces.
Please answer the quick check for
understanding questions, and then, you get
to see Corey warm up.
You'll be glad to know, we didn't leave
him all shivery and cold.
We warmed him up using some groovy
experimental devices to do it.
So check it out in the next module.
Thank you.