>> You'll be in a a setting that, it seems
death-like, you know,
it seems like a grave or, it's so quiet
and so cold.
But yet you're in your own bubble of
warmth, and
you can just move freely through it and,
and feel really awake and alive.
>> Jill Homer, a freelance writer and
adventure racer has a resume that includes
some of the world's most prestigious and
difficult cold weather, ultra endurance
events.
Since moving to Alaska in 2005 to work as
a newspaper editor, she has used races
such as the Alaska Susitna 100, Homer Epic
100k, White Mountains 100, and the 350
mile Iditarod Invitational to test her
mental and physical limits of performance.
Both on foot and on a bike.
Ultra endurance events can push the limits
of human tolerance by distance alone.
But throw in isolation, temperatures as
low as 50 degrees below 0 Fahrenheit,
partially frozen waterways and no support
crew and you have the potential for
life- threatening disasters at any moment.
Jill has learned first hand how to
understand and respect the cold.
For these reasons, and many more, it is my
great pleasure to welcome Jill Homer for
Experiential Interview on the Physiology
of Cold.
Jill, thank you for taking the time to
meet with us today.
>> Thank you for having me.
>> so, I understand that you didn't even
own a bike until your early 20s.
So how did you go from that to adventure
racing on a bike?
>> Well, I as a youth I did hiking.
I grew up in Salt Lake City, Utah.
So I was a pretty avid hiker and turned
that to backpacking.
And then later decided to try bicycle
touring, traveling by bicycle,
which is really when I took up bicycling
was to start doing this traveling.
And then in 2005, I was 25 years old, and
moved to Homer, Alaska to take a job at
a newspaper, and also because I wanted the
adventure of going to live in Alaska.
But I moved up there in September, and
thought oh the, you know,
the long winter is coming, and I really
need something to get me outdoors.
And considered skiing, but
then I discovered that people in Alaska
also ride bikes on snow in the winter.
Which seemed very intriguing to me, and
through that,
I discovered this race called the Susitna
100.
Which, I looked at the photos, and it
looked like such a great race, you know?
And the only caveat was I had never raced
anything before, and
this was 100 miles in the winter in
Alaska.
So, I signed up for it, and even my
boyfriend at the time thought I was crazy.
It's like where did that come from?
You're not really a competitive person.
You're not an athlete.
Really?
I mean, you like to ride bikes.
But I thought that having this goal would
keep me going outside in the winter.
I'd have to go out and train every day.
And that was appealing to me to have
something forcing me to do this even when
it was 20 below out or windy or snowing.
So, I ws really excited about riding my
bike in this race, the Susitna 100.
And that was February 2006, was that race.
That was my first.
>> Were you hooked?
>> I was hooked.
It was very, very hard.
And it was life changing.
>> But you made it?
>> I made it.
I finished, yes.
It took me 25 hours.
A lot of that was walking because at the
time I didn't have,
they have specialized fat tire bikes that
are made for riding on snow.
At the time I didn't have one, I just had
a regular mountain bike.
And that was a uniquely warm year in the
race, and
there was a big rainstorm, turned all the
snow to slush.
And then I could no longer,
my wheels couldn't get purchase on top of
the snow so I had to walk about 30 miles.
And I was drenched and, and I was
hypothermic because I was cold and
it was 35 degrees or so.
It was, I was wet and it was cold.
But I was just determined.
I'm going to finish this race.
I'm not going to hop, you know, the snow
machine sweeper was going by.
Like, do you need help?
But I'm, no, I'm going to finish, so, I
did, and I was, it was great.
I was
>> So, you were in Alaska, so
you were doing cold events then, but now,
you live in a warmer climate, and
yet, you're still drawn to these cold
events.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> So, why the cold?
Why is that so appealing to you?
>> Well, I mean, this probably sounds
insincere, coming from someone who lives
in the Bay area, which prob'ly has the
friendliest climate in the United States.
And I love it here, but cold is really my
favorite weather.
I really, every year we take these trips
to Alaska.
I really look forward to them.
And I think the reason I like cold so
much, is the way it just changes the whole
environment.
I mean, when you get sub-zero
temperatures, the air become very clear.
It becomes very silent.
I've been out where I've heard it, about
20 below, and I've heard footsteps on, and
I'd be in this wide open plain, and you
can't see the creature that's walking.
It's probably a half mile away, but I can
hear it like it's right next to me.
And, you get this tingle in the ear from
the ice crystals that
sound like tiny little bells ringing next
to your ears.
And, in the winter, you get that low angle
sun, which casts long shadows and
the great colors.
It's just really a magical place.
And not many people experience that, like
not many people go out into the cold.
And so it's just kind of like you have
this whole world all to yourself and
it's beautiful icy white, you know,
heaven-like setting.
And I love having the freedom to move
through the cold.
I mean, you'll be in a setting that, it
seems deathlike.
You know, it seems like a grave or it's so
quiet and so
cold, but yet you're your own bubble of
warmth and
you can just move freely through it and
feel really awake and alive.
So, I love it.
>> That's beautiful.
Makes me want to go do it.
>> Yeah I agree.
I, you know, I, I miss it.
I miss not living in Alaska.
I love living here for lots of reasons,
but it's a sacrifice in other ways.
>> So, you love being in the environment,
but you add on this
ultra-endurance component to it, as well,
which adds all sorts of new challenges.
So, how do you prepare, when you're
getting ready for
an event of that distance, where you have
no support crew, and
you're going to be in temperatures down to
50 below zero?
>> Well, I mean the most important thing
is having the right gear.
And it's always nice to test out new gear.
We don't get many opportunities here,
but just having all the survival gear you
need, all the warm clothing you need.
Knowing that that works well for you.
That, in a way, is more important than
being physically fit.
Although it is very important to be
physically fit as well,
you need to not get so tired that you
can't go on.
And you need to be mentally focused on the
task at hand.
Because you're going to be, I mean, there
are times when it's just very scary.
And, there's, a, you know, a really strong
urge to bailout in anyway possible.
>> And how often are you completely alone
in these situations?
>> We'll it's really up to you.
I mean a lot of times in these races,
there aren't many people involved but
people do team up and travel together.
They make the decision.
In the races I do I generally chose to be
alone.
I just like doing my own thing and
often times it just hasn't worked out for
me to travel with another person.
Although the year that I first
raced,Susitna 100 on foot in 2011,
Bayad and I did it together and decided to
travel together the whole time.
>> And Bayad is your partner?
>> Yeah, partner, boyfriend, so.
>> That's great.
So, what piece of equipment wouldn't you
leave without?
I mean that you have to take with you
every time?
>> Well, there's really a lot of things.
But definitely a down parka.
You know, something that I actually
probably, if all goes well,
I might not even wear.
But something that will help save my life
if something goes wrong.
>> And what have you noticed when your out
there about your physiology and
your performance as the temperature
fluctuates.
So, you know, your in a moderate
temperature of
20 below [LAUGH]
>> Yeah.
>> And it drops to 50 below, and what do
you notice there?
>> Well it's interesting because as it
gets colder, I really do slow down.
I mean, I'll feel like I'm work, you know,
if I actually had like a, some kind of a
odometer or
GPS, I would notice my speed decreasing,
even just walking or running along.
And, I think that's because it really gets
to
the point where your muscles aren't as
warm, and they can't warm up.
And that just slows you down.
I think of it as a little bit like a old
truck driving along and
the engine's sputtering, and you feel that
way.
That's one thing I've noticed.
Also, your body temperature becomes more
difficult to
regulate when it gets very cold.
I actually can, you know, put on too many
layers and start overheating and
start sweating, which is dangerous.
It's, that's the one thing you really try
to avoid, is sweating too profusely.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And when it's 20 above, it's pretty
easy to regulate temperature.
You just put on a few,
just enough layers to keep your skin from
being too exposed to the cold air.
And you output a lot of heat when you're
doing strenuous exercise.
>> And what's the tip point for
temperature that you can't have any
exposed skin or you'll get frostbite, do
you think?
>> I find about 30 below.
>> Sure.
[LAUGH]
>> Is still.
Yeah.
20 to 30 below.
I, I have been out at 20 below with my
full face exposed because I was running.
And then, you know, a ice mask would form
around my
the buff that I was wearing
>> Uh-huh.
>> Thirty below is when I really need to
put on the goggles or
my eyes are going to start,you know, I
feel that scratchiness.
Oh, my eyes are starting to freeze.
When it's windy it can be a lot warmer.
If you have a headwind and
even at zero, and it's blowing directly in
your face, really have to cover up.
>> And, you, there have gotta been times,
there has to have been times, when you
were out and you were scared.
That, you know, something was going wrong,
or
you just didn't want to be in that
situation.
So, describe some of those experiences.
>> Well I started the Iditarod in 2009.
And about 25 miles into the race I was
crossing a lake.
And there was a part where this stream was
coming in and
there was a, a pressure crack that I
didn't see.
That was just covered in a very thin layer
of ice.
And at the time I was, had a bike but
I was walking because the snow was very
drifted and I couldn't ride.
And I actually stepped right into that,
that thin ice crack and
punched my leg all the way through, almost
up to my hip with one leg.
I managed to in the the frantic-ness of
it,
managed to scramble out before I put any
other body parts in which could have been,
I mean, I could have ended up in a lake.
Because it was just, it was probably wide
enough to, to punch through, all the way
through, but I, I got part of my bike wet
as well but I managed to crawl out.
And I had a wet leg, And at the time it
was about zero maybe five below, but
there was a really strong wind cranking
over the lake.
And I knew I needed to, you know, I could
hear water sloshing around in the boot
that I was wearing, mountaineering boot is
what I use for biking.
And so I knew I needed to deal with it but
I didn't want to do it out on a lake where
it was so exposed to the wind.
I'm like I'm going to get off the lake and
go to, to these trees.
But it took awhile to get to the trees,
and by the time I got there
a pretty thick layer of ice formed all the
way up my leg, and I had gaiters on.
And I would chip at it, and there was just
no way that boot was coming off.
I mean, I don't know how I would have
gotten it off so
I'm like, well next checkpoint is about 30
miles away, and
maybe if I ride 10 minutes and run 5
minutes,
I'll keep my foot warm enough to, to get
there without any problems.
But I, I was doing this and, and
I was actually feel, okay, I feel okay,
you know?
And I would, I made an effort to wiggle my
toes.
And I thought I was continuing to do that,
but in retrosp, you know,
in hindsight I probably was only imagining
myself wiggling my toes.
They probably weren't actually moving.
Because, as I kept going, the water inside
the boot froze solid.
It got colder and colder right around my
foot.
So it was just encased in a block of ice.
And the temperature dropped to,
other racers told me around Around 35 to
40 below that night.
So when I got to the next check point and
finally, and I sat by the fire for about
20 minutes before I could undo my gaiter.
I'm trying to pull my boot off and it's
not coming off.
I'm like, what's wrong.
And I couldn't get the boot off.
It took, I mean, I had my foot up against
the wood stove.
It took another, probably 25-30 minutes of
thawing before I
was able to pull my bare foot out of the
sock that was frozen into the boot.
And it was, the whole foot was just chalk
white and I'm like, that's not good.
When I tried to move my toes, it was like
looking at them and nothing was happening.
So I decided, well I was going to try to
get some more miles in that night and
go to the next checkpoint but I, at the
time like that,
that could be a bad idea so I'm going to
wait it out, and went to sleep.
And then my foot started to thaw which was
probably the most painful experience I've
ever had was the thawing of the frozen
foot.
And as soon as it thawed, it blistered up
heavily.
The tips turned black.
And I actually even consulted the check
guy,
the official at the check point about it.
I'm like, what do you think?
How bad is this?
It was really painful.
I could barely walk.
>> I've seen worse.
>> [LAUGH] And he's like, he's like, you
won't keep your toes if you go on.
He's like, he's like, he told me he hadn't
seen frostbite that bad in awhile.
>> Wow.
Okay.
>> On, on, you know, on a foot, so.
>> So that was it?
>> Yeah.
He said, he said,
you know, you can't continue in this race,
even if you,
you know, you're putting your life at
risk, maybe.
So, I scratched.
Went back and it was a long recovery
process.
Ori, initially,
they told me they were going to chop off
the tips of two of my toes.
But I had a really good doctor in Juno.
She was actually a burn specialist from
Fresno.
She had just barely moved to Alaska from
California herself.
But she was really good at recovering dead
skin, and
>> So you have all your toes.
>> I saved my toes.
>> Nice.
[LAUGH]
>> But with it you asked me if it
was really scary.
At the time it wasn't really frightening,
because I was just,
I thought I was dealing with the situation
as well as I could, and
in hindsight I made some poor decisions,
but.
>> And what would, what would you have
done differently?
>> What I really should have done is,
I should have stopped on the lake the
minute I got my foot wet.
Even with the snow, you know, and gotten
my sleeping bag out to put,
taken my boot off right away, gotten the
sleeping bag out, and then,
stuffed dry snow inside the boot to try to
draw out as much moisture, you know?
And then try to put a dry sack in there.
And use that system to get to the next
check point.
Keeping my foot as dry as possible.
>> What else have you learned with these
races that you,
you know, that you wouldn't do again?
Or that, you know, are sort of rookie
mistakes?
If you can share it with people.
>> Well other things that I've learned is
just how quickly wind can effect your body
temperature.
When Bayad and I did the Susitna 100 in
2011, you know?
That was after I had lived in Alaska for
years.
I had actually moved away from Alaska by
that point,
but I thought I was an old pro at that
point with the cold weather.
And since we were running early in the
race, we were really warm and
we were dressed pretty lightly for the
temperature, which was about 10 below.
But then it got dark and the wind started
cranking.
And we were still dressed in our, just our
single tights and our one, you know,
it had like two layers on top.
And we turned on this river directly into
the wind, and
it was just like this furnace blast of
cold air.
Like oh.
And, and I said,
I gotta get my down coat out.
I'm really actually suddenly really cold.
And I want to put my down coat on.
And so we stopped, and we were digging
around in our sleds.
And as we were doing this, like my fingers
went really rigid, and
it got to a point where I couldn't even,
like I was trying to work to the zipper.
And so now I'm really frantically, like
I'm pulling my down coat on,
and I'm trying to zip it up, and like I
just had these claws for hands.
And they weren't moving.
I'm like oh.
And and I called out to Bayad, I'm like
can you help me zip up my
coat because I can't, you know?
And he was able to help me do that and
help me get my mittens back on.
We got our sleds out and started running
really quickly so as were running and
I have my down coat on, slowly it's
thawing out, you know.
But it is really scary to lose the use of
your hands and
if Bayad hadn't been there I would have
had a lot more problems.
Not being able to zip up my coat up, it
wouldn't give me any warmth,
because there, you know, the insulating
properties wouldn't work so.
>> Yeah.
It seems to me,
you've just given us several examples of
why you may not want to do this.
>> [LAUGH] Exactly.
>> Why, why, I mean,
you can go out into the beautiful
environments that you're talking about,
and not be doing a 350 mile Iditarod race
on your own.
So what, what drives you to keep that
challenge alive?
Other than the environment.
I mean why, why, why push yourself in
those environments on your own?
>> Well, it is, it's a very intense
experience.
I mean I love just the experience of being
alive, feeling everything,
all my senses sharpened.
And the endurance aspect of it really adds
to that intensity.
I mean, it's an intense experience just to
walk out of your house into 20 below and
stand out there, just for a few minutes.
That actually is, as well.
But there's just something deeper about
going out and just, basically, surviving.
I mean, that's, obviously, we'd survive a
lot better in California.
But, but getting that sense that I'm out
here, and
this is a really harsh environment but I'm
alive and
I'm, it just, it makes you feel very alive
and it's a very rewarding experience.
And there is hardly, there's no margin for
error.
And these are, the mistakes I made at the
time, I thought were very small mistakes.
They grew into bigger mistakes very
quickly.
And so you just have to be really focused
and
I kind of like that environment where you
have to do everything right.
I mean it really keeps me focused which is
a rewarding experience as well.
So, what kind of advice do you have for
people who want to do this?
>> Well, the two most important things for
doing a cold weather event are gear and
experience.
Because everybody responds differently to
cold,
as I'm sure you've seen in your studies.
And so, you've gotta figure out what works
for you.
You can't just go online and see oh, well,
this person bought all of these pieces of
gear, and I will buy exactly that and be
fine.
You actually need to test out different
kinds of materials, different, you know,
layers of gear.
And so, really testing gear is important
and also just gaining the experience in
the cold if you can to see how your body
reacts.
It will help you make better decisions
when you actually go out there.
I don't live, I mean I'm in the same
situation now where,
a lot of my experience is older and now I
live in California.
We're going to get a few training trips in
this season.
But I worry about that, I worry about
having lost that experience and,
you know, when it's 40 below again and
I need to make a very fast decision, so I
don't freeze my hands.
The, you know, making that decision before
my core temperature drops so
much that I freeze my hands.
>> So, do you have any last words of
wisdom that you'd like to share with our
viewing audience out there?
>> I, my only words of wisdom is I think
this is a very worthwhile
experience for people.
I, I highly recommend it.
Anyone who's interested in endurance
sports, or
cold weather sports, should just give it a
try.
It's a very small sport.
There aren't a lot of events out there.
But they're a worthwhile goal.
So.
>> Thank you so much for your time.
>> Thank
you!
[BLANK_AUDIO]