Hello everyone.
We hope you enjoyed watching Corey get
cold.
There were some interesting surprises in
how his body responded to the cold.
And we'll explain why those occurred in
one of the upcoming modules.
Before we get started with the material
though, let's take a look at a series of
questions that we will address throughout
this physiology of cold section.
Of course we will answer the questions
that we left you with at the end of
the Corey gets Cold video.
Why didn't Corey's core temperature drop
much in the bath?
Why did his temperature drop rapidly on
the treadmill?
And why was it harder for
him to control his hands and legs as he
started to cool down?
But also in this section,
we will talk about what factors determine
whether you get cold?
How your body responds when it is cold?
How your exercise performance is impacted
by cold conditions?
What are the ways that you can adapt to
make cold less stressful?
We'll talk about cold related risk such as
hypothermia, frostbite and
cold water immersion, and what you can do
to prevent them?
And then we'll talk about the interesting
phenomenon of paradoxical undressing, and
who knows, if we're lucky, maybe we'll
even get a demonstration of it.
To my right is the organization of the
modules within this section that
will help us answer those questions that
we just laid out.
You've already seen the Corey Gets Cold
Module, so next we
will move on to acute responses, and then
Corey's Temperature, Data, and Questions.
After that, you get a bonus story video
where you get to watch Corey warm up.
After he warms up, we'll move on to
exercise in the cold,
chronic exposure, and risks, consequences
and practical tips.
Okay then, let's get started with module
two: Acute responses to the cold.
First, a bit about body temperature
balance.
As you probably know, core temperature in
humans is regulated around
37 degrees Centigrade or 98.6 Fahrenheit.
Core temperature is a little cooler in the
mornings and
gets higher during exercise or with a
fever.
Can also be impacted by things like,
hormones, menstrual cycles,
illnesses, problems with your thyroid,
ovulation, drugs, and many other things.
But the bottom line is that your body
works hard to keep core temperature in
a relatively tight range when possible for
optimal functioning of body systems.
Heat gain comes from two sources.
The internal generation of heat and the
heat from the environment.
As homeotherms, we humans use metabolic
activity to regulate our
body temperature usually at a temperature
higher than the surrounding environment.
Every metabolic reaction that takes place
in our body is only about 25% efficient.
That means that 75% of the energy used to
do the reaction is given off as heat.
We trap a portion of that heat as needed
in our body to keep ourselves warm.
We're also constantly losing heat to the
environment through radiation, conduction,
convection and evaporation.
Radiation is the loss of heat through
infrared rays.
Conduction is the transfer of heat between
solid materials like sitting on
a cold bench.
Convection removes heat with the flow of
air or water across our skin.
And evaporation is the loss of heat
through a phase change from liquid to gas,
like with sweat.
The four methods of heat transfer take on
a different level of
importance based on multiple factors such
as ambient temperature,
clothing, humidity, and exercise.
On this slide,
we will discuss what determines how cold
you get in a particular environment?
You can think of these items as risk
factors for hypothermia.
The first category we'll discuss is the
most obvious: environmental factors.
Clearly the colder the ambient temperature
the more likely you are to feel cold, and
then to eventually get cold.
We need to experience a fall in core
temperature known as hypothermia.
Whether you're in the water or air also
makes a difference.
Water conducts heat away from the body 25
or more times faster than air,
thus shortening both time to hypothermia
and survival time.
Movement of the air or wind across your
skin means more air
molecules touching you, so faster removal
of heat.
The air that is warmed by your skin then
moves on being replaced with
colder air which again draws heat from
your body.
There are charts available online that
show how much colder it feels for
a given temperature and wind speed.
For example, a temperature of 15 degrees
Fahrenheit will feel like minus two in
a 20 mile an hour wind, and a minus eight
in a 40 mile an hour wind.
You saw a more minor illustration of this
when Corey got into the water bath.
Remember when he complained about the
water pump being on?
Accidentally on, I might add.
Anyway, he said something like, the
courage is the worst part, and
then, oh, that's so brutal.
It felt much colder for him when the
warmed water around his
skin was moved away and replaced with more
cold water.
Individual characteristics.
Age.
Kids and adults over 60 have more trouble
staying warm.
You may have seen this illustrated in your
family: parents, grandparents, children,
et cetera.
Older adults have a compromised ability to
vasoconstrict peripheral vessels, so
they lose more heat to the environment.
They also tend to have a lower metabolic
rate so
they produce less internal heat to start
with.
On the other hand, kids actually have a
higher metabolic rate relative to
their size, but they also have a higher
surface to volume ratio.
The increased surface area means that they
lose more heat to
the environment relative to the amount of
body tissue they have generating heat.
Gender.
Women have certain advantages when it
comes to staying warm, because they on
average have more subcutaneous fat, that
serves as an insulating layer.
On the other hand, women, and again it is
on average have less muscle mass and
a higher surface area to volume ratio,
because we tend to be smaller than men.
Body size, we just discussed.
So bigger and thicker equals higher heat
retention.
Muscle mass is also very important.
Muscle is the most metabolically active
tissue in your body.
The more muscles you have, the more
cellular work, and
the more heat generated.
Next category is insulating factors.
First is the amount of subcutaneous fat
you have.
Just like elephant, seals and whales have
a lot of blubber to protect them
from frigid ocean temperatures, we too
have insulating layers that keep us warm.
Not that I'm calling you an elephant seal.
Think of subcutaneous fat as Styrofoam cup
around your coffee.
Both are effective insulators, but not
terribly desirable these days.
In the video, Corey didn't have much fat
to insulate him from the surrounding cold.
Clothing is next.
Corey didn't have a lot of that either.
Clothing is our most effective way to
insulate ourselves.
We know from a very young age that some
clothes are warmer than others.
This has to do with the clo rating of the
clothes.
Just an FYI, one clo represents the
thermal insulation sufficient to
keep a resting person warm at 20 degrees
centigrade,
with less than 50% humidity, and a wind at
six meters per minute.
The colder the temperature and
the less active the person, the higher the
clo rating needs to be.
It is important to dress in layers during
activity,
because sweat will lower the insulating
capacity of clothing,
which brings us to the next item on the
list, wet versus dry.
Intuitivelly, we all know that wet clothes
do not insulate as well.
Have you heard the expression cotton
kills?
This is because cotton has branchy fibers
that soak up moisture like a sponge and
hold it next to your skin,
preventing you from forming a warm
insulating layer around your body.
Synthetic fibers with wicking capabilities
or wool, are better insulators when wet.
Phew.
This is a really long slide.
But only one more category to go.
Heat production.
Your basal metabolic rate, or BMR, is your
lowest metabolism.
Essentially what it would be if you were
just lying in bed quietly.
It is your baseline rate and is impacted
by a variety of things like hormones, age,
gender, drugs, body size, and especially
muscle mass, as we discussed earlier.
Your BMR and any activity you do
determines the inside of
the heat balance equation when you in,
when you are in a cold environment.
We will talk about heat coming from the
environment in the heat section later
in the class.
Okay, so all of these static factors will
combine to determine whether or
not you become hypothermic when exposed to
the cold.
But your body is not going to just give
into those determinants without
a good fight.
It is going to do what it can to help you
stay warm regardless of
the outside conditions and your body
characteristics.
We saw some of the acute responses in
Corey's video.
First on the list is shivering.
Shivering contracts agonist and
antagonistic muscle groups simultaneously,
thus producing small contractions that
generate heat, but little movement.
In contrast, non-shivering thermogenesis,
next on the list, can't be seen, but still
generates heat.
With some of your cells, there are ways to
decrease how efficiently you
use oxygen and fuels to produce energy, a
process called oxidative phosphorylation.
We'll talk about this in more detail
later, but basically uncoupling in
the process is like revving your engine at
a red light with the clutch in.
You're using fuel, producing heat but no
forward movement is taking place.
Another way your body keeps itself warm is
by vasoconstricting the vessels to your
skin and the periphery.
The result is that warm blood from the
core of your body stays more in the core.
Therefore, you lose less heat to the
surface of your body and
the surrounding environment.
The signal to constrict is mediated
through the sympathetic nervous system,
local signals, and circulating hormones.
And finally we have piloerection on the
list.
A funny word, but essentially it just
means goosebumps.
In the video, Corey made a joke about his
mass of chest hair keeping him warm.
That's because goosebumps used to be more
effective when we were hairier, so
that raising each hair follicle would form
an insulating layer under
which warm air could be trapped.
A built-in fur coat, as it were.
Now, with less hair, it is less effective,
but still a common response.
Overall, controlled body temperature in
the cold falls to the region of
the brain called the posterior
hypothalamus.
Many signals from different parts of your
body are all integrated there to create
a comprehensive management plan for your
body's derma regulation.
Your body has a certain order in which it
tries to keep you warm.
It doesn't all happen simultaneously.
To my right are a couple of blank graphs.
In the upper one, we're going to diagram a
typical pattern of heat production on
the vertical axis, versus outside or skin
temperature on the horizontal axis.
In the bottom one,
we will plot core temperature across the
same range as skin temperatures.
Basal metabolic rate lays the foundation
of heat production.
Around the thermoneutral zone,
where you are most comfortable, your body
manipulates blood throw,
blood flow through the vessels to regulate
temperature.
On the low end, say around 20 degrees
Celsius,
your peripheral vessels will be maximally
constricted.
On the high end, above 37 degrees, you'll
be maximally dilated to allow for
excess heat loss.
Above that you will also start sweating.
But we'll talk about more, talk about that
more in the heat section.
If you have already maximally constricted
down and you're still getting cold,
your body will start to compensate through
shivering and non-shivering thermogenesis.
Combined, those two mechanisms can
increase your metabolic rate four to
five times.
The leaner someone is, the more they will
need to shiver for
a given ambient temperature.
So there are ranges where your body
focuses on different strategies.
First it will use the less energetically
costly mechanism of vasoconstriction.
And then it will increase metabolic rate.
Evolutionarily speaking, it's kind of a
risky behavior to shiver.
As you have probably experienced, it is
harder to do activities of daily living,
like tying your shoes, throwing a ball, or
hiding from a sabertooth tiger when you
are shaking.
It also could waste valuable energy that
you might need later,
if you don't have much luck in the hunt.
In our case, the hunt may consist of
finding the nearest 7-11,
but in earlier times, it was for actual
living food.
The bottom graph indicates that we are
pretty good at regulating our
core temperature over a wide range.
There was a gradual fall in the middle,
with sharper rises and
declines on the two ends.
That's it for Module 2.
At the end of this module and
most others, you will find some Check for
Understanding questions.
Please answer them when they are available
before moving onto the next modules.
Next up, Module 3, Corey's Data.
You should have enough information now to
answer some of those questions we left you
with at the end of the Corey Gets Cold
video.
Thank you.