Welcome back to the Physiology of Cold:
Module 7- Risks,
Consequences & Practical Tips.
You can see some of the risks in the
pictures to my right: missing toes,
sailors with hypothermia rescued at sea by
the US Navy.
There are a lot of things to consider and
prepare for when you're out in the cold.
Let's start with hypothermia.
Hypothermia is when your core temperature
drops below normal.
But there are various degrees of
hypothermia.
A two degree drop in core temperature is
considered mild hypothermia, and
that is where you get maximal shivering,
which is just about where Corey was at the
end of his experience in the cold room.
Do you remember this?
Yay, victory.
>> Awesome.
>> [INAUDIBLE] [LAUGH]
>> You did different warm
[INAUDIBLE] to that.
>> Yeah.
>> Are we done?
>> Yeah we're done, let's get him warmed
up.
>> It's so cold [INAUDIBLE] background,
there's no heat in the shoe so
you can't feel that your hands are so
cold.
>> Your hands are just [LAUGH]
>> [SOUND]
>> Okay, let's get you out of here.
>> Anyway, you get the idea.
That is some serious shivering, shivering.
A four degree centigrade drop in core
temperature is
considered moderate hypothermia.
At that stage, you can expect to see
apathy and
ataxia, that means uncoordinated
movements.
You also start to make bad decisions
because you're not thinking clearly.
Then, with a six degree drop,
you get severe hypothermia, which can lead
to unconsciousness.
A drop greater than six degrees can lead
to abnormal heart rhythms,
decreased brain blood flow, and death.
A core temperature between 23 and
25 degrees is usually fatal, with some
exceptions.
To get hypothermia, it doesn't need to be
frostbite cold.
You can get hypothermic whenever the heat
loss is greater than the amount of
heat your body is producing, that can even
be during exercise,
despite the high metabolic rate.
I remember some distinct times back in my
youth, before performance fabrics were so
common, when I made myself hypothermic
even in Marin County,
California in the summer, which is not
that cold.
I would ride my mountain bike up Mount Tam
in the afternoon in the sun,
get all sweaty in my cotton t-shirt, and
then head down the shady side of the
mountain as the sun was setting.
Again, not that cold out, but between the
hypoglycemia, which is low blood sugar,
the shade, the wind chill from riding
down, and the sweat, I was so cold and
shaking so uncontrollably on my bike, I
had to get off and walk down the mountain.
The thing about hypothermia is that it can
get bad fast.
When you depress the central nervous
system,
shivering actually stops when you need it
the most.
You also may out of the energy you needed
to do the shivering,
plus you start to get very confused.
So you start making poor decisions, that
can make a bad situation worse quickly.
Because of the depression of the central
nervous system and
the slowed reaction rates in your body,
your heart rate may beat one to
five times per minute, right before you
die of hypothermia.
In that condition, you're not actually
dead yet, just in a sort of,
suspended animation.
Some people have been revived from such
condition as they warm up.
You've probably all heard about children,
who have been pulled from frozen lakes,
after thirty minutes, and survive, even
though they look initially dead.
It happens more in children because their
small body size means they lose heat
faster, so they go into suspen-, suspended
animation more quickly,
before they get brain damage.
So a good rule of thumb is that you're not
dead until you're warm and dead.
Keep that in mind if you find someone out
in the snow who is non-responsive.
In such a situation, it's difficult to
know whether to start CPR,
because the very low ventilation and heart
rate are hard to detect.
If you start CPR and the heart is still
beating,
you can cause ventricular fibrillation, or
an irregular heart rhythm.
In fact, when the heart is very cold,
any type of abrupt movement can put the
heart at risk, so be careful.
Therefore it's recommended that, you start
a short period of assisted ventilation,
to hopefully increase Oxygen levels, and
thus cardiac function, to a point where it
can be detected.
After that, if you can't find a carotid,
pulse in more than 60 seconds, start CPR.
Here's some practical advice on avoiding
and treating hypothermia; most
of it is common sense but we'll go through
it quickly anyway.
For prevention, cover up in layers that
you can remove during exercise and
quickly put back on afterwards.
Stay dry and avoid over exertion both
because, the sweat will make you wet, and
if you deplete your energy reserves it'll
be harder to stay warm.
If someone is hypothermic you can do the
following: remove their wet clothes and
insulate them from the cold ground.
Warm them with blankets or whatever you
have available.
If the person is not shivering, then
moderate external warmth like body heat or
heating pads can be helpful.
We've all seen scenes in movies when two
people have to get naked in
a sleeping bags to recover from
hypothermia.
It usually leads to no good in the movies,
but
it can be an effective way to warm someone
up.
However, if someone is still shivering,
they'll warm faster if you just dry them
off, insulate them, and then, then let
them shiver, because moderate external
heat can suppress shivering and won't warm
them up any faster.
By the way, the best places to put warm
compresses or
pads are the neck, face, groin, and arm
pits.
Don't put warm compresses on the
periphery,
as it could force cold blood back to the
core and increase after drop.
If available, a warm water bath starting
around 42 degrees centigrate and
gradually rising to 45 degrees can be an
effective way to rewarm someone.
But be careful of a fall in blood pressure
due to rapid vasodilation.
Also, in severe hypothermia, be cautious
about including the arms and
the legs in the bath, because it could
induce after drop,
causing core temperatures to fall rapidly
before rising again.
The stagnant blood also becomes very
acidic when it is trapped in
the peripheral tissue for long periods of
time.
It can cause abnormal heart rhythms if it
is returned too rapidly to the core,
due to peripheral rewarming.
Therefore, it is safest to start by
rewarming the core, and keep the arms and
the legs out of the water bath at least
initially.
If conscious, give warm beverages and
easily digestible calories to
treat dehydration and hypoglycemia, which
frequently accompany hypothermia.
Don't use hot water or apply direct heat
that can cause damage to the tissues.
And finally, with moderate or severe
hypothermia, seek medical treatment.
Warm intrevenous fluids can be given, or
in extreme cases,
blood can be removed from the body by a
machine like a dialysis unit, warmed, and
then recirculated back into the patient.
Overall, remember to be gentle when
handling someone with hypothermia,
jarring or aggressive moments could lead
to cardiac arrest.
Also, watch rescued victims closely, even
if they seem okay initially,
because frequently core temperature will
get worse before it starts getting better.
Frostbite usually affects smaller exposed
areas of skin like,
fingers, toes, noses, ears, chins, and
cheeks.
It occurs when the skin and the tissue
right underneath it freezes.
First, your skin becomes very cold, then
numb, hard, and pale.
Frostnip, the first stage of frostbite,
irritates the skin, but
doesn't cause permanent damage.
Severe frostbite, on the other hand, can
damage skin, tissue, muscle, and
even bones, leading to complications,
complications such as infection, gangrene,
and nerve damage.
Gangrene is death and subsequent decay of
the tissues as above, and
frequently requires amputation of the
affected areas.
You can get frostbite both by fall in core
temperature,
accompanied by prolonged interruption of
warm blood supply to
the peripheral tissues, or from direct
contact with a freezing surface.
If you are trying to give first aid for
frost bite, slowly rewarm the tissues in
moderate temperatures and don't rub.
Direct heat, hot temperatures and
rubbing can damage the tissues that are
frozen and numb.
Also if there is a chance that the tissues
are going to refreeze don't try to
thaw them until you are all out of danger.
If it doesn't look like the effected areas
are getting better,
seek medical attention; a variety of
different strategies can be applied,
such as sterile dressings, pain killers,
debridement, which is the removal of
dead or damaged tissue, antibiotics,
hydrotherapy or surgery.
When things go bad continued: Paradoxical
Undressing.
20 to 50% of people who experience
moderate to
severe hypothermia undergo a phase of
disorientation, confusion and
combativeness that ends in their taking
off all their clothes.
That in turn increases heat loss and
accelerates their hypothermia and demise.
Although rescue workers are trained to
expect it, the nakedness of
the victims has sometimes led to the
mistaken assumption of sexual assault.
When I asked my Stanford class why they
thought this might happen, I got some
interesting responses, ranging from
delirium and confusion which does probably
play a role, to nerve endings that can't
feel cold anymore, which is a reasonable
explanation, to if I'm going to die, I may
as well go out in a dramatic fashion.
Okay, whatever.
To I'd rather look good than feel good,
cute.
Anyway, the mechanism is unclear,
as you can imagine it is a hard research
study to do.
But one theory is that the severe cold
disrupts the hypothalamus
that is responsible for the body
temperature regulation.
My favorite theory is that as you get
exhausted, cold and
hypoglycemic, you lose the ability to keep
your peripheral vessels constricted.
Therefore, you get a sudden flush of
warmer blood from the core to the cold,
peripheral tissues.
You suddenly feel very warm and
flushed; in your, in your confused state
you take off all of your clothes.
Wait, what was that?
[LAUGH]
Terminal Burrowing is something else that
occurs in end stages of hypothermia, and
is often associated with paradoxical
undressing.
It is a preservation behavior, where an
individual tries to squeeze into tight
spaces, like under desks, in the holes of
trees, or under beds to stay warm.
Okay, I'm not trying to depress you or
anything, [LAUGH] but some of this
information could come in useful sometime.
I hope not, but you never know.
So when things go bad final: Cold water
immersion.
Let's say you're out sailing in the winter
on the ocean and your boat capsizes.
Yikes!
If the water temperature is very cold,
you're at risk from the initial cold shock
response.
You've probably experienced it; you jump
off of a rope swing into a lake that
is much colder than you expect, and it
knocks the breath out of you.
Your first response is to gasp, and
if you are underwater at the time, that
can be deadly.
Hyperventilation is also common, and
in some cases, it can lead to cardiac
arrest if the shock is great enough.
The key is to try not to panic, which will
make the cold response worse.
If you survive the first minute, you need
to start to worry about hypothermia.
As we talked about earlier in the cold
section,
water draws heat from your body much
faster than air.
The numbers at the bottom of this slide,
give an indication of how long a person
can survive water of varying temperatures.
You can see that there are pretty wide
ranges, but if you were in water that
is just above freezing, the survival time
is only between 30 and 90 minutes.
You may be tempted to swim for
shore, but keep in mind that it will make
it harder for someone to find you.
If you're away from your boat, your head
will look like a basketball in the ocean.
Also, in the long run,
swimming can make you colder by increasing
the movement of water across your limbs,
sending blood to the periphery, and
depleating important energy reserves.
Few people can swim a mile in 50 degree
water.
If you find yourself in such a situation,
and
I hope you don't, the general advice is as
follows.
Swim, only if you are close to shore,
otherwise stay with the boat,
which will be the most visible thing in
the water, and wait for rescue.
Try to get out of the water by climbing on
to debris.
If you are with others, huddle together,
face first, to reduce heat loss.
Try to trap air into your clothing, to
make yourself more buoyant, so
you don't have to tread water, which will
waster energy and increase heat loss.
Signal rescue with whatever you have:
flares, mirrors, flashlights, whatever.
Congratulations for finishing the
Physiology of Cold Section!
We hope you will never have to use the
information in the last modules on risk,
but we tried to provide you with some
practical tips, nonetheless.
To get credit for this section please take
the final quiz.
The next section is the physiology of heat
so get ready to see Corey get hot.
[LAUGH] Thanks for watching.