>> The culmination of your efforts, the
feeling is just so
visceral, the sense of accomplishment.
And, like, I can do anything if I've done
this.
>> Emilie Cortes is an avid high altitude
and glacier mountaineer.
Her previous climbs include Makalu, Mt
Mckinley, Mt Rainier,
Kilimanjaro, and Mexico and Ecuador
volcanoes, among many others.
Emily runs an all-women's adventure travel
company called Call of
the Wild Adventures.
She recently left her 17-year finance
career,
where she managed $7 billion in assets, to
align her passion and vocation.
Empowering women through positive
experiences in the outdoors.
Although her previous career was
impressive, it is her life transition and
current role of inspiring women through
outdoor experiences that we
are interested in discussing today.
So, Emilie, so excited to have you here
today.
Thank you for agreeing to talk with us.
>> Thank you for having me.
>> Yes, and so we met while I was
preparing this class, and that is one of
the great perks of this class, is just
meeting very interesting people like you.
And I was so inspired by your story of
this life transition that you
made from a very lucrative corporate job
into these outdoor adventures.
Can you share your experience on how that
transition took place?
>> Sure, and first I'm like flattered to
have anybody call me interesting,
because I still think of myself as little
old me.
[LAUGH] But that may be a, a theme
throughout all of my story.
So I basically went into finance because I
didn't have a lot of family or
a lot of support and I was super driven
and super focused and
just wanted to do something that was
lucrative in order to take care of myself.
And I was pretty good at it, and I enjoyed
my clients and my relationships and
I'm good at math, but in the end, I just
wasn't feeling super fulfilled.
And there are a lot of demands and aspects
of the corporate world that had
become more and more unsavory to me as I
got older.
When I was about 30 or so, I just kind of
fell into climbing, and
I'd never really considered myself an
athletic person before.
I was always kind of the, the slowest one,
or the last one picked for dodgeball.
Actually I remember I would like, try to
hide and skip PE a lot.
[LAUGH] But I, I totally fell into
climbing, and
that's a whole nother story in and of
itself, but
I found that if I prepared, and I did a
lot of the things that were really re,
required especially in high altitude,
which is to go slow on purpose.
To be body aware, to be disciplined, that
I was actually pretty darn good at it.
And it really kind of shocked me that I
could be good at something that was so
physically demanding.
So along the way I very slowly and
methodically acquired skills.
I really understood that there was danger
in this activity and
I didn't want to get myself killed.
So, I also then began to lead trips.
And that was a really big growth
experience for
me, to take the responsibility of others
in the back country, and
actually believe that I had the ability to
do that.
But along the, the way with that, I would
see with these co-ed groups that I
would lead, the guys would kind of come in
with a lot of confidence, and
they would acquire the skills, and they
would be appreciative and
they would leave with a lot of confidence.
And, you know, making generalizations of
course.
But, the women would usually come in and
have a lot less confidence, be worried
would they be able to hack the cold,
would they be a burden, could they really
do this.
And then when they did, because they
pretty much always would and
were capable, especially with some
coaching and
guidance, they would just practically be
transformed as people.
And I've heard, heard gals say things
like,
nothing in the office is going to seem
hard now because I did this thing.
And that's the transformational aspect
where I feel like I'm
having real impact on real people and
that's so
much more meaningful for me and I made the
plunge to make that my full time job.
>> Very daring.
So, when you take these women out, do they
come back for more or is it, sort of,
one experience that they have and they
have this confidence and then that's over?
>> No, they usually keep coming back for
more.
I mean, it's almost an addicting thing and
whether, you know,
a five mile hike is hard for you or
backpacking the top of Mount Whitney is
hard for you but within your abilities.
You go, wow, you know, I see the results
of having worked hard, of having a goal.
Like, I'm also way more motivated by,
you know, climbing Denali, than I am
looking good in a bikini,
to actually be consistent with my own
workouts and training.
But, there's just something different
about when you get to
the top of the mountain.
And it's like the entire world expands
before your feet.
And all these hours, and all of the
prioritization and all the hard work, and
even potentially, and I may be now, you
know, tell it, not great marketing for
my company, but there's sometimes a little
suffering involved right?
[LAUGH] You work through that, and then
it's like, the culmination of
your efforts, the feeling's just so
visceral, the sense of accomplishment.
And, like, I can do anything if I've done
this.
>> So you've been on both co-ed trips, and
maybe even led co-ed trips, and
then all women trips.
So how do they differ in their feelings,
between those two groups of people?
>> Yeah, they're quite different.
Actually shockingly different, in a few
ways.
One is, sometimes I feel like I have to be
a little gentle with the male ego.
So, if a guy's trying to redirect
something that I want to do,
I have to really acknowledge them and make
sure they don't feel threatened, and
then do what I'm going to do anyways.
Some of that, just, the gender dynamic is
gone with an all female group.
But the thing that really struck me the
most when I started leading all female
groups, was that there were women in the
leadership, and there were no men around.
And like, my guide, my partner in Nepal,
says to me, he's like, what do
you mean there are no men on your trips,
what happens if something goes wrong.
And it's like, well, we, we figure it out?
And I feel like it's this reflection of
the corporate world, as well.
When you look around, and it's mostly
white male, and
it's starting to change, but most of my
career it has been.
There's something that becomes very deeply
engrained in you that,
that's how it should be.
They, they, those who are not like you
should be in charge.
And when it's people who are like you,
it's other women or
ideally, women of color as well and you're
coming up behind them.
You're going, of course I can do that.
Because I'm, I'm like them.
So it's really a different feeling when
you're in the back country,
it's all women, you're making your own
decisions,
you're dealing with the situations that
will inevitably arise.
And you go, yeah, of course we can do
this.
Maybe we're even better?
>> [CROSSTALK]
So, did you consider yourself a leader
before you started doing this?
>> No, not at all.
No I, I even have a talk I give I call the
leadership bone about how I
didn't have a leadership bone in my body
or so, so I believed.
I was super shy when I was growing up,
completely terrified of authority and
all I knew how to do was put my head down
and study and get good grades.
it, climbing really was what changed me
the most.
So, being out there and making decisions
and slowly, and
carefully, not biting off to much at
first.
Not going on a double black diamond run on
your first time skiing out, you know.
I realized, like, wow I actually have a
capacity for making good decisions and
people are resonating with me, and they're
listening, and in fact they may
even be inspired by me, because I've
worked hard to prepare, and I'm small.
And I don't have the build that one would
expect a climber would have.
And they go, wow, you know, maybe, maybe
she really knows what she's talking about.
It's, there's something different about if
it's a 6 foot 5 guy, who's really big, and
he's like, you can do it, and
you're like I don't, I'm still not really
sure if I can do it.
But when I say it, they seem to believe
it.
And it took a while to get comfortable
with that aspect of thinking about
oneself with leadership capacity.
And I also think that's something women
may struggle with more than men.
But eventually, the ability to impact
others outweighed any
doubt that I had in myself as a leader.
>> Mm.
So what kind of training did you go
through to get to that point,
to be able to lead your own trips.
>> Oh, experience.
Just lots of experience.
I've led a lot of trips,
I led a lot of different group sizes,
things where I've done it before and
I was just going back and leading,
something I was comfortable with.
I've led a number of trips where I've
never been before, so
I'm figuring it out on the fly, while
giving other people confidence.
And my ability to make sure things don't
go wrong.
But yeah, it's really just getting out
there and doing it.
I mean yeah, there's leadership courses,
and I read outdoor leadership,
by I forgot his name, Graham something
it's a [INAUDIBLE] book, and
there's sierra club leadership, and I did
the wilderness first responder.
That's a ten hour, ten day course that
really prepares you for
medical scenarios in the back country, and
all of that helps.
But I think it's like just getting out and
doing it, and being even open.
I always solicit feedback on how I can be
a better leader.
>> Mm-hm.
>> People will say like,
you need to step it up and be a little
more autocratic.
Or on this one, we all kind of know what
we're doing.
Consensus would be a little bit more
appropriate.
So I'm super open for that kind of
feedback.
Because I want people to feel comfortable.
I want our objectives to be met, and
I want it to be done in a way that's safe
and enjoyable.
>> And have you had your moments,
I'm sure, where you've been there
thinking, wow.
Am I really the right person for this?
Are you, you doubting your judgement on a
certain situation?
>> Honestly, not really.
>> [LAUGH] Good for you.
>> I think it's also because I'm so
deliberate about what I step up for.
And I try not to go beyond my limits when
I'm in a leadership capacity.
I'm usually really trying to lead things
that are below my limits.
When I go and do thing personally, I'm
pushing the limits and
then sometimes I'm like, thank goodness
I'm not in charge of anybody else
here because I can barely take care of
myself.
But that may be part of why I haven't put
myself in a leadership situation where I
really thought I couldn't handle it.
>> So speaking of those situations where
you're pushing your own limits.
>> Mm, yes.
>> So what, first of all,
what's the, the accomplishments you're
most proud of?
In terms of climbing, or, being outside.
>> I would say, a lot of stories revolve
around my experience of MaKalu,
which is one of the 8,000 meter peaks.
There's 14 8,000 meter peaks in the world,
that's around 25-26,000 feet.
And it's a really small group of people
that actually want to try and climb them.
Especially those that want to try and
climb the 8,000 meter peaks that aren't
Everest, because you get no glory for it.
They're mostly mu, much more difficult,
even if they're just a little bit lower.
So Makalu is the fifth highest mountain
the world, and I had kind
of a once in a lifetime opportunity to
jump on an expedition in between two jobs.
I had not trained at all.
And normally I will train like five or six
months like a maniac to
do something even like McKinley Denali,
which is 20,320 feet high.
But I basically went there with the goal
of learning as much as I could and
not getting myself killed.
And, I thought if I can summit it'll be a
huge coup.
And just going there with such a small
team, there were four of us total.
Everyone else had climbed at least one
other 8,000 meter peak, if not, more.
So I was kind of the, the newbie along for
the ride and very conscious of my position
there, trying not to be a burden or
ask too many questions and also be a
contributor to the team,
which was challenging in such an extreme
environment.
But, I ended up making it up to Camp Two.
And even slept at Camp Two, which, you
know,
is a big difference between just tagging a
new altitude and sleeping there.
And did fantastically well with altitude.
Like, floored myself with it.
It still is, like the hardest thing I've
ever done.
And walking across maybe half football
field of,
of flat terrain to get to the camp, took
almost an hour.
And that's just, it's really hard to
describe how
hard [CROSSTALK]
>> That's amazing.
>> It is when you have to take a step and
like take a few breaths just to take
another flat step.
But no, no AMS and really felt like,
oh my god, I might actually be able to do
this thing.
And then, we got shut down by the weather
and
this is part of the 8,000 meter peak game,
there's a lot of waiting,
there's a lot of trying to find a weather
window that will work.
Sometimes it does, sometimes it doesn't.
And we then ended up leaving without
launching another summit, so it was kind
of a bummer but it's, it is the experience
of climbing a mountain like that.
>> So you say you do pretty well at
altitude, right?
So you had no AMS, how did you accomplish
that?
Did you have a very slow ascent?
>> Well, I think there's a few aspects
about dealing with altitude.
Or, I like to say there are four things
that determine how you're going to
do at altitude.
One is your genetics, so I clearly have
pretty good genetics.
One's your own personal fitness.
So the more fit I am, the better I do, the
less I'll struggle.
And I wasn't super fit, but I was, you
know, pretty decent.
Another is your personal care, how much
you're paying attention to your pace,
you're hydrating, you're eating, you're
not ascending too quickly,
these things that are in your control.
And then the fourth is randomness.
So there are the most experienced climbers
in the world that
will come down with pulmonary edema like
after 17 years of guiding on Denali.
So you just never know and
you have to be aware that that can happen
and to listen to yourself.
So, I think, in this case it really was
just the acclimatization program works.
You climb high, you sleep low, you rest
for three or four days, you wait for
another window, you go up, you tag that
previous camp and you sleep high again and
you come all the way back down and you
recover yet again.
And as you get higher and higher you can
start to feel how it really is
impacting your body, and I'm just lucky
that I don't suffer,
that I don't get nausea, I don't throw up,
I don't get splitting headaches.
But I do get super exerted, so I,
everything just feels really hard.
And like that, you know, taking an hour to
go half a football field.
My, my partner was already at the tent,
and like basically watching me.
The struggle across.
But then he's got, you know, nausea and
a terrible headache so then I, you know,
basically end up taking care of
a lot of the people around me even though
I'm much slower than they are.
So I think there may also be something to
the fact that I have to go slow.
And I'm, I, I worry more about the people
that are triathletes and
marathoners that come on my trips because
they don't respect altitude and
they only have this one gear that's
pushing really hard.
And if you push really hard, you have to
recover.
And at altitude, your recovery is severely
compromised and
the next day, you have to get up and do
the same thing and maybe go even higher.
And I just seemed like I can only operate
in this one gear, and
it's a pretty slow gear.
And I can suck it up and get it done.
And, I just don't feel bad when I do it
that way.
>> Yeah, and in fact you brought a little
device in here.
>> Yes.
>> Oxygen stat meter which you use
regularly.
And so, probably if you were to measure
yourself,
when you were walking very slowly across
that football field.
You might have had higher satch than your
partner who just scurried across and
dropped it down, and that may have given
him the headache,
because his satch might have been lower at
that point.
So that, slowing down, is actually a good
strategy I think.
>> Yeah, and interestingly, I'm like one
of the only people who carries this
around, but I really want to know.
It's a data point, I don't rely completely
on it, but
in the context of where we are, what the
ascent profile has been, how I feel.
If I experienced oxygen saturation of 69%,
I felt really bad.
And just seeing that number knowing that I
wasn't like, 83 and
I feel really bad, but at 69 like, I knew
okay, I have to take this seriously.
I'm in trouble.
Although, I had to direct my own care,
which is also kind of scary because
you can go down pretty quickly when you're
that low.
So, yeah I, I feel like it's just such a
lightweight, it's only, they're only like
30 or 40 bucks, like a great tool to have
if you are in the altitu, altitude arena.
Yeah.
>> And do you like being alone in the
mountains or
do you prefer to always have other people
around?
I've talked to other women in particular
that seem to like that sort of isolation,
and that solitude.
>> It depends.
It sort of feels like, like graduating to
be able to be comfortable,
or have the confidence that you can do it
alone.
So, in the beginning, and
this is part of why a lot of people, a lot
of women come on my trips.
They don't want to be alone, they're not
sure,
they want somebody else to help, hold
their hand, ask, answer their questions.
And you graduate to where, okay, you're
leading other people.
But you still have that camaraderie, and
I even tell people like my, you know, my
issue is, I'm a little hypoglycemic.
If I ever start getting really cranky, or
I bonk, like this is how you need to help
me your guide.
And that's pretty much the only thing that
will come up.
Give me some food and I'll be, get a lot
nicer.
[LAUGH]
but going solo just takes it
to a whole another level, where you're
like, I feel like I can do this.
It's still going to be scary.
The hardest part's being alone with your
own self talk.
And not having anyone else to say, I'm
worried about this.
And I say oh, don't worry, it'll be fine,
we'll get there in time.
No, you're just worried about it.
And there's no way to resolve that on your
own.
The other thing that's
really, fulfilling about doing it alone is
challenging people's perceptions.
So, when I've climbed Shasta alone, or
when I did Mount Whitney,
backpacked around the backside alone, the
shock, the absolute shock and
horror that a woman was traveling in the
back country alone.
And the guys traveling alone, they don't
get that at all.
So there's this interesting like constant
reinforcement that you're not supposed to
be doing this.
Or you should be scared by doing this.
And it feels very empowering to directly
challenge that societal norm,
that women would not be out alone doing
things that are kind of scary.
>> Hm.
So what advice would you give people,
women in particular, who are considering
doing something like this for
the first time?
>> I'd say just go for it.
We hold ourselves back a lot out of fear,
and think we can't do things,
and are afraid of even the potential of a
little bit of suffering like feeling out
of breath, the uncomfortable situation of
being the last one in the group,
like we go, I'm not even going to try.
And, there's the corollary of like, bite
off what you can chew.
If you've never been hiking before, go do
some easy day hikes, don't go to Makalu.
But, I'd say, just, just try it.
You know, sign up for a trip, call
somebody and say this is what I can do,
is this appropriate for me, and if they
think so, don't hold yourself back.
Just go for it.
I mean, I like to tell people that, I tell
my
story about these crazy experiences in the
mountains so they can learn from it,
and they don't have to go as far as I did
to get it through my own thick skull.
But, when I come back from these trips.
My perspective is completely shifted,
where I'm not longer afraid of
managing $7 billion, which is a pretty
intimidating thing to do.
Some people are scared to death of doing
presentations, and
what's the worst thing that happens?
You don't do so well, nobody remembers it
in a year.
So in my, my thinking has really shifted
about.
If I take this risk in the mountains,
there could be loss of life or injury.
And then I come back and I go, if I take
this risk in this safe,
civilized world that we have, maybe I can
get that job.
Maybe I can get that date like what,
whatever it is.
Like, there's really only upside, so
that's what I think.
Just.
You know, be smart about it, but go for
it.
>> That's great advice.
And any last words of wisdom on any topic
that you'd like to
share with our viewing audience?
>> I'd say, just don't hold yourself back.
I mean, you can't see how small I am, but
I'm 5 foot 1, and
when you see me with these other people
that are climbing, they just.
They can't believe I can do what I do, and
I'm really not that fit.
I work really hard, I try to be smarter, I
have to make up for
the fact that I don't have a lot of, just,
natural athletic gifts.
But I don't hold myself back, I still say
this is what I want, and
I'm going to do it to the best of my
ability.
So that's, that's one other of my things,
like, take the risk,
be smart about it but, take the risk and
then just don't hold yourself back.
>> That's a great place to end.
Thank you so much for your time Emilie
it's great talking with you.
>> Thank you.
Thanks for having me.
[BLANK_AUDIO]