Finally ready to start.
Woo hoo!
This class is a culmination of many
factors in my history such as
storytelling and science, teaching,
research, and even cocktail party chat.
And of course, the fates were kind when
they put Corey in
my Stamford class at this critical
juncture.
This online course would definitely not
look as it does today without him,
both for reasons on camera and behind the
scenes.
There are a lot of other people that made
this class possible,
including our producers, Carlos Saligo and
Wes Choi, our intern, Lexi Ross, and our
scientific advisory committee.
I want to thank the Program in Human
Biology, the Office of
the Vice Provost for Online Learning and
the Dean's Office of Humanities and
Sciences for their financial support and
encouragement of our efforts.
And finally, I want to thank you for
being a part of this class, we wouldn't be
here without you.
We are so excited to start.
[LAUGH] We hope you are too.
Get online, learn, and then go outside and
use your newfound knowledge.
Have fun.