Our environmental physiology class is
about how your body response and
adapts to the world around you.
[SOUND] In the class, you will follow the
experiences of
your TA who will be placed in extreme
environments we will be discussing.
[SOUND] You'll be traveling to these
environments, observing his responses, and
listening to discussions by top scientists
in the field.
Through this process, you'll be engaged in
a journey of discovery about your body.
You will see how the body adapts to
survive in environments that are so
hot, you can fry an egg on the pavement.
So cold, your spit freezes before it hits
the ground.
And so high, most people would die without
supplemental oxygen.
Our power of survival is awesome.
[SOUND]