Corey and Sanford, thank you so much for
agreeing to talk to me.
[SOUND] TAing the exercise physiology
class.
This year, in addition to the normal
duties associated with TAing,
I'm going to ask that you give your bodies
to science.
[SOUND] So, I've written up a couple
contracts here you can look through.
>> Where do I sign?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Alright.
Look, your RER values are at 0.74.
You really haven't eaten much today.
>> Yeah.
>> All right, ten seconds, so
we're going up, we hope.
[LAUGH] If that is working right.
>> Where are you at, Sanford?
>> I am [INAUDIBLE].
>> Okay, up we go.
Yes, up we go!
[LAUGH]
>> Ten seconds!
>> Come on!
>> Push it, [UNKNOWN]!
>> He got it!
Alright, alright, alright.
That it?
You done?
Good.
>> Yeah, now you're pumping that VO2 up.
>> Yup, there you go.
>> You're looking great,
you're looking great.
>> That a way Corey come on.
>> Come on.
>> You got this.
You got this.
>> Just 30 seconds.
>> Aah!
>> You got, it Corey.
>> Keep that speed up.
>> Fight hard.
Come on Corey.
>> [UNKNOWN]
>> Huh-uh.
>> Does it feel like it?
>> [UNKNOWN]
>> Come on.
Every rep, every rep.
Let's go.
Drop and drive.
Chest up, chest up, chest up.
>> Aah!
>> Keep pushing, alright.
I'm bringing the wattage down.
Keep those legs spinning a little bit.
You can take off the headgear whenever you
want.
>> Single it now, single it.
Gotta work hard here, we gotta work hard.
Come on.
Go hard.
Finish, finish, finish.
Way to finish it.
>> Way to go.
Keep pushing.
Alright.
Well you went a lot farther didn't you.
You went a whole stage farther.
>> I definitely feel stronger.
>> Good.
And you've been putting on weight, right?
>> Yeah.
So, I'm up about eight pounds right now.
So hopefully that's muscle.
[LAUGH]
>> Okay.
The TAs are back for their final testing
round.
Now they've traded places.
Sanford is getting his dexa scan done to
get his body composition and bone density.
Corey and Sanford look over their body
composition results.
>> This is, if he does this for reps, this
is probably about ten pounds heavier.
I'm sorry,
20 pounds heavier than what his estimated
one rep max was what three weeks?
Four weeks ago, when we did our midterm
testing with him.
>> Come on, baby.
What do you got left?
Squeeze it now.
>> Lets go Sanford.
>> Cmon baby, what do you got left?
Come on!
Chest up here we go.
Push!
Come on, baby, squeeze it!
[SOUND] His squat went up about 8%.
>> Is that a significant gain that you
see?
>> Absolutely.
>> If you actually pay attention to,
kind of like, the numbers and
the actual progress you're making,
it's a little, a little bit more inspiring
at the end when you know, you've improved.
>> And that's one of the great motivators
with physical activities.
>> Yeah.
>> When you start to track it and
see those changes that'll keep you coming
back for more.
>> And sometimes, you don't get the
results that you're looking for.
I mean, I was very disappointed.
Yesterday, I was very disappointed.
>> So do you think you're going to keep
cycling?
>> I think I will keep cycling, actually.
So the story is that two of my best
training partners are these
two 13-year-old female twins.
Beat these two little 13-year-old girls
up.
This is, like, literally the seventh time
we've gone up.
All bonded together.
So it's an important perspective.
To realize that being a 13-year-old is not
the end all, be all.
I made her cry.
And I feel more bad about making her cry.
[LAUGH] But I did good about getting
better.
So. [LAUGH] >> She's gotta learn, you
know?
>> [LAUGH] To meet with failure too.
>> Life lesson.
>> Yeah.
>> Life is about.
>> You can't always be on top.
>> Yeah.
[LAUGH]