[MUSIC]
>> So, Dr. McCraty, could you teach me one
of the techniques that you use?
>> Sure.
Let's also facilitate it with some
technology that measures your heart rate
ability or more specifically, the
coherence in your heart rhythm.
So, I have a iphone here, a little sensor
plugged in.
>> Okay.
>> These are pulse sensors, so I'd like
you to put that on your ear lobe.
Not here up top.
In the fleshy part, because we have to get
a pulse.
>> How's that look?
>> That looks like that should work.
So to start this particularly device,
you just tap on the screen and we'll
bypass that.
So now we're seeing your pulse here on the
screen.
And then that's going to quickly, we show
the pulse so
we can make sure you're getting a good
recording, you got a good hookup because
we're measuring the time between each
heartbeat and that's being plotted.
Now here's your heart rhythm or your heart
[UNKNOWN].
So in this screen, we have a mandala here
that is a breathing pacer, and
if you follow the breathing pacer, you
know, breathe with it,
that helps start the process of shifting
you into a coherent state.
It's, again it's that optimal state where
improved cognitive functioning as well as
sensory motor integration and so on.
And then it's giving you feedback here
whether you're in high,
low or being in coherence, whether low is
red, medium coherence is the blue dots,
and green is high coherence which you have
not hit yet.
So I'm going to shift to another slide,
another screen view here, so
we actually get to see your heart
variability.
The pattern of it.
And what we're looking for here is rather
than this kind of incoherent looking
pattern, this jagged looking pattern,
as you practice one of the techniques that
it becomes more sine wave like.
So, and here we have a breathing pacer as
well.
And this graph here is going to show us
how coherent you are over time.
See here now you're in red.
We haven't used the technique yet.
So, I'm going to walk you through a
technique called Freeze Frame, Cory.
>> Okay.
>> And this is really a technique that's
appropriate for, it's multipurpose, but
for especially if you have to make a
decision.
Or you don't quite know the answer or
you need some out of box solutions for
something.
Or you can also use it just to freeze the
frame.
Like if you're getting stressed, you know,
getting ready to get anxious or angry, or
before you take a test.
Something like that, for sure.
Anyway, the way you do the technique is
the first step we
call heart focus breathing.
So that's where you put your attention in
the center of your chest.
You pretend like you're breathing right
through the center of your chest.
Now I know that you're really breathing
through your nose and
mouth but you, but your attention here and
almost pretend like you
can feel the breath coming right in
through the center of the chest.
And breathe in about 5 seconds, 4-5
seconds.
It's not an overly deep or exaggerated
breath.
Breathe out, the same rhythm, 4 or 5
seconds.
Just, you know, do that.
And you, you don't have to have your eyes
closed.
You can, that's one of the beauties of
these techniques, you can do it
right while you're diving, or in a staff
meeting, or right in the moment.
So you can, if you need a breathing pacer,
you can use that.
Now what that's starting to do is that's
actually using the physiology to
help get the system more coherent from
what we're talking about earlier.
Now to really take you to the next level
of coherence and sustain that,
that requires, or it certainly helps if we
can add a positive feeling.
I don't mean, I'm not talking about
thinking something.
'Kay.
It's really feeling something.
When you're first learning this, how do
you activate a positive feeling?
Right?
Sometimes you might have to visualize,
you know a, what it feels like when you're
in a special place in nature or
that you really, that really evokes that
feeling.
Or it can be the feeling that you have
when your pet greets you at home.
Right, or if you're a teenager, it might
be the feeling you
have when you get a really good deal at
the mall, you know.
It doesn't matter.
It's that positive feeling.
So I don't know if you have something that
you can do to, or
it can be simply, god what a beautiful day
it is.
>> Mm.
>> I appreciate that.
You know, it's just kind of a nice day.
So while you're doing the breathing just
sort of pretend almost like you're
breathing the feeling.
[MUSIC]
Okay and what we see happening here is you
just went into
a much higher state of coherence.
Big shift.
See the pattern in the rhythm here.
You know, freeze frame, once, once you're
into that coherent state,
you've now facilitated a lot of your, your
mental and cognitive functions.
So then you can, can simply just ask
yourself, you know, what would be a better
choice in this situation, and you would
assume that this is, you're trying to make
a decision, or it's a social situation,
what would be a better response.
[MUSIC]
>> Then the next step is you kind of have
to be quiet inside and
listen for the answer.
Now these are abbreviated simple steps but
that is the simple essence of the
[INAUDIBLE] technique.
>> Excellent.
Well that was pretty amazing to watch.
>> Yeah, a huge shift there right, see.
Now when you see here, you've come back
down from a high coherence to
a medium coherence, as you're talking and
reengaging.
And with practice, what people learn, is
that when you first do it,
you kind of gotta be quiet and really try
and get into coherence.
But with a little practice,
you can actually maintain your coherence
while we're having a conversation.
That's a good way to challenge yourself.
Once it gets easy to be coherent.
The way I recommend you practice this, is
challenging yourself in a different way.
Just doing that, can I maintain that
coherence when I am having a conversation.
Or when I'm on the phone,
especially when I'm on the phone that
somebody that stresses me out.
>> Yeah.
>> Stresses you out.
>> Exactly.
Because that's really what this is about,
is being able to
take these techniques into the real world
in maintaining that composure and
that ability to stay cognitively
facilitated rather than inhibited, right?
>> Right.
>> So it's not about walkin' around with
this thing.
>> Mm-hm.
>> You know?
Am I coherent?
>> [LAUGH] But it'a a wonderful tool to,
when you use these techniques,
am I getting that physiological shift that
underlies those cognitive abilities.
And really my message is pretty simple
right.
You have all these centers in our nervous
system and
brain that underlie our cognitive skills.
If they're disordered, how can we expect
them to function properly or optimally?
So it's really about getting our self in
sync and
optimizing the very functions that we need
to utilize especially in today's world.
>> So have you found in your own personal
experience that
the more you've practiced these techniques
that you continue to get better at them?
>> Oh, absolutely.
In fact the real goal and in fact, we call
it creating a base line shift.
With enough practice, usually about 6
weeks if you're sincere about it,
from using the techniques and technology
to be coherent, you are retraining your
nervous system to where coherence becomes
the new familiar or the new normal.
So you'll be going into a coherent state
just sitting down without even
thinking to use a technique That'd be Dr.
Schumann in a, in a published study.
>> And, and you seem to have found that
the more you practice it,
the less you need these different
biofeedback tools.
You've sort of developed an understanding
of.
>> You develop what it feels like.
This is helping you know that I'm in that
state,
because it's really easy to fool ourselves
especially when you're first learning.
You feel all coherent and sync, and oh my
god, I'm totally not.
>> I'm in the red!
And I'm having a conversation.
>> So it's a skill, that we learn.
Once it's becomes more familiar,
it's much easier to shift into that state
[UNKNOWN] of life.
Or a stressor.
It's kind of naive to think that we're
going to learn a technique like this and
walk right up into the big stressors and
be able to make that shift.
I mean, it takes some practice.
You have to gain that inner familiarity
with it, a new base line.
>> Slowly developed over time.
>> Yeah.
And you can use it with stronger and
stronger stress instances.
>> Exactly.
>> Just sort of like lifting weights.
>> Well, exactly.
>> You can't just lift once and then go in
and squat 400 lbs.
>> Right, and that we, we talk a lot about
resilience in our work.
So that and we actually talk about
resilience in 4 different primary domains,
physical being one of 'em.
So, from the resilience perspective, that,
that would be reflected in your endurance
right?
Your strength, your physical flexibility.
Right?
And if you want to
increase your capacity in that domain, how
do you do it?
>> You train.
>> Well, you train, right?
You stretch past your norm a little bit,
and put out that extra energy.
After a few sessions of doing it
hopefully,
you get some recovery in between, right?
Then that's your new norm, that's your new
baseline.
>> And.
>> It works the same way in terms of our
emotional resilience.
So for a lot of people, kind of a really
common one is traffic just drives 'em
crazy, stresses them out and getting all
frustrated and impatient, right?
So you take on that.
Say, wait a minute.
Getting all irritated and impatient's not
going to make the traffic move any faster.
I'm going to do something different, this
time.
And you take that one on, and bring that
one into management.
Right?
So you've increased your capacity there,
your self regulatory capacity.
Then you take on the next maybe bigger
thing in life.
And so on.
>> So I'm hearing a lot of the benefits of
learning how to better regulate ourselves
and perform more optimally in our daily
lives where,
what might be some of the costs of turning
a blind eye to your message and
continuing to, to live the same sort of
emotionally disregulated life.
>> Yeah, shorter life span.
Certainly not as happy, and [INAUDIBLE]
for
well being, I think damage relationships.
And, I mean, the list goes on and on.
And if we really are, you know, honest
with ourselves, and
take most of the, the major issues in our
society today,
it almost always traces back to a failure
of self regulation.
[MUSIC]