>> We need oxygen.
The oxygen levels achieved are in the
range of
20 to 30% of what they would be at sea
level.
And are way below that which would ever be
tolerated by any doc
in any emergency room, sitting and seeing
those numbers.
They're truly frightening.
>> Dr. Stephen Ruoss is the Clinical Chief
of Pulmonary and
Critical Care Medicine Division and the
Medical Director of
the Transfer Center and Respiratory Care
Services at Stanford Medical Center.
His research primarily focuses on the
optimal diagnosis and
treatment of lung-related infections.
However impressive his achievements are as
a physician, Dr. Rouss' expertise and
experience isn't limited to just the
hospital.
Dr. Rouss is an avid and accomplished
mountaineer with
a climbing career that has included
multiple expeditions to the Himalaya's.
Among the Halee-,
Himalayan climbing experiences was an
expedition to Mount Everest in 1988.
Which included as another member of the
team the first American woman to
summit on Everest.
His medical expertise and mountain
adventures have brought him in direct
contact with some of the most severe
environmental stressors in the world.
For those reasons and many others it's a
great pleasure to now turn to our
experiential interviewee in altitude
physiology, Doctor Stephen Ruoss.
Thank you for agreeing to talk with us.
>> And thanks Ann, it's good to be here.
>> So, how did you first get involved in
mountaineering and
did you always have Everest as a goal in
sight?
>> The Everest thing was only a much later
evolved aspect, but
as a kid growing up outside of Seattle the
mountains were close and
my family was very outdoor oriented.
And although my mother cringed about it
later, part of the original exposure was,
and this would not be an invite invitation
for parents to do it now.
But they would, my parents, would take my
two younger brothers and
I out into the Cascades and drop us off on
a Friday afternoon or
evening and come get us on a Sunday
afternoon.
And I was probably 13 at the time and they
were a year and
a half and three years younger.
So we were, sort of, thrown into the
wilds, not quite like wolves.
But it was, hiking became, oh, I want to
be up there,
became a growing interest in climbing and
I collected myself,
friends who are climbers and off went my
climbing experience.
So I've been doing it for a while.
>> That's amazing.
Did you look forward to those experiences
where you're just left in the woods, or
was it something you kind of dreaded and
had to look out for your younger brothers?
>> Oh, no, no, no, it was, it was the, the
sort of
wonderful thing of the wide-eyed kid
getting to know the mountains and
getting to know being out in the
wilderness, which is really one of
those sort of enduring great qualities
about doing this stuff even now.
It's just fun to be out there.
And it wasn't anything that was
uncomfortable or threatening about it,
which was a great initial introduction to
being in the mountains.
I had more na-, na-, enough opportunity to
get scared later.
But for initial exposure, it was
wonderful.
It's fine.
>> So, in 1988 you were on expedition that
had Stacey Allison on it,
who was the first American women to summit
Everest.
How did you get involved in that
expedition?
>> That was also a little bit of
serendipity much like growing up in
Seattle was serendipity.
I had been on a number of climbing trips
in a variety of places and happened to be
on a separate climbing expedition in Nepal
and ran into some Seattle
climbing buddies on a trail up in the
Khumbu region which neighbors Everest.
They on a different expedition and I and
another climbing buddy were on a small
expedition to do first ascent on a peak.
And we ended up in a tea house chatting
about climbing projects.
And, they thought that it'd be fun to have
me along and
invited me and, there it, evolved.
And it was, then a collection of people,
largely from Seattle.
But, a group of friends, and it assembled
itself really as a nice group effort.
And it was in contrast to what oftentimes
happens on Everest now.
A very grass roots sort of thing.
There was no commercial enterprise to it
at all.
And it was, it turns out, not only fun,
but relatively inexpensive.
Certainly by today's comparisons with
these commercial trips,
those are big tens of thousands of
dollars.
And I think I was out of it, maybe $2,500
out of pocket.
>> So, it's obviously the highest mountain
around.
So you were going to be higher than you'd
ever been before.
So how did you prepare for this particular
trip?
And, being a physician and
a pulmonologist, did that impact how you
prepared for that trip?
>> It did, but it's probably worth, as I
did,
reflecting on my track record which had
been a climber growing up and
doing progressive climbing activities and
including at higher elevation.
And only later became a physician, so
the fact that I was a doc was sort of an
incidental feature.
I was asked to come along as a climber.
And just happened to be a physician at the
time and a pulmonary physician at that.
So my perspective was, knowing a lot about
all those funny things that
happen to you when you're on big
mountains.
And now sort of introduced to the, the
physiology and the revelations about
what's truly going on as these intricate
and quite remarkable adaptation responses.
And it helped, I think, for perspective of
knowing what was going on,
but it was still, as it had been before,
an incredible experience to,
to be in a situation where it's so
marginal as a physiologic exposure.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I don't think there's,
I mean, knowing a lot about the medicine,
I don't think would really prepare me
any better than simply trooping up a bunch
of mountains to get that exposure, but.
>> Yeah, except maybe on the treatment
side.
So knowing what medications could
[CROSSTALK].
>> Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
>> Yeah.
>> Treating problems when they arose?
>> Yeah, it was.
>> Definitely.
>> It was much nicer to be a doc.
>> [LAUGH] And have, have instant
familiarity with a lot of those concepts.
>> Yeah.
>> When people got sick, and indeed they
did knowing how to,
how to manage those sorts of things and
how to anticipate what might happen and
keep it all sorted out.
Yeah, it was, it was very handy and I'm
sure, sorry,
I know our expedition benefited from
having a doc along and
multiple other expeditions who were on
Everest at the time definitely did.
>> Sure.
So, let's talk a little bit about the
process once you get to Nepal and
you're preparing to go up the mountain and
you are acclimatizing your body as
you move up the mountain up to that fourth
camp.
What do you do and how do you go through
that process?
>> It's, it's a lot of what, what ends up
being some degree of drudgery.
And those who aren't climbers oftentimes
find
themselves saying to people who are
climbers, how can you do that?
That is such a slog.
Why do you put yourself through all of
that?
Because the all of that,
is really progressive, sometimes
sequentially up and down.
But progressive exposure to and slow
adaptation to that greater
elevation and lower barometric pressure
and lower net oxygen level.
And the time span for
that exposure, and adaptation, is days
becoming a couple of weeks.
To do it faster invites all sorts of messy
circumstances and bad physiology.
>> Mm-hm.
So, it's a long period of time,
were you you ready to get off the mountain
by the time you actually get to the fourth
camp, or you just so excited to be up that
high?
>> It, it's always fun.
It's just even the, even the hauling loads
and setting up camps and
getting back down and hauling some more
gear up.
It's an amazing place to be.
And whether it's Everest or
somewhere else, the, the, the tasks are
actually part of the entertainment.
So, humping a big load up a hill is, it
always seems like a task and
indeed it is, but sometimes they're
exquisitely pretty hills and
the view off of those hills is amazing.
So, it's, it's never,
it's never quite like emptying your
garage, I'd have to say.
>> [LAUGH] It's not that kind of task.
So, in your case, in your expedition, when
you got up to that fourth camp, and
you were preparing to ascend to the
summit,
your team had to make some very difficult
decisions.
Can you talk a little bit about that?
>> Yeah, the, a little bit of back drop
which is that the,
in the usual organization and logistics of
climbing Everest.
That fourth and last camp is that, is that
a pass between,
let's say the neighboring and also quite
high peak and Everest and
that passage is about 26,000 feet.
So, we hauled loads to that pass without
using supplementary oxygen.
And then used supplementary oxygen above
that 20,000, 26,000 foot pass.
It's not always done, Everest has of
course,
been climbed without supplementary oxygen.
A lot of people still use supplementary
oxygen.
So, some of it was simply to get to that
point and get sufficient material,
tents and logistical support to then,
climb up higher.
And by that point we sorted ourselves out
into groups of people who were climbing
together and in rotation.
And it then turned out that I and
two other American climbers, including
Stacey Allison and
the climbing leader Jim Frush, were then
in position to climb up to the summit.
Which indeed we tried to do, and got high
on
the mountain to around 27,000, just short
of 28,000 feet.
And Sherpa's who were with us, who we'd
split up the loads with and who
had some spare oxygen bottles, they became
concerned, never having been up there.
And fearful of the environment and the
unknown, and with their uncertainty,
they without discussion with us, up and
bolted, they were well below us.
And what they didn't do was,
explain that they wanted to go down, they
just turned and left.
The other thing they didn't do was drop
their load, which included oxygen bottles.
They took it all with them and went down.
So then there were, we three U.S. climbers
and one other Sherpa who had been with us.
And we had a single other spare oxygen
bottle,
and we had to then determine who would get
that oxygen bottle.
And we held a lottery and I've never been
particularly good at winning lotteries and
Stacey won the the short straw, as it
were.
And continued on to the summit with the
Sherpa and
that single spare oxygen bottle.
To that point it had been a bit of a slog
working at that, at that elevation.
And then there was a period where we were
working through probably 45 degree
slope climbing up and it was knee to thigh
deep unconsolidated snow.
And it's, it's an amazing experience to
have to go as slowly as we were.
Knowing that we're going to be short on
oxygen, I was just turning off my
oxygen supply for a while, and climbing
without oxygen, and breaking trail for
stretches and it was an amazing taxing
experience.
I mean, it's many, many breaths, 10 or 12
breaths, take a step,
another 10 or 12 breaths, take a step and
try to count down and
do enough breaths and steps and then say,
okay I'll give myself a break.
Well, you could argue that you're taking a
break all the time, but it just was a,
an immense slog to be able to keep moving.
And without supplementary oxygen it was
just made that much worse.
>> And, let's go along those lines a
little bit.
So what else are you feeling?
Are you in pain?
Or is your mind clear or is your mind
muddled because of the hypoxia?
What else are you feeling at that
elevation, 27,000 feet?
Which is incredible.
>> It's a good question and
it's I, I'd call it a contextually
deprived circumstance.
So, all you have is a mountain.
>> [LAUGH]
>> The mountains going to be
there whether I'm there or not.
And then, if you want to cross check with
another individual,
they're going to be as hypoxic and maybe
brain damaged as you are.
And short of them being less responsive or
unconscious or not able to move, there's
not much of a great comparator.
Everything seemed to be okay.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And, you know, there was color vision
and I could look and
think, including that my feet were both
numb from the cold.
And that I did not want to, and I've been
doing a bunch of climbing before.
I had no interest in freezing my toes or
feet off and
climbing without the supplementary oxygen,
I was clearly getting my feet cold.
So, I could keep up with the other people
using oxygen, but I had cold feet.
And thought for a while, well, I can look
over on the summit ridge and
it's not that far to the summit.
I ought to be able to this, but I did not
want to freeze my feet.
And, made the decision, quite it seemed,
conscious and appropriate, to not
run the risk of freezing my feet and turn
back rather than continue to the summit.
An amazing experience which I had not
anticipated but did a number of times was,
climbing with the oxygen off and then
turning the oxygen supply on.
And it was to two liters per minute flow
rate, which is very modest.
I mean, it's a low, a low oxygen
supplementation flow rate.
The only way to describe it was, this is
like, the sensation which I'd never
imagined I'd be able to have, which is of,
the, the sensation of aerobic metabolism.
The equivalent would be as if somebody
took a perfect,
like 100 degree bucket of water and poured
it in into one's belly.
This sensation of warmth emanating from my
core when
I would turn the oxygen back on, it was
very interesting.
Which of course made me, the physician,
shut it off.
>> [LAUGH].
>> And then turn it back on [CROSSTALK] to
get that cool sensation and
I mentioned it to co-climbers of, how
amazing it was that you can actually feel
the improvement of aerobic metabolism and
generation of body heat.
Which I'd never thought and I've
subsequently learned, yeah of course,
people have noticed this before doing
exactly that at extremes of altitude.
But it's an amazing sensation which it'd
be really hard to duplicate down
here except in like the Army labs
environment, where the Operation Everest.
I don't know whether they tried it,
but I suspect if they had, they probably
had the same experience.
>> Mm-hm.
Yeah, and also knowing it and experiencing
it are two different things.
So, intellectually you could know that's
going to happen, but
to feel that flush, that must be amazing.
>> Yeah the, you know, when you're hand-,
you're out, you know,
throwing snowballs as a kid, and you go
back in, and your hands warm up,
and they tingle, and then they feel so
nice and glowing warm, kind of like that.
But it was in your core.
I mean, it's an amazing experience.
>> So, can you share what some of those
catastrophic things were
that prevented you from getting a second
shot at the summit?
>> There were, yeah, some of, it kind of
fell into three categories.
There were some storms that brewed up
where it's blowing like crazy and
we retreated down.
There was a period of about 10 days, where
I spent as the only person up at a camp
at the base of the Lhotse face, which is,
it's a little short of 21,000 feet.
And we had a bunch of tents there and
gear.
And there were multiple expeditions,
including some New Zealanders who
subsequently didn't fare well.
Rob Hall among them.
And, so I spent a little while in storms
hanging out with the Kiwis,
eating some nice tasty treats and holding
the tents down.
And that, that blew through and
we then were back in a bit, a bit of a
better weather window.
And then had a problem where a member of a
Spanish expedition got sick, again,
well above the south call, in the range of
20, probably 27 to 28,000 feet.
He became sick with some dehydration,
and probably evolution of high altitude
cerebral edema.
Like a, a brain related hypoxic injury
circumstance can be devastating and
fatal, including in a fairly short period
of time.
Which actually was what killed Rob Hall's
climbing partner and ultimately guiding
partner, a guy named Gary Ball,
who died on Gashiram Four, in Pakistan of
acute cerebral edema.
He was sick, didn't feel so good.
And when the sun went down, and he was
dead by the time the sun came up.
So the Spanish climber got sick, was
stumbling, and had cerebral edema, and
I had to spend a lot of time helping him
get down and ultimately off the mountain.
So that chewed up a, a fair bit of time.
And then the other full-sail absolute
disaster was a Slovak
climbing team came up and set off to do a
fast alpine, oxygen free
ascent of the southwest face of Everest,
which takes off right above this camp.
And we loaned them a radio so
that they could be in contact with people
including base camp.
And, unfortunately what we were able then
to witness was the slow disintegration and
ultimately death of all four of them.
Initially getting sick on the very upper
edges of the southwest face.
One, then two behind, one finally went to
the summit.
And they all four then were going to try
to descend and they were asking for
us to help to find them because they were
going to be coming down the route
that we would try to ascend that night.
And bad storms and they were, you know,
making radio
calls to try to get us to help them saying
they'll leave their head lamps on.
And they probably got blown off the ridge
later, but none of them were recovered.
>> It must be so
hard to listen to that from afar, and hear
everything going wrong and be so helpless.
>> And here the voice, and hear the voice
of a dying person.
>> Yeah.
>> They were,
they were definitely in dire straights.
It was, it was quite clear even before
they said they were in dire straights,
that they were in, in a deep bit of
disaster.
And that was, between them, they had over
20 ascents of
peaks of 8,000 meters and they were, they
were very experienced climbers.
And they were just in the wrong
circumstance, at the wrong time.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And the margins, again it's, it's a
very big peak.
It's not technically that tricky to climb,
particularly by those routes but it's,
it's very high and it's the hypoxia that,
that leaves really no margins.
>> So on Everest, were there people that
you encountered either in the camps or
in your own team, that you looked at and
talked with and
thought, ooh, you know, they, they're on
their way to being in trouble.
Either because of their problems with
cognitive function or symptoms and
you thought that they should, really
should be going down and
you, have you had to make a call for
anyone else like that?
>> No, with one exception.
So my time on Everest was before the era
of commercial expeditions to Everest.
As a doc, I don't think I'd want to find
myself remotely close to Everest Base Camp
now, because I might be frightened at the
broad range, much broader range of
experience, and climbing skill, and time
in the mountains.
And might be much more frightened by some
people who have relatively less experience
and are thus, maybe unwittingly, at the
mercy of the elements and
a guide much more than I would ever want
to find myself.
So I, it's nice to go to the mountains,
I would choose to go to anything except
Everest again.
>> No business being there at this point,
yeah.
>> Yeah.
We did have one, one interesting
experience, which is sort of a nice little
physiologic quirk.
Which is a, a really terrific ranked long
distance runner
accompanied our expedition because he
wanted to be there, not because he had
a lot of climbing experience, but wanted
to go to Everest Base Camp.
And along the, and he also happened to be
a doc and
along the way, in talking, I said, well,
this is really interesting.
because, you know, marathon runners have
fairly blunted ventilatory drives,
they tend in general not to breathe so
rapidly in response to hypercapnia,
CO2 going up, or hypoxia, O2 going down,
and you're one of those.
You're an elite athlete in a different
field and your breathing response
might well be the thing that wouldn't be
so good if you encounter extreme
sulp-hypoxia because what you really want
to do is breathe like crazy.
And he didn't really like the implication
that I might find that
he was going to not do well.
But in fact, at progressive elevation, he
just felt terrible.
Probably because in part,
not because he isn't a great athlete, but
because his ventilatory
response probably makes him much more
suitable to be a marathon runner.
Where we're clearly coming from different
flavors and, and
our physiologic backdrop context probably
does have bearing.
As I oftentimes say in these physiology
lectures, we are ourselves,
and we do well that which we do well.
>> [LAUGH]
>> You can't make me be a high speed,
100 meter runner because I am all about
slow twitch fibers.
And I do very well, because I pant like a
dog when I'm hypoxic.
And that's probably why I like going to
elevation.
because it works.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Whereas somebody who doesn't have that
very exquisite adaptive ventilatory
response doesn't tend to do so well.
>> It's fun to watch that physiology play
out in real life [LAUGH]
>> Yeah, yeah, but my other,
my other statement is choose your parents
wisely.
>> [LAUGH] Exactly.
And so what is it like when you come back
from being at altitude for
that long of a time?
Do you notice things in your daily
existence that's different,
in your physiology I should say?
>> Yeah, one of the things one notices is
people saying, my god you're a skeleton.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So I, I weigh probably 165 now.
I weighed probably 175 pounds going to
Everest.
And I lost 12 kilos of weight.
>> That's a lot of weight.
>> So I look like a stick figure coming
back.
the, the muscle, just fuel wasting.
You burn up lots and lots and lots of
calories, and it's just,
it's impressively difficult to eat that
much to keep the weight on.
One's appetite suffers greatly.
So the, the weight loss is, is an amazing
feature right up front, and
it makes you feel incredibly weak doing
that.
At lesser elevations, where you don't tend
to lose so much muscle mass.
One of the amazing features is how that
adaptation of
higher elevation exposure makes your body
run really well.
I mean, you get a, a beneficial adaptive
response,
which is why so many category one cyclists
now live in Boulder, Colorado.
Because they get to spend some time at, at
relatively modest elevations, but
they get that higher altitude modest
hypoxia adaptation response.
So there's some of that, and
I've certainly noticed on other trips
coming back feeling va-va-voom.
Being able to out-ride my cycling buddies
here by easy strides.
I mean, I can just run away from them.
From that adaptive response.
The other thing that, that I've noticed
which actually was fairly carefully cat-,
categorized on our Everest trip was, we
had some funding from NASA to,
to do some neurologic evaluation.
So this is learning and memory.
So psycho-motor evaluation.
And the interesting and frightening things
were that fine motor,
like finger, literally, simple little
finger tap tests suffers greatly.
You don't do it so well during and after
extreme hypoxia exposure.
>> How long after?
>> Mm.
Sometimes fairly scary amounts.
>> Like forever [LAUGH]?
>> The work studied, the sixth month
post exposure data are getting back to but
not fully back to the baseline state.
The other thing that flies apart is,
learning of new knowledge under profound
hypoxia is appalling.
I mean, you're back to, fairly rudimentary
skills.
When it, when it comes to just learning
new information.
And this is sort of rote recollection of
number sequence, word sequence, and
then to regurgitate it in a test
circumstance.
And the test circumstance happened to be,
you know,
like sitting in a tent at 24,000 feet
going through these damn NASA test reels.
But the ability to remember is, is really
impaired.
And I find my, found myself back as an
academic in the hallways of my parent
institution, seeing people and not quite
being able to pull out their names.
>> Uh-oh.
I do that anyway.
[LAUGH]
>> It was, it was profoundly, noticeably
worse.
On arrival back in Kathmandu, I wanted to
call my wife when we were back,
you know, around the telephone.
I wanted to call her and say hi, you know,
back to civilization, doing well.
I could not remember my own phone number,
but I could remember, sort of, deep back
cobwebs, my parent's phone number, which
had not changed for 25 years.
So I called them to find out what my own
phone number was so
I could call my wife and tell her.
>> Did that worry them [LAUGH] that you
couldn't remember your own phone number?
>> No, I found it a little disconcerting,
but they seemed to be okay with it.
>> Just a couple more questions.
So are there any life lessons that you
took away from the mountain that you've
brought back to either your work or your
personal life?
>> I think, yeah.
And the, the short answer is, yes.
I think the slightly longer answer is that
I think climbing,
however radically different from being a
doc,
including an intensive care medicine
doctor.
That the circumstances of climbing in the
mountain and
being responsible for lots of things.
And having, having to sort out problems
from
little to suddenly massively large
problems without the,
the immediate recourse to somebody that,
for somebody to come in and save the ship.
Makes, either calls from all of us in
humanity, a subset of people
who don't mind that stress circumstance
and can sort their way through it.
Or helps those of us who get in that
circumstance,
adapt our way into thinking more clearly
in problem solving sorts of ways.
So I think there's, there's a nice
bi-directional help of my medicine
exposure and my alpine climbing exposure
to, I think make each of them better.
>> Sort of self-sufficiency that comes
with that.
>> Yeah, and, and need to problem solve
and not lose grasp of the situation.
>> Good and what kind of advice would you
give to young students who may be
watching this or older students who may be
watching this,
who want to get into mountaineering and
climbing?
>> Get yourself out there and get exposed.
I, I think it's, if there's not a love for
being out there, then I think the rest
will just seem overly, drudgery.
but, but if you, if you like being out in
the mountains then,
then a lot of the rest of it really fills
in, in due course.
And spend time out, out in the sticks
alone and
get used to that sense of being out there
because it's incredibly beautiful and
it's fun to be out there and it's great to
not have people be around.
So long as that's comfortable and
if that's uncomfortable, then you're
probably in the wrong place.
But I think as you develop increasing
comfort simply being in, in a solitary
circumstance, then the details of climbing
skills and exposure and
technique and experience, I think will
fill themselves in quite handily.
>> Good.
>> Yeah.
>> And the last question.
Do you have some take home message from
your experience in the mountains or
climbing or life that you'd like to share
with our audience?
>> yeah, I guess, since we were talking
before we got online about a recent
accident of breaking my legs and getting
them patched back together climbing.
There are, there are risks, but I think
the rewards are so
vastly greater that it's, it's, in the
analysis, a great thing to do.
I, I, I love the exposure and I think
people ought to try to get more of that.
>> Alright.
We'll end it there.
Thank you so much.
>> You're welcome.
>> Great talking with you.
>> Happy to be here.
>> Good, thank you.