The way I recommend that you practice
this,
is challenging yourself in a different
way.
>> Can I maintain that coherence with
somebody that.
>> Stresses me out.
>> Stresses you out, exactly.
Because that's really what this is about,
is being able to take these techniques
into the real world.
>> Dr. Rollin McCraty is director of
research of
the heart math research center at The
Institute of Hearth Math.
A non profit research and
educational organization located in
Boulder Creek, California.
Heart Math is at the cutting edge of
creating positive emotion focus,
intervention tools, and technologies which
have been demonstrated to reduce stress,
enhance health and performance, and
improve quality of life.
Dr. McCraty has an extensive professional
background in research and
development, systems engineering, and
instrumentation design.
He received his Masters in radiational
physics, and his PhD in health sciences.
After a successful engineering career, Dr.
McCraty's research interests lead him to
establish the Heart Math Research Center.
Where he applied his background in
engineering to the study of
emotion physiology, and the development of
cutting edge interventions for
stress reduction and optimal performance.
As a result of Dr. McCraty's and Heart
Math's life, millions of people have been
positively impacted by their technologies,
and their educational programs.
So for those reasons and many others it's
a great honor to now turn to
our experiential interview and stress
physiology with Dr. Rolland McCraty.
Dr. McCraty thank you so much for being
with us today.
>> Oh.
>> It's a real honor.
>> My pleasure Cory.
It's it's great being here.
>> Yeah it's great to have you.
So I thought a great place to start today
would be with your own personal story.
So what was it that got you interested in
stress, positive emotions and
ultimately developing these stress
intervention tools?
>> Wow, well the, the honest answer to
that is at the,
the time I really got interested in this
type of things was I owned
a A company I had founded, and a few years
into it it was successful, and we were
doing very large scale installations in
the field of electrostatics.
And, big manufacturing plants,
like Chrysler, Ford and head offices all
over the world.
And especially in,
in the US companies it amazed me that
these companies could stay in business.
To be honest the amount of dysfunction
that was going on between unions and
workers and management and, I mean,
I, because I had to inter- I had to deal
with all levels.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To get what we were trying to do in
these factories.
And it just struck me that something's
gotta change.
There's gotta be some better way for us to
get along with each other, and
cooperate, and collaborate, rather than
the constant fighting, and
looking out for self over everything else.
So that was one of the, the turning points
for me.
And I think, probably honestly speaking,
around that same time period,
I kind of been in to the humanities
earlier and kind of got fed up with that,
and so I'll go make money again, and
started that company.
But I was also realizing that same time
period,
that another sports car in the driveway
wasn't going to really do it for me.
So I really wanted to do something more to
help people and you know,
a lot of people will say that but it was a
true kind of heart felt feeling for me.
>> That's incredible so then that brought
you to Heart Math.
>> You know that was I wont say accidental
but
I, Heart Math didn't exist at that time
but I met the founder of Heart Math.
Through some mutual friends, And Doc, a
guy named Doc Childry, and with actually
on business on the east coast where he was
at that time in North Carolina.
So I thought I'd go meet him,
spend an hour meet this guy that friends
had told me about.
Ended up spending three days with him,
we in his some people in his group, around
him.
Just hit it off, just became good friends,
and, and
he told me that his vision, and resonated
with me, so.
>> And the rest is history.
>> So, that's a nice segue into talking a
little bit about heart math, and
the Institute of Heart Math.
So, what are they, and what are some of
the, the tools and
the educational programs you've developed?
>> Okay, well, the Institute of Heart Math
is a nonprofit research and
educational organization.
You know, we obviously do both fair amount
of energy into research.
And we're primarily a basic physiology
research facility.
Then we enjoy a lot of collaborative
relationships with research centers and
universities, really around the world.
Especially when it comes to the applied
science side.
You know so if we're working with the
clinical population, or
an organizational population, that's
always in partnership with someone else.
But Heart Math is, probably the simplest
way I can say it, it's a set of tools,
techniques, and technologies that help
people learn how to better self regulate.
But to do that from a more intelligent
inner reference point,
is as if you can tell people you should do
this, you should eat this way,
don't smoke, do this do that, but that
doesn't really do much, unless it
comes from your own inner, inner guidance
if you will, or locust of control.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, the tools and techniques, as we
like to say, in,
in fact, in our mission statement is,
it's really helping people align with the
intelligence of their own heart.
And that helps unfold who they truly are.
So that's what, what they're about.
>> So that's what you do.
>> That's what I do.
>> And then that applied, the applied
science and
the technology is really what has
attracted us to you.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Find it really, really incredible and
fascinating work.
So before we move more towards talking
about the science.
One thing that I found really fascinating
about your own story is that
you have made pretty big career change.
And a successful background in
engineering, systems engineering and
instrumentation design and then, a switch
over to Heart Math.
And I was wondering if you could talk a
little bit about the journey from point
A to point B, and how you've been able to
leverage your knowledge of physics and
engineering into the work you currently
do?
>> Well, looking backwards it was a
perfect combination.
Of course, in the field of
psycho-physiology there's a lot of
equipment involved.
You've got to hook up electrodes up to
people, and do you know,
these measurements of having my electronic
training background made that
a lot easier and so the psycho-physiology
was really my second career.
And really honest,
probably not having a formal academic
education in it was really beneficial.
Because we didn't know what wouldn't work
So we tried things that most would say,
no that won't work don't try that.
>> So you'd say you, you weren't limited
by the, the standard academic approach?
>> To be true, to be honest, really
honest.
So, I got into this, before I got any
formal education in psycho-physiology,
I later on went and got a PhD in it.
But in the beginning, in fact I remember
many, many years ago,
probably close to 30 years ago.
Driving over here to Stanford actually,
from where I live, Boulder Creek,
to the book store and trying to find a
book on electoral cardiograms.
I got a, what is this stuff?
Figure out how to read it,
and so we spent a few months just reading
and understanding it, and
wiring people up and we got onto some
things in our early years.
One of the maybe help answer that
question.
We had already sort of an, call it an
intuitive knowledge and
understanding that it just made sense that
if we're feeling better.
You know, like appreciating, or caring, or
being compassionate, that ought to
have a physiological correlate with it you
know, that's hopefully beneficial.
And so we we're that time,
well this is 1991, somewhere in there,
that all the library searches and
all that, before we had all the
online/Medline searches, by the way.
You actually had to go to libraries and
look up references and
go find things back then.
>> It's a different world.
>> It's a different world, but at that
time there were three,
maybe four publications that I could find
that were looking at the effect, or
the physiological correlates of positive
emotions in the scientific literature.
It's hardly anything.
Now of course there are, you know, it's
quite different.
We even have a whole field called positive
psychology now.
But anyway we, we got onto well let's look
at positive states.
From a physiological perspective.
Not just stress and negative ones.
And that was, turned out to have been the
right approach.
And so we were doing all these little
three letter acronyms,
you know EEGs and GSRs and ECGs and all of
that stuff at that time.
And what we found, we were taking a little
bit deeper look at the heart.
You know with the forced ECGs, what kept
happening was, it was a change in
the heart rhythm pattern, which is now
called heart variability.
We were sort of doing this even before
that term was coined.
That was the most reflective emotional
state, and
this time, nobody even thought of looking
that I don't think.
That actually drew the attention of what
ended up being some some mentors that I
really appreciate, one of them being Carl
Preben.
A name you might know cause he was the
director of here at Stanford of
brain research for, I think for 30 years,
very famous guy.
So he got interested in our stuff, I found
out later,
it was confirming one of his theories.
Didn't know that at the time, why he was
so interested.
But he ended up being a great champion.
Still is actually, Carl's 94 years old
now, and still teaching actually.
Now teaching at Georgetown a couple days a
week But then a few other mentors,
and that worked through to us.
I'm making a long story short here, but,
like Don Singer who's the man who's
credited with coining the term heart rate
variability.
He's on our advisory board and, has been
for over 20 years.
Anyway a whole string of people like that.
So my education was really through mentors
and
which is a really neat way to do it, by
the way.
>> Mm hmm.
>> And they fussed at me and said, Okay,
if you're going know all this publishing,
you gotta have a PhD, go get a PhD.
>> And.
>> And I did that later on.
>> And so you did it.
So, that's a, that's a nice transition
now,
talking about some of the work that you do
at the institute.
So, there seems to be some central themes
that can be drawn out of a lot of
the educational programs and the tools
that you've developed.
And it seems to me that one of them, is
this concept of physiology coherence.
So what is physiological coherence, and
how can, how can understanding it help me
and you make our lives better.
>> Sure I don't want to give too long of
an answer here, but that term, coherence,
my advisory board I was telling you about,
it took us two years to agree on a term.
A lot of consideration went into that But
basically,
what it's really a term that describes, to
say it really simply, inner harmony.
In other words, the activity in our
physiology is cooperating.
You have synchronization, if we're talking
technically with
synchronization with different rhythms and
signals.
And many years and many studies later now,
it's been kind of confirmed as the
baseline state for optimal functioning.
Especially cognitive functioning.
And we got on to it from what I was
talking about earlier by looking at
heart rate variability, the beat can be
changed in variability, but
not how much variability.
Which is what most people still look at,
but the pattern of it.
So what we've found was that you can think
of the heart,
this beat to beat variability, it's like
morse code.
The heart's beating out a message, and
that message has profound influences on
brain functions.
So, when we're feeling, when we would do
things back end,
whether it was showing them films or, self
induction techniques.
You know, or throwing firecrackers at them
which we
literally did in one of our studies.
>> [LAUGH]
>> We had a lot of fun in the lab.
>> I'd love to read that paper.
>> Yeah.
I don't think we ever published that, but.
>> [LAUGH]
>> You have to get creative on
how you induce emotions.
>> It's very tricky.
>> You really do because once you do it
once, they're on to you.
But, anyway, what consistently I'd
mentioned earlier was
this heart rhythm was what reflected
emotions.
But what was happening when people were,
however we got them there, really feeling
a genuine, positive emotion.
Compassion, kindness, care, appreciation,
any of these.
The heart rhythm became a very different
pattern.
And it's like a sign wave pattern in the
rhythm, about a 10 second cycle rhythm.
And that was occurring no matter how we
got them their independent of you know,
control breathing, any of that, in fact we
left that out of the equation back then,
by my purpose, on purpose.
And that's what we ended up calling
coherence.
Cause as we dug deeper into that,
following the data, right,
we realized that that state was reflecting
increased synchronized activity.
Literally between the heart and brain,
which we went on to develop ways to
measure, you know, degree of synchronized
activity, literally.
And the degree of synchronized activity
between sympathetic and
parasympathetic branches of the nervous
system, and so on.
And between our respiratory rhythms, and
heart rhythms, and blood pressure rhythms.
was, was basically an optimal state.
The heart's doing a lot less work and
getting a lot more done when we're in that
state, for example but not just the heart.
It's a lot of effects on.
>> Hm.
The whole body?
>> The whole body, yeah,
for the central conductor, if you will,
the heart is.
>> So that's, that's really exciting.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And I'm very curious to see maybe at
the end of our interview today,
you might be able to teach me a way to
sort of get into that state.
>> Sure.
>> another, another central theme that
seems to be drawn out a lot of
the work is this, the, emotions, our
emotions.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So,
what do emotions have to do with stress?
>> Well, good question, actually.
So, stress, right?
Kind of a safe word?
You know we say, you're stressing me out,
right?
What are we really saying?
Usually you're upsetting me.
You're causing me to feel frustrated, to
feel out of control, something.
So, the real essence of stress in most
cases, we're talking in
this domain it's always emotions, to have
two people on the roller coaster, right.
One person is white knuckle ahh, the other
person is yay,
right, going down the same ride.
It's a very different emotional response.
We can debate about what all the brain
mechanisms are and different appraisals
and perceptions and stuff, I have a little
different perspective on that than some.
But the point is, it's the emotion that is
what really is stress.
So for most people when we talk about
stress,
it's the emotional response, either to an
external or internal thing going on.
And that's important, because it's
emotions that drive physiology.
Really easy to see, in fact, on the
devices we make.
Like, if you're looking at the heart
rhythm, or blood pressure.
Doesn't really matter what physiological
measure you use.
You can have some pretty, somebody wired
up to all your equipment, and
having them think, or do cognitive tasks.
Yeah, you see some changes.
But you get' em, you induce an emotion,
you get' em pissed off, all right?
Or really caring about something,
and you see a lot of profound changes very
quickly.
So it's really the emotional system, is
this really higher up in the hierarchy,
of what drives physiological systems.
Whether we're talking about the HPA axis,
or autonomic function, and so on.
So the emotions I would say are the next
frontier,
in really understanding how to well, in,
certainly in human performance research.
>> Mm-hm.
And you guys have really taken,
you've really taken that a step further
into applying it with this concept of what
you've alluded to earlier, positive
emotions.
>> Sure.
>> So what has studying positive emotions
taught you about how we can better manage
our own stress states?
>> Yes well positive emotions are
certainly part of the equations but
managing our own stress states really
ultimately boils down to being able
to self regulate.
Make better choices, especially in the
moment.
You know it's kind of easy to feel good
and
self regulate, I call it in fair weather
times.
You know, all the traffic lights are green
and everything is going our way.
But to be able to do that when we're
challenged.
You know, when we're in the traffic jam or
the traffic jams of life, that's when it
really counts.
Can we really maintain that composure and
that ability to maintain, self regulate
ourselves then, is what's key.
So, once we understood the physiology, and
the benefits of feeling positive that
became a, a useful tool to self regulate.
In other words if we can activate a
positive feeling that's shifting our
physiology into this optimal state.
And that's having a profound influence on
cognitive function.
We make better choices right?
It opens, broadens, literally our
cognitive centers.
I mean I give an example if we have time.
>> Absolutely.
>> You may have probably never have done
this Corey but
you may be in dialogue with, I don't know
if you're married or
not but your girlfriend or colleague
whatever and
they say or do something that just kind of
gets you a little mad.
>> Oh, happens.
>> Happens.
>> It might have happened with my boss
today.
>> Yeah and then you say or do something?
You know, like, almost instantly after
that, and about a minute later you're
saying to yourself, oh my god, I can't
believe I just said that?
>> Oh, many times.
>> And does that usually create a lot more
stress and
energy drain that you have to clean that
up?
>> Absolutely, absolutely.
A whole mess to clean up.
>> A whole mess to clean up.
Yeah, so what happened?
Why when we were angry or
anxious state did we, that our brain, kind
of go into fog.
Right, so that's, was one of our, our
questions.
And as it turns out, there's a vast
literature on this.
In fact, one of the most famous hypothesis
in the field of
psychophysiology goes back to the 1970s.
And the term introduced back into the
describe that
very thing was called cortical inhibition.
So when the hearts in these erratic
patterns,
these incoherent states, it's basically
interfering with
the thalamus' ability to synchronize
activity of all our neurons.
Inhibiting cortical function.
So that's when we say or do the thing that
may not have been in our best interests,
so if we can learn to freeze that frame,
right?
Pause, learn that self-awareness.
Just take a few breaths, get ourselves
coherent, activate a positive feeling.
We go into that very different coherent
rhythm.
Now we're facilitating all those same
functions.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So we can make a better choice.
>> So the role of positive emotion seems
to be after creating awareness around
making a shift, is to, and do some more
optimal stay.
To make a better decision, and perhaps I
did the last time.
>> Yeah, or, or perform better.
We also know that coherence, that coherent
state is facilitates reaction times and
coordination, that's why it's so much in
athletics and professional athletic teams.
There's a carry over effect so, just being
in that coherent state for,
even a couple minutes, improves central
motor integration.
Those are reaction times, 37 milliseconds
on average for
example, which is huge, in sports.
>> Absolutely, so, one of the things that
maybe I can imagine myself or
other people associating with a lot of the
work you are talking about is
this concept of, of relaxation, sort of
calming the body down and.
>> Right.
>> Removing that
stressful feeling and state.
So, what is this concept of coherence,
physiological coherence,
how is that different than relaxation.
>> Great question.
So obviously, relaxation is an important
skill to have.
You know if it's time to relax, it's time
to relax.
You don't want the autonomic shifts to
occur that are associated with relaxation.
However, I'll have to say one of
the myths about relaxation is that it
increases performance.
That's true if you're at a high anxiety
state and getting ready to take a test or
something, sure.
But if let's say you are a police officer
or EMT, the last thing I
want you to do is be overly relaxed if I'm
the one hurting you're walking up right.
Like wow man maybe we should go over there
and see if he's bleeding or not right?
But I want you, I do want your heart rate
up.
I want you ready to take care of business
but
I want you to be composed and coherent.
So you can use coherence, once you learn
the skills to shift into a coherent state
to help you relax, chill out, increase
parasympathetic function and all that.
But you can also shift into a coherent
state And
coherence equals composure, right?
And improved cognitive functions with very
high heart rates.
So we, I, you may not know this, but we
developed the Resilience Program for
the Navy and all of the Army's advanced
performance centers use our,
our techniques and technologies.
And with training they're able to get
these individuals, and
it takes some practice, it's not day one,
to be in a coherent state, with heart
rates up over 120.
So it gets the pattern of the variability
here which reflect in our
degree of inners, increa,
inner-synchronization.
So, I hope that is an answer.
So it's, so coherence does not equal
relaxation per se.
>> Mm-hm, there seems to be some overlap,
but they are,
they are distinct from one another.
>> Oh absolutely.
Physiologically, they're very distinct now
at the same time you can be in a quote
relaxed state, low heart rate, increased
paracine [UNKNOWN] and all that right?
And have a very incoherent heart rhythm.
Be very out of sync.
And that's typically, not, again, not that
you would ever done this,
the end of the day, we're a beautiful part
of the world here, right?
You know, looking at a great, scene in
naturey,
or, in nature, overlooking, Pacific Ocean
here.
And, sitting there, maybe rehashing that
disagreement you had earlier in the day,
or a meeting that didn't go right.
God, I can't believe they said so and so
and next time I'll say such and
such, and, you know what I'm talking
about.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So you're relaxed physiologically
speaking, but
you're still incoherent, and that's still
an inefficient state.
You're still burning a lot of energy,
right down to the metabolic and
then we're starting to see now even
genetic effect level.
From that state even though you're
relaxed.
>> That's really, really interesting
stuff.
So, so then now we transition in talking
about science and applying the science.
And Heart Math is at a really fascinating,
sort of locust or
convergence between science and creating
these practical tools.
>> Mm hm.
>> So
from your perspective what are some of the
limitations and
challenges of trying to draw in what is
often the limited understand in science?
And then translating that into something
that can make our lives better.
>> Any time there's any new discovery,
there's always disagreement and
different interpretations.
I mean that's still going on in quantum
physics, for
example, a lot of interpretations and, and
so on.
So that's to be expected.
the, I think for the real part of your
question is how do
you turn science in something useful to
help people?
>> Mm-hm.
>> First of all, I think you have to have
the intent to do that.
To really be honest, I mean a lot of
science, I mean we could do basic
research and just keep doing that and
never care about if it got applied or not.
We have a different mission and intent,
which is really to help humanity so
when we, for example, I was talking about
when we discovered coherence,
that became very simple in a way.
I mean I don't want to make this sound
over simple but,
but, okay we've identified an optimal
physiological states.
How do we help people, self activate or
shift into that state?
Especially when they're in challenging
times.
So then that became another research
topic.
In developing tools,
techniques and then later technologies, to
help people do that.
I hope I'm answering your question near
enough.
Of course we do a lot of studies and
research that don't work.
[LAUGH] I mean, you know, we've paid our
dues here.
Often times, some of our studies have
worked really well.
Better than, I couldn't have, if I'd have
wrote down what I hoped the outcomes would
be before we start the study, I would've,
you know, limited the study.
I mean, even better outcomes, sometimes
too, so.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> I don't know if I answered your
question.
>> No, you are, you are addressing it.
It's trying, well I'm trying to articulate
is it seems to me like, of,
people will be very interested in what it
is that you, you guys are doing which is
applying science which is very different
than basic science research and how.
What are some of the challenges associated
with that?
>> Well, hah.
Well one of the biggest challenges depends
on the field we're talking to
actually as well.
Would be the idea that the heart the
activity of the heart affects the brain.
You know, I can't be, right?
So it's peoples' mindsets, and what
they've been taught.
Their histories, and
a lot of people have a lot invested in
what they've learned, right?
So if you're coming up with something new
or different than what they've learned,
that's challenging.
And, so the, I mean theres been a few
critics over the years.
But almost all of them have been people
who didn't bother to actually read any of
our research papers.
Just hear, you know, somebody says well
the heart fixed the brain for example.
Can't be, nonsense, right?
But they would bother to actually read our
work and
the vast literature that preceded it they
would be.
Well, they wouldn't be saying that.
I mean, the fact that the heart for
example, here's one that, still people
when they first hear it,
a lot of, a lot of the time don't believe
it, or just write things off.
And that is that the heart sends more
information to the brain than
the brain sends to the heart.
Absolute fact.
Been known since the late 1800s.
In fact, it was a, a key theory in early
psychology, right?
Up until the 1930s or so.
I mean it's anatomy but still when, that's
not currently taught in medical school or
probably a lot of psychology, in the
classes and so on.
So, people who haven't heard that, it's
wow I can't be.
>> So, who are some of these critics?
Where do they come from?
>> Well it, when they first hear that well
let's say
that the group that actually really gets
it pretty quickly is cardiologists.
They no problem at all with that
statement.
Often times, cause they know about the
afrin system and
all that and pain and that type of thing.
it, it can be academics especially in
psychology and
it actually surprises me sometimes in
talking to clinical psychologists and
stuff how little physiology training
they've had.
I mean I've literally had to explain how a
Neuron works to some physiologists
over the years.
The general public in general doesn't have
any problem with that.
Right?
>> Because it's coming from this intuitive
place [CROSSTALK]
>> Well, they all,
yeah, I mean I'll, I'll be honest Cory
though.
Probably the most common thing i hear from
the general public about our work and
our research is, God thank you.
You've actually confirmed something that
I've intuitively believed or
knew to be true all along.
So, it's really, thank you for showing
this.
I have more confidence in it now.
And actually go apply this stuff in my
life.
I don't know if I answered your question
or not yet.
>> No you absolutely have, thank you.
So moving away from sort of,
the science and the tools now and looking
more towards the future.
So, if you were to imagine, five, ten,
maybe 15 years from now,
what you might expect we have to look
forward to in this field of
the development of these stress
intervention tools.
>> Sure.
>> What do you think is in store of us?
>> A much deeper understanding of the role
of emotions.
I mean I, I really do mean that it's the
next frontier.
Once we understand that what most of us
knew when we were talking about stress.
And I'm not talking about the sort of
physiological stress of
being in extreme temperature, and things
like that.
But just what people's lives, when they're
talking stress, it's,
it really is emotion.
And, most people have never been taught
or, or
don't understand that that's something we
can self regulate.
We can choose our emotion diet.
In it, the biggest factor in health, in
our health care costs and people health
and well being is, is the lack of being
able to self regulate their emotions.
I-E stress.
So it's, it's really in the next frontier.
I mean especially kids.
They, they love the, our stuff.
And being taught at you see, they take to
it very quickly.
And what a, what a great gift to give a
kid, to be able to self-regulate.
And to be able to avoid a lot of the stuff
you have to unlearn later.
>> The problems we created for ourselves
in adulthood.
>> This is actually an area, if you kind
of relate it to your earlier question,
that science hasn't really been that
helpful in some cases.
There are still authors out there talking
about emotions like they're
almost a literal quote.
Emotions are something that just happen to
us, we have no control over them.
Nonsense.
Maybe if you're a rat.
[LAUGH] which, while these people are
studying, that's true.
But, no, we have great self regulatory
capacity, as humans.
You know, we have more, as you would well
know as in your field,
more responses than fight or flight, or
freeze.
We have the ability to self regulate,
socially engage, work out our problems.
So that's to me the.
>> Emotions are the next frontier.
>> Emotions are the next.
Understanding emotions, what they really
are and
the impact that they really have on, not
just physiology but socially I mean,.
>> So, also looking towards the future a
little bit.
If a, a student, many of our members of
our audience are, are students.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And many of whom might be interested in
becoming involved in study of stress or
the development of related tools.
So if one of them were to come to you,
asking for advice.
>> Mm-hm.
>> What would, what advice would you give
them?
>> You mean to go into that field?
>> Mm-hm.
>> Well, certainly, you're going to need a
background in physiology.
And probably psychology.
And there's actually a field that I'm, my
PhD's in, is psychophysiology.
A kind of combination of the two.
I don't know if you have a program, a
psychophysiology program here or not.
But, but if not Psychology and physiology,
but also it wouldn't
hurt to get some biomedical engineering
programs in there as well.
It is technology driven and that's when
things are rapidly changing is
when people's ability to self monitor from
a technology perspective.
Help provide feedback Monitoring of what's
going on in our body.
Which helps us, helps educate and motivate
people as well.
>> So, you would say, so, get in,
get understanding of psychology,
physiology and Biomedical engineering.
>> Biomedical engineering.
Excellent.
So, then, that leads us to one of our last
questions today.
Which is.
What's the, what's the take home message?
If you could leave one sort of soundbite
or
idea with the audience that really
reflects what's most important about your
message today what is that take home
message?
>> Well for yourself learn and
practice, being more self-aware of our
emotions and what's going on.
And learning how to self-regulate, be in
charge of ourselves.
Make better choices in our emotional diet.
>> Excellent, excellent.
Well then that, concludes our interview
today.
Thank you so much for being with us today
Dr. McCraty.
>> My pleasure.
>> It was a real pleasure.
>> Yeah, likewise.
Thank you.
So.