I'm excited for your students to get to
experience this class.
>> Tom McFadden is a Stanford graduate in
human biology,
he is passionate about science.
He has combined his love of music,
storytelling and science to create online
rap videos that have attracted online
viewers from around the world.
His interests have let him to outreach
work in New Zealand and
the Yucatán Peninsula in Mexico.
Tom McFadden has a Masters of Science
Communication and is Fullbright scholar.
He is now an eighth grade biology teacher
at the Nueva School.
His videos have created a new opportunity
for
students to express their passion about
science.
For those reasons and many others it's a
great honor to now turn to our
experiential interview in science
communication with Tom McFadden.
Tom, it's great to be here with you today
and thanks for coming down.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me, I'm very
excited about what you're doing.
>> Yeah, we're excited too.
So, I thought the great place to start
today with you Tom,
would be with your story about how it all
got started.
How did you, how did you begin this, this
journey of science, story and rapping?
>> Well worked at a summer camp for
my buddy, asked me to start making some
songs about milkshakes.
Started performing live.
This is right after I graduated and I kind
of discovered my love of
making goofy songs about stuff that were,
aren't a lot of songs about.
When I started teaching human biology it
was very natural fit.
There was a lecture about RIMs
reproductive isolating mechanisms, and
there was a lot of songs about rims that
already existed.
>> Pretty convenient?
>> Natural fit,.
And then it was just a total experimenting
and
doing and, not knowing what I was doing,
and throwing stuff online and
getting feedback in over the, over the
months.
I would just keep cranking these songs out
and getting more and more feedback, and
recruiting more people collaborators and
they kind of just got better and
better and I clarified my goals a little
bit more.
Started trying to make songs that were not
only useful to my Stanford students but
also to advanced high school students,
to anybody who is interested in learning
about the material.
Tried to dial-up the storytelling element
a little bit.
And those videos got enough media
attention and,
and love that I was, I've been able to use
them to do quite a few things that kind of
led me to the, the Fulbright in New
Zealand to study science communication.
While I was there I learned a lot about
storytelling and science communication.
And many people have really different
definitions of what, what that means.
And I thought a lot about it.
Used that to inform how I wanted to
continue to explore music and science.
And have used a lot of those lessons to do
work back here in
the United States with young students in,
in the Bay Area.
>> Great, so, so
tell us a little bit about some of those,
those projects that you're involved with.
What things that you've created with your,
your rap and storytelling?
>> A song that I, that I made while I was
still in Stanford its called Oxidate it or
Love it/ Electon to the Next One.
And, and I was kind of, I'd read this or
heard a piece by Robert Krowech
on on Radio Lab, kind of saying the citric
acid cycles,
the most horrible thing in all of high
school biology is, it's, you know?
I have to memorize the whole thing.
No-body likes learning it.
It crushes the soul out of any biology
student.
And I heard that and I was like, Robert,
you got it all wrong.
And the citric acid cycle is the most
beautiful, amazing thing ever.
And if you could just convey to students,
kind of the bigger picture,
the context, the story of where the citric
acid cycle fits into this larger picture,
then people can get excited about it.
So try to focus on turning food into ATP
and ATP into doing stuff.
And all told through a parody of a 50 cent
and Jay Z song.
So the music is kind of the hook.
The story's there if you can follow it.
But there's quite a bit of like, jargon,'
cause it was, it was meant for a,
a Stanford college class, and, I realized
that,
and in fact, Robert Colvitch wound up
writing a blog post about it
that was kind of like, I liked this video,
but I feel giddy, yet mystified.
Like, for a popular audience who didn't
know what,
what a lot of these words meant that song
doesn't communicate almost anything.
It's kind of fun, but you don't learn
anything about what's really going on.
So when I was in New Zealand, I tried to
adjust the message of the songs to be able
to appeal to younger students, to people
who are just general, the general public.
Made a song called Fossil Rock Anthem.
That was Party Rock Anthem, but about
fossils and paleontology.
And that.
>> That's a great video.
I love that one.
>> Thank you.
Yeah, I had to learn a lot of animation
skills to help tell the story because I
think the visuals are a really important
part of it.
And that one has been a hit on the road
cause you get people dancing and
shoveling and all sorts of stuff.
But there still isn't much of a story to
that one either.
It's kind of just like, I guess that, it's
a grand story, about we can
understand the world via we can understand
the earth by looking at fossils.
We can understand life by looking at the
earth and
those are, those are big grand narratives.
And then, most recently,
my projects have been trying to integrate
history into science songs.
So, you know, having students kind of take
on the personas of
scientists where they're discussing
evidence based arguments, ideally,
about, about science as a process but, so
you're also getting into social context,
you're getting into ethics, you're getting
into history.
Very interdisciplinary.
You still get some science, but you get,
what I think is even more important, which
is the nature of science.
>> Yes, so, it seems like all of these
sort of,
all these sort of things going on at once,
gives the student a bunch of
different lens, angles, ways to approach
the science.
A lot of different ways for the science to
possibly stick.
So, you're also involved in other
projects.
One of them is a Kickstarter campaign that
was successfully funded in,
in, in progress right now.
Can you tell us a little about that?
>> Yeah, absolutely, so yeah, when I was
talking about the science history that was
the, the Kickstarter project.
And I got a little bit of funding early on
from HP and
Silicon Valley Education Foundation who
wanted me to, or
who generously allowed me to make a couple
of videos with kids in the Bay.
And I've met five different students,
five different teachers at five different
schools in San Jose and Oakland.
I was just like, you know, I've got to do
them all.
I got to do projects at all these places.
I can't, couldn't say no.
So, needed to raise a bunch more money.
Because another thing I've learned over
the years is that production values
really matter.
They don't, they don't necessarily matter
as you're learning because
that's an important, you know, learning
curve.
For me, my, my first videos were of
horrible production values.
And they were critical parts of my doing
and learning process.
But at this point, I kind of have more
taste and, and,
and opinions about how things should look.
And when you just give kids a camera and,
and, and let them do whatever they want,
they're so early in that process that
their final product is going to be really,
really powerful for them but not for a
random science teacher in
Australia who's never see, you know,
doesn't know these kids.
There's no emotional attachment.
They just want a product that is good.
So the Kickstarter is a way to raise more
money, increase the budget, get some
professionals and help shoot and edit it
and to really do these stories justice.
And, and the kids would still have this
powerful experience of creating it but
their products could be used by people
around the world.
>> So, it sounds like, I mean,
you've done, you had these impressive
projects all around the world.
So, can you tell us a little bit about how
rapping and
telling stories about science has helped
you and your students reach their goals?
>> Yeah, absolutely.
I think one, there's many kind of ways
that I think it can be helpful.
One is, just for
me as a teacher, a way to bottle-up my
excitement about the topic, right.
This guy is making songs about video,
there must be some interesting stuff,
right.
It's a way to capture that energy.
Two, so it's a way to connect to students'
lives.
I think that's a really important thing in
education,
that if you can make things relevant,
however that works, that's important.
And if it happens to be relevant musically
or culturally or, there's so
many ways to do it, then that's kind of
nice.
I remember when I was teaching at Stanford
I had a song called Going Back to
Plasma Membrane which was to the tune of
Going Back to Cali.
And a student came up to me.
She's like, Tom, Tom, last weekend at the
frat party, they played that Biggie song.
And we were all singing Going Back to
Plasma Member.
And it was awesome.
So, like, yeah.
And so ideally, when a student hears a
song on the radio or
is engaging with that material outside of
class,
they, they end up thinking a little bit
about biology at that moment and
just kind of like sticky, the stickiness
of these songs is a, is a big part of it.
These pop songs like Party Rock Anthem
that people hear millions of times and,
what, it would be nice if they were
thinking about paleontology instead of
just partying.
So that, that is one of the other
benefits.
I think it's, it's kind of what you were
saying when you have a really multifaceted
project, where there's, you have to
understand the material and the history.
And be able to write lyrics, to story
board,
to draw things out, to work as a team.
There's so many different tasks for so
many different learning styles and
types of kids; for introverts, for
extroverts, for everybody.
There's ways for everybody to plug into
the material, and so,
that's a big part of the current projects.
We've got big groups of students all, all
working together on them.
And yeah.
It's just a, it all started really as just
a combination of my interests and
I've come up with all these justifications
afterwards.
But I think it, it has been, pretty cool
for a lot, for a subset of students, not
for everybody but there are a few students
in every class who really enjoy it.
>> And you can definitely see the passion
in the videos.
I mean you're clearly passionate about
what you do and
I think that attracts a lot of people.
It attracted us.
It's very, very cool.
So, tell, tell us a little bit more about,
you've been around this for a while now.
So, what are the,
what are some of the things that you
learned about good ways to tell stories?
What are the ways to tell stories about
science?
>> Mm.
>> And which ones don't work out well,
which ones do work well?
>> This was big, big theme of my masters
experience in New Zealand.
The mantra of the department was science
communication is about
good story telling and I didn't really
know what it meant when I got there.
I was kind of like, that sounds nice,
like that seems to make sense but I didn't
quite understand what it meant.
I spent two years trying to figure out
what that actually means, right.
Like, how do stories allow you to teach
science or communicate science better?
And I realized that people have really
different ideas.
When one of the main ideas that exist out
there is kind of telling these
archetypal narratives about, you know, the
rags-to-riches or
this, these eight essential human
narratives.
And then just imposing those narrative on
a, onto a footage of penguins.
And there you, you know, March of the
Penguins, box office smash hit,
really when people are watching it,
they're thinking about human beings, and
love and all these and kind of imposing
all these things onto the animals.
And I worry a little bit about sometimes
about that style of, of storytelling,
because it's very entertaining and you
walk away feeling good about penguins,
but you don't necessarily learn a lot
about, you know,
why penguin behavior from a scientific
perspective.
That's probably not their goal, right?
They're just trying to make a cool movie.
But I think there's other ways to get more
at the science.
One of those ways is kind of what I would
consider the Carl Sagan style which is to
tell these incredibly beautiful, grand
narritives about human existence that are
almost spiritual in nature because
they allow the audience to really connect
with the material to their own existence.
Like, wow, I'm made of stars and
we're just tiny little things in a huge
universe.
And, and that's very powerful storytelling
for a lot of people.
And, and it's one of the reasons I'm
personally attracted to science.
That's why I study science, is because I
think the stories that
it tells us about our own lives and our
own existence are the most compelling and
true and interesting stories that exist.
Same goes for evolution and understanding
our connection to all living things and,
and our relation to each other, and our
relation to the the living world.
So that's a whole to kind of the grand
narratives.
There's also a lot of science stories that
are more focused on short stories
that are often funny and relevant to
something in, in your life.
So Stephen J Gould was kind of the king of
this.
He wrote all these short essays that would
connect whatever he was trying to
communicate to baseball or to Mickey Mouse
or to something else.
And you wouldn't know why he was doing it
but
then all of a sudden boom, analogy made,
story completed.
You just learned something awesome.
Mind blown.
Robert Sapolsky here at Stanford also a
total jedi of this,
this kind of technique of storytelling.
And one of the things I've noticed that
both of them do is they
often incorporate the historical
narratives into the storytelling.
So they will kind of oversimplify in a
funny way that allows you to know like,
they're not you know, these characters
he's describing weren't really like this.
But the story's so gripping that you just
want to go on this ride, and
you learn all of these, these things, you
know?
Stephen J Gould versus E.O. Wilson, and
their different philosophies of evolution.
Or Barbara McClintock looking for
transposons, and no one believed her.
And it was her against the, she was this
hero fighting against the male
establishment, and, and, those are all
compelling stories that are,
you understand are a little bit over
simplified, but
allow you to get that transposons, like
I'd, I'll never forget what those are,
because of those stories that he told.
Huge advantage of incorporating history,
is that you get to learn
about what scientist actually do, what
science is about, the ethics of science,
the nature of science, the historical
context and so
many really important things for
understanding what science is.
That's one of the big shifts that I've
made in my own science song,
storytelling world is that I'm, at this
point I'm less interested in
telling you the story of the citric acid
cycle as a, a, a,
you know, an experience that might have a
lot of jargon in it that is kind of just,
the, yeah, the, the communication of
these.
Although it's still very exciting.
It doesn't tell you much about how we
learned that information, or
how scientists study biochemistry, or, or
what science is.
It's like oh, here are the facts.
Here's the story as it already exists.
Whereas when you get into some of the
history you actually are learning about
science as a process.
Which is a mo, ultimately a more important
lesson for students of science.
Last category is,
is kind of stuff that I would learn when I
was doing science in labs.
At lab meetings a lot of PIs will be like,
what's the story you're
trying to tell in this lab meeting and a
lot of times that can be based around your
experimental logic, Even if that's how you
did it or not, you, you're kind of framing
a story of like, then I was doing this,
and then I found this, so then I did this.
It's a quest, or a model,
like scientific models of how things work
are kind of stories.
This molecule, talks to this molecule and
that's the reason blank does blank,.
So yeah those are, I've thought a lot
storytelling in science.
I think there's more that I haven't
mentioned.
I think there's overlap between the things
that I have mentioned.
But I think it's really a valuable
exercise for any student of science or
scientists, anybody who's interested in
it.
To really think about the structure of the
stories they want to tell and
why they're telling them that way.
>> Yeah, so I'm hearing, in particular,
short stories and
historical context you've learned along
the way are really helpful.
>> I wish I had any sort of research to
back that up, there also, it's partially
a personal taste thing right, it's like
for me that is my favorite, right.
I would much rather read a, a Steven J
Gould essay than watch March
of the Penguins, but like, that's not true
for everybody.
So I think there's room for all these
different things.
>> Absolutely, and so hopefully what
we're,
we're trying to do with especially these
interviews is to draw students
closer to the people who are in the field
experencing these environmental stressers.
Or the scientist who are, you know,
at their lab bench discovering the things
that we end up learning about in school.
So, it's pretty exciting to see some
overlap here.
>> Oh, and I think that's, that's, those
are two really,
really important things for students of
science to be thinking about is like what,
how's this relevant in everyday people's
lives, right?
To a mountain climber, to this, to a sky,
like you have to know science in order to,
or you get to know science, and get to
understand these things better.
And then, of course, the scientist who are
studying this.
There's so many rich stories there.
So that's, exactly, exactly,
I would put into that same awesome
category of, like, yeah.
>> It's awesome.
>> You're learning the information, but
you're also learning how you discover that
information.
>> Yeah, that's I think its really
exciting,
its exciting to see where all this stuff
is going to take us.
>> Uh-hm.
>> So
that leads me to my next question which is
a kind of difficult question, but if you,
if you could guess into the future so lets
say five, ten, fifteen years from now,
we'll talk about this field of science
communication and story telling.
Where's it going to take us?
>> Yeah.
>> Where do you think we're going with
this stuff?
>> I think one big part of it will be
interactivity.
Just because the way technological tools
are changing.
There's so many opportunities for people
to be a part of any given story.
Whether that's sort of citizen science,
people collecting data and uploading or
people choose your own adventure, you
know,
like you kind of having this control over
what direction you want to go.
So I think that there will probably be
more and
more exciting tools that allow for that.
And allow the, the quote unquote consumer
of the story, or
the student, to really be able to direct
where the story goes.
I also have never really, like until I saw
your guys' videos, I never thought about
structuring an entire college course
around this, this train that they
used to call that in school, this, this
narrative train that drives everything.
And there is peripheral stories and side
stories, but this thing that kind of
keeps it all united, and characters that
keep it united.
and, and to me, that seems like a very
smart move, and a very, I,
I would not be surprised to see many MOOCs
copying what you guys do, because I
think it'll be extra entertaining, and
extra fun to follow, and, and
will keep people motivated and keep people
interested as, as the course goes on.
>> So, also looking towards the future.
You've done a really cool,
really unique exciting things with your
time as a student and beyond.
And there might be other students are
watching like wow,
Tom McFadden is the man, I want to, I want
to tell stories about science maybe it's
through rapping, maybe it's a different
medium like we use.
What advice would you to a student who
came to you,
wanting to follow in your footsteps and
was looking for advice?
>> One of the, the most empowering things
to me was just,
I had these many, many interests when
coming to college.
I was interest in humanities, in Spanish,
in music and science and
all these different things.
And I had many different life experience
and
these, this career path of connecting
science, music, working with kids,
multimedia, making videos was this crazy
combination of all my interests.
And it wasn't obvious that that should,
should be my, my road.
But once I found it,
it was just boom, like this is exactly all
the things that I like to do.
So one, one piece of advice is I,
I assume that most students have a variety
of interests, right?
Some people are very focused, I just
want to do this.
But I think more and more it is becoming
possible to
create your own connections of your
passions and your own interests, am,
especially if they involve communication
or technology or multimedia.
You can bring in your love of this and
that and the other thing all together and,
and so to not shy away from, from trying
to combine passions.
another, this is kind of a common piece of
advice but
like, those first songs that I made, were
crap, right?
They were not good.
Like the students would kind of like, oh
my ha, ha, ha, my TA is making,
making a rap song and they liked it but it
wasn't like, it was bad, right?
It was, it was poorly recorded.
The video was totally bare bones.
Like, I tried to sing and I can't sing, I
can't carry a tune pretty much.
And, and it was bad but like you have to
go through that stage and
by continuing to produce quantity you can
get towards quality.
And you, that's the only way to learn is
by doing stuff and
learning from your mistakes and talking to
smart people who are in that field and
collaborating and and just the power of
doing something and
instead of just sitting around and
thinking about it, is pretty important.
As we wrap up today, one last question to
leave you with and
it's, what is your, what's the take home
message?
If you have one, you have one token, one
golden nugget,
to leave with us today, what would it be?
>> Let's see, the take home message.
Let me think about that for a minute.
I saw that question earlier and I was
like, man.
>> They're going to hit me with that.
>> I don't, I don't have one take home
message.
I mean, and it's hard to do one without
sounding cliche, you know?
Like, one is, obviously, follow your
passion, like, for you.
because once you,
once you're kind of obsessed with
something everything else becomes easy.
Because you want to be doing it and you're
going to put so much work into it and
you're going to put in so much more
effort.
And that is the only way to make quality
work, to do,
to produce quality material, is to put in
that much effort.
But it doesn't feel like effort if you're
madly in love with doing it.
That's a lot easier said than done to find
that passion.
So I guess part two would be do a bunch of
stuff [LAUGH].
And, and that's, that can be difficult to
do as well, but I've
benefited tremendously from being able to
explore different fields, different,
media and different experiences and, and
see what really felt right to me.
So if you can do both of those things,
you'll be all right.
[LAUGH]
>> Excellent.
Well, what a great message.
And thanks for being here, Tom.
It was really a pleasure to have you in
and I can't wait to see all of your,
your music take off even more than it
already has.
>> Likewise, I'm very excited to see how,
[LAUGH] how this kind of novel form of
online education takes off.
>> We'll see where it goes.
So, I've got one last thing I just thought
of.
Which is I, do you do free style rapping?
>> [LAUGH] I have, I have in the past.
It's not my, my, my best skill.
But, I can practice and you edit it out.
>> I don't either.
I've never really rapped before.
But what I can do, is try to make a little
beat.
And we can just see what comes out of it.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Well, go for it, let's see what happens.
>> It's like I see people put their hands
up to their mouths.
>> That's to protect the audience from the
spit.
>> Okay, got it.
So it's like [NOISE]
>> Sittin' here at this table of Stanford,
lotta questions and a lotta answers.
Just the interview was Corey and Tom and
maybe you up in the online atmosphere.
Yeah, what happens here is going to go
around the world, and
it's going to keep twirling and I got no
more rhymes.
[LAUGH]
>> Error, error, error, error, error, er.
Urrgh.
[LAUGH]
>> They you go.
>> That was great.
[LAUGH] We don't have to use any of it if
you don't want to, but I had a great time.
[LAUGH]
>> Yeah, good.
Sweet, that's fine, I've never freestyle
so that was pretty.
[LAUGH] So alright, made a few rounds.
>> Great, [LAUGH] good interview.
[LAUGH]
>> Sweet.
>> Even for freestyle.
[LAUGH] So, a good day.
>> Did you want to get in here,
do a little freestyle.
[LAUGH]
>> I don't have that.
>> Oh c'mon!
[LAUGH] This is the beauty with a video
is, you can always edit it out.
But if it's fantastic, then -
>> It's true.
>> it's something you'll never forget.
Oh, Wes is here, too.
>> I think, I think we have [INAUDIBLE].
>> What's up, Wes?
>> Hi, Wesley.
>> I feel like what we just did is,
that's the intro to the video.
>> [LAUGH].
>> We just skip that
whole introduction part.
>> Uh-huh.