[BLANK_AUDIO]
What a journey we've had together.
Lets take a little walk down memory lane.
You joined us on a voyage across the
United States into the depths of the human
body where we gained an appreciation of
how the body responds to cold, heat,
aging, stress, altitude and variable
pressure.
You visited us here on Stanford's campus
where we dunked Corey in
the water tanks and then heated him back
up again.
You got to travel to MIT,
where we wandered the streets of Cambridge
in the Agnes suit.
You got to see me throw myself out of an
airplane for the good of science, and
you were soothed by Corey's calming voice,
talking about stress and relaxation.
And let's not forget our adventures in the
mountains of Colorado and
flying planes in Livermore, California.
Phew.
We got to go all over the place and have a
lot of fun doing it.
But what really made the journey special
was that you joined us,
sharing your interesting insights and
different perspectives on
the material from around the world through
the discussion forums.
>> And when you started joining our class,
you really joined us from all over the
world.
We were looking at participants starting
to register at, Kundelis registered from
Lithuania and, and Fenna from Germany, and
Michiyuki from Hong Kong, Mohamed from
Egypt, Wilson from Scotland, and then
Croatia and then Russia, South Africa,
Indonesia and our backyard, San Fransisco,
back over to France, Pakistan, Columbia.
You really came from, from all over the
world to participate in this journey.
Even down to Fred, from our own backyard
in Palo Alto, California.
And let's not forget, let, let us not
forget about you from your own hometown.
You all joined together,
through your computers, to share this
experience with us.
It was so exciting when you started to
introduce yourself.
That first post that came through.
We were live, and then they started to
flood in from all over the world.
>> Yeah, and, one of the highlights of the
first couple of days was the Titanic post,
combining my favorite movie with
physiology.
I didn't know something so beautiful could
happen.
>> Yeah.
And then you all start falling in love
with Corey.
He's so cute [LAUGH].
His voice is so soothing.
>> She loves to embarrass me.
>> [LAUGH] And, we want to hear more from
Corey.
Yeah, thank you a lot for that one, by the
way [LAUGH].
>> Yeah, well let us not forget all about
all the middle aged men who
were attractive to Dr. Friedlander.
>> How do you know they're middle aged?
>> And her curvy intellect.
>> [LAUGH] Curvy intellect.
>> [LAUGH] Well setting that aside we had
some bumps along the way
technical issues for example, and I have a
confession to make.
Some of those technical issues you may
have encountered were my responsibility,
so sorry about that.
And thanks for the, thanks for
the feedback so that we could correct it
as soon as possible.
But we were all making mistakes.
At least you didn't miscalculate the
conversion from meters to feet [LAUGH].
That was kind of embarrassing, and
then I really emphasized it just to make
sure that everyone would notice.
But we fixed that.
>> Yeah.
>> So it was a little chaotic for
us here and there behind the scenes, but
overall, for
our first online class, I think it went
pretty well.
>> Mm-hm.
>> We also received so many wonderful
comments from all of you.
Even when we messed up, you were kind in
the way that you pointed it out.
At the end of the day, the thing that
excites us the most is the opportunity to
share our passion about learning and
physiology with you, to awaken that
lifelong learner inside.
So we'd like to propose a toast to all of
you who have taken the class.
Here's to you.
You made it, through the good, the bad,
the highs of the mountains and
the lows of underwater, the annoyance of
the check-all-that-apply questions.
You did it.
We toast to your supreme efforts.
Cheers.
>> Cheers.
Clink.
You did it.
I suppose this is our final goodbye, and
my last chance to thank you for
the amazing opportunity that I feel like
we all had to share this time together.
I learned so much.
It's contributed a great deal to my life.
And I really hope that you can walk away
from your experience with us
with a couple of things that it added to
your life too.
Cheers.
>> Cheers.
[SOUND]
Bye.
[INAUDIBLE]
Before I sign off as well,
I just want to repeat the theme of the
class for you one last time because I
believe it is so important that you leave
with this message.
Your body is awesome.
Learn about it, appreciate it, take it out
for a test spin periodically to
see what it can do, and most of all, treat
it with respect.
It works hard for
you every day to help you experience the
world around you in the best possible way.
Do what you can to keep it healthy and
strong.
It's been a great journey.
We'll miss you.
Bye.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You did it.
We toast to your supreme efforts.
Cheers.
>> I suppose it's my.
>> No, you're supposed to drink.
>> Oh, geez.
>> [LAUGH] You're supposed to drink, and
then.
>> Okay.
Okay.
We should do that over again.
>> [LAUGH]
>> [INAUDIBLE] here, drinking up my own.
You're just staring at [LAUGH] [SOUND]