[MUSIC]
>> Alright.
>> Hey.
[INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]
>> Hello everyone.
We have arrived at the last module for
this section on heat.
>> Are you talking to me on the other side
or are you talking to Zack?
>> [UNKNOWN] [LAUGH]
>> Oh, you know [LAUGH] time chiming
first.
>> I like cold.
>> [LAUGH].
>> [LAUGH] He came to really come for my
exercise this morning.
>> [LAUGH].
>> [LAUGH] Good boy.
>> Wait, were you talking to me here?
>> I'm off the hook.
>> So you're going to be there once a day
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Actually, you know,
we should be writing stuff like this down.
All right, last one of this.
>> You can do whatever you like.
>> Now am I too low energy now?
Am I too mellow?
>> No, I think that's great.
>> Alright, alright.
You can, you've already got to see Corey
get hot.
I'm sorry.
Can I start that over, is that actually
proper English?
You've already [SOUND] got to see.
You already got, okay.
Not you've already [INAUDIBLE].
Welcome back to Module 5 - Minimizing the
Negatives.
We just spent a couple of modules talking
about hot, ho, ho, huh [SOUND] [LAUGH].
>> [LAUGH]
>> Was that enough of a step [LAUGH].
>> That was awesome.
I was like yeah!
[LAUGH] Go get it.
>> [SOUND] Alright.
[MUSIC]
>> How about this flicker, huh?
>> It's pretty good.
>> It's working, it's working.
[LAUGH] Alright.
[LAUGH] Now I'm not going to be able to do
it without laughing.
[NOISE] I notice that I stepped.
He's thinking, finally.
[MUSIC]
Before we move on to Module 6.
I'd like to say a couple words about drugs
and hyperthermia.
Disturbances in dopamine and
serotonin in the brain have been inclemen,
implecate, have [LAUGH].
>> Implemicious.
>> Implemented, implicated [LAUGH] have
been [SOUND].
Hey, hey, [NOISE] wake up out there!
This is important.