And it's just an amazing experience.
It's almost hard to put into words.
It's both fascinating and exhilarating.
>> Ken Zemach is a Senior Managing
Scientist at Exponent, Inc.
an engineering, consulting company that
performs complex analysis on projects and
problems around the world.
While consulting for the military in Iraq
and
Afghanistan, Ken decided it was time to
start running to get back into shape.
He started running through the desert, the
machine yards and
the dust storms that never stopped.
He quickly accomplished his initial goal
of running 50 miles, and
started looking for the next challenge.
His desire to push his personal limits
eventually led him to
the Badwater UltraMarathon in Death
Valley,
considered by many to be the world's
toughest foot race.
During this past summer of 2013, Ken blew
through the desert heat
in a blistering 28 hours and 37 minutes to
come in seventh overall in the race.
Because of his stellar ability to push the
limits of human performance,
especially in the heat.
It is my pleasure to welcome Ken Zemach,
as our Experiential Interviewee for
the Heat section.
Thank you for joining us today.
>> Sure, my pleasure.
>> So, it's a great story that you were in
Iraq.
You just decided you wanted to start
running and
then that took you to one of the most
challenging races in the world.
Can you tell us a little more about that?
>> Yeah well the whole process started, I,
through working too much for
a couple decades and I let myself go.
And woke up one day and finally said it's
it's time to actually commit to getting in
shape, losing some weight.
About 35 pounds worth.
So obviously a lot of that was better
eating habits.
And I figured I might as well just start
running.
So you know, I'd go out and run every day.
you know, three miles, five miles, and
ran into another contractor who had, was
training for a 50 miler.
And I thought, well, I need a goal.
If he can run 50 miles, I'll bet I can run
50 miles.
Now, remember, I've never done a marathon.
Still haven't done a marathon.
And so I decided that was going to be
goal.
So that would be what I would train for
while I was deployed.
I come home, I'll run a 50 miler, then
I'll hang up the running shoes, and,
you know, go back to doing whatever.
And came home, ran a 50 miler, but
I kind of already knew what was going to
happen, because while you're training for
a 50 miler, you, you know that the 100
milers exists.
And the problem is, is if you finish 50
miles.
Then, the real question is: Well, could
you have run a hundred miles?
So I ran a hundred miler.
Fairly pedestrian hundred miler as far as
they go.
It would be 7,000 vertical climbing and
descent on it.
>> [LAUGH]
>> As they go.
As they go.
And then the question became.
Well OK I can run a hundred miles, but can
I run a hard 100 miles.
And then off-course all of this leads
towards setting higher goals and
Badwater has both the reputation and, and
really the provides
the experience of something that is shall
we say on the extreme side.
>> Yeah, let's actually talk about the
Badwater.
So, the Badwater Ultra covers 135 miles
non-stop from Death Valley to Mt.
Whitney in California, in temperatures up
to 130 degrees Fahrenheit,
with a cumulative elevation gain of 13,000
feet.
So, that drew you.
That just felt like the ultimate challenge
for you?
>> Yeah.
You know, you hear about it and it sounds
crazy.
And then I got a chance to actually pay
somebody for it.
So, you know, there's a racer will have a
support crew.
And so I volunteered to be on somebody's
This Italian guy was coming over who
needed some Americans to help him out.
And that made it seem both all the more
crazy and yet tangible.
You know, watching somebody actually doing
it.
It's, it's an experience thats very hard
to explain.
But, it's very community oriented.
It's a race but it's, not really a race
like the way a triathlon is run.
You know, the top competitors are all
talking with each other about their
families and what's going on while they're
racing.
It's very friendly.
Competitive friendly.
And it's, it's just an amazing experience.
Its almost hard to put into words, its,
its both fascinating and exhilarating.
>> So you want to be part of that?
>> Oh, absolutely and I, you have that
question can I do it?
>> hm.
>> And you know, people then say why would
you do that, and I,
I think the response is why would you set
a goal that you know you can make.
So that what you pat yourself on the back
and then, you know, based on what?
Why don't you instead, set a goal that you
don't know if you'll actually succeed and
maybe in the process of years succeeding
or failing, you'll find something out
about yourself that you wouldn't have, if
you hadn't had to press yourself so hard.
>> So did you expect to do as well as you
did?
Because you came in second.
>> No.
>> That's pretty impressive.
>> I mean your place in these things is.
[COUGH] Excuse me.
There's definitely a genetic backing to
that.
You know, some people will never be,
you know, two thirty marathoners, no
matter how hard they train.
But you reach out to whatever your genetic
potential is.
And mine is, you know, I kind get where I
fell in,
in the speed of running over long
distances, distribution.
And, you know, I was figuring on a regular
BadWater year based on how
people finished in other races, who've run
BadWater.
I'd, I'd be, you know, yeah, I could
probably break 32 hours.
And on a hot year, which this year
happened to be which made it
about 7 to 10 degrees hotter than your
average Badwater year.
I think the highest,
unrecorded, unofficial temperature was 125
degrees during the day, in the shade.
Of course, there was no shade where we
were running.
You add a couple of hours so by the time
we got the start I was thinking
I can break for 36 hours I'll be happy,
and I did it in a little over 28 and
half and a half I just, I did not know how
I did that.
[LAUGH]
>> While you we're running,
could you tell that you were doing better
than expected at each mile or
did you just get surprised at the end?
>> No.
I mean it's definitely it is a very data
intensive race.
Because you have a support crew with
usually two support vehicles of
six people.
You've got people who are logging your
water intake.
People who are logging your electrolyte
intake, your estimated calories.
Checking pace, you know, logging what
running shoes you're in,
how many times you're gone to the bathroom
you know, and approximate volume.
I mean it's, it's a very data intensive
race.
So I knew how fast I was going cause
actually we
were all a little concerned cause in any
race 50 miles and up.
In the beginning it feel good because you
always feel good.
because you go in so slow, that how can
you not feel good.
So everyone there is a tendancy to run too
fast in these things.
In the beginning you're like I feel great,
of course you feel great,
you're like on mile 20, you know.
[LAUGH] So, you know, how you going to
feel about 60 or 80 or 110.
So there was a little concern that I was
going to fast.
And I just had to go what I feel.
One thing I did was I'm a bit of a data
geek.
So I wore a heart rate monitor.
And I always wear a heart rate monitors
when I train.
Heart rate monitor is probably one of the
better objective measures that
you can use for effort.
obviously, it's not a direct measure of
muscular versus cardiovascular effort, but
it's a pretty good guess.
Now, what I didn't know is, would it work
with the stress that you experience in
the heat, and I just had to take it on
faith that it would.
So, I basically ran, and tried to keep my
heart rate below a certain level.
The whole time I ran and, and
then use that as my, as my metric for not
letting adrenaline and,
to be fair, testosterone keep you from,
from over exerting yourself.
And it worked.
I was, I was quite surprised.
>> Yes, that's very impressive.
So what was the most challenging element
of the race?
>> Of the race, well,
I would say the most challenging element
of the race was the training for the race.
[LAUGH] It was brutal, but we can talk
about that later.
The, the race, I, I think the most
challenging element is, well,
there's, there's the physical stuff which
is certainly a heap.
I mean, it feels like your body won't
lasts for us.
It really does.
I mean it is just you know,
you have soaked the sleeves of your shirt
with the water.
Ice water you know every time you got a
crew change out or something.
And they, they'd just be dry you know for
minutes.
If you, and your arms would just be hot.
And your face is hot.
So there's certainly physically.
It was hot.
I think the heat was certainly bad.
So one of the more challenging parts,
though, was, you know,
to race like this, you have to be really
careful that nothing goes wrong.
because when things start to go wrong and
cascade, it's very difficult to recover
from that.
Let's say you're running a 10 mile race.
And your knee starts to tweak.
Mile eight, and partly finish.
If you're in a 100 mile race and
your knee tweaks at mile 80, you're in a
lot of trouble.
And so the problem in Badwater isn't just,
you know, oh, you know,
my stomach's a little upset like it was in
that other, you know, 20 miler I ran.
You know so I ate a few, a little few
gels, or whatever.
You know, Badwater, at hour five.
If your stomach start to feel a little
upset, it might not be a big deal.
But if it becomes a big deal, it's a big,
massive deal.
It can be a showstopper.
So, managing, all of the little things
you're feeling.
Of course, then you start getting these
self fullfilling prophacies.
And these you, you, over analyze things,
you know.
Oh, for a while, I thought I was getting a
blister on one of my heels.
So, I immediately stopped.
I got to take care of this blister.
I took off my shoe.
Three of my crew, are physical therapists.
Ones a Veterinary Surgeon and the other
was a vet.
And, so they look at me and go, there's
nothing wrong with you.
[LAUGH] Oh no, I feel, I feel, I'm getting
a blister.
I'm getting a blister.
They're like, you're not getting a
blister.
And then as I'm putting on my socks both
my legs cramp up and like I can't walk.
And, you know, it's just.
You know, it's like is this a good cramp
or bad cramp?
Am I going to be able to get over this
one?
And you just.
It's, it's, it's, it's this constant
massaging of how are you feeling.
Yeah, I'll tell friends when I go out for
a long run and you say oh, I'm happy I ran
100 miles, I ran 135 miles.
And then he'll say God, you must be so
bored, what do you think about?
And it is anything but boring, because if
you, if you come along somebody at,
you know, mile eighty, and let's say they
don't have their pacer with them.
You can come over, and you're, they're
racing.
You have a conversation with them, you
know.
And the conversation will be for, you
know, a good five minutes, and
I'd be like, look, can, can you shut up?
Because I've got a lot going on.
I'm trying to look at my pace, I'm trying
to see how my heart rate's going.
You know, I'm really busy.
And especially these trail hundred milers.
They're different from Badwater because
you're on an open road, but
a trail hundred miler.
You, you are mentally taxed to the limit
by hour fifteen.
Because you're tired.
You know, might be 3 am.
You, you've got ten more hours to go or
it's going to get lost.
How's that heel?
Or are you taking in enough calories.
The next aid station is coming up.
How many calories are you going to take
there?
How much are you going to refill your
water.
Oh, how's your pace doing?
Oh, and how's that other ankle feeling.
Oh, have you checked in on your knee
lately.
How's your heart rate going?
You know and you're just.
>> Be careful of the trail, through the
rough section.
>> Yeah, ex, exactly, what do you have, do
you have a rough?
[LAUGH] Alright, so,
Same thing with Badwater although you
don't have the problem with getting lost.
If you get lost there, you're in a lot of
trouble.
You're actually really busy.
And you're busy because there is not only
is there a lot to do,
but you're mental faculties start to go.
>> So what were you wearing, and is it
true that you're shoes melt on,
on the pavement?
>> Yeah, so there's, there's a lot of lore
about Badwater.
Some of which is true, some of which is
probably not true, and
some of which I think depends.
You know, if there is a the, people have
said that, it's so
hot you have to run on the white line or
your shoes will melt.
>> you, perfect.
>> That's not true.
Now what is true,
according to some longtime veterans is
some of the earlier shoes, the the glue
that laminates the layers together was,
not thermaset and that would melt
until they'd literally get delamination
with the sole or the bottom of the shoe.
And I've heard that some of the insoles
would actually start sticking like
they weren't using full cured rubber.
However the shoe manufacture would make
them.
Those would stick to the socks.
You know, you peel them off the socks.
But, you know, you don't have to run on
the white line.
You could run on the black asphalt.
Now the black asphalt could be 190 degrees
farenheight, right?
I mean.
It's hot or [CROSSTALK].
>> You feel that heat coming up.
>> Yeah.
Oh, it is just
>> In your calves.
>> It is.
So miserably hot it's unbelievable.
And you don't just lay on the ground.
You get off the road.
And it's, it's just brutally hot.
Yeah, you know, there's just, there's
there's just some things about
Badwater event that that are, are so
unique.
I mean, first of all there's just the
brutal temperature.
They start everybody in three waves based
on what they predict your speed will be.
6 AM, 8 AM and 10 AM.
They start the slow people, slower people,
slow.
Nobody's really fast, either, in this kind
of race.
But start, people who are going to take
longer at 6:00 am,
and then the faster ones at 10:00 a.m.
I've got a 10:00 a.m.
start.
The point of that is not just to
spread it out.
So you don't have a giant bobble, on the
road.
It's, it's to make sure that everybody
runs.
This must be the hottest part of Death
Valley,
the hottest part of the day, the hottest
time of the year.
>> Well, that's nice of them, put that in
there.
>> It's very considerate.
Well, I mean, you wouldn't want to feel
cheated.
>> Right.
>> You know.
>> You're pushing your limits.
You may as well really go for it.
>> Yeah, people say well, come on.
It's so stupid to run it in the middle of
July.
You know, why don't you run it in
December?
It's like, well then, why not run it on an
air-conditioned treadmill.
I mean, you know.
>> Then it
wouldn't be the toughest race around.
>> [LAUGH] Then, then, what's the point?
You know,.
You know, so, you do that, you start off
and it's just so hot.
And then you get, then you get to start
going up hill.
And the first hill you get to, Town Pass,
I can't remember how long it is, something
like 15 miles up hill.
If you can.
Anywhere between five and 13 degrees slope
and the thing is this happens usually for
everybody around when its dark again, when
it's getting close to night.
So you're climbing at least it's not that
hot when you're climbing.
Most people are, you know, you're speed
hiking it or
power hiking it as the [INAUDIBLE] like to
call it.
But the way that Death Valley is,
as it sets up these thermal winds that are
picking the heat.
And I am not kidding.
And ev-, it is at least.
And I've done a lot of sailing, so I'm
pretty good at estimating this.
It is at least an average of 25 mile an
hour wind in
your face the entire way up this pass.
So you don't even get to a little place
where it would be flat.
And you try and run and
it's just, it's such diminishing returns
because the, the head wind is so strong.
There's no point in even running.
And it is just blasting you.
Somebody had given me a very good tip, a,
a veteran who had run before.
He said, make sure your whole crew and you
have clear safety glasses.
>> Mmhmm.
>> Why?
Now some people wore sunglasses.
That's the start of the day.
Obviously if it's sun and the reflection
why would i need clear glasses for night?
Why?
Because of the wind.
And they were not kidding.
It's like, it's and then when, you know
sand and dust would blow up in it.
It was like being hit with a sandblaster,
but sandblaster and the blast hurts.
It was just, you know, and, and you don't
think you'd be.
You know, you're passing somebody or
somebody passing you not very quickly of
course and you just look at them.
It's like I, I can't run.
And I'm like nobody can run.
>> What did you do for food and drink
during the race for that 27 hours?
>> So, Yeah.
So, obviously you, you churn some long
hours and you've done a lot of races.
Nobody even gets to enter this race.
Can't even apply to the race unless you
run at least three hundred milers.
That's the minimum qualifying stance.
Everybody whose has done this is towing
the line, has run for
at least 20, 24 hours before.
So you kind of know how your stomach is
probably going to handle food.
And you know, there's a popular you know,
a lot of people who take these gels.
Yeah it's an efficient form of energy.
Well, yeah they don't taste so bad.
But you try eating gels after 7 hours, oh
and
by the way 7 hours you just started, kay.
After 7 hours of gels, you know,
those things do not taste like a fun snack
anymore.
It's not like people go home, they look in
their cabinet and go oh a gel.
I think I'll have a snack.
They're already bad enough as they are.
So you basically bring a wide variety of
foods.
This is compounded, you know, by the heat.
Because as you all know.
As anybody who's been in that really hot
sun is not that hungry.
But you've gotta eat.
So but you don't want to force feed
yourself cause you don't want to throw up.
But if you're not eating regularly you
will balk.
You will not finish.
So what did I eat?
Well I brought what I thought I could eat
which was a mixture of gels and
this this stuff called [INAUDIBLE] made by
a particular component which is
a maltodextrin mix that isn't too sweet
tasting.
And then it was, you know, gore up with
salt,
nuts and raisins and different bars.
And then you know, different things start
to taste good.
We had cheese pizza.
[INAUDIBLE] At one point [INAUDIBLE]
cheese pizza said we out and
drove into town and got a cheese pizza and
think, wait run in the heat.
How can you eat cheese pizza.
You'd be shocked.
Cheese pizza is really good while you're
running.
No kidding.
[LAUGH]
>> Yeah I worked once at the Western
States 100, one of the aid stations.
And they had the most bizarre foods there.
People would just come by and
crave everything
>> Oh.
>> From, you know, pizza to peanut butter
and jelly sandwiches.
Everything, just wild.
>> Oh, yeah, yeah.
Burritos and actually, my girlfriend is
the inventor of the Ensure smoothie.
So, she used to work at an aid station
and,
basically it's Ensure which is a great
thing for an ultra-runner to be eating,
but mix in with fruit in a blender, and I
can share some of these.
Did a lot of soup, you know, because it's
a good way, it's salty, it's got, sort of,
it negates the sweet that you've been
pounding down the first ten hours, and
obviously it's got a lot of liquid, and
you can get some calories in that way
without throwing up usually.
I was lucky.
I have a fairly cast iron stomach, but a
lot of these people throw up a lot.
And, you know, when you start getting
nauseous, or most upset,
it's just, you know, just get it out,
reset the clock, start eating again.
You know, as long, as long as you're
getting calories in.
You know, that's better than, you know, to
not be too cruddy, but
some people get the runs.
You know, that, if you're not digesting
well.
And that, I've never had that, but that
just sounds miserable.
>> So you said the training was some of
the hardest, or the most uncomfortable.
What, what was the training?
>> Yeah.
So, maybe it's different for
veterans of this race.
But, your first time into this race, you
know?
You may not get, its, it's very.
Unde, ill-defined selection process so if
you get selected which is rare.
I got lucky.
I don't know what it was about my essay.
They want a whole series of essays in
addition to the qualifying standard.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Oh, oh yeah, it's, it, you know, I
probably spent three days on mine.
It's like I spent more time on my essay
for
Badwater than I did on my grad school
application.
Right?
>> [LAUGH]
>> And it, so you get in it and then
you've got one shot at this.
And even if you finish, you might not get
invited back.
So, you really don't want to screw this
up.
And it costs a lot of money and you've
gotta put a lot of training in.
And we all know how to train for a 100
miler.
And 135, while it is longer than 100
miles, is not that significantly longer.
It's the heat of Badwater and
can my, what are my joints going to do
after 135 on the pavement.
Less stress on the ankles from not being
on rough running trails.
More stress from the repetitive unchanging
impact.
So if you have one little tweak, it's
going to get tweaked every single time.
But it's the heat trend is really what
it's about.
How are you going to perform in that kind
of heat,
especially if you live in the San
Francisco Bay area like I do
where it's just, it just doesn't have heat
training.
People take, generally take two approaches
to the heat training.
Well, people try the third.
The third is, there is always the option
of do nothing.
Right?
>> That sounds like a bad idea.
>> Yeah, that generally
>> [LAUGH]
>> People have said,
does not work out very well.
People finish that one.
But they, they don't have a lot of fun.
And fun, in quotes.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, people take two general approaches.
And a lot of this is invariably community.
We share stuff, and some people research,
other people what works for them.
Its also very anecdotal for them.
The two methods are either actively
training or passively training.
Active heat training is you know, your put
on a buddy suit or
a Tyvek suit or a winter coat, hat and
gloves in the middle of the summer, and
you know all your ski gear and you go
running.
Or you get on a treadmill and put a dryer
vent on you.
Or you, you know,
put a treadmill in a sauna or you put a
stationery bike in a sauna.
A lot of people do, you know, the hot
yoga, although that's not very hot, so
I don't know unfortunately how that works,
but, it's not for that level of training.
So, and, and, that is probably, you can
argue that is
the best approach because you're actually
training in that hot temperature.
There's a different school of thought,
which is the one I bought into,
which is, yes, that's probably better for
you adaptation to heat.
If you exercise in the heat,
you better replicate what your body's
going to be going through.
Both physically and mentally.
But, your training will suck.
So remember, you don't just have to
survive in the heat.
You actually have to run hard for five
months.
So, you need to be able to get enough
training in, at a good enough pace, with
enough pounding, and enough repetition, to
be able to run 135 miles irregardlessly.
So, once, with this school of thought is,
separate your heat training from your
regular training.
Train, do your regular running.
The morning or, you know, early evening.
Your heat training is passive training,
afterwards.
What I mean by passive training.
I mean, go to a sauna.
There's a guy that's actually from Napa
who's developed what he
calls his protocol for passive heat
training.
And everyone just seems to follow him.
Let's face it, he's finished Badwater ten
times and
you know, ran it in like 32 hours at age
70 and I think that's crazy.
So, cause, cause I'm mean.
And [LAUGH] well, I'm 44, It's not bad.
I, yes, it's crazy.
And so he has this protocol list
developed, and you start off.
You know, start off easy, it's a three
week protocol.
Go into the sauna, every single day and it
increases in time and
it increases in temperature.
Just keep upping the sauna temperature.
It starts off and you look at it in the
beginning.
Like that's going to be easy.
You know, it's like, 140 Fahrenheit for 15
minutes.
It's, yeah, whatever.
You know, I'm, I'm good in the heat, I
spent time overseas, you know, I'm,
I'm, I've run, you know, in Iraq.
I've, you know, in the middle of the day.
It's, It's maybe 115 there, no problem,
it's, who cares.
I'm good.
It's, it's been a long time since I've
been in Iraq, so, get in the sun, I'm
like, yeah I'll.
Let's do 25 minutes at about 140.
Well, at five minutes, no problem.
Seven minutes it's definitely hot, I'm
starting to sweat, but
clearly I basically haven't saturated, you
know my body's ability to, you know,
I've reached that steady state of trying
to get heat out and keep the core cool.
And around I don't know, nine minutes.
Oh my god I'm going to die.
And I mean 15 minutes and I was, I maybe
crawled out of there at 17 minutes.
And, I joined a gym to get access to a
sauna and I get out and
I just lay down on the bathroom floor of
the men's bathroom.
And even there were a few, like three
people walk by, sir are you okay?
Yeah I'm fine, I was just in the sauna.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> They're like should be call somebody.
Of course this happens every time for the
next month.
>> This is the last question,
so what take home message do you want to
give to our students for watching this.
Maybe you just gave it but.
>> Well I don't know.
I would give.
Well.
Two, two take home messages.
It's going to be lengthy.
But the first one I found very interesting
with the heat and
I'm sure you'll talk about this in the
classroom from a technical standpoint.
Doing the heat training before the race I
noticed that my run,
I was just running faster.
Like just day to day.
Same heart rate.
You know, we're wearing a heart rate
monitor, same effort.
I was just faster, I guess that's the
plausibility of it.
Just for varying, granted the heat turns
awful,
it was just so hard, but time wise, you
know, hour in the day about,
a little bit of laying on the couch
afterwards moaning softly to myself, but.
You know?
The heat training, while miserable,
was fairly short.
And I saw massive improvements in my
running.
Way more than an extra hour of running
would have helped, or
weight training, or really, anything.
So, one is sort of an athletic takeaway,
which is.
I question why more people in any athletic
pursuit do not make
heat training a part of their training.
Because for one, you know, one hour a day,
which takes a lot of time,
but the benefits massively outweigh an
extra hour of
training in whatever your sport is.
The question, of course, then is where is
the point of declining benefits.
And then how often do you have to go,
once you reach that plateau to keep at
that plateau?
Do you only need to go to sauna once a
week?
Twice a week?
Three times a week?
Once a month?
And what does it take to, to prod your
physiological system to get,
to keep that adaptive response I don't
know.
The person who figures that out is going
to figure out the least time method for
optimizing physical performance and a
whole host of sports.
And I think there's serious untapped
potential there.
There's a research project.
So, the second thing.
>> You heard it here first.
>> I'm patenting it.
Silicone Valley.
[LAUGH] So the second thing is, I, I would
say and
I mean, I kind of touched on this in the
beginning.
And it's got nothing to do with running or
whatever it is or
whether you can disagree or.
You know, I think as you're learning in
this course,
your students are learning in this course.
The human body is an amazing machine and
its adaptive process to any number of
environments, except maybe cold, but you
can argue with me.
It's, it's phenomenal how much your body
will change to stimulus, response,
stimulus, response.
Remember the stimulus is the one that
makes you
stronger as the stimulus recovery
response.
I mean, you've got recover to,
you know, go weight train, you're actually
weaker, gotta wait, then you're stronger.
It's that response thing.
So you're learning in this class that,
the human body has a phenomenal amount of
tension.
And, it also works best intellectual,
physically,
when it is stressed within a stress and
response, you know,
as long as that stress isn't exceeding the
the adaptation rate.
I think that people in Western, and people
today in the world,
we just have people who have lost the
ability to set goals that are,
that are hard enough.
To maximize that gap with response.
And I think we're cheating ourselves in
terms of regardless of what it is.
And people say, oh my god, you ran 135
miles.
That's crazy.
Well, is it crazy?
I mean, I, I don't remember what the
number is but
it was only a couple of decades ago, women
weren't allowed to race in
most marathons because they were
physically incapable to run a marathon.
I mean are you freaking kidding me.
This is a, practically well I'm old, but
this is like my lifetime practically.
Women couldn't compete in like Olympic
marathons.
There was no women's Olympic marathon
cause women were too weak.
Well we all know that is ridiculous.
Women can run 135 miles as well as a guy.
Okay.
So clearly society's view of what's normal
it's probably a little to conservative.
And so my take away message would be A:
probably set harder goals for yourself.
Realistic goals.
In terms of, you know,
don't say oh I'm going to run, you know, a
100 miles tomorrow.
You know, you try, but I don't want you to
get hurt but, but, you know, you need to
set harder, I think we can set a lot
harder goals regardless of what it is.
And then the second part of it is that
there is something to be said.
Once you understand what it is that you're
reaching for.
Whether it's in science or whether it's in
humanities or,
or doing good world wide, or on some
physical pursuit.
Set a goal that you don't know you can
actually succeed at you know.
And, and fail.
You might learn something.
>> This is a great place to end, or maybe
succeed.
>> Maybe, don't know yet, you haven't, you
haven't aired it yet.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Absolutely, thanks for having me.
[BLANK_AUDIO]