Unlike cold, heat can severely compromise
exercise performance.
The difference is that in the cold,
the active exercising is counteracting the
cold stress by generating heat.
In contrast, exercise in the heat is
adding to the problem by adding to
the heat stress.
However, not all types of exercise are
impacted equally, or
even at all, for that matter.
Let's take a look.
First, what is the relationship between
exercise intensity and cold temperature?
When you exercise, metabolic heat
production rises.
Some of that rise will be counteracted by
the convective losses as you
move through the water air drain activity.
But for a given person with a given
ability to dissipate heat,
their core temperature will rise in
proportion to the ambient conditions and
the exercise intensity.
To my right is a graph of core temperature
in the same person,
under the same environmental conditions,
at four different constant workloads.
You can see in the lower intensity bouts
core temperature doesn't rise as much and
eventually stabilizes at a higher set
point.
In contrast the higher work intensities
elevate core temperature more and
never quite reach steady state.
Those higher intensity bouts will
eventually lead to temperature induced
fatigue.
So how does elevated core temperature
impact exercise performance?
Well, it depends on what type of
performance you're considering.
If you're just talking about muscle
temperature and
performance, then increasing temperature
is actually good.
Do you remember our discussion about Q10
effects in the cold section?
For every ten degrees centigrade that your
muscle temperature goes up,
the enzyme reactions double in speed.
Therefore, as your muscles warm up, they
work faster.
That is one reason why it is important to
warm up before competition on cold days.
A classic example comes from a study of
more than 70 years ago,
by Asmusen and all.
Who demonstrated that single spreet,
single sprint speed improved by 5% for
every one degree increase in muscle
temperature following either passive or
active warm up.
On the other hand, a core temperature rise
above
38 degrees centigrade begins to impair
performance in a variety of activities.
These include prolonged exercise between
40 and 80% of maximum for
about an hour or longer.
Maximal, or near maximal, activity of
greater than three minutes.
Maximal isometric contraction, and repeat
sprint bouts.
Let's investigate why a rise in core
temperature impacts all of
those latter types of exercise.
First, let's look at VO2 max, your maximal
aerobic capacity,
which is the gold standard for measuring
your cardiovascular fitness.
As core temperature goes up, your body
will try to get rid of
that excess heat by shunting blood to the
periphery in the skin.
The dilation of those additional vessels,
will increase the total volume of the
system causing blood pressure to fall and
oxygen transport to the muscles to
decline.
Blood pressure and
cardiac output will try to compensate, but
won't be able to do it for long.
Think of it as adding an addition hose to
your faucet without increasing the amount
of water coming from the faucet.
Now the same water will have to go through
two hoses, so the pressure and
the amount of water in each hose will
fall.
The increase in system volume, the fallen
blood pressure, and
the decreased heart filling time because
of the increased heart rate,
will all combine to lower the amount of
blood coming back to the heart and
filling the chambers, which is known as
preload.
With less preload,
stroke volume declines, cardiac output
declines and VO2 max declines.
The compromised blood flow to the muscles
can also cause peripheral fatigue that
will impact VO2max, but we'll get to that
in a couple of slides.
As we saw in the previous slide, as core
temperature rises, blood is
shunted to the periphery, causing stroke
volume and muscle blood flow to fall.
This happens during submaximal prolonged
exercise as well.
In addition, the sweating that is surely
happening in the heat will start to
compromise plasma volume.
The fall in plasma volume will further
reduce cardiovascular capacity.
Heart rate will try to compensate for
the fall in stroke volume to keep cardiac
output stable.
Over the course of an exercise bout, heart
rate will drift up more and
more as you relax vessels to the periphery
and continue sweating out plasma volume.
This gradual increase in heart rate is
called cardiovascular drift and
is now illustrated on the figure to my
right.
Athletes who use heart rate as an estimate
of exercise intensity need to
be aware that thresholds should be
adjusted in hot conditions to
accommodate cardiovascular drift.
A workload in the heat can feel more
stressful,
even if it is a lower absolute workload.
At higher workloads in the heat, the risk
of thermal injury increases.
In order to keep blood pressure from
falling too much and
thus not getting adequate blood flow to
the brain, your body may
override the local temperature signals and
prevent excessive vasodilation.
That keeps your blood pressure up, which
is a, this good in the short term, but
it increases the potential for dangerous
heat accumulation.
It's a cardiovascular triage of sorts,
prioritizing what seems most important at
the moment for your brain and body.
So far in this section we have focused on
the cardiovascular challenges of
exercise in the heat.
However there are other elements of
performance that need to be considered as
well.
Namely, peripheral and central fatigue.
Peripheral fatigue means that it is your
muscles that are causing you to
get tired and slow down.
Central fatigue means that it is your
brain telling you to slow down,
maybe as a protective mechanism to spare
your tissues any damage.
Fatigue is complex and thus there are
likely many sources of fatigue that
rise and fall in importance depending on
the individual, the type of exercise and
the environmental conditions.
What follows is a description of a few of
the main players, but
it is not an exhaustive list.
Muscle fatigue likely plays a role when
you're at,
working at your hardest in the heat.
At maximal effort blood flow, oxygen
delivery and
waste removal is compromised in your
working muscles.
Therefore, a greater shift to
non-oxidative metabolism, so
energy is produced without using oxygen,
causes you to use up your short term
energy stores and increase the build up of
waste products in your tissues and blood.
As a result, your muscles don't work as
well and performance suffers.
This happens during normal temperature
exercise to, but
it happens faster, when you're overheated.
In contrast, during moderate intensity
endurance exercise in the heat,
your muscles can compensate for the
decreased blood flow by
increasing the amount of oxygen that you
take out of your blood so
muscle, fatigue seems to be less limiting
during prolonged submaximal exercise.
So then, what does cause fatigue during
more prolonged exercise in the heat?
Well, this is where central fatigue seems
to have an important role.
As body and brain temperature go up,
voluntary muscle activation declines.
40 degrees centigrade is frequently cited
as the critical core temperature, but
it varies, depending on the individual
drive, training status, exercise mode, and
importance of the competition.
In addition, skin temperature seems to be
a critical player in the fatigue equation.
If your skin temperature is high, as was
the case in most of those earlier critical
core temperature experiments, then your
performance will be impaired and
fatigue will occur around 40 degrees
centigrade.
If, on the other hand,
your skin temperature is lower, and core
temperatures can
rise above 40 degrees without a
significant drop off in performance.
Researchers in the Thermal and Mountain
Medicine division of
the US Army Research Institute for
Environmental Medicine.
Phew, that's a mouthful.
[LAUGH] Hypothesized that skin temperature
is actually more important to
performance than core temperature.
Hot skein, skin means more blood needs to
be sent to the skin.
So less blood is available to deliver
oxygen to the muscles,
less blood is available to come back to
the heart, and VO2max decreases.
The fall in VO2max also means that all of
your submaximal workloads would
feel much harder, because they become a
higher percentage of maximum.
Thus, fatigue would occur more rapidly
during submaximal workloads, as well.
Central, peripheral, maximal, submaximal.
How can you really distinguish between
central and peripheral fatigue, anyway?
To help us answer this,
I've put up data from a classic study by
Lars Nybo in the graph to my right.
Two minute maximal voluntary contractions
are measured over time in the same
volunteers when they're core temperatures
were hot, hypothermic and normal, control.
The upper line with the triangles
represents the control group.
The lower line with the squares is the
hypothermic group.
The volunteers were trying as hard as they
could in both conditions.
But you can see that less force was
produced over time when they
were hyperthermic, the lower line.
What is really cool, or hot, about the
study,
is that the investigators overlaid
electrical stimulation at certain points.
Those points are represented by the little
vertical lines and
open symbols above the top line.
So when the muscles were stimulated to
contract from an outside source,
the muscles produced the same maximal
force with and without hyperthermia.
This indicates that muscles themselves
were not impaired, but
the volunteers weren't able to recruit
them fully when hyperthermic.
That clearly points to central fatigue is
the key factor,
at least under those laboratory
conditions.
Ain't science grand?
The full citation for Nybo, the Nybo
studies on
the skin temperature studies mentioned
above, are included in the resources for
this section in case you want to read a
little bit more on the topic.
Given all this information,
when should different types of athletes
prefer to compete?
Well let's look at what we know.
Sprint performance improves with warmer
muscle temperature.
Endurance performance is compromised with
high core temperature.
We are colder in the morning than the
afternoon,
due to natural circadian rhythms.
And ambient temperatures are usually
cooler in the morning, than the afternoon.
What do you think this all means for
when sprinters, versus endurance athletes,
like to compete?
And what's the impact on athletes
competing in sprint events where
they have multiple heats, throughout the
day?
It's not rocket science, right?
Just think about it for a little while.
Sorry if that was a complicated module.
When it comes to humans, exercise
performance and
fatigue, there's usually no easy answer.
Fatigue and athletic performance are
impacted by multiple factors
simultaneously, especially when you have a
systemic challenge like hyperthermia.
The good news is that we now get to move
on to a more concrete module of what
happened to Corey in the hot room.
Answer the Check for Understanding
questions, and I'll see you soon.
Thanks.