Welcome back to Module 5 - Minimizing the
Negatives.
We just spent a couple of modules talking
about how hypothermia negatively impacts
endurance and maximum performance.
It's time to share some ideas on what you
can do to help relieve the heat
related stress and negative impacts.
The most obvious thing that will help you
in the heat is acclimatization.
Your body, the amazing machine that it is,
will quickly adapt to its new environment
to try to make things easier for you.
Complete heat acclimatization takes up to
14 days, but
some of the early adaptations occur within
the first week.
Early in the process, plasma volume will
increase in response to
more plasma proteins and increase sodium
chloride retention in the kidney.
Increase plasma volume means more blood
available to go to the skin,
working muscles and back to the heart.
So heart rate and perceived exertion will
return closer to baseline during exercise.
Exercising in heat will accelerate the
acclimatization process.
The body also adjusts a variety of
parameters relating to
sweat during the acclimatization period.
Sweat rate can increase three times to
above two liters per hour.
You start to sweat more evenly over your
body rather just in your armpits and feet.
You sweat sooner to try and prevent an
initial rise in core temperature.
And you reabsorb more of the electrolytes
in your sweat and
urine to minimize electrolyte losses.
Interestingly, some of these adaptations
can be achieved simply by training,
even in a cool environment.
Things like plasma volume expansion and
increased sweat rates are normal training
outcomes.
However, the adaptations will be greater
and
faster if the training is done in the
heat.
Heat acclimatization adaptations may
disappear after only a few days or
weeks without the heat stress stimulus.
The first adaptations to change back are
those that develop first,
plasma volume and heart rate.
How fast you lose the adaptation depends
on the number of heat exposures per week,
and the intensity and type of training
sessions.
If you've already acclimatized, and you're
looking for
more of an edge, there are some cooling
strategies you can employ.
Remember that you only want to be using
cooling methods,
if you're doing some prolonged exercise
when core, skin or
muscle temperature are at risk of climbing
above optimal levels.
Ice vests, ice packs, mist fans, and cool
air have all been used by atheletes and
have been studied in the lab with mixed
results.
The bottom line is that they can lower
subjective feelings of discomfort but
their positive impact on performance is
still debatable.
Varied study designs and lack of true
performance outcomes,
make recommendations of particular
methodologies, challenging.
Cooling of hands, feet, and especially the
full limbs through a variety of
techniques has been shown to reduce core
heat load during physical activity and
accelerate cooling during hyperthermia.
You saw this when Corey was in the hot
room.
Simply putting his hands into cold water
brought his core temperature down.
The technique capitalizes on the venous
anastomoses,
the heat exchanging vessels that we've
mentioned before.
And other surface vessels as a means to
dump heat out to
the cool surrounding temperatures.
This now, now well researched technique
reminds me of
a time way back when I was 10 years old.
And I went to Farvey Ranch Camp in a very
hot place called Marysville, California.
On a particularly hot day, I was told by
Joy Palmerly,
the owner of the camp, to run my hands
under the drinking fountain to cool off.
It was surprisingly effective, and must be
based on the same principle of bringing
cool blood back to the core, meaning
cooling from the inside out.
Common wisdom meets science.
Joy, you were ahead of your time.
Another extensively studied method of
cooling is
precooling with cold water immersion.
Precooling of both skin an core has been
shown to improve performance.
The fundamental idea is that by lowering
core temperature prior to exercise,
an athlete has a greater capacity for heat
storage, before they fatigue.
That allows a higher self selected work
rate, lower sweat rate,
smaller initial cardiovascular changes and
decreased central fatigue.
If a higher initial work rate is selected,
then eventually core temperature will
catch up.
But more work will have, will, will have
been completed before that time.
The specifics of how precooling is
achieved logistically in the field, and
how it interacts with an athlete's warmup
is not easily resolved.
However scientifically the methodology
seems to have merit in
situations with hypothermia is a critical
factor.
Because of the connection between skin
temperature and performance mentioned in
module three, it's not surprising that
many of these methods result in
cooler skin temperatures, either as a
focus or as a beneficial side
effect can positively impact performance,
at least to a small degree.
If you're going to be training and
competing in the heat, there are some
adjustments you should consider.
Training volume and intensity should be
reduced but some short, high-intensity
bouts should remain in your workout even
early on in the exposure process.
Consider reducing the intensity and
duration of your warm-up to minimize
pre-event heat storage.
Practice your competitive race pace in the
heat to evaluate temperature rises and
sweat race.
Monitor first morning void urine color and
body weight for dehydration status.
Increase your fluid intake both during
training and through out the day.
Select appropriate clothing.
Depending on the environment and event,
loose-fitting, long-sleeve, breathable
fabrics may be better than exposed skin.
For example, during the Badwater Marathon,
which is a grueling race across
Death Valley desert, most runners are at
least covered up on their upper bodies.
The coverage prevents radiant heat gains,
sunburn, and
provides an evaporative cooling layer
close to the skin.
Before we move on to Module 6,
I'd like to say a couple words about drugs
and hypothermia.
Disturbances in dopamine and serotonin in
the brain have been
implicated in central fatigue associated
with hypothermia.
Therefore, drugs that target the
metabolism of those neurotransmitters have
been used to manipulate CNS control of
hypothermia-induced fatigue.
The studies are interesting,
because they give insights into the
underlying mechanisms of fatigue.
The drugs also have shown some limited
success in
improving performance in the heat.
However, because the drugs override the
body's natural protective response to
hypothermia, a person is at far greater
risk of thermal injury.
Therefore, such drugs should be avoided,
in non controlled laboratory settings.
Speaking of risks, that's what's up next,
in Module 6, Risks, Consequences and
Practical Tips.