Hello everyone, welcome to this section on
the physiology of heat.
Most of us have experienced being in the
heat in some form or
another, we may live in a hot environment
or just visit one on occasion.
Being in a warm climate can feel great if
you're on vacation and
can spend a lot of time frolicking in the
cool refreshing water.
But what if you're trying to do physical
work or athletically compete in the heat?
Firemen and hazmat crews sometimes have to
do high-intensity work wearing outfits far
more restrictive in terms of heat flow
than the one you saw Corey in for
the video.
Athletes sometimes compete for
hours on end in environments so hot you
could fry an egg on the pavement.
Fortunately, unlike cold,
our bodies are well equipped to adapt to
reasonable heat loads.
Even so, work and exercise performance can
be severely compromised, and
our health put at risk by prolonged heat
exposure.
Watch the videos in this section to learn
about the challenges, adaptations, and
risks that occur in hot environments.
Here are some questions we will consider
as we go through the material.
Of course we will address the questions we
left you with at the end of
the Corey video.
Why did Corey's heart rate stay elevated
well after exercise?
How did Corey's body cool down if the room
was warmer than his core temperature?
Why did putting his hands in cold water
help lower his core temperature so much?
Also we'll talk about what factors affect
whether your body gets hypothermic or not,
how your body responds acutely to heat,
how heat impacts exercise performance.
How your body compensates during exercise
for the greater heat load.
How you can minimize the negatives
associated with hot
environments through acclimatization,
cooling techniques and training.
And what are the heat related illnesses
and how can you prevent and or treat them.
To my right is the organization of the
modules within this section,
that will help us answer those questions
that we just laid out.
You already got to see Corey get hot in
module one,
and we'll come back to some of those
issues in module four.
But as you can see we will address similar
topics as
we did in the prior cold section.
Okay, let's get started with module two,
acute responses.
If you've already been through the
physiology of cold section,
you've seen a version of this figure.
It illustrates the balance of temperature
in your body.
Here's a very brief reminder.
Core temperature in humans is regulated
around 37 degrees Centigrade or
98.6 Fahrenheit.
Core temperature's a little cooler in the
mornings and
gets higher in the afternoon during
exercise or with a fever.
It can also be impacted by hormones,
menstrual cycle,
illnesses, problems with your thyroid,
ovulation, drugs and many other things.
We talked a lot about heat loss in the
cold section but
now in hot environments, heat gain
obviously becomes more of an issue.
Not only do you have significant heat
produced from metabolism, but
now you have the potential of heat gain
from the surrounding environment.
That gain will be balanced against the
avenues of heat loss,
radiation, conduction, convection and
evaporation.
The four methods of heat transfer,
take on different levels of importance
based on multiple factors such as
ambient temperature, clothing, humidity
and exercise.
For example, in the Corey gets hot video,
we were able to manipulate changes in
his core temperature based on clothing,
exposed skin and hand cooling.
We'll talk more about those in detail when
we get to Corey's data module.
Definitions of the different types of heat
loss are included in the glossary in
case you need a refresher.
This slide is going to get a bit
complicated, but its purpose is to
organize the components we will be
discussing throughout the section.
There are many factors that ultimately
determine whether you
will get hypothermia.
Hypothermia is the elevation of core body
temperature above normal.
Lets talk about the components in the blue
box on my far right.
Heat production lays the foundation of
heat gain.
Your basal metabolic rate in any activity
above that will
generate heat as a by-product of
metabolism.
Remember that you're only about 25%
efficient in your reactions, and
the rest of the energy generated is given
off as heat.
Your body's circadian rhythm also affects
how warm you are.
As I mentioned earlier, core temperature
is usually lower in the morning and
then peaks in the afternoon.
The pattern matches hormonal cycles in
your body, and
can impact peak performances in different
athletic events based on the timing of
the competition throughout the day.
We'll talk more about that in a later
module as well.
Older adults are more at risk for
dying in heatwaves, so it was assumed that
age impaired thermo-regulatory capacity.
However when the effects of chronic
diseases and
sedentary lifestyles are taken into
account,
heat tolerance seems to be only minimally
compromised by age.
However, control of peripheral and central
blood flow is impacted by age.
Also dehydration is more risky in older
individuals, and re-hydration is
harder due to the differences in thirst
sensitivity and renal function.
Men and women do equally well in the heat,
although they get there in different ways.
Women tend to do it through smaller body
sizes and
better efficiency of evaporative cooling.
Whereas men have the advantage of higher
sweat rates and
less subcutaneous fat on average.
As we talked about in the cold section,
body size, surface to volume ratio and
subcutaneous fat, all play a role in the
efficacy of heat loss in the body as well.
All of those factors in the blue box can
then be modulated by the elements in
the light green box that just appeared.
Clearly, the environmental conditions of
temperature, humidity, and
wind are critical.
The combination of heat and
humidity is the heat index, a measure of
how hot it actually feels.
If you throw in wind and
solar radiation, you get a measure of the
external thermal load.
That number is usually calculated using a
wet bulb globe temperature, and
is used by coaches and race organizes,
organizers, excuse me, to determine
the risk associated with athletic training
or competing on a particular day.
We'll talk about all the other cool
modulators [LAUGH] in the green box,
a bit later.
In warm environments, you're body will
actively try to
get rid of excess heat to keep your core
temperature from rising.
It will do this by vaso-dilating skin
vessels to send more heat to the surface
to be released to the environment by
convection, evaporation and radiation.
Under the non-hairy surfaces of your body,
so your face, hands, the soles
of your feet, you have special vessels
called Arteriovenous anastamomoses.
These vessels serve as special shunts
designed as heat radiators in the body.
Under warm conditions, they open up,
allowing enhanced blood flow to the
surface and increased heat dissipation.
Both local signals and the sympathetic
nervous system regulate vasodilation.
Sweating is another important weapon
against hyperthermia.
When the ambient temperature is greater
than your body temperature,
evaporative cooling is the only means of
heat removal from the body.
High humidity compromises the
effectiveness of evaporative cooling, so
hot and humid environments are the most
risky in terms of hyperthermia and
heat illness.
Sweat, made up of mostly water and
some dissolved ions, is released by
eccrine sweat glands under the skin.
The sweat travels up the sweat duct,
through the sweat pore, and
onto the surface of the skin, where it
evaporates.
Heart rate will increase to compensate for
the elevated demands on the circulation.
The heart rate response is exaserbated by
dehydration because there is less blood to
go around and
thus less blood coming back to the heart
causing stroke volume to fall.
Ventilation will increase as well, to
expel heat through evaporative,
evaporation, in the lungs.
But is only a minor path way in humans.
The bodies' cooling mechanisms are
coordinated by the anterior hypothalamus
region of the brain in response to
multiple sensory inputs coming
from the brain and the periphery.
At my right is a typical pattern of heat
loss during rest and
exercise in a reasonably clothed person in
normal ambient conditions.
At rest, with little wind,
radiation is the predominant means of heat
transfer out of the body.
However, during exercise evaporative
cooling takes on the leading role in
heat dissipation.
If the exercise involves movement through
the air or
water, there's also a jump up in
convective cooling.
Although the pattern in the graph, is
reason,
in a reasonable example, it is difficult
to generalize, because so
much of the heat loss balance depends on
the environmental conditions,
personal characteristics, type, and
intensity of exercise.
That's it for the Acute Responses Module.
Please answer the Check for Understanding
questions and move on to Module Three.
Which addresses exercise in the heat and
why it is so dang hard.
Thanks.