Hello everyone.
We've arrived at the last module for this
section on heat.
Risks, Consequences and Practical Tips.
Let's start with dehydration, otherwise
known as hypohydration.
We've referred to it throughout our
discussions, but we haven't yet
talked about it directly.
Dehydration has varied degrees of
severity.
At about 1% of body weight fluid loss,
the osmolarity of the blood increases,
which induces a thirst response.
Fluid losses on the order of 2 to 3% of
body waste,
weight, start to negatively impact
performance.
Then as you can see on the slide beside
me,
things deteriorate more seriously as the
level of dehydration worsens.
Moving through discomfort and lethargy, to
more dangerous levels and
eventually death.
If fluids are available throughout an
event, most athletes are pretty good at
keeping their dehydration levels less than
2% through practice and or thirst.
Not all performance is effected equally by
dehydration.
At a 2 to 3% decrease in body fluids,
single sprints, strengths, or
ballistic movements, or sport skills are
not measurably impacted.
However, certain activities like
sprinting,
may be impacted by offsetting effects,
like decrease in
power countered by a lower body weight
equals the same performance.
On the other hand, aerobic exercise,
repeat sprints, and team sports of
varying types have been shown in studies
to be impaired by moderate dehydration.
The pattern of activities is similar to
those impacted by hypothermia, so
some of the mechanisms likely overlap.
Obviously getting dehydrated is not
optimal,
however the opposite can be worse.
Given the strong emphasis on drink, drink,
drink, certain recreational sports
participants and ultra endurance
athletes are at risk of drinking too much
which can lead to hyponatremia.
Hyponatremia or low sodium causes excess
fluid in the blood to
be drawn into the extracellular spaces
such as the brain.
Excess fluid in the brain can press on the
brain stem, suppress breathing, and
can be fatal.
As more slower marathon runners are taking
to the courses with
ample opportunity to drink water, their
sweat rates may not exceed their intake.
Thus, runners may actually put on water
weight during an event.
Additional effort should be made to point
out the risks in both directions.
There are many guidelines out there for
hydration, but all of them have a common
theme.
Avoid dehydration of more than 2%, and
don't drink so
much that you gain weight in an event.
In addition to the recommendations listed
to my right, other
suggestions include choose a drink that is
cold in temperature and tastes good.
The more palatable it is, the more you
will drink.
Also, if it includes electrolytes, you
will reduce the risk of hyponatremia.
After prolonged exercise, ingest a
carbohydrate and electrolyte solution.
In addition, avoid carbonated drinks, as
they make you feel full and
decrease fluid intake.
Heat cramps.
Heat cramps occur in the large muscles of
the legs, arms, and
abdomen, usually after several hours of
strenuous activity.
They're common in people that have lost a
large volume of salt and
water through exercise.
It can be delayed a few hours after the
event.
Because they often happen in hot
environments, when people have lost lots
of sweat, the causes were originally
thought to be dehydration and a loss of
electrolytes, resulting in an inability to
control contraction and relaxation.
However, more recent research suggests
that as the muscles tire from
excess activity and work, they lose their
ability to
regulate contraction due to altered neural
muscular control.
Although heat cramps can be painful,
they usually don't result in any permanent
damage.
Heat acclimatization and possibly
electrolyte beverages may
decrease the risk of experiencing heat
cramps.
Both of these are prudent, regardless of
whether they reduce heat cramps or not.
If you're experiencing heat cramps, move
to a cool place to rest,
drink electrolytes, and perform gentle
stretches on the affected muscle groups.
Heat cramps are considered the first step
on a continuum of heat illness.
A warning sign of sorts.
The next step on that continuum is heat
exhaustion.
As the slide to my right indicates, with
heat exhaustion,
you may experience profuse sweating, cool
skin, and goose bumps.
Have you ever felt that?
Very hot but suddenly you get the chills.
That's a sign that you're having some
thermoregulatory issues.
You also may have a rapid weak pulse and
low blood pressure as your body tries to
compensate for the excessive vasodilat,
vasodilation to the skin.
Dizziness, disorientation,
lightheadedness, nausea, and
headache are also associated with heat
exhaustion.
This condition should be taken seriously.
The treatment is similar to heat cramps,
but more pressing.
Stop all activity, rest in a cool place,
and drink cool water or sports drink.
If you don't take this seriously, it can
lead to the next stage of heat illness.
Heat stroke.
Heat stroke is a medical emergency and can
kill you.
About half the people with heat stroke
keep sweating, but the other half stop.
Skin will be hot and dry in the latter
group.
Core temperature can get to be higher than
104 degrees fahrenheit with
rapid heart rate, confusion, or
unconsciousness.
Essentially you're at risk of cooking your
organs and your brain.
It is fatal in about 20% of people and
those that survive are predisposed
to heat stroke in the future, partially
because of damaged sweat glands.
If you put all of these illnesses and
symptoms together, it looks something like
this.
Going from upper, your upper left to your
bottom right,
the symptoms get more and more serious.
But they're all a continuum of the same
process of overheating.
Be careful and
interrupt that deterioration before you
get too far along the continuum.
Keep an eye on those you are with as well,
to make sure they are not exhibiting these
symptoms.
We've talked about the initial treatments
and
the context of heat cramps and heat
exhaustion already.
But what about when it gets more serious?
Traditional treatments include lying a
person down and elevating their feet.
That helps return the blood back to the
brain if they're having difficulty coping
with the excessive peripheral vasodilation
and are feeling faint.
Remove excess clothing and put cold
compresses on the face, neck, armpits and
groin, those non hairy surfaces.
A recent unpublished study out of Craig
Keller's lab at Stanford suggests that
the face, which is not as commonly used
for
cold compresses, is actually one of the
effective regions for cooling.
You can also mist someone with a fan to
aid evaporation cooling and
of course, seek medical assistance.
According to the CDC, an average of 675
people
in the United States die of heat-related
complications every year.
That is more than from tornadoes,
hurricanes, floods, lightning, and
any other weather event combined.
The most susceptible are the elderly,
individuals with other illnesses, or
people working or playing sports outside.
It is not an insignificant problem.
Every year, a number of young football
players succumb to heat stroke.
Be careful out there with yourselves, your
parents, and your kids.
Alright, one last topic before we finish
up.
Hypothermia and pregnancy.
This is important because hypothermia puts
your baby at risk for neural tube defects.
What happens is within the six, first six
weeks of pregnancy,
a neural tube birth defect is an opening
in the spinal cord or brain of a baby.
The early spinal cord of the embryo begins
as a flat layer of cells,
which rolls into a tube 28 days after the
baby is conceived.
This process can be impacted by high body
temperature and
many women don't even know that they're
pregnant that early.
This is especially problematic for
female endurance athletes like marathon
runners, who frequently get their core
temperature up to 40 degrees centigrade in
hot environments during competition.
Endurance athletes may have irregular
menstrual cycles,
which makes it harder for them to know
whether they are pregnant.
If you think you might be pregnant, or
trying to get pregnant,
be careful of hot tubs, or hot baths
lasting more than then minutes, and
prolonged, intense exercise that raises
body temperature.
Also if you have a fever,
be sure to seek medical assistance to
manage your symptoms in a safe way.
If you think you've been hyperthermic
during your pregnancy, you should talk
with your physician to see if they
recommend screening tests for your baby.
Congratulations for finishing the
physiology of heat section.
Hey, I've got a joke for you.
What does a bee do when it's hot?
It takes off its yellow jacket [LAUGH].
Stay cool, thanks for participating.