In this module, we're going to take a look
at how Corey fared in the heat.
Did his hometown of Phoenix,
Arizona help him cope with those stressful
heated conditions?
Let's take a look.
First, a friendly reminder of what
questions we left you with at
the end of the Corey Gets Hot video.
How did Corey's body cool down if the room
was warmer than his core temperature?
Why does putting his hands in cold water
help lower his core temperature so much?
And why did Corey's heart rate stay
elevated well after exercise?
To my right, is a graph of Corey's core
temperature data as measured by
the esophageal probe over the course of
the experiment.
There was a rapid rise in core temperature
during the set workload exercise.
Remember that he was in a double-layered
charcoal suit that was semi-impermeable.
The room was 104 degrees Fahrenheit, or 40
degrees centigrade.
Within 20 minutes, his temperature went up
two degrees,
from 37.25 to 39.25 degrees centigrade.
Then he got off the treadmill and there
was an initial fall in temperature as
we put on his additional coverage; gloves
on his hands, baggies on his feet, and
a ski mask.
In that scenario, we were able to clamp
his core temperature,
because there was essentially no way for
him to dissipate his heat.
You can see by the yellow line,
that his temperature remained stable
during that time.
We then uncovered his head, his hands and
feet.
His core temperature began to fall again.
Check out the light blue section of the
line on that graph.
Amazing.
So it seems intuitive that he would not be
able to lose heat when he
was completely covered up.
But what about the first Corey question.
How did he lose heat when he was
unclamped, and
the room was warmer than he was?
Well there's really only one option,
evaporation.
He was cooling the exposed skin areas
through evaporation.
Converting liquid to gas requires the
input of energy.
That energy is drawn from the heat in the
surface of the skin that's
cooling the skin.
And then he put his hands down in the cold
water, and
his temperature began to fall even more
rapidly, as indicated by the purple line.
And the second question.
Why did his temperature fall more rapidly
when he put his hands in the cool water?
By doing that, we provided him with an
external cold sink.
His body was sending hot blood down to his
hands,
where it came in contact with the cool
water, dumped some of the heat, and
brought the cooler blood back to the core.
If the water had been too cold, then it
would have caused localized
vasoconstriction, and the heat exchange
would not have been optimal.
However, when the temperature's in the
right range,
it can serve as an effective heat sink.
It must have felt like such a relief for
poor Corey in that crazy outfit.
What a good sport he is, eh?
[LAUGH]
In this graph, Corey's heart rate data in
orange, is plotted against his
core temperature values in blue during
exercise and recovery.
When he started exercising,
his heart rate went up from just over 90
beats per minute to around 160 initially.
You can see the access scale on your right
of the graph.
It then should have plateaued there for a
while, since it was a set workload.
However, you can see that his core
temperature continued to rise and
his heart rate did as well.
By then end of 20 minutes, his heart rate
was over 190 beats per minute.
Can you think back to why his heart rate
continued to rise?
Cardiovasuclar drift.
As he got hotter,
more blood was shunted to the peripherate
in an unsuccessful attempt to cool him.
So stroke volume was falling, and
heart rate was compensating in order to
keep cardiac output sufficiently high.
After exercise, Corey's heart rate fell as
expected, but rather than
approaching baseline, it remained elevated
around 150 beats per minute.
How come?
He was still hot.
[LAUGH] Have you ever had that experience
where you're just sitting somewhere on
a very hot day and your heart feels like
it's racing?
Your heart rate is elevated to try and
send more blood to the skin for cooling,
and trying to compensate for
the fall in stroke volume that we talked
about earlier.
In Corey's case, post-exercise, he was
also a little bit dehydrated.
Even though the sweat was not evaporating
through his suit,
he was still sweating up a storm, getting
quite wet inside his clothes.
After the whole event, he was down about 1
kilo or 2.2 pounds of water weight.
As you may recall, we also gave Corey a
cognitive function test before,
several times so that he could practice,
and
immediately after exercise during the heat
clamp portion of that study.
The test, called the Tower of Hanoi,
requires problem solving by
moving disks around as fast as possible to
match a given pattern.
Corey showed no decrement in cognitive
function,
even a slight increase in his performance.
The data and the literature are mixed.
But overall, it seems that cognitive
function is well maintained in the heat.
Initially, there is even a slight rise in
performance as people focus their
mental resources on a particular task.
Then there's a middle range of heat
stress,
where people can compensate with increased
focus on the cognitive activities.
Once a decrement does start to occur, it
is exacerbated by the degree of
heat stress, the duration of exposure, and
the complexity of the task.
The relationship between those three
elements are combined in
the graph above my head.
Feel free to pause the video if you'd like
to take a longer look at the graph.
I hope you, now have a better sense of
what was going on with Corey in
the hot room.
Next we'll move on to what things you can
do to improve your experience, and
performance in the heat.
Major practical tips coming your way.
Thank you.