Because Stanford is so into acronyms I've
come up with an acronym for it, SLURP.
So stories are the best vehicle for
learning, understanding, remembering and
persuading.
>> Welcome to our expert interview for
this introductory section.
One of the great things about working at
Stanford is you get to meet and
work with all sorts of interesting people,
like Jonah here.
Jonah Willihnganz has taught literature,
creative writing and
media studies at Stanford since 2002.
He has published fiction, essays and
literary criticism and holds a PhD in
English from Brown University and
an MFA in creative writing from Hollands
University.
He's also the director of the Stanford
Storytelling Project, and
it is in that latter capacity that we are
interviewing him today.
He and I have worked together over the
past couple of
years to promote communication in science
through storytelling.
You may be wondering why we are
interviewing an expert in storytelling for
an environmental physiology class.
Well, as you may recall from the
introductory video,
this class is woven together by story, the
story of where is Corey now?
Corey and I will experience a variety of
environmental stressors together that will
introduce the learning material for the
class.
Hopefully as you get to know us you will
root for
us as we experience these challenges and
not against us.
Either way, though, we thought you might
like to hear why stories are so
important in our lives and
how they can impact our learning and our
communication, even in the sciences.
So it is a pleasure to be here, today with
you, Jonah.
Thank you for agreeing to talk with us
about story telling.
>> My pleasure.
And it's a lot of fun.
>> Good.
So let's start with your work here at
Stanford.
So what is the Stanford story telling
project?
>> The story telling project is an art
program in the Vice Provost's office for
Undergraduate Education.
And what we do is we create a radio show.
We make grants to undergraduates who are
studying oral traditions, or
who want to tell stories that are memoir
oriented, or documentary oriented.
>> Are you doing more than just relaying
this information?
Is it being integrated into teaching?
Why should we care about story telling in
teaching and learning?
This is the first basic question is why is
it that stories are so,
alluring to us and why are they the best
way to communicate with one another?
And the basic answer is that our brains
are conditioned for stories.
And some cognitive linguists and
evolutionary psychologists think that that
conditioning started, hundreds of
thousands of years ago.
Serves a very basic social function.
psychologists, of different stripes think
that it.
Our propensity to learn, and remember, and
understand, and
communicate through stories has to do with
individual needs of
the psyche as well as social
communication.
But anyway you boil it down, the brain
seems to be wired for story.
It seems to want to learn.
Through story, and part of this is because
we don't have just an intellect.
That intellect is married with emotional
responses.
Until maybe 20 years ago people didn't
appreciate how deeply the intellect and
our emotional selves were linked.
And once we begin to understand that
particularly in, in psychology and
in linguistics, and to some extent in
neurobiology, we begin to learn that
if the intellect is always operating in a
charged way, it's always
operating with some emotional valence,
then the way that we receive information,
we process information and we deliver that
information matters a lot.
If it's very abstract and not attached to
anything, we're less likely to learn it,
we're less likely to remember it, we're
less likely to understand it, and
we're a lot less likely to be able to
communicate it back.
>> So do you have any last take home
message for our audience,
whether it be for students or executives
or anyone watching these videos at home.
>> Because Stanford is so into acronyms,
I've come up with an acronym for it.
SLURP.
So, stories are the best vehicle for
learning, understanding, remembering, and
persuading.
So, I think if people can just remember
that when you want to make a case
to somebody else about even something that
is maybe even particularly something
that is complicated, that the best way to
do this, is to deliver it thru a story.
So for example, in the altitude segment,
you have Cory up on the mountain arriving.
And then beginning to experience the
pressure of, or, the stress on the body,
of adapting to the higher altitude and the
the low oxygen,
and, you're going to actually see the
things that happen to the body.
And as you see that, you're going to have
a a visceral,
identification with the experience of a
character, who's going through something,
so that when the information that explains
the causes of that.
Things that may mitigate that appears, as
that information comes in,
it's going to stick to something that's
very concrete.
The last thing that I'll say is, you know,
the research in particularly in
cognitive psychology and neurobiology
about how mirror neurons work, have shown
us that the brain really doesn't make very
much of a meaningful distinction between
stuff that we experience ourselves and
things that we watched experience.
So what that means is when we're watching
Corey, we generally are able to imagine,
interpolate ourselves into his position,
and have those experiences to some extent.
So when critical information then gets
attached to that,
that stays in our brain it stays and
we understand it better than had it just
been presented in the abstract.
From your lips to our students brains,
let's hope that works,
that's what we're going for, thank you so
much, that's a perfect place to end.
>> Great, it's a pleasure.
[BLANK_AUDIO]