It is a privilege to be here today, to
teach this class that combines so
many of my passions.
A love of the outdoors, a love of physical
movement, a love of adventure,
a love of science and teaching, and a love
for the amazing capacity and
resilience of the human body I'm Anne
Friedlander and I along with Corey Dysick
will be your guide in what I hope will be
a new intellectual adventure for you.
I've been teaching a variety of physiology
type classes at Stanford for
more than 15 years now.
This is my first online class.
It's also the first time that I've thrown
myself out of an airplane to
illustrate a point, and
the first time that the class preparation
may rival the fun of actual teaching.
So it is with great excitement, and
a bit of relief, that we finally get this
class underway.
Why should you care about environmental
physiology?
Because it is really about your body in
the world.
Many of you are here because you're
pushing the limits of human performance in
extreme environments.
I've heard from students already that have
climbed Mount Everest,
broken depth records for free diving, and
run ultra-endurance events in
temperatures that most of us would find
uncomfortable while lying by the pool.
If you fall into that category, you will
gain new insights about your performance
and adaptations by learning the underlying
physiology in those environments.
We will also provide you with practical
tips on how to lessen the negative
impact of the environmental stresses.
But in addition to the extremes,
this class is about everyday adventures as
well.
Topics like fatigue in the heat, risk of
hypothermia, and
the effects of aging on strength and
cognitive function, are relevant to people
who may never leave their hometowns.
Depending on where you live and what you
do,
the environmental factors we were
discussing could affect you every day.
And the aging and
psychological stress factors are probably
affecting you right now.
Understanding more about your body, what
makes it tick and
how to make it run more smoothly can be
inspirational and useful on many levels.
This class is structured around the trials
and tribulations of Corey Dysick.
Corey was my teaching assistant for
several years in Exercise Physiology at
Stanford.
Highly dedicated to his students, he
wanted to enhance his teaching by
brining his knowledge of physiology to a
new level of understanding.
We decided the best way for him to do that
was to experience firsthand how his
body responded to a variety of stimuli.
What followed was a series of wild and
crazy, Where's Corey Now, adventures that
we hope will both entertain and teach.
Each week in the six-week class, you will
be exposed to a new topic.
A story video that allows you to
experience the particular environmental
condition with us will lead off each
section.
These initial story videos are designed to
inspire questions rather than
provide answers.
When you see what happens to Corey, we
hope you will want to learn about
the underlying physiology that explains
his experiences.
Other more traditional teaching videos and
learning materials on each topic will then
support the story videos.
Each section concludes with interviews of
experts in the field as well as
discussions with adventures who have coped
with extremes that we are,
that we are talking about.
Everest mountaineers, bad water ultra
distance runners, senior Olympians and
cold weather adventurers, just to name a
few.
Oh, wow, I can hardly wait.
We understand that people are taking this
class for a variety of reasons.
For example, you maybe a physiology
enthusiast You may be preparing for
a trip to high altitude, or you may just
want to see Corey fly a fighter plane.
Therefore, we understand that you may skip
to one particular section or
only watch the story videos.
You're welcome to do so, but we hope that
many of you will dive deeply into
the material and give the full class a
chance.
For those that want even more,
we provide some additional resources at
the end of each section.
This class has learning opportunities for
everyone.
There are more details about the format,
requirements for certificates, and
other logistics, in the, Welcome to Class,
document that follows this introduction.
For now, the bottom line is that we hope
that you will learn a great deal over
the next six weeks, and
that you will enjoy watching the videos as
much as we enjoyed making them.
Have fun, study hard, see you soon.
Thanks.