As you go through this class, one thing to
remember is that sometimes,
students might feel unmotivated or
discouraged during an online course.
Sometimes, this is because they believe
that their ability is more or
less fixed, and can't be changed much.
At other times, people recognize that
abilities and skills can be changed,
with effort And by figuring out what
learning strategies work.
It seems simple, but when you encounter
challenges in this online course, it could
help to notice if you are responding with
the attitude that your ability is fixed,
or the attitude that your skills can
change.
For example,
you can remind yourself that believing
ability is fixed can hold you back.
While believing that abilities are
malleable can motivate you to
put an effort to focus on how you can
effectively learn and solve problems.
One way you can practice this is by
attempting to answer questions even when
you don't know the answers or might get
them wrong.
If you think your ability is fixed, it's
embarrassing to be unsuccessful.
But, if you believe your ability is
changeable, then even when you think you
can't provide right answers, putting in
the effort to brainstorm answers is just
part of the reflection process, and can
prepare you to learn more later.
Taking a course online may be a novel
experience for you.
We believe that if you put in the effort
you will get what you
want out of this course.
And we're excited to see the growth that
you experience along the way.