To go through this class, one thing to
remember is that sometimes,
students might feel unmotivated or
discouraged during an online course.
Sometimes, this is because they believe
their ability is more or
less fixed, and can't be changed much.
At other times, people recognize that
abilities and
skills can be changed with effort, and by
figuring out what learning strategies work
It seems simple, but when you encounter
challenges in this online course,
it could help to notice if you are
responding with the attitude that your
ability is fixed, or the attitude that
your skills can change.
For example, you could remind yourself
that believing ability is fixed can
hold you back, while believing that
abilities are malleable can motivate you
to put in effort to focus on how you can
effectively learn and solve problems.
One way you can practice this is by
attempting to answer questions even when
you don't know the right answers, and
might get them wrong.
If you think your ability is fixed, it's
embarrassing to be unsuccessful.
But if you believe your ability is
changeable, then even when you think you
can't provide right answers, put in the
effort to brainstorm answers as
just part of the reflection process and
can prepare you to learn more later.
Taking a course online may be a novel
experience for
you We believe that if you put in the
effort you will get what you want out of
this course and we're excited to see the
growth that you experience along the way.