Where's Corey now?
Well, Stanford's a very tranquil place,
and so
we've come to the gates of hell to
introduce our next module.
because our next module is on stress.
And we're just back from a time outside of
Las Vegas in the desert to film our
stress module.
And we have a little bit of a surprise for
you in this module because Corey was tired
of being the guinea pig so
I volunteered to be the subject and he's
going to be the professor.
The thing is when I volunteered for
this we were going to jump out of the
stratosphere which
is a 108 story tower attached to this sort
of cable, bungee jump thing.
And that seemed completely doable.
But due to a last minute change in our
plans that we had to make,
we ended up skydiving.
So, I was in a little over my head, but
the good news is,
is that everything worked out.
We got great stress data.
And Corey still hasn't stopped laughing
about it.
So, with that introduction, I'm going to
pass over the microphone to Corey,
Professor Dysek, who is going to take it
from here.
Take it away Corey.
>> Thank you Doctor.
I'm tired of being the guinea pig.
You're jumping.
And you're going to be doing it from
15,000 feet out of a plane.
>> What?
>> So where is the doctor now?
We currently find ourselves just south of
Las Vegas at Skydive Las Vegas,
preparing Dr. Friedlander for her 15,000
foot skydive drop.
The human stress response is the humans'
elegant way of turning
on all of the systems in the body that are
absolutely crucial for either fighting or
fleeing and turning off or
turning down the lower priority body
systems that can wait to use energy later.
As we watch Dr. Friedlander in the next
few moments prepare, we're going to be
appreciating the look of terror that she's
probably going to have on the outside.
>> [LAUGH] Just imagine what's inside
right now.
>> [LAUGH] While simultaneously measuring
physiologically what's going on,
on the inside of her body.
Hopefully painting a picture and creating
a story about her inner physiology.
We're going to be taking a variety of
measurements.
Her heart rate with a Garmin heart rate
monitor.
We're going to be using the SenseWear
armband to collect data
on skin conductance and skin temperature.
And we're going to be collecting blood
specimens to
get information about what's happening to
her stress hormones in the body.
So beyond gaining an understanding about
what's happening inside of her body,
we want to be able to better understand
what that means for
Anne's daily functioning and performance.
So we're going to be doing a series of
performance tests.
A cognitive performance test and a pain
test to give us more information about
how stress manifests itself, how stress
impacts her body?
I'm starting to feel nervous, how are you
feeling?
>> I'm very nervous.
>> The doctor's nervous.
I'm nervous.
Let's see what happens.
[NOISE]
>> Let's go do the test!
>> Woo!
>> Alright.
Any major surgeries, injuries, pins,
plates, screws, rods, neck problems, back
problems, knee problems, anything?
>> No.
>> Not right now.
>> Yeah.
You mean ever in our lives?
>> No.
>> No pins, plates, screws, rods.
>> No, no, no.
Congratulations, and have you been 100%
drug and alcohol free for
the past eight hours.
>> Yes.
>> Yes, yes I am.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Wow, that's dry.
>> What a gift for us to be able
to watch Anne stress out.
[MUSIC]
>> Let's do it.
>> Bye.
[MUSIC]
>> This was a bad idea.
>> [NOISE]
[MUSIC]
>> Standing in a landing field doing
science.
>> Brings her lab and go anywhere.
>> Yep.
Anytime, anywhere.
[MUSIC]
>> Okay, just made it.
Three minutes to spare.
[MUSIC]
>> And, time starts now.
[LAUGH]
>> Oh.
Okay.
When you are ready, flip over the page.
>> Wow.
>> And your minute is up.
>> Cow, Donuts.
I think I remembered that one.
>> Caribou.
>> [LAUGH].
X
>> Bear.
>> All right.
We did it.
We did the test.
We did the jump.
>> We got the data.
We're all going to make sense of it.
[MUSIC]