[SOUND]
>> Where’s Corey now?
Surprise.
We’re on the top of a mountain in
Colorado.
Pikes Peak in Colorodo Springs, 14,000
feet.
And this is a continuation of our high
altitude module.
So we were in Usariem in Natick,
Massachussets for the acute exposure, and
now we've come more than 4,000 feet
higher, up to the top of Pike's Peak, and
we're going to do another max test and see
how his altitude performance is impacted.
And we're also going to have a little bit
of chronic exposure in this module.
So, we're going to stay up here and
see how it feels to live at this elevation
for at least 48 hours.
A lot of the adaptations that occur in the
body in response to altitude take place in
that first 48 hours, because we're in this
incredibly stressful environment and
our body is just screaming out for some
kind of oxygen [CROSSTALK] [LAUGH]
[INAUDIBLE] and it's impacting our brain,
and we can't think of the right words.
And so it's, we're trying to acclimatize
very rapidly here, because the oxygen's so
low in our blood and we want to get it
back up as soon as possible.
How are you feeling about this, Cory?
>> I'm feeling a little bit less nervous
than I was on the car drive up here.
And we're starting to pass a little gas as
through.
>> [LAUGH] Shh, it was a secret.
>> cameraman, I'm feeling a little bit
light headed.
But not much so I,
I'm feeling a little bit more optimistic
about how painful this is going to be.
>> I'm feeling a little delirious, and I'm
supposed to be the altitude person.
So, maybe, kind of funny because I could
just crash and
burn in the next 48 hours, and Corey could
just come out smelling like roses.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Hopefully we'll be able to get all the
footage we need for this episode or
else, well now, we'd be, come up here for
absolutely nothing.
>> Here we are, the moment that we've been
waiting for.
We're up in the Azarian research station
at 14,000 feet for Cory's max text.
And we're here with Chuck and
Katelyn who'll be running the test, just
like they did in the chamber.
And we're expecting some good things out
of our decathlete Cory, but
we're not sure how he's going to hold up
under these low oxygen pressures.
>> Now, what I want you to do is put that
in like a snorkel.
And those clip on.
We want to start you at 3% grade and three
miles an hour.
Rory, right at the moment, your heart
rate's 114.
86 saturation.
Cory, in 15 seconds, we're going to go
four miles an hour.
The grade'll stay the same.
Four miles an hour, 3% grade.
>> Feel it?
You're doing great.
>> The saturation is down to 78%.
[SOUND]
Okay Cory, 10 seconds I'm going to bring
it up to 7% grade.
>> Up you go.
Looking good.
>> Alright Cory.
151 heart rate.
If we can get a an RPE please?
>> 15.
But I'm going to increase the speed.
Get you running.
Six miles an hour, okay?
Run whenever you feel like you need to.
There you go.
Okay.
[NOISE]
Heart rate's up to 169.
Saturation is 73.
>> Hang in there, Cory.
Looking good.
>> Cory, I know you got a long way to go
yet, but
when you feel like you've only got a
minute to go, just put up a finger, okay?
Let us know.
Okay.
Heart rate's 177.
mLs per kg is 35.
Looking good, Cory, keep it going.
>> Great Cory, stay up, stay up on the
treadmill.
>> 189 hot, that's it.
Grab the, grab the rails.
>> Grab the rails.
>> Okay, let's cool him down.
>> You feeling okay?
>> So, is it common for test subjects to
vomit [INAUDIBLE]
>> It happens.
Been known to happen, it's been known to
happen in dramatic fashion,
like the time I was doing
>> [NOISE]
>> [LAUGH]
>> Oh, Jesus.
>> [CROSSTALK]
>> You made about ten hot spots.
>> [LAUGH] I was just going to say, I was
doing a max test, and one of my subjects
threw up into an industrial-sized fan,
which blew it back against the wall.
>> Nice.
>> Into like a,
a police outline on the wall.
Oh, it was nasty.
Yeah, it was a $6,000 hurl, because it
broke the bike,
because the hydrochloric acid got on,
underneath the bike.
>> We just stood right behind you, but you
were, you were shifting your gait.
>> Forward, back, sideways.
>> [LAUGH] You were like a ping pong ball,
just going back and forth.
And at that point, you know.
>> Yeah, I do.
>> Called in to read.
>> We did, we just, I'm just kind of like,
okay six foot one guy falling on me.
>> What I did feel is a real,
like the head the lightheadedness that we
felt when we got out of the car.
>> Yeah.
>> I felt that, just, you know,
steamrolled, just really exacerbate.
>> Part of altitude mountain sickness,
especially when they become hypoxic,
there's that sense, one of euphoria, two,
that you're invincible.
>> Yeah.
>> But you're going off down the deep end
down a very different path.
>> But as many people know It's like, you
know.
because a lot of folks, livin' in the
mountains, and they say, well,
let's just go off on a long hike, let's
go,
let's go climb that 14-er, without really
knowing what it's going to do to them.
By doing these kinds of things, allowing
people to,
to know
>> Yeah.
>> Exactly what to expect.
Already important.
Very important.
[LAUGH]
>> So, Chuck, you have people that look
like they're working pretty hard for you.
>> They're working very hard.
>> Trying to test with this particular
procedure.
>> Well, we, we did this test at sea
level, and
what they're doing right now is, they're
carrying 35 pound packs.
And, they're going to go as fast as they
possibly can for five miles.
I realize now that, they don't look like
they're going very fast.
But remember, we're at 14,000 feet.
Very, very difficult.
When we take folks who are not carrying
packs, from sea level directly up to
14,000, like these folks have done, it's
not unusual to find 50% decrements.
It takes about 50% longer to, to do the
five miles.
So this is exactly what we want to do, to
find what that decrement is, so
that we can use that information and give
it to commanders in the field so
they can better plan, assaults, and, and
so forth.
[SOUND]
>> Little hard to build stuff [INAUDIBLE].
>> [LAUGH]
>> Last night was our first full night on
the peak, and, for me, I think, without a
doubt, it was one of my lowest moments,
if not the lowest moment I've had, during
this entire video series.
We really struggled last night.
We really felt pretty bad.
Pretty big headache, lot of rolling around
in the bed, not much sleep.
Think I got up four times to go to the
bathroom during the middle of the night.
[LAUGH] Which wasn't so funny then but
it's kind of funny now.
[LAUGH] Feeling a little bit better, as
the day goes on.
But, I didn't quite see last night coming.
It was a lot more painful than I thought
it would be.
We've, we've done some things that have
been some, like,
painful in the short term, and I'm used to
that with training and exercise.
But that was, the long stint of 12 hours
of night time sort of low grade misery.
And I don't expect it to get any worse
than that.
>> We had a little bit of a rough what
night last night.
Wasn't sleeping too soundly, had quite a
headache.
We did no climatization while we were
preparing for this trip.
We wanted to sort of see what the acute
effects would be at 14,000 feet.
But I have to say that I'm feeling pretty
good now, because I'm out of the building,
my headache's gone, I've had some food.
So, the good news is that climatization
does happen pretty rapidly,
your body adjusts to all these stresses
that are put upon it.
[SOUND]
>> We've been up here for three days now,
and we'd like to do a [UNKNOWN] and see if
you've changed at all.
I can, I can tell just by looking at you,
you look a lot better.
Not as hypoxic.
You have a little bit more color than you
did last week.
But let's see let's see what your maximal
performance is.
Okay, Cory, I'm going to start you at
three miles an hour.
Okay, just to give you a little bit of a
warm-up, just like we did last time.
Cory, everything's looking great.
Right on schedule.
Saturations are a tad bit higher this
time, and
heart rate seems to be a little bit lower.
So you're, seems to be acclimatizing quite
well.
Okay, if we can get our ratings, please.
Stronger steps this time,
it seems to me, not, not wavering as much
as did the first day.
Okay, Cory.
Next one, Cory, we're going to start
running.
Start running when it feels comfortable.
>> Good Cory.
>> Need another ratings, please.
Saturation is seven, eight, 78.
Speed, we'll say it's six.
We're going to go up to 3%.
We'll stay at six miles an hour, but we're
going to to a 5% grade.
Keep pushing it, Cory.
>> You're doing great, Cory.
>> Looking great.
>> Stay, stay on the treadmill.
>> 'Kay, and now the ratings please.
>> 'Kay.
Hang in there.
Keep pushing.
>> Keep going Cory.
>> Doing great.
>> Saturation is 76.
Stay in the middle, come on Cory.
Gimme some more, gimme some more, c'mon
gimme.
No don't, don't hold him, don't touch him.
Keep it, keep it going, keep it going,
come on.
Keep it going, come on.
That's it, that's it, that's it.
Come on Cory.
Well, Dr. Freelander, I'm
going to let you have his results and,
have you explain it to Cory.
>> I saw the numbers on the screen.
Dang.
I'm surprised.
I really thought I would get better.
>> Self-contained meal.
Everything he needs.
>> [FOREIGN] The heating pouch.
Tear here.
Fancy pouch is going to heat up my meal
for me.
Put a little on both sides.
>> So the heat is on either side of the
food now.
Heat it up.
It gets quite hot.
>> Mm, good.
>> Wow, you are constipated.
Those are hard stools.
>> The moment I got out of the car,
everything changed.
First of all, I immediately had to go the
bathroom.
Apparently, you have to urinate because
you're evacuating the plasma to
get a higher blood cell concentration.
>> Look at your hands.
>> Huh?
>> Look how white your hands are.
>> Are they white?
>> It sounds very hollow in here.
There's an echo going on.
[MUSIC]
Don't run Carlos over now.
>> Oh, my leg's breaking!
[MUSIC]