[SOUND]
Where is Cory now?
Well we've flown all the way across the
country to Cambridge Massachusetts,
where we're on the MIT Campus.
And there are a lot of things that we
could do on the MIT campus.
But we are interested in particular in the
age lab,
because this module is on the effects of
time on physiology.
So, aging.
And they do a lot of different things here
in the age lab,
like this car that we're in, Miss Daisy.
They investigate how older drivers move
throughout the car, and
where they look, and how their response
time is.
They work with corporations, and industry,
and
academics, and students in order to study
the impairments that occur with aging and
to design new products that will help that
process.
But we are interested in particular in
Agnes, Age Gain Now Empathy System.
It's a suit that's going to give this
healthy, young athletic person,
the feeling of aging.
So some of the impairments associated with
aging.
So changes in his manual dexterity.
Changes in his joint flexibility, in his
vision.
And he's going to fatigue more quickly
with the weighted vest.
So he gets to experience what it's like to
age, and
they get into a very interesting process.
And then we're to use that to discuss some
of the things that
happen with the aging process, and how we
can prevent them in certain cases.
So are you ready?
>> Very curious, I can't wait.
>> Good, let's do it.
[MUSIC]
[laugh]
>> Life expectancy is about 30 to 40 years
longer than it was 100 years ago.
But we have yet to invent what we are
going to do to fill that time in.
So this is Agnes.
Age gain now empathy system.
And basically what Agnes is is a tool that
we developed for students and
for companies to work with to give that
ah-ha moment of
what it's like to do the simple things
that we take for granted, getting in and
out of the car, going shopping, opening up
a pill bottle or a box.
So we've got a variety of things that my
colleagues here in
the lab have designed to replicate that,
that tightening of the neck that
happens unfortunately in our 30s and 40s
if we don't stay as sharp, as we once did.
So we've got various straps and harnesses
and
the like to replicate the feeling of
stiffening joints around arthritis.
But this is not destiny.
One of the teachable moments we learned
about Agnus,
was that while we were using it as a tool
to give the approximation of a 75,
80 year old woman behaving badly with
diabetes and osteoarthritis, this is also
a teachable moment that with behaving well
and eating well, exercising, that you
can push off what may be considered the,
the destiny of various co-morbidities.
How well you live tomorrow in your old age
is how well you treat yourself today.
>> Yes.
Step into there and step into there.
I hope these fit you.
[MUSIC]
So the more foam that you have in shoes
the less proprioception you have,
the less feeling that you have of terrain.
So we're using these knee braces.
Do you feel a little bit, oops, there it
went.
Okay.
We put gloves on to simulate the decreased
sensitivity to touch.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And particularly, as we get older, we,
we, we don't hear high-frequency sounds.
>> What?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Quick, you have to call Carlos.
>> Damm technology.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I actually can't remember why I called
you.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I gotta go pee.
Let's go explore the city.
Wonder if there are any cute girls in
Boston.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND] There's nobody in here.
It's a little bit more difficult than
normal.
>> Did you wash your hands?
>> Screw it.
>> [LAUGH]
[LAUGH]
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
I have to move my entire body to,
to see what's going on behind me.
I'm already noticing that I just make
different choices walking out here.
>> Like what?
>> Normally, there's a little median
there.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Normally I do a little hop skip on top
of it and just blow right through it.
I walked all the way around.
The ground is pretty unstable.
You know, I noticed it was a stressor for
me to get across the street in time.
[SOUND]
>> Can you even see the light?
It's not green.
>> I can, I can see the light.
>> Okay.
>> But
these people keep blowing through it.
>> That's because they can get across
faster and
they can jump out of the way of cars.
You can't.
>> I can see
this person over here doing a little
giggle.
[LAUGH] l saw that.
[LAUGH]
>> Makes you feel like you're 75 years
old.
It's an aging suit.
>> I aged 50 years today, my friend.
Hold onto your youth while you have it.
>> Dang crosswalks take forever.
[LAUGH] Where's the button?
>> Is there a button?
>> There's a button.
[NOISE]
>> Oh, time to go.
>> I hit the button.
>> [LAUGH] Oh, it's turned red already.
You're only halfway across.
Keep going.
Come on.
Oh,
it's
red.
>> Already I'm afraid of the traffic.
Hey.
>> It's green.
>> Hey.
Hurry.
>> Let's go.
You had a couple of seconds to spare on
that one.
[MUSIC]
>> This one's a Frank Ghery, right?
>> I actually haven't even noticed them.
I hadn't looked up.
>> You see it?
>> Wow.
That's interesting.
It's pretty hard to see.
There's some funky stuff going on on the
right side of that building.
Right
[MUSIC]
I don't know.
Pretty soon I'll have to wear this suit
for a week.
It's not that I can't do anything.
It's that some things, because they are
such a pain, that I wouldn't want to do.
>> Yeah.
Well, that's why you have to stay active
for your whole life.
So can you imagine exercising?
>> What I imagine is a struggle.
>> Yeah.
well, what do you think?
Should we give it a try?
And see how these impairments impact your
ability to exercise?
Because we know that exercise is so good
for
you in changing the trajectory of aging.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And so,
you know, you may as well start now, start
exercising.
>> So, you think if I do a little
exercise,
I might be able to improve some of these
deficits?
>> Well, let's check it out.
>> Alright, I'm game.
>> We're at the MIT track right now and,
we're going to see if you can run a little
bit.
[MUSIC].
>> Agnes does not have an age, and it's
changed.
Maybe 10 years ago, she would have been
the average 75 year old.
I don't think she's the average 75 year
old now.
I think she may be the average 85 year
old.
>> She is ageless.
She represents impairments.
>> Uh-huh.
>> That we commonly see in older age.
>> Hi.
>> How are you?
>> Good, you're looking great.
>> Thank you.
>> We are back here, in Palo Alto,
California, at the Stanford track.
And I am here with Bill Caspari, who is a
sprinter extraordinaire.
He's 79 years old and it does not look
like he's wearing the Agnes suit.
So when he's done with his workout, we're
going to sit down and
talk about his secrets of healthy aging.
>> See you in a minute.
Okay take care.
>> Bye.
>> What got you into sprinting and what
drives you to continue?
>> I remember the day well because I was
sitting in front of my TV watching
the 1968 Olympics, and I had a cigarette
in one hand and a beer in the other.
And I'm watching all of these outstanding
athletes and I just, I got mad at myself.
And so I put the cigarette out and I
crumpled up the pack and threw them away.
And I told myself okay, you're going to go
down to the track.
I lived by the San Carlos High School
track at the time.
And your going to go down there everyday
for two weeks.
Your going to make yourself run four laps.
And at the end of that two weeks you can
quit.
And I did that, and I never stopped.
And so for the next 37 years or
so I did a lot of trail running and a lot
of road running.
But I always had this love of the sprint.
One of the things that, that I've noticed
as I've gotten older,
is that people seem to think that easier
is better.
And they'll go out and
they'll buy this machine, to do something
that they could do, you know?
I still want to, if I want to dig a ditch
I don't go get a machine.
I'll get out my pick and shovel.
I still cut up my own firewood and I do
that, because I,
I actually enjoy it, it makes me feel
good, you know?
They think, or they'll say, well, you
know, I just turned 65, so I,
you know, I can't do that anymore.
Well, but I know guys that are 80 that are
doing it.
It's, that's the attitude part of it.
I was talking to a lady in an insurance
office and
she was telling me how she'd backed her
car into this pole a couple times.
And she said, because I, I can't turn.
She says it's just hard for me to turn.
Well, I, I know she wasn't close to my
age.
And, so I said to her, I said well, you
know,
every evening I just do this back
twisting.
I said, takes me five to ten seconds,
that's all.
Just a little bit, like that.
And, she kind of looked at me oh, I don't
do that stuff.
And all I could think was keep backing
into the pole.
>> So how old do you feel?
>> [LAUGH]
Oh about 79.
No.
It's again it's like I don't think of it
as old.
We think oh I'm old now because of this or
that and we put a number on it.
My dad was, when he turned 65 he was
designing a power plant in Korea and
they walked up to him on his birthday,
65th, and
said sorry John, we have to take you off
the project, you're too old now.
What do you mean?
Yesterday I wasn't and today I am?
It's that,
it's that whole attitude, I think that's
part of what should change in our culture.
Is that attitude of that old just means
you can't do anything anymore.
>> I think that.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]