[LAUGH]
[SOUND]
>> So at that temperature of water, how
long would it have taken him to drop his
core temperature down to dangerous level?
How long could he have survived in that
tank?
>> Well to 32 degrees.
Yeah it's going to be a linear drop.
>> So it would have been along time?
>> Yeah.
>> I mean it takes a while to get down.
>> When I was in the cold bath I was, I
was not expecting that,
my body was going to be so good at keeping
my core temperature stable.
>> Yeah.
>> [CROSSTALK]
>> You want a towel on your shoulders too?
>> It's like, you know when you're,
I've been really cold before.
Like, I don't know maybe it's because I
know it's a science experiment or
something.
My brain knows that I'm warm, and I'm
okay.
It's observing, like I'm observing cold in
my body, but not actually cold.
>> You look cold.
>> Isn't this, isn't this nuts?
>> So these are the Avacore cooling and
warming devices, and so, they have warm
plates in there, and so they're,
heating the peripheral blood now and
bringing the warm blood back to the core.
So this is one of the things that they
test here in the Heller Lab.
They're heart chambers here that have a
vacuum that draw blood down into his
hands, and then he has his hands resting
on the warm plates.
So the blood's warmed on the plates and
then goes back to his core, so
he's actually being warmed from the inside
out,
which is a more effective way than
traditional methods of rewarming.
>> It can be really helpful for treating
patients who have hypothermia and
warming them up.
I'm really taking advantage of the
knowledge of the body, and
how we have very dense capillary networks
in different regions of the body.
And we are able to either dump a lot of
heat, or extract heat and
in this case primarily through my hands
but also in our face and our feet.
That's where we have these little networks
of
vessels with clamps that open up the
mastamoses that draw blood in or
prevent blood from entering these
capillary networks.
>> Look at how his, dark it has become.
You were talking [INAUDIBLE] before.
>> Yeah, you were.
>> Was that the not before?
>> You were a little bit shaky.
>> Really?
But
it's coming along, it's getting a little
bit better.
>> How would you like a little warm
beverage?
>> Oh I'd love it.
>> Why don't you take that hand out there?
>> I don't know if I can.
>> Oh.
>> [CROSSTALK] [SOUND] Thank you.
>> So we're going to give a little warm
liquid and
you have the esophageal probe and you
want to take the.
>> Oh hot chocolate, thank you.
>> You're welcome.
[LAUGH]
>> This is awesome.
>> Yeah, you'll want to to take
the esophageal probe out.
[NOISE]
>> You became childish.
Like you reminded me of my son when he's
small.
Like you're kind of like, oh, a little
cold, trying to walk.
You're going through all these things that
kids usually do all the time at
normal temperature probably because,
they're learning them.
Like they don't have the muscle control.
>> Right.
>> And even the cognitive deficit is
a little bit like childishness.
It's like oh, making it.
>> Yeah, it's kind of going backward in
time a little bit.
>> Yeah.