[NOISE] Come on, almost there.
[NOISE] Come on.
[CROSSTALK] You got it.
You got it.
You're almost there.
>> Come on, come on, come on.
Come on.
>> Come on, Corey!
>> Where's Corey now?
Well, we're just outside of Boston in
Natick Massachusetts at USARIEM,
the US Army Research Institute of
Environmental Medicine.
And this module's going to be on high
altitude physiology.
When you're at high altitude, you're at
one of the most stressful environments you
can be in, because the oxygen that's
available for your use is greatly reduced.
And so your body goes through a whole
series of
systemic adaptations that tries to
accommodate that low oxygen availability.
And we're here with the altitude chamber,
one of the premiere chambers in the world
where they've done studies for years on
taking people up to high altitude.
>> So what we're going to do today is prep
you for your PhysioFlow.
What the PhysioFlow is going to do is give
us a measure of your cardiac output,
along with some simple measures like heart
rate and stroke volume.
We're going to do three EKG leads, and
three leads that are going to be more for
our cardiac output measure.
>> And they've done studies taking them to
the top of Everest at 29,000 feet.
Now, we're not going to take Cory that
high.
We're only going to go to about 10,000
feet, but
we're going to have him exercise to
maximum.
Both at sea level and at altitude and so
we're going to see how he responds
differently at those two elevations and
how his body tries to compensate for that.
>> Take off your shirt.
So I'm going to glove up for sanitary
reasons.
We don't know what we're going to get into
here.
>> That's an excellent idea.
>> [LAUGH] [LAUGH].
[INAUDIBLE].
>> So Corey's going to have some kind of
fun now.
Because, we're going to be looking at his
maximum exercise capacity.
Both at sea level, and then again, at
10,000 feet in the chamber.
And, we're going to measure a variety of
things.
It'll give us an indication of what's
going on in his body.
So, we're going to have these electrodes
on his chest.
That'll measure heart rate, stroke volume,
and cardiac output; So
how much blood he's pumping from the heart
per minute.
He'll have a little device on his finger,
the pulse oximeter,
that'll measure his oxygen saturation, so
how much oxygen is being delivered to his
tissues during the exercise.
The headgear and mouthpiece he'll be
wearing will feed into a machine that'll
tell us how much oxygen he's using to do
the work, and
then how much air is coming in and out of
his lungs; so his ventilation rate.
We'll get a sense of how much pain he's in
with the RPE scale,
the rate of perceived exertion, so he'll
be pointing to a number there and
then we'll of course get the maximum watts
that he achieves during the test.
After the test, we'll have a sense of how
his brain was impacted by this low O2.
So we'll give him a reaction time test on
an iPhone.
And then finally we'll see if he's feeling
at all sick; so if he has any symptoms of
acute mountain sickness, using the Lake
Louise questionnaire.
But with all those together, we'll have a
good sense of how that lack of O2 and
that reduction of the O2 at 10,000 feet
will impact his exercise performance,
his brain, and how he feels.
[LAUGH]
>> I'm here with my good friends, Steve
Muza and Chuck Fulco.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And so, since they run the show, they're
going to be taking Cory through this test.
So, every two minutes, he's going to pedal
harder and
harder against a greater resistance.
And he's going to go until he can't go any
more.
So, this is going to be his maximum
capacity, maximum aerobic capacity.
So, we are ready to go.
And Cory, are you all set to do the test?
Ready to go.
>> Alright.
>> Let's do it.
>> Periodically, I'm going to hold this
sign up.
This is procedure to.
>> Sorry, got to [CROSSTALK].
[INAUDIBLE]
>> This is it.
I'm going to win that 10,000.
Woo!
>> You want that again?
>> What level are we at now?
>> 2,000 [LAUGH].
Okay, we're at 4,000.
Not even a dent?
>> Not even a dent.
>> Corey, We're at 10,000 feet
>> Yes.
>> And we're going to do a maximal oxygen
consumption test exactly as we did it at
sea level.
>> Okay.
>> And we're going to complete our every
workload, every px like you did last time,
so everything is identical.
So, are you ready for it?
>> Yeah.
All right.
>> Let's do this.
>> Okay, Corey, we'll start [INAUDIBLE]
right at 50 watts.
>> Okay, 50 watts.
>> Okay, we're only now at 100 watts, been
there for
about 20 seconds, and look at this!
Corey's saturation is falling.
His level has dropped down to about 90%
versus
staying stabilized roughly 97, 98% at low
altitude.
>> Isn't physiology grand?
>> That's science right there.
>> What are we going up to?
>> [CROSSTALK] to 150 liters per minute.
>> The important thing is his oxygen in
his blood is still 98%
of his hemoglobin is saturated.
>> [CROSSTALK] [CROSSTALK]
>> Burn.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Alright, Cory, alright, Cory.
Going up to 250.
[CROSSTALK]
>> This is where it's really tough for
you, you're almost there.
[CROSSTALK]
>> 18. [CROSSTALK] >> Come on Cory, 18,
[INAUDIBLE] keep working.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Come on Cory, 18, come on.
>> Come on Cory,
you've gotta keep it going [INAUDIBLE].
[NOISE]
>> Okay, Cory, come on.
>> Keep it going, keep it going.
>> You've gotta finish the stage.
Come on.
>> [NOISE] Push hard, push hard.
>> [NOISE] Come on, come on, come on,
you're almost there.
>> [NOISE] Come on Corey.
You got it.
Push it, push it, push it.
>> Ten minute, at the ten minute mark.
>> Okay, we'll call it.
That's it Cory.
>> Bringing it down, okay.
>> Okay, bringing it down to 160.
>> Keep those legs going.
Nice.
>> Nice!
>> Come on Corey.
>> Bring it to 325.
>> Yeah, 325.
C'mon, push, push, push, push if you can.
[NOISE] I think that's it.
Okay.
Alright.
>> [CROSSTALK]
Heart rate max 194, VO2Max was around 3.7
>> Boy that was a heck of an effort.
>> Yeah, nice job Corey.
>> Alright.
[NOISE] Consider that for the next round.
[LAUGH]
>> Basically 49.5 milliliters of oxygen
consumed per kilogram body weight per
minute was Corey's VO2 Max at sea level.
>> C'mon Corey just finish up the stage.
>> Finish up the stage Corey, c'mon.
>> You got it. You got it. >> Alright keep
it going, come on.
>> Not much time on the stage.
>> Come on, come on, come on.
>> Come on, come on Corey.
Keep those legs going, keep those legs.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Come on keep those revolutions up, come
on.
Keep it going.
>> Come on
Corey.
>> Well in, in, over here they have two
chambers that are identical.
Except one is the tropic chamber.
And one is the arctic chamber.
And if you, if you want to come over here,
it's probably the best way of describing
it.
The tropic chamber's capable of going from
zero to 165 degrees, relative humidity,
from very low to very high.
Winds up to 40 miles an hour.
It can rain up to four inches per, hour.
[SOUND]
>> Oh.
>> We have two, two, six men treadmills.
And the whole time everybody will be
outfitted with you know,
rectal probes, thermistors, sweat
capsules, and so
forth, so that everything is known in real
time.
>> Does it feel like the wind's going up?
>> Yes.
>> [LAUGH]
Crank up the wind.
Can we crank it up?
[LAUGH]
>> Now this is pretty cool.
>> It's kind of cool.
>> Yeah, it's nice.
>> Yes this is, it's unbelieveable.
>> Yeah, I can feel the radiating heat.
>> Feel like I'm on a beach in Hawaii with
the breeze.
>> I feel like I'm about to be abducted by
aliens.
[LAUGH]
>> Parameters that you need,
environmental parameters We can duplicate
it here.
>> It's amazing.
>> And then and also heat and cold as
well.
Guys are all over the world, and we have
to be able to simulate their environment.
>> A lot of toys here.
>> Yeah.
[LAUGH]
>> No wonder you've been doing research
here for how many years?
>> 33 years.
[BLANK_AUDIO]