>> Jester's dead.
I feel the need, the need for speed.
>> Where is Cory now?
Well, we're in Livermore, California,
at the local municipal airport, because
this unit is on variable pressure.
So things like scuba diving, g-forces,
zero gravity.
Now I was all set to do a nice mellow
kickoff for this unit, like scuba diving.
But we had to amp up the excitement, so
we are going to test the effect of
g-forces on our body.
So we've contracted with Air Combat USA to
go up in their fighter planes.
And do some controlled maneuvers to test
the g-forces.
Then the end, we're going to do a little
dog fight.
So, Cory and I will duke it out, up there,
in the skies.
[LAUGH] And rumor has it, we actually get
to fly the plane, so
I'm not exactly sure what that means,
except that everyone should avoid
Livermore airspace while they can.
The military pilots are subjected to these
forces on a regular basis and
they learn to adapt so they can sustain
higher and higher g-forces and
they have compensatory mechanisms, like
g-suits, that pressurize the lower body.
Or they use the g-strain maneuver.
Which is essentially, what we like to
call, the butt-clinch.
And we're going to give that a try while
we're up there.
We're going to tighten up our lower bodies
to try and
keep that blood up in our heads.
We're going to see how this middle aged
woman holds up against this young guy,
that looks like he's straight out of a Top
Gun movie.
And, incidentally, a lot of his family
members are pilots and so
he's had a little bit of practice.
Not, that I'm making excuses or anything.
But, we're psyched to see how it goes.
It's going to be a wild ride up there.
How are you feeling about this?
>> Good.
I'm, I'm happy that we've been practicing
our butt clinches at the office for
the last five days.
So I'm hoping that pays dividends on the
back end.
>> Get our nose down.
Get some good energy.
Get that airplane really humming so we get
right here with lots of speed and
energy because we'd like to go vertical.
We want to both pull up.
And we're looking at the other airplane.
And here's where we see who had the most
energy.
Somebody works their angles a little
better, pulls their Gs a little better
than the other one, and works in behind
them and takes that shot, guns, guns.
You're going to be doing 4g turns.
Since you're going to be four times your,
your body weight, essentially.
The reason we're concerned with it is, as
you pull Gs, the blood in your head
tends to be drawn, wants to flow out of
your head down into your lower body.
We begin to lose peripheral vision.
It closes in.
Strangely we begin to lose color.
So we start to see in black and white.
And our vision ultimately turns into just
a little tube.
We're looking through a soda straw.
Squeeze the muscles in your lower body.
It, it tightens the muscles, constricts
the blood vessels, and
helps stop the blood from flowing down out
of your head.
Another maneuver that we talk about, we
call it the hook maneuver because you,
you breathe against a closed glottis or
throat [SOUND].
And you're tightened up here.
It helps keep the blood pressure and blood
flow up in your head.
[SOUND] We're also doing things that our
bodies aren't used to.
We're turning, we're diving, we're
rolling, we're going up and down, and
our inner ears that give ourselves the
balance is getting all confused.
And it's screaming in there, what are you
doing to me?
Please use the white bag if you're
going to be sick.
If something really catastrophic might
happen.
Dive out of the airplane out into the open
sky [LAUGH].
[MUSIC]
>> Here you go.
>> Perfect, into the blue.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
>> [INAUDIBLE] tower and then report to
[INAUDIBLE] right.
[UNKNOWN]
[SOUND]
>> want to do some Gs?
want to do it?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
We'll do it together.
going to, going to put on about three gs
in a left hand turn, here.
>> Okay.
Just put the nose down.
Now, pull back on the stick, a little bit.
Nice and smooth.
There's two, and there's [CROSSTALK].
>> Woah!
>> Two and a half.
There's three gs.
>> Wow!
>> Back up.
There we go.
>> Woo!
>> There you go.
>> Over the jump.
>> Woo!
Look over the chop this way.
>> Losing the vision here.
>> That's all right, you're back, you'll
get it back here in a second.
You're doing good, huh?
>> Yeah, okay.
>> Of course all you students want me to
get you sick,
that's the first thing they say.
You're not going to get sick Okay, start
pulling back, pulling back.
>> Oh, There we go.
>> Over the top,look out the side.
>> Alright, cool.
Okay.
>> You can keep that [UNKNOWN] helmet
if you like and we'll do our yo-yos.
>> Okay, relax the back pressure, relax
the back pressure, over the top.
Oh yeah!
>> Straight down baby.
>> [NOISE]
>> Back up we're going to do another one.
>> Okay over the top.
>> [NOISE]
>> Over the top, keep pulling, now stop,
stop the pull, roll it.
>> Yeah, oh my god.
>> Now he's going underneath us now roll
right here he is.
Down here.
Roll right.
And a little back sticking; bring that
gunsight right to him, now.
>> Okay, we're going to do a go ballistic
here and just stall it.
>> [NOISE]
>> The next time, bring that nose up and
[INAUDIBLE]
>> I'm actually feeling a little sick.
>> You want this on film or not?
You want that barf bag on film or not?
Just go straight up, and we'll spin it
here.
We're going to spin, okay, just go
straight up, and beyond air speed here,
we'll just start a spin.
Okay?
Here we go.
[NOISE]
>> [NOISE] Okay, here we go.
>> Wahoo
>> We're going to skip the rest of this,
talking to Ralph.
Over here, she actually wants a picture of
it.
>> That okay?
>> Oh yeah, about lost it for a second.
>> You were a good sport about it filling
the bag,
a lot of guys that do this have the ego
that they want to hide it,
they put it in their flight suit, they
don't want anybody to see it.
>> All for the good of the video.
>> Yeah, well we got a lot of it.
>> To two five left six mike echo.
[SOUND] [CROSSTALK] We survived our air
combat
USA experience,
some of us survived better than others.
I kind of lost my lunch a little bit up
there.
I don't usually get motion sickness, so I
don't know what that's about, but
I did experience those g-forces right
before I threw up.
And then, while I was recovering, Corey
was doing some unbelievable maneuvers.
>> Whoa!
That was insane.
That was probably the coolest thing I've
ever done.
My body's feeling all these strange sorts
of things, your visions coming in and out.
Like, ground and
air sort of this fluid concept where, it's
always changing over so.
Now, one thing I didn't expect is when we
got of the plane, I felt the wobbly.
Like, I really felt like I'd been on,
you know
>> Doing this.
>> I don't know, how long has it been?
Five minutes?
>> Yeah.
>> Finally kind of getting,
get my bearings.
>> Yeah, you actually looked more sick
when you got off than when
you were in the plane.
>> And I tell you what, man, it was like,
exactly like you read about.
Pull up, because like the g-forces start
getting stronger and stronger.
I feel the, my vision coming in a little
bit and
then it started to get a little fuzzy and
less color.
And then we pulled really hard and fast
and everything kind of went.
>> Yeah.
I only made it to about three and
a half Gs before I got sick and that was
incredible.
I can't imagine people who go up to seven
or nine Gs.
>> You're in a cockpit like capsule.
Take a drink of water and okay you’re
ready?
No, I’m not ready, I don’t ever want to do
that again, but, of course you go yeah.
>> The Air Force people, who have to,
they have to tolerate nine Gs before they
get in the F16s, it’s unbelievable.
>> It’s not like you go okay there’s 1g,
2gs, you know.
It’s like bang, you’re at 9Gs.
When they set it for nine, and
it's, it's really brutal.
[MUSIC]
>> So, who won the dogfight?
>> He clearly won just about everything.
[LAUGH]
>> Now, hold on, look at my elbow.
[NOISE]
>> Up high, down low.
Ready?
Oh, yeah.
[MUSIC]