Ow.
[LAUGH]
>> Where's Corey now?
Well we've come over to Craig Heller's
lab.
Today we're going to be experiencing
physiologic effect of cold on the body and
so Cory has volunteered to try and drop
his body temperature down so
that we can see what happens in that
process.
We'll have three different measures.
Heart rate will show his response to
shivering.
His heart rate should go up go we have his
core temperature measured by
the esophageal temperature and
we'll have the skin temperature measured
by this probe on his hand.
Non layers, he's taking off layers.
>> Go Corey.
Yes.
Alright
>> I was going to say It actually didn't
feel very cold in here, but
I realize that's ridiculous since I'm in
my ski jacket.
>> It's pretty cold in here.
>> There it is, skin probes.
>> The rector muscles are hard at work.
So you're going to think that I have such
a thick, mad chest hair.
>> That'll keep you warm.
>> This is really working.
The blood has pulled out of my fingers and
my toes.
White hands.
I'm just starting to shiver a little bit.
A couple of minutes ago I was feeling
pretty nervous not really knowing quite
what to expect, what this is going to feel
like.
I don't particularly manage cold well.
Has there been any change in my core
temperature?
>> In fact you're going up because you're
shivering.
You're 36.7 now so it's still crazy you
know.
>> Isn't that partially partially also
because he's vascular constricting
the periphery so he's sending more of the
blood to the core?
Amazing compensitory mechanism.
[LAUGH] Fun in the cold room.
>> Yeah you can't really tell but I have,
I could feel a little bit of difference.
>> Temperature is still going up.
>> Good up, what's the matter with you.
>> You try and mess with this body.
>> [LAUGH] [CROSSTALK] oh, look it just
dropped.
>> Stop talking to us.
>> Well first his heart rate will go up,
and
then heart rate will go down inside, were
not recording that are we?
Ok, so it was in the 80s to start and it's
up to 99 now for his heart, so
he's trying to compensate by increasing
his metabolic rate.
And then we'll eventually get to delirium
and unconsciousness and then death.
Okay, maybe not that far.
[LAUGH] So what's going to happen here is
we're going to accelerate this
process since we all have things to do.
So we're going to put him in the, in the
water bath because water conducts heat
away from the body 20 times faster than.
>> Whoo.
>> Air.
And so we'll put him in there and it'll
get cold faster.
>> Oh man.
Now I see some goosebumps.
>> [SOUND]
>> [LAUGH] Okay.
>> Back down a little bit.
>> Heart rate's up to 105.
>> Turning up the, current there is a
little bit brutal.
That's mean.
Ohh!
>> Going down farther.
Oh, nice little tub.
>> The current's the worst.
>> Yeah it's a bit challenging.
>> Getting goosebumps?
You're turning a little pale.
Your lips aren't blue yet.
That's good.
How, how you?
>> Starting to feel pretty cold.
>> Yeah.
>> But I know my body can last quite a
ways longer.
>> You're not shivering violently yet.
>> Not even close.
>> Yeah.
>> But he doesn't have much fat, so he's
very lean and so
there's not a big insulating layer there.
So.
[NOISE] He's been in there for about a
half an hour now, so
he's not able to compensate quite as much
any more.
He's starting to shiver a little bit more.
And we're not going to keep him in too
much longer.
>> Can I catch this ball?
>> [LAUGH]
>> Try to throw it up, yourself, and catch
it.
All right, just like do it like you're
juggling.
Like can you throw it straight up?
That's pretty good.
>> It's really not much fine motor going
on here.
>> So, we're trying to see if he's still
has some, or
if he's losing his manual dexterity.
So why don't you try and tie my shoe Cory?
Now imagine you're out in the cold trying
to build a shelter.
You have to tie that knot.
Okay.
So we're going to cut your misery and get
you out of the tank.
>> Ugh.
Right here?
>> huh.
>> I don't feel anything.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> And just hit the one on the left or
the.
>> That's the incline.
>> Go about three.
>> Oh wow.
>> Now he's got some shaking going on.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> [LAUGH]
Your legs still function.
>> [CROSSTALK] automatically.
>> Oh, my gosh.
>> There's something that you normally do
with just his type one fibers.
So he's doing gross movement patterns and
he feels very uncordinated.
Those nerves are just not signalling down
those legs very well.
If I focus I can make my entire body stop.
>> Stop jerking?
Not entirely!
>> It's just like a, work really hard for
a [INAUDIBLE] Isn't that amazing?
>> Amazing, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> So Corey's really hurting now.
I think we've tortured him enough, so
we're going to, we're going to take him
out soon.
Let's see if you can catch.
Yeah.
Can you try from one hand to the other?
>> Yeah.
>> Try to do some of the other tricks you
did earlier.
[LAUGH] Let's do a little,
one more shoe tie, and
then we'll get
get you warmed up.
Yay!
Victory!
[LAUGH] What do you think?
>> You deserve a warm blanket for that.
>> Yeah.
>> Are we done?
>> Yeah, we're done.
Let's get him warmed up.
Temperature down to 34.5.
[CROSSTALK] You're getting chills and
[INAUDIBLE].
Your hands are real cold.
>> Your hands are just.
[SOUND]
>> Let's get you out of there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]