We're going to see how his body works to
get rid of that heat even when he stays in
a very hot environment.
And there's some tricks that we're
going to do to try and
manipulate that process that could be
quite interesting.
So are you psyched for this?
>> I'm not nervous at all, I'm a
thermoregulatory machine.
>> So where is Cory now?
Well, here we are back in Craig Heller's
lab, and last time we were here,
we cooled Cory down, so this time, we're
going to heat him up.
Because they both ways here in the Heller
Lab, they stu-, study hypothermia, so
low body temperature, and hyperthermia,
high body temperature.
And so, instead of cooling him down,
we're going to heat him up in the hot room
today.
And we're going to see what happens to his
physical performance on a treadmill, and
then we're going to see how his body works
to get rid of that heat.
Even when he stays in a very hot
environment.
And there's some tricks that we're
going to do,
to try and manipulate that process that
could be quite interesting.
We're going to put you in a military
thermal insulation suit.
So, this is what they use when there are
chemical spills.
And it has some charcoal in it that
absorbs the toxic fumes.
And so that is a partially insulating
suit.
So we're trying to keep that body
temperature in when you're
on the treadmill.
You're not going to be able to conduct, or
irradiate, or
have convection off your skin surfaces
while you're walking on the treadmill.
And then you walk until you get your core
temperature up to 39 degrees, and
then after that, we will clamp your
temperature there
by closing off what surfaces you have left
that are exposed.
So your face, your hands, your feet.
So we'll clamp those off and we'll see how
it feels for
you to maintain that core temperature at
39 degrees.
And then we'll see what happens when we
remove those,
even if you're still in the hot
environment.
We'll be measuring your core temperature,
like last time, with the esophageal probe.
We'll measure your skin temperature with a
skin probe, and
we'll measure your heart rate with the
heart rate monitor.
The three monitors will we able to see how
you're doing physiologically, and
then we'll throw in some cognitive
performance tests that you'll do
before you get hot, when you're hot, and
on the other side.
And we'll see whether that core
temperature change will
impact your cognitive performance and your
coordination on the test.
>> Starting to get a little nervous as I
put all these on.
Not really quite sure what Dr. Freelander
might have in store for me.
>> Here we go.
Into the hot room.
Wow.
So last time we were in here, it was 40
degrees, and now it's 104.
Okay, so go ahead and start the treadmill.
>> So three and a half, hows that?
>> Yeah.
Do we have a core temperature reading?
Feels good, huh?
Just like home.
This is a protocol that they use in this
lab to study the Abacore cooling devices.
So they get military personnel and
students and
a variety of different populations up to
39 degrees and
then they see how they can manipulate the
cooldown process.
There's a little temperature and humidity
marker over there.
22%, 103 degrees.
Whew, toasty.
>> 158.
>> 158, a little cardiovascular drift.
You're spiking at 38,3, you're looking a
little sweaty.
How are you feeling?
>> I'm starting to sweat.
>> Yeah?
>> It's hot.
>> All for the good of science.
>> I love you students.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Does this mean [CROSSTALK].
>> Okay, so you speaked, you,
you peaked up high enough,
>> Right.
>> but we're making sure that it's not
just.
>> Stabilizing [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah,
we're going to get to the mean at 39 and
then
>> Okay.
>> we'll let you get off.
All right. 15 seconds. >> Okay.
>> You can start bringing yourself down.
Get my feet out of the way.
Piece de resistance.
Careful with the esophageal probe.
>> Yeah.
>> Can you make sure it goes down over?
Oh boy.
>> Just another day in the life.
Oh, baby.
>> Okay, so we're going to see if your
temperature will stay, just where it is.
>> We've clamped.
We've clamped the core.
What we're clamping is temperature, so
anytime you lock a physiologic parameter
>> at any certain level, you've clamped
it.
They actually developed this system
because they were trying to
figure out the affect of temperature on
cognitive performance.
But if you take people off a treadmill,
when you get them to the right
temperature, their core temperature falls.
And so there's no way to stabilize that to
see cognitive function, so they lock them
in, and then you can do a whole series of
tests and measure the effect that it had.
So that's, that's where this protocol came
from.
>> It looks like you might be stabilizing.
[CROSSTALK]
>> You are stabilizing, yeah.
>> The sweat's starting to come through
your baklava.
>> My baklava?
>> [LAUGH] Or your, your ski hat.
Elite athletes who run a marathon for
example in the heat can get their
core temperature up to about 40 with no
ill effects.
But that's, often people think that that
is the high limit of physiologic capacity.
So at that point, you start to have
cognitive impairment of performance.
Your body's trying to protect you from
getting your body much higher so
you don't denature your proteins.
So rarely do people get their temperature
above 40 degrees.
And so we didn't want to take him all the
way to the top,
but 39 is still, still up there.
But not uncommon for athletes to get into
that range.
So you've been clamped now at the same
temperature for.
[SOUND]
[LAUGH]
Yikes.
For about 15 minutes.
So now we're going to take off the gear.
So even though the room is hotter than his
core temperature right now,
we'll see whether he can use his
thermoregulatory capacity to
drop his core temperature down.
>> A drop came when he got off the
[INAUDIBLE]
>> It's a very big relief, already.
>> Off the treadmill, uh-huh.
Staring at Corey waiting for something to
happen.
His core temperature while he was on the
treadmill walking, going up, up,
up, up, reached a peak there.
He got off the treadmill, there was an
initial drop, and then we covered him up,
and he sat there and we clamped the
temperature at about 38.8.
Once you stabilized there,
it's all the same temperature, uncovered
his hands, his feet, his face.
Those venous anastomoses that serve as
heat shunts in the body.
But the thing is that in this particular
case, he is in a room that's
probably warmer than his body temperature,
so we are seeing now a fall in
core temperature and it's interesting to
try and figure out how that's happening.
The core temperature is dropping now, even
though it's warmer outside than inside his
body, and now the camera crew is sweating
profusely too.
[LAUGH]
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Okay, so it's been 23 minutes
since he's stopped exercising, and he's
just been sitting here the whole time.
His heart rate is still at 162, so you are
working hard.
A lot of cardiovascular drift there to try
and get rid of all that heat.
Your body's looking for a way out for all
that heat.
Put his hands in cool water,
see if we can get some of that cool blood
back to the core.
Your body is saying, cool me down.
Save my proteins.
Save my brain-power.
And then, adapt for next time so it's not
as painful.
Restore that homeostasis through a whole
series of adaptations.
And you're going down again, so you had
sort of plateaued again.
>> Yeah.
>> When you took off the gloves and
everything, and now you're starting to
fall again.
>> [UNKNOWN]
>> What a good looking curve, so now it's
plummeting.
>> So then, what's more beautiful to you?
A fit in shape 30 year old woman or that
curve?
>> [LAUGH]
data, data, data.
>> Corey's going to do his last cognitive
performance test,
his core temperature's come quite a bit
down; I'm going to see how he does.
Okay, so next thing,
we're going to get your body weight
>> Okay.
>> see how much you lost and then we'll
give you something to drink.
Feels good out here!
>> Corey
>> [LAUGH] He deserves it.
[LAUGH]
>> Thank you.
>> Alright
>> So Corey, now that you have survived
both the cold module and the heat module,
which was harder for you?
>> I suppose they were both,
there was very different, opposite ends of
the spectrum.
I would say the cold module was harder for
me.
I think part of it, maybe I'm just more
mentally accustomed to
heat
>> Mm-hm.
>> and so that wasn't as brutal.
Maybe it had something to do with the
temperature ranges that we chose to hit.
But I would say, I feel like I was
cognitively affected less.
I'm going to recover faster
>> Yeah.
>> after the warm module.
I think, in general,
people's bodies are more used to going up
in temperature than they are down.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So it's very rare that you let your
body get down to 34.5,
which was what we did in the cold module.
Whereas athletes regularly get their
temperature as high as
you did during an exercise.
And so, to
a seasoned athlete like yourself
>> Mm-hm.
>> you're probably more used to that
feeling.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Not usually clamping at that
temperature, but sort of less unusual.
And you have more mechanisms in your body
to dissipate that heat once you
get up there
>> Mm-hm.
>> then you do the other way in cold
direction.