[SOUND] It's kind of a relief to get out
of the cold and into the heat.
>> Yeah, cold is a tough section.
>> Yeah.
But it was a great week because you came
into the class and you started posting
comments and questions.
And that got us all excited.
And you seem to be enjoying the class,
which made us very happy.
So thank you for that.
>> And we've gotta say, we've, we were
both really impressed with how thoughtful
and challenging a lot of your questions
were and it's really rewarding for us to
be, to be able to monitor and participate
in some of the discussion forum threads.
the, there's been a lot of work coming up
to this point to be
able to offer the class.
And this week was just, for both Anne and
I, just really exciting.
We're just super grateful that we have the
opportunity to share this with you,
and that it seems like many of you are
getting something out of it.
>> Yeah.
And we wish we could reply to every
question and every comment, but
unfortunately there are only a couple of
us and so that's a little hard to do.
And so, it'd be great if you guys could
start helping each other out.
There's some questions on there I think
other people could answer and
then we'll try and get in on some of those
longer discussions and
give in our two cents when we get the
opportunity.
>> Mm-hm, I think the best thing about the
discussion forum is really for
you guys to be able to converse with one
another.
And a great way to do that is instead of
making your own separate thread for
each question, just search for previous
threads that are related to the topic
that you are going to be bringing up, to
see if something already exists, and
that way you can start a conversation or
continue a conversation.
Rather than start your own.
>> And it's so great that we have 144
countries represented from around
the world in this class because as you may
have noticed with the posts from
last week, people who live in Canada and
Siberia were expressing their
experiences in the cold and people from,
you know, India were saying, really?
[LAUGH] And so now it's going to shift
because this week we have issues of
heat and so all those people who live in,
in hot climates can help those people out
in the cold who may not have experienced
those same things.
>> Yeah, so this week we're looking
forward to the physiology of heat.
We go back to the Heller Lab and,
unfortunately for me,
it was probably just as challenging.
[LAUGH] As the physiology of cold.
I appreciate the sympathy that some of you
extended to me.
>> Poor Corey.
[LAUGH] Physiology and heat was a little
bit tough, too.
>> Yeah, so keep it up, stay engaged.
Hope you enjoy the heat like you enjoyed
the cold and,
we'll see you on the other side.
>> Oh wait, real quick, Dr. Beth.
What was your favorite thing that happened
this week?
Physiology of cold.
>> Well for me, the favorite thing was
that first post that came through
when we realized there was somebody out
there in the world paying attention.
That was very exciting and then they came
flooding in and so, that was my favorite.
How about you?
>> I want to give a shout out to the
participant who made the Titanic post.
>> because I know you were going to say
that.
>> I was, I absolutely loved the
creativity that went into that post.
Looking at the risks of hypothermia and
how if Rose and Jack had only known.
Then perhaps their romance would still be
alive today.
>> Yeah.
It's Cory's favorite movie.
[LAUGH]
>> That's embarrassing.
No, it's not.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah, it is.
>> Alright, maybe it is.
>> Alright, see you out there.
>> Bye.