[SOUND]
>> Here we are, at our first weekly
check-in.
>> Our first screen-side chat.
>> Screen-side chat, by the warm fire.
This is the cold section, so we're bundled
up after just coming inside.
And the purpose of these check ins is
really just to check in, with all of you.
Talk about what happened last week.
What's going to happen with the next week.
>> Yeah, it's really it's really our
opportunity to,
at the beginning of every section, check
in with you, let you
know where we're headed and give you some
of our reflections on where we've been.
And give you a chance to get to know us a
little bit better.
It's a little bit of a risk because I'm
not sure if you'll like us very much.
>> [LAUGH] Beware.
>> But we figured we'd, we'd give it a
shot.
>> Yeah, and since it's our first week,
we don't have a lot to talk about last
week, but one thing I would like to
emphasize is that right before this weekly
check-in there's a section, with a survey.
And, we would really appreciate if you'd
take the five to ten minutes to
fill it out.
We offer, this class for free.
A lot of resources have gone into it and
one of the things that we hope to get out
of it for us is to learn, about you.
And who's taking the class, and how you
like to learn, and what's effective and
what's not.
So by taking that little bit of time for
us at the beginning and
then at the end, for the follow-up server,
survey, you can really help us.
And you can really help us create the next
generation that's even bigger and
better than the last one.
So please, if you haven't done it already,
go back and do that.
>> And then after you take the survey,
you can join us on our first journey in
the cold.
And, this was our first, our first video.
That's where we started.
Actually, before we even had a plan for
making a class at all.
Sort of our impromptu first video.
It may not be as good as the rest of the
videos, because we didn't knew,
know what we were doing at the time.
But we're still pretty excited about it.
And we think you'll like it.
>> Yeah.
I'm It's the start of the journey so its
still very exciting.
>> Well we'll see you in the cold.
>> Take me to your leader.
[LAUGH]