I'm so stressed.
[NOISE]
This week, we're halfway through
the class, it's so stressful and this next
module is on stress.
>> The physiology of stress.
Something that we are all experts on.
>> Yes, and not only the physiology of
stress.
The physiology.
How to calm yourself down in stressful
situations.
>> And how to make stress work for you
instead of against you when you need it.
>> Yes.
>> But before we go toward stress,
let's take a look backwards at physiology
ageing.
>> Yeah.
So we've got a lot of great comments from
people who have really been
enjoying the ageing.
Section and that's wonderful for us, we
really appreciate it, people have been
talking about how it's changing their life
and they're being motivated to,
to exercise more and be healthier and
that's wonderful.
We did get a couple comments that people
thought we might be making fun of
ageing with our initial story video when
we had Corey in the Agnes suit and
we really apologize if we gave that
impression.
We were trying to make.
It light and
have a positive message about ageing mixed
in with a very serious information.
And as river coachman said, you know,
it's one of the great challenges in life
is to bring balance to all things.
So thank you for that river coachman.
That's very well said.
And thank you for all your other posts as
well.
Mm-hm.
Absolutely.
It's it's always really important to us to
learn to create some space to get some
feedback from you guys.
We can learn how to teach better and
create a better experience.
And also, at the same time we have to that
some of the, the positive feedback and
encouragement has really been
heart-warming for us.
because that's why, really why we're here.
And so we thought we've give a little
shout out to a couple who have been
involved in, in the posts and
actively engaging [UNKNOWN] are just a, a
handful of people who have really engaged.
And really made this experience rich.
For us.
>> There are a lot of you out there.
>> [CROSSTALK] Classmates, but that's just
the short list, because there are,
there are so many of you.
And we're grateful to have you here, we're
excited about it.
>> We're still enjoying the forum so much,
and hearing your discussion points.
>> Mm-hm.
Absolutely.
>> So we're on to stress.
Anything else you want to say about
stress?
>> Physiology of stress, yeah.
>> Big surprise.
>> It is a big surprise, and so regardless
of whatever surprise comes your way,
try not to get too stressed out about it.
And we just want you to know that that
there's going to be some changes,
and know that along with those changes the
content of the material
will continue to be high quality just like
all the previous sections have
been peer-reviewed by multiple experts in
the field.
The physiology of stress is no different.
And we we really hope that the quality of
the material and the way that
its presented will be presented in such a
way that it really could change your life.
>> I hope so.
Stick with it, and see you on the other
side.
>> Ciao.
>> Take care.