Our last section, variable pressure.
Kind of a sad moment.
But also a nice moment.
A moment of accomplishment,
a moment when it's almost time to look
back on all we've done together.
We have all sorts of stuff going on in
this module,
sort of threw a bunch of crazy things in
there.
We flew fighter jets.
Something that I never thought I would do,
ever.
We have diving.
We have free diving.
Scuba, micro-gravity.
You're glasses are totally steaming up.
[LAUGH].
Can you you even see me?
>> Actually, I can't see anything.
>> [LAUGH].
Hello?
How many fingers am I holding up?
>> Got a little nitrogen narcosis going
on.
>> [LAUGH].
That's good.
Good demo.
You going to start acting drunk?
[LAUGH]
>> [SOUND]
>> Corey's also, he has a little bit of a
head cold.
So, he's a little delirious.
So, if he says anything unusual it's
because of that.
How you doing Corey?
>> I'm doing good.
I got nothing.
>> [LAUGH] Nothing.
>> I got nothing.
>> You've been talking at the camera for
six weeks and you've got nothing now?
The last chance.
>> Yeah, well, okay.
Let me tell you.
I've got one last thing to say.
>> [LAUGH] The camera's over there.
This has been a pretty awesome journey
that we've been able to share with you.
And unfortunately, we're, we're rounding
down to the end.
This is our last section.
Which is unbelievable.
It's not our last video, there'll be one
more goodbye video that we'll share with
you guys, but this unbelievable journey is
finally closing in on us, so.
>> Yeah.
So thank you so much for sharing with us
along the way, we are pretty pumped.
Has been some highs and
some lows, and good times and bad times,
>> Yeah.
>> So, So hopefully, you're a little sad
too, and not actually relieved.
[LAUGH] One thing, just like in the very
first check in when I
said please fill out the survey, please
fill out the end of the class survey.
This is your last week in the class.
This really helps us move forward.
It helps us do things better next time.
If you have comments on things that we
should add next time,
topics you're interested in,
things we can do better, Whether you
learned something in the class.
Now that's helpful for us because, you
know,
we'll need to go forward and try to make
more of these and
we need some support to get additional
funding momentum.
So if you think this class was a useful
format and
effective,then we'd love to hear about it.
So thank you for that and please do take
the five or
ten minutes to fill in the survey.
>> Yeah, and your positive testimonials
will justify to Nadine and
other funny sources that what we did was,
was worth it.
>> Not that we're trying to bias you or
anything.
[LAUGH] What you feel that.
We want criticism as well.
But the good stuff is really helpful.
[LAUGH] So enjoy the last module, we've
got a little bit of everything.
We have, you know, we talk to astronauts,
we fly plans, we go underwater.
And hopefully you'll enjoy that very much.
And then, see you on the other side for a
final check in.
>> Yeah, see you on the physiology of
variable pressure.
>> Take care.
Bye.