>> [SOUND] Is my helmet on straight?
>> [LAUGH]
It is.
And I especially like the two tufts of
hair that are sticking out the different
holes.
>> [CROSSTALK] Alfalfa style?
>> Looks good.
Little horns.
>> Well that's embarrassing.
Anyway, transitioning from the physiology
of stress due
to the physiology of altitude.
>> Were you surprised last week, with Cory
giving the lectures?
Wasn't he great?
Did such an amazing job.
So proud of him.
And, you know, I hope it left you with
some tools that you can use in that arena.
He was so good at delivering the stress
unit.
because he's so calming and soothing.
>> You know, well, what a great
opportunity for me, and
I really hope that it was a positive
experience for you.
It's something that, you know, I won't
forget any time soon and
that's really helped me grow take my next
step, and to become a better teacher.
So, thank you all for giving me that
opportunity.
>> And so this week we move back to
altitude, and
[SOUND] I'll be giving the lectures again.
And altitude is one of my favorite topics.
I love being in the mountains, and I've
done research at altitude.
I know a lot of you out there are climbers
and you're excited for this unit.
So, we're going to be talking about all
sort of great things.
We have a couple different stories, videos
for you, both in a chamber and
up on the mountains and, we're going to be
talking about farting, and peeing,
and insomnia.
>> It's not all going to be pretty.
>> [LAUGH]
>> That's for sure.
>> It's all great stuff.
>> Some of them are ugly.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah but it's, it was a great
journey on that one too.
So hopefully you'll learn a lot from this
unit.
And, come out the other side safer and
better mountaineers.
>> Yeah, and unfortunately I've become a
guinea pig again.
[SOUND] And the physiology of altitude is
no walk in the park.
>> [LAUGH] Yeah.
So we'll see you on the other side.
Enjoy.
>> See you soon.