Welcome back to the Physiology of Stress.
We've learned a lot about how stress is
more than simply a, a fleeting feeling.
It grips our physiology in measurable ways
and
can have a big negative impact on our
health if not managed appropriately.
The fact of the matter is, stress is a
major problem in our world.
It's estimated that 60% to 90% of visits
to primary-care doctors are for
stress-related problems, 90%.
It's no exaggeration to say that stress is
an epidemic in our society.
So, it's also not too hard to imagine that
you too could
gain huge benefits by developing a better
relationship with stress.
So what do we do?
Fortunately, there is something we can do
to combat the negative effects of stress.
And we don't have to go very far, to find
it.
Mother nature, in her infinite wisdom, has
pre-programmed each and
every one of us with the capacity to
combat stress.
We call this gift the parasympathetic
nervous system.
So here's a quick glimpse at where we are
headed in the next three videos.
We will start now with an overview of the
parasympathetic nervous system.
The next video, after this one,
will talk about the physiology of the
parasympathetic system and
what vagal tone is and strategies that
exist to increase it.
And lastly, in our last video of the
section,
we're going to present a number of
practical tools developed by scientists to
help you optimize your now new and
improved relationship with stress.
Thus far, we've focused primarily on the
sympathetic branch of
the autonomic nervous system, responsible
for
mobilizing resources necessary for dealing
with stress.
Now we're going to move to the
parasympathetic nervous system.
Often referred to as the rest and digest,
or the tend and befriend system.
In contrast to sympathetic activation,
parasympathetic activation focuses
resources inward in a, in an anabolic, or
a rebuilding effort.
So what we're going to do now is a little
learning, by doing.
You'll have to extend a little bit of
trust as I help lead you
through an exercise in activating the
system that we're learning about.
I'm going to lead you through our first
stress-management tool,
borrowed from the HeartMath Institute.
This tool capitalizes on the knowledge of
the physiology of
the body to alter the internal
environment.
For this reason, versions of this tool are
used widely by successful mental-health
providers, psychologists, and coaches from
all over the world.
So now's a good time to find a
comfortable,
relaxed position in your chair.
And prepare yourself for about a five
minute activity.
Pause the video now for a few minutes to
get yourself ready.
Close the door to your room and office and
remove any distractors that you might have
around you and then feel free to click
play whenever you're ready.
We're going to start by redirecting our
attention,
from our heads to our hearts.
And taking a few deep, breaths.
If you're anything like me or most people
for
that matter, you end up spending a lot
more time up here then down here.
Focusing on our breath helps engage our
vagus nerve and our physiology,
which is why breathing techniques are so
commonly used in relaxation exercises.
I like to help direct my focus towards my
chest by placing my hand on top of
my heart and making little circle motions
or just holding it right there.
Do whatever feels most natural to you as
you let your everyday thoughts slip away,
and turn inward to your heart, and to your
breath.
Close your eyes if you feel comfortable.
As you continue to breathe, as if you were
breathing in and out of your heart.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
To shift our physiology to the next level,
we're going to have to make an emotional
shift.
Keep your eyes closed, and continue your
deep breaths as I speak to you.
Our hearts are incredible machines.
Whether we care to notice the heart or
not, it continues to beat and give us the
gift of life.
For many of us, it will beat more than a
billion times in our lifetime.
Wow.
A billion.
That's incredible.
Lucky for us, we have a lot more to feel
grateful for
in our lives than just our hearts.
I want you to remember a time that you
felt a really positive feeling
of appreciation.
A time when you felt grateful.
Whatever the first memory is that comes to
mind, big or small, it doesn't matter.
I just want you to relive that experience
in your mind.
Who were you with, what were you doing?
What sorts of things did you hear?
And how did you feel?
As you focus on that feeling of
appreciation and
gratitude, I want you to make that image
clear.
The sounds louder and that feeling
stronger.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Stay in your heart, breathing deeply, as
you continue to feel that great feeling.
Life is a pretty mysterious and
beautiful thing, and we have so much to be
grateful for.
Enjoy that state, and enjoy that feeling,
and I'll be waiting for
you in the next video when you're done.