I think what's really cool about your
approach to
stress is it sort of brings a different
light that maybe we
don't hear about often in the common media
which is that some of
your work has looked at some of the
positive things that stress can do for us.
Dr. Firdaus Dhabhar is an Associate
Professor of Psychiatry and a member,
member of The Cancer Institute, Emnuology
Institute, and
neuroscience program at Stanford
University.
He was the first to discover mechanisms by
which short term stress physiology
enhances the body's immune defences during
a fight or flight response.
His research explores the basic mechanisms
of good stress.
As well as the potential to harness the
fight or
flight stress response in a clinical
setting to improve immune responses during
surgery, vaccination, and cancer.
He also investigates mechanisms underlying
chronic or
bad stress that is known to have numerous
deleterious effects on the brain and body.
Professor Dhabhar's research for
developing a more nuanced relationship
with stress.
Turning up good stress, and turning down
bad stress.
He is a highly decorated researcher and
educator with numerous highly cited
scientific publications, as well as
recognition in the press and media.
Yeah.
For those reasons and many others.
It's a great pleasure and an honour to
turn to our expert interview in stress
physiology with Professor Ferdose Dhabhar.
Thank you so much for being here today,
I'm really excited about having you.
>> Thank you it's a pleasure to be here.
>> Awesome.
Well, I think a great place to start would
be at the beginning.
And I was wondering if you could tell us a
little bit about the story of,
how you made a career out of stress.
What was so
interesting to you about stress physiology
that it's taken you to where you are now?
>> Okay.
so, you know, I think it was really a
combination of circumstances and
having good mentors along the way.
Circumstances in the sense that I grew up
an India, where just the sort
of way of life is a very naturally sort of
holistic way of looking at things.
My dad, you know, used to talk to us about
how
aspects of the brain and mind could be
quite important in you know,
affecting performance and affecting, you
know, health.
And so I grew up with that appreciation.
>> It sounds like it started really early.
You got exposure to a lot of different
things and some great mentors.
Especially where you are now.
>> And I think the mentors, yes, is, is,
is, I really you know gratefully believe.
You know, we're key to sort of enabling
you and supporting you, you know,
to do something like this.
>> Mm-hm.
Great mentors are key, Dr. Freelander is a
good mentor for me, so.
>> That's terrific.
>> I can relate.
>> So you know what I'm talking about.
>> Yeah.
>> So that, that leads me into starting to
talk a little bit
more about the work you're doing now.
If you could speak a little bit to why you
think stress has such a bad reputation.
And, and in light of that, what's your
sort of general stance on, on stress?
>> Sure.
So, you know, stress does have a bad
reputation.
And in many ways it's well deserved.
So, you know, a lot of research has shown
that,
chronic stressors are general stressors
that go on for weeks to months to years.
Can have numerous deleterious effects on
both brain and body.
They can contribute to disease, exacerbate
disease, and so
that's one of the primary reasons why
stress has a bad reputation.
The other reason is that people in their
own lives can, you know,
relate to experiences when they have been
under a lot of stress.
And you know, not very nice things have
happened or bad things have happened.
So it's a well-deserved, you know, bad
reputation.
But there are several things that we
sometimes forget about, you know,
when thinking about stress.
And, if you remember those things it sort
of,
gets you to appreciate that stress is not
all bad.
And that it need not necessarily always be
this big, bad pathological entity.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So what are those things?
One is that mother nature gave us the
stress response.
The fight or flight response.
To help us survive.
Not to kill us.
So nature's purpose to the stress response
is to enable survival.
The other is, and this is related to the
first-born, is that it's
generally short term stressor, stressors
that we define as lasting for minutes or
hours in duration, that actually have
these protective effects.
And that's the way, for the most part,
mother inten, mother nature intended the
stress response to play itself out.
'Kay?
And then the third factor is that we all,
all biological organisms have an amazing
amount of resilience.
So, we're built to sort of take.
A considerable amount of stress or a
considerable amount of challenge and
that's the resilience that keeps us going
in even in the face of challenge.
But that it can be, you know, broken down.
And so the, the, the message would be that
yes,
you know stress has a bad reputation and
that's well deserved.
But, it's only one side of the equation,
there is a very important other side of
the equation, the other half of the
equation, if I may.
Where actually, stress can have survivable
promoting beneficial effects.
And you also want to keep in mind, there's
resilience.
So there are mechanisms to sort of,
keep going, even as you are dealing with a
larger and larger amount of stress.
But it's better not to, not to push it too
far because the system can break down.
>> Right.
So, so there's that,
there's this other side of stress that
gets less attention, this good side.
And some of your research, as it relates
to the immune system,
has touched on maybe what some of these
positive, these, this good sty,
side that might be when it comes to stress
physiology.
So.
What, what would you say are some of the,
the takeaway points, the central
discoveries of your work in that arena?
>> Sure.
So on the good side of stress you know,
there are sort of several central points
that we found.
The first is that we found that during a
short-term stress response,
again you'll specifically define it as
being minutes to hours in duration.
Just always think, fight or flight in
nature.
It doesn't go on and on forever.
I mean, it, it goes on for a short period
of time, and then things come to an end.
During that response, one of the first
things we found is that
there's a large scale redistribution of
the bodies soldiers, or
immune cells, that goes on during this
fight or flight response.
So early during the beginning of the
stress response, and
by early I specifically mean within a few
minutes,
say five minutes to about 15 minutes of
the beginning of a stress response.
You actually have a redistribution of the
body's soldiers, or
immune cells from their barracks in the
body into the boulevards of the body.
So the barracks are organs like the
spleen, during, you know,
in which many, many immune cells reside.
And the boulevards are sort of a poetic
way of saying, blood vessels.
So there's a large scale redistribution,
beginning of a stress response,
soldiers rush out of their barracks and
enter the boulevards because they have to
go somewhere.
And this registers as an increase in
immune cell numbers in the blood,
early during a stress response.
If you just start out, for example, with
100 units.
Just a general units of, of blood cells at
baseline under resting conditions,
you'll end up with 140 or 150 soon after
the beginning of stress.
But it doesn't stop there.
What happens then is that those cell
numbers slowly begin to come down.
They go back to baseline.
And then they actually start going below
baseline.
So about 20 minutes on out, as the stress
response continues, you know see
a decrease in immune cell numbers in the
blood stream, or the boulevards.
And what that decrease represents is a
redistribution, so the, the,
the soldiers are leaving the boulevards
and
are entering potential battle fields in
the body.
The skin is a very important one.
So, this is summarizing, you know, many
years worth of work.
But this is what we found.
So, there's a redistribution.
Immune cells leave the blood stream, I
mean leave the barracks or
organs like the spleen, enter the
bloodstream, and
then take up positions in potential
battlefields.
So what's going on is that the short term,
or fight or
flight stress response is preparing the
immune system to deal with challenge,
even before any wounding or infection has
taken place.
And so, you know, someone might ask, but
now wait a minute.
Now, if this system is being prepared for
the lion to attack the gazelle, and
wound the gazelle, how do the immune cells
of the soldiers know
in advance where the lion is going to
attack.
And the point is that the immune cells do
not know a priority,
do not know in advance where the attack
will be.
They're basically fanning out to all
potential battle stations.
If something happens, the acute stress
response has done two important things.
It's made more cell available to fight the
fight,
and it's also enhanced their ability to
fight.
So it increases their effectiveness.
Is there, if there is indeed a battle.
So the, the, the battle vigor is greater.
If there's no, if there's no wounding or
antigen entry that takes place,
then within about a few hours everything
just comes back to normal.
So that's, those are sort of the two im,
im,
important things that, that we discovered.
The next sort of aspect of this is that
what we've also begun to show, both in,
in, in our lab as well as other people
independently building upon our work and
replicating it, is that not only is this
going to be really nice interesting
system to, to study but that there is
potential for tapping it clinically.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So.
>> Going from the basic lab studies, we
and
others have been able to show that if you
couple a short term
stress response in a clinically relevant
manner to a clinically relevant outcome.
Such as recovering from a wound healing
after surgery or
amounting a vaccination response following
an immunization.
Coupling the short-term stress response
and adaptive short-term stress
response with those clinical outcomes
enhances those clinical outcomes,
which is you know, likely due to enhancing
immunity in those times.
And then the last major aspect of the work
shows that chronic stress,
that long-term stress, stress that lasts
for months to
years that we talked about earlier seems
to put a damper on all of this.
So we've also found that if you increase
the chronic stress burden
then the ability of the organism and
perhaps even the patient
to mount the good short term [INAUDIBLE]
stress responses dampen.
And we're still trying to understand
exactly why that might be the case.
>> So this work is really exciting and I
think really interesting and I think
about applying it to my experience getting
sick let's say after studying for an exam.
So, what might be going on where, you
know, I'm stressed out for, for
a few days getting ready for a test, after
which I,
I experience a more likelihood of getting
a cold or getting sick.
Which is sort of my experience.
>> How often have you really had that?
I've probably had it a couple of times in
life.
So maybe it's not enough times to be a
pattern.
>> We need to understand this phenomenon
because people do experience it.
But one thing to keep in mind, is that we
may be giving it a greater saliance.
So maybe remember the times this happened
more,
than the many many times it didn't happen.
The street-bound effect is there, because
many people sort of report it and
remember it.
The key is to keep in mind that it may not
be as frequent as our memories in fact,
make it.
So if you really think back, if you think
back to all the exams you had,
the times you felt sick after the exam,
there's likely to be a minority of times,
that you did, right?
But still, that just puts it in
perspective, that it still happens and
then figuring out what might be going on,
you know, in terms of how it happens.
It's still, you know, something that we
need to work on.
>> Mm-hm.
This is all exciting research.
Tell us a little bit more about what these
future, what the current or
future clinical applications might be.
>> Sure.
You know, we're very, very keenly
interested in taking as much
of our work as we, you know, reasonably
can from the lab to, to the clinic.
Okay, to, to sort of apply it clinically.
And there are several sort of avenues that
are under investigation.
So one is that could we, by understanding
how this fight or
flight stress response when it's mounted
the right way.
Enables or enhances post surgical healing.
By understanding that, could we harness
this response during different kinds of
surgery to, you know, maximize healing and
recovery after surgery?
One of our studies on surgery and
humans showed that if you take a, take a
number of patients undergoing surgery.
There is a group of them that actually
mounts a very good a priori, so
previously defined adaptive stress
response during surgery,
in terms of this redistribution profile of
immune cells that we talked about earlier.
Those patients who mount that response
generated by the stress of undergoing
surgery, the stress of surgery itself,
actually recover much, much better.
And show much higher recovery.
Much, better maximal recovery, compared to
patients who for
some reason, don't mount that good stress
response during surgery.
So in this case, the clinical procedure
itself is the stressor.
Some people mount a good stress response
during that clinical procedure,
in this case it's surgery.
And they recover really well.
Some people, for whatever reason,
don't mount a good stress response during
surgery, and they don't recover as well.
So based on that study, some of our
clinical applications would be,
could we use the ability or not to mount a
beneficial stress response during
surgery as a predictor of how well someone
would do?
Could we, by some chance create the good
stress response.
Create a beneficial stress response during
surgery, for
a patient who's not mounting a beneficial
stress response.
And as a result, give them the advantage
that mother nature has,
has set the system up to give us.
And also, could we understand better, and
this would enable the other, other two,
you know, outcomes.
Could we understand better why some people
are not mounting their adaptive fight or
flight stress response during a medical
procedure like surgery.
Because if we understand what's broken, in
the context of understanding what's
working the right way, you might be able
to fill in the blanks.
And, you know, repair things.
So that's one, you know, example.
The other is to, to couple short-term
fight or
flight stress responses with vaccination.
And use Mother Nature's immune boosting
mechanism to actually boost vaccines.
And so for example, you know one way to do
it,
would be to induce a short bout of
exercise before vaccinating someone.
And based on my work and in thinking about
this,
when my kids asked me to run after them if
I take them to the pediatrician for
thier shots I happily do that in the
little playground, you know?
Because, I, I don't think it would hurt.
And it might only help them if their fight
or flight response.
>> It, it might get a lot better for your.
>> Yes, if their fight or flight response
is enhanced.
And I also, you know, film every, every,
every, almost every shot that they
get from multiple angles because I then
use that whilst teaching,
to illustrate how, [LAUGH] Instantaneously
stress responses and
immune activating events are coupled in
nature.
So a baby getting a vaccination is like a
perfect illustration of what happens in
nature again, again, and again.
So typically when your immune systems
activated through wounding or
antigen entry.
You feel the pain and it generates an
instantaneous stress response.
Sometimes your stress response comes
first, and
your immune response follows soon after.
Oftentimes your immune response comes
first, and
your stress response follows, so that
coupling.
So anyway, but those are the ways in which
we want to try to,
sincerely try to harness the basic
research on stress, stress physiology and
how it relates to immune function.
But to harness it directly in a clinical
setting.
And other examples would be, these are
more complicated examples, the two I
gave you for surgery and vaccination have
been translated to, to humans.
The third one is still pre-clinical,
where they're trying to see whether
pulsing the system with these
short term stress responses during the
development of a cancer.
Could actually enhance anti-tumor
immunity.
>> That's fascinating.
>> So these are the ways in which, you
know,
we're sort of grappling with clinical
applications.
>> That's fascinating and one of the
things you said previously is striking me.
So do you have any leads on what might be
broken you say in
the system where patients aren't mounting
this appropriate stress response?
>> This is like still sort of preliminary
you know, work in progress.
One factor appears to be the degree of
chronic or
bad stress that the patient comes into the
surgery with.
Okay and again we still have some work to
do and
we still have to sort of understand this
better but it seems if you put
together the pre-clinical and the clinical
studies together It seems like the greater
the amount of chronic or bad stress that
an individual experiences, the lower their
ability to mount good fight or flight
stress responses when they need them.
Okay?
>> So that gives us an overall,
mechanistically, we still need a better
angle to see what's going on So
one of the things that I very much want to
do is see whether in
somebody who's not mounting adaptive fight
or flight immune [INAUDIBLE] response,
you could recreate it by sequentially
administering the hormones that mimics.
What would happen during a fight or flight
stress response?
Again, it's easier said than done.
Because we have to understand, we still
have to figure out and see whether that or
not would be sufficient to create that
response.
Or whether there are other elements of the
response that need to be fixed.
All right?
But that's how also, we hope to do an
intervention, where in some cases you may.
The, in some cases, you might be able to
bypass the psychological aspects of
the stressor, and recreate it
pharmacologically.
>> And as a doctor, just go straight in
and turn it on for them.
>> Yeah.
I always believe that the whole package is
the most effective.
But I also believe that if they're
instances in which you could
biochemically replace the whole package.
And if that's the best that's available,
it's still worth pursuing.
And so we, you're really to, you know,
sort of work that out.
>> That seems kind of funny and ironic,
at least, that there's this potential to
harness stress to do good for us.
But because of stress's bad reputation,
we're, in some ways,
we're having a hard time pursuing it.
>> Yes.
I mean, you, you, you said it really well.
Stresses bad reputation has made my life
quite difficult at times,
and actually quite stressful at times.
>> Yeah.
The irony.
>> The irony all the way through.
>> But it's changing and hopefully.
You know, we'll get better.
>> Right.
>> And, and remember that the bad
reputation is well deserved.
Mm-hm.
You know, that also makes it hard.
You know, so that there is a dogma, and
the dogma is that stress is bad, and the,
the problem is that it's not always an
entirely bad, and
that sort of aspect is missed but, but
there's a reason why.
You know, that stress has a bad reputation
because science has, you know,
validated the bad effects of stress.
People can feel them, but at the,
the, again, like I said earlier, there's
the entire other half of equation,
which is actually the reason why mother
nature gave us the response.
That will hopefully, you know, be given
it's sort of fair share of attention.
So your, your suggesting that there's some
good things about stress and
there's some bad things.
So how can I, or people who are watching
in their every day lives sort of use this
model about stress is sometimes good
stress is sometimes bad to live better.
So, so you know what, what we've been
doing is Explaining stress,
and studying stress as a spectrum of
possibilities.
Okay?
So at one end of the spectrum, so
to your left, okay, so to my right, if
you're looking at me.
You have your short-term, acute, fight or
flight stress responses.
This is your good stress.
Okay, at the other end of the stress
spectrum you have prolonged chronic long
term stress responses.
That is the well known bad stress.
Again we define the bad stress as
stressors that result in changes in
stress related factors that are prolonged.
So weeks, to months, to years.
Good stress is where the change is pumped
in, so minutes to hours in duration.
And then between these types of stressors,
you have this zone that I call the zone of
low or
no stress, or the green zone, that's kind
of your resting equilibrium, okay?
What you want for good health, and
science seems to be pointing to this from
different directions,
is that what we want for good health is to
minimize the bad stress.
Maximize the green zone, of sort of lower,
no stress.
Because that's the zone you do a lot of
rebuilding, rejuvenation.
Then you want to optimize that fight or
flight stress response, mounting it only
when you really need to.
And making sure you turn it off as soon as
possible.
And all of these things are easier said
than done.
So one has to recognize that.
And that's actually a very important point
when one is dealing with, you know,
stress or sleep problems or anything in
one's life, is to say, you know,
sometimes you'll succeed at handling it
well.
Sometimes you won't.
But the key is not to let stress become a
stressor and
not to become stressed about stress.
You know, for example.
So then how do you get to that, to, to, to
that better side of the stress spectrum,
where you basically want to stay in the
green zone as far as possible and
optimize those fight-or-flight stress
responses.
So there seem to be, and again, this is,
you know, some of this is hypothesis,
some of this is, you know, trying to
synthesize, you know,
what is known, and all of it is a work in
progress, okay?
But there are different ways in which you
can stay within that healthy side of
the stress spectrum.
We do believe.
So there are sort of principles, sort of
lifestyles type of ways of which sleep,
nutrition and exercise, perhaps in that
order.
Sorry, exercise is third.
Okay, perhaps in that order.
I'm kidding about that order.
But sleep, nutrition, and exercise are
major factors.
So you have a reasonable amount of sleep,
that doesn't mean you have to pull a few
all nighters.
You know you're not going to be keeling
over or anything like that.
But by and large, you have a healthy
amount of sleep.
You sort of, eat in moderation.
Good stuff, and then sort of every once in
a while and
you have a giant chocolate sundae.
And you exercise in moderation, for most
people, who are not athletes.
It could be just, you know Taking the
stairs all, as much as you can, or,
like, you know, walking as much as you can
every day.
That kind, kind of exercise.
Then there are aspects of,
of, you know, sort of leading ones life
that also sort of affect this equation.
And, so there are issues like, you know,
having, having certain perspective.
That breeds genuine gratitude for, for
things that are you know worth being
genuinely grateful for.
Hopefully, you know,
people, most people are going to have some
of those things in their lives.
Genuinely sort of remembering that helps
you deal with the tough stuff.
The stuff that you did have or didn't go
well, so if you can really have
an overall evaluative coping perspective,
this is actually, a do have.
This actually has to be genuine, because
if it's not coming completely from within,
it might not be as beneficial.
also, you know, having a compassionate
sort of lifestyle, a,
a compassionate attitude both towards
others as well as yourself.
I think you know plays a big role in
keeping you towards the good
side of the stress spectrum.
So I think the Dali Lama you know,
is said to have said that if you want
others to be happy practice compassion.
If you want to be happy, practice
compassion.
So there are those aspects.
Then there are individual specific things
that one can do and
again what I'm talking about is what we
believe are avenues that could contribute
to helping an individual stay within the
good side of their stress factor.
So the more individual avenues are things
like whatever works for you.
And those are going to be different
strokes for different folks.
So for some people it could be exercise,
running, over and
above the sort of normal lifestyle
exercise,
it could be actually directed exercise,
going for a jog, running on a treadmill.
It could be meditation for some, yoga for
some, levitation some, you know if people
are so inclined, different things right?
It could be, you know.
photography, art, music, whatever, and the
key then is to find what resonates with
yourself, what really helps, you know,
calm you down, and then practice that.
It doesn't matter.
It could be fishing, you know?
It doesn't have to be running.
It doesn't have to be meditation.
It doesn't have to be the contemplative,
you know, practices.
Bring this whole equation together, and
if one can apply it in one's life, as much
as possible again.
You know, recognizing that these things
are easier said than done,
recognizing that you might not be able to
strike the perfect balance all the time.
But if you maximize the chances and the
time for
when you can strike that balance, it could
be very useful that's what we feel.
So, as we're closing and wrapping up
today, Professor Dhabhar.
I'm thinking about sort of,
what might be the most excellent point you
want to leave with us today.
If you had a take home message to leave
with our audiences, what would it be?
>> I think about this and
I don't say it exactly the way I'm about
to to my boys who are still little.
But this is still how I really feel in a
larger sense, also.
And that is that, the technical message
would be, whether you're dealing
with stress or whatever it is you know,
work hard, but enjoy what you are doing.
Try and do something that, you know, is
useful and
helpful to, to those around you in
addition, you know, to yourself.
Be genuine and
authentic, so you feel a resonance with,
you know, what you are doing.
And you know, in a way sort of the point
of resonance and
harmony would be what Mahatma Gandhi said
about when he defined happiness,
which was, happiness is when what you
think, say, and do are in harmony.
And you know it, you know?
When it works that way, you know it.
So try to maximize the amount of time.
All your life might not be like that.
And the entire, all the hours in a
particular day might not be like that.
But, as gently as possible to yourself but
as genuinely as possible, try to maximize
your, maximize the time that you can have
that harmony, is what I would say.
And it helps, I think, stress and, you
know, many other things.
>> What a beautiful message and what a
great place to end on.
Thank you so much for your time, and for
your words of wisdom.
Such a pleasure to have you, thank you
Professor Dhabhar.
>> It's been wonderful being here.
Thank you.
>> Yeah, thank you very much.
>> Good luck with what you're trying to do
with the course.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks, thanks.
>> [BLANK_AUDIO]