Welcome back to the physiology of stress.
Today we are going to go straight into the
heart of stress.
We're going to begin our exploration of
how body systems respond to
stress by looking at how the circulatory
system, the heart,
its vessels and the other associated
components respond during stress.
So here's our road map for where we're
headed in the mini-lecture.
We will talk about heart rate and stress.
We'll explain Anne's heart rate data.
We'll describe some components of stress
cardiovascular physiology.
And finally, we're going to end with a
really interesting story about stress and
public speaking.
The heart is one of the most iconic
symbols of all of humankind.
It means a lot of different things to
different people.
To physiologists, it's a hard-working,
relentless muscle that serves the human
body endlessly.
Transporting nutrients to capillary
networks, and the tissues of the body
where the nutrients will be exchanged with
waste that needs to be discarded.
The circulatory system is both the food
caterer and
the waste management system of energy
breakdown of the muscle.
As such, it's highly responsive to times
of stress when we need access to
a lot of nutrients and when we need to be
prepared to transport a lot of waste.
The heart is often one of the first things
that people think about when they
think about what it means to be stressed
in their body.
Think about the pounding in the ears of
the athlete who is preparing to perform or
the fluttering in the chest of that
hopeful girl,
who's crush turns to ask her a question in
the middle of class.
Our hearts are extremely reactive during
the stress response.
Removing parasympathetic break, and
driving on the sympathetic to elevate
heart rate.
So, here's the main question.
What does an increased heart rate do for
us?
Well, remember that the circulatory system
has a job to do,
to deliver oxygen and nutrients to the
muscles so that it can do work.
So during a stressful event when the body
is preparing to do a large amount of work,
it ramps up its delivery and
waste removal system so that the muscles
can get everything that they need.
We call this increase in transport an
increase in cardiac output, or
the amount of blood leaving the heart.
An average person has about five to six
liters of blood in their body,
depending on how large they are.
During times of rest that blood, it gets
cycled about once a minute.
And during times of intense exercise your
body can get that blood to
cycle six times as fast or
faster, meaning your blood gets circulated
around your entire body every ten seconds.
So in order to increase the cardiac output
to meet your body,
body's needs, the heart, it beats faster.
As you can see next to me, cardiac output
is a function of two variables.
Heart rate, so fast your heart beats and
stroke volume,
which is the amount of blood that leaves
the heart per beat.
Meaning, more blood leaves the heart,
the more rapidly the heart beats and the
more blood it can inject per unit time.
The stress response makes the heart beat
harder and
faster in order to get the blood around
the body quickly.
And this is exactly the physiology we saw
when Anne went
sky diving out of the airplane.
Though her average resting heart rate is
in the mid 50s somewhere we see
an elevated heart activity pattern at 130
beats a minute as she
jumps out of the airplane.
If you think about it,
it's really pretty incredible how reactive
the stress system is.
Within moments of Anne's brain perceiving
something as stressful,
her heart almost immediately reacts.
So let's take a look at what happened
here.
In the half-hour leading up to the jump
out of the plane,
you see what we call an anticipatory rise.
Anne knows the threat is coming and she
gets more and
more stressed as she approaches the event.
Explaining why she is 30 to 40 beats above
her resting heart rate for
the entire hour before the jump.
The three spikes leading up to the jump
represents moments where
an activity happened that triggered fear.
Let's go back in time and take a quick
look at what happened.
So we see the walk out to the plane, take
off,
[MUSIC]
The first opening
of the door as we are ascending in the
airplane.
And finally, the big moment arrives.
>> This is a super bad idea.
>> And Dr. Freidlander makes her epically
huge leap,
causing a heart to jump from a rate of mid
90s to a whopping 130 beats [INAUDIBLE].
[MUSIC]
What an incredible thing [INAUDIBLE] to
do.
Then there's a rapid decline back to 100
beats a minute when the parachute opens.
And finally, a return to baseline once she
hits the ground.
In addition to an increase in heart rate,
the smooth muscles in the linings of the
arteries constrict.
I like to think of the body as a container
of a certain size.
Holding, as we said, about 5 liters or so
of blood.
When you're stressed and
arteries constrict, it makes the size of
that overall container much smaller.
As a result, the pressure in the container
increases.
Hence, an increase in blood pressure in
the body.
This vasoconstriction is an important way
that the body directs blood
resources to the place in the body that
need it.
The second thing that most people commonly
might think of,
as happening when they get stressed, is
that they start to, to breathe harder.
Breathing harder during stress is a great
example of how interconnected our
systems interact, in order to meet our
needs.
In this case the ventilatory system works
with the cardiovascular system.
So we know we breathe harder when we are
stressed.
And we certainly breathe a lot harder when
we exercise,
as we saw what happened to Anne in the
stress video.
One reason we increase ventilations is
because we increase the driving pressure
of oxygen into arterial blood when we
breath more.
The hyperventilation serves another vital
function for the body.
Stress increases ventilation in
anticipation of doing a lot of work.
When your body breaks down the energy it
receives as food, the garbage it leaves
behind in the blood stream is carbon
dioxide and hydrogen ions we call acid.
One way that waste can leave the body is
through the the lungs when
you [SOUND]
exhale.
In the case of a serious physical
stressor, like running, you're going to
consume a lot of energy and create a lot
of waste in the blood stream.
You may have never considered this, but
every time you breathe out you're actually
breathing out the waste that was discarded
from energy that you used in your muscles.
So nevertheless, a stressed out body means
there will be a lot of
trash piling up in the boulevards of the
bloodstream.
And breathing harder is one of your body's
main strategies for cleaning up that mess.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We had a great and
a really interesting opportunity to add to
Anne's heart rate data.
And as it turns out it's a really
healthful way to
introduce an important theme of stress
physiology that I
really want you to take away from our time
together.
To really understand stress, we need to
accept that the mind and
the body are connected.
And that psychological stressors, like
negative self talk,
public speaking, Imagining bad outcomes
for yourself.
These things turn on the exact same
physical stress systems as
being chased by a bear.
Here at Stanford, Anne was asked to give a
speech, a commencement speech for
the program in Human Biology.
And in the spirit of this course, which we
were making at the time,
we decided to gather her vitals in real
time as she spoke.
And we were pretty floored by what we saw.
Well, we knew that stress was
psychological and that giving a speech
would turn on her stress systems, but we
were amazed by how much.
To our surprise, we found that Anne's
heart rate data, from giving a speech,
mimics, almost beat for beat, the data we
collected from skydiving.
Perhaps we shouldn't have been so
surprised,
as public speaking is often listed by
people as one of their greatest fears.
You can see a similar anticipatory rise 30
to 40 beats above baseline,
as she waits on the stage to give her
speech.
Followed by a spike up as the speaker
before her introduced her.
And culminating with a whopping rise to
the same max heart rate she reached while
skydiving, 130 beats a minute.
Our data seemed to suggest that for
Anne, public speaking was every bit as
stressful as jumping out of an airplane.
And keep in mind, Anne speaks publicly for
a living, she's a professor.
Imagine someone who doesn't.
It's no wonder that public speaking is
such a common fear.
What Anne's experience teaches us and
reminds us is that stress is quite a
psychological phenomenon.
We seem to be wired in such a way that our
brains and our bodies can't really tell
the difference between real stressors and
imaginary ones.
This is such an important concept for us
modern day humans and
first world humans because most of our
daily stress is psychological in nature.
So beware, when you stress yourself out
with your mind, your body prepares for
battle, whether you meant it to or not.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this concludes our mini lecture on the
cardiovascular system and stress.
We were built on an understanding that
during stressful times the body needs to
access a lot of nutrients and unload a lot
of waste in a very short period of time.
As a result, the body systems respond by
increasing heart rate,
stroke volume, blood pressure, and
ventilation rate.
Ann has taught us a lot about stress
already, but
our journey still has a lot of story left
in it.
So, mobilize your resources, and get
excited.
Because we've just scratched the surface
of the stress response.
I'll see you soon.
[BLANK_AUDIO]