[LAUGH] [SOUND] Welcome back to the
physiology of stress.
Today, stress gets hormonal, and
we're going to unpack the role of hormones
in the stress response.
And this is our roadmap for this mini
lecture.
We're going to start with a quick overview
of the hypothalamic pituitary access.
The slow stress response.
And then talk about some of the major
hormones involved in getting stressed,
relating each one along the way, or
as many as possible to Dr. Freelander and
her experience at Skydive LasVegas.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I'm starting to feel nervous.
How are you feeling?
>> I'm not nervous.
>> The doctor's nervous, I'm nervous.
Let's see what happens.
>> [NOISE]
[MUSIC]
>> Standing in the landing field doing
science.
Freelander lab, we can go anywhere.
>> Anytime, anywhere!
>> A big part of Anne's stress experience
is
mediated by these important hormones that
characterize the stress response.
We took blood from Dr.
Freelander to measure hormone levels at
various points during her experience
to give us a picture of how they play a
role in stress response.
The data next to me give you an image,
an idea of her changes in hormone levels
approximately ten minutes post-jump.
From the plane compared to her baseline
levels which we took on a previous day.
Within this time frame you see some pretty
changes in blood levels of
these stress hormones.
Doubling tripling and sometimes increasing
by an order of 92.
The hypofolamic putuitary access is a set
of connections.
An interactions between the hypothalamus,
the pituitary gland and adrenal gland.
It represents a connection between the
nervous system and the endocrine system.
And is involved in regulating many
processes including the stress response.
The HPA Axis results in a release of the
famous stress hormone cortisol.
And this is how it does it.
The hypothalamus releases CRH, or
Corticotropin Releasing Hormone,
which stimulates the Anterior Pituitary to
release Adrenocorticotropic Hormone
from the Anterior Pituitary, which is
released into the blood stream and
eventually stimulates the Adrenal Cortex,
to release, Cortisol into the bloodstream.
The green forward arrows represent the
feed to forward signals that increase
production and
the blue lines represent the feedback
signals that reduce hormonal production.
Its a little messy and complicated but
really the important point that I
want you to take away, is that the brain
controls the release of these hormones.
And, it's controlled and regulated at
various levels.
As you remember from the previous mini
lecture,
the sympathetic nervous system has nerve
connections that synapse directly onto
the body organs that are affected by the
stress response.
This includes nerves that reach to the
adrenal medulla signaling for
the quick release of hormones,
epinephrine, norepinephrine, and dopamine.
The diagram, the left side of which,
demonstrates how the HPA access leads to
the production of cortisol.
Passing chemical signals through the blood
stream from
the hypothalamus to the anterior pituitary
and then to the adrenal cortex.
The cortisol is released into the blood.
In contrast, very fast electrical signals
of
the sympathetic nervous system The signals
carried throughout the HPA axis
are much slower taking on the order of
minutes and longer to have their effect.
Epinephrine and its support hormone,
norepinephrine, account for
much of the immediate and short term
effects on stress response.
Target organs and tissues of the
sympathetic chain release Norepinephrine
right at the site of activation.
These hormones often referred to as
Catecholamines are the first
wave of stress hormones that activate
second
messenger cascades within moments to
seconds.
They are also released in the blood stream
by the adrenal medulla accounting for
activation of body organs, on a more
intermediate timeframe, like 30 seconds.
Tissues from the head to the toe tend to
be really dense in
these catecholamine receptors, causing
changes all over the body.
You can see the increase in catecholamine
levels in Anne's blood, right next to me.
At ten minutes post skydive,
you see significant increases in
catecholamine levels in our blood.
These catecholamines signal for
an increase of energy breakdown in the
muscle, preparing the body for action.
These catecholamines commonly called
adrenaline.
Are largely to thank for helping us
recruit massive amount of
bodily resources, in a short period of
time.
Now glucocorticoids like cortisol, are the
second hormone wave of the stress,
stress response, and they have an impact
on a longer time frame,
pushing from minutes to hours.
The HPA access releases glucocorticoids
like cortisol and aldosterone.
Though we didn't measure aldosterone in
Ann, it's a hormone that
helps the body retain fluids, increasing
blood pressure and cardiac output.
The release of cortisol happens on a much
slower time frame.
As indicated by Anne's blood cortisol data
at ten minutes post jump.
We likely measured Anne's peak catoclamine
levels, her peak cortisol
levels probably were still on the rise at
the time of our measurement.
So once the HPA access stimulates the
adrenal cortex,
we have an increase of cortisol floating
around in our bloodstream.
So, what happens next?
What does cortisol do upon acute exposure?
One of it's major actions is to act as a
catabolic signal.
Cortisol signals for the breakdown of fats
and proteins.
It signals for increased breakdown of this
stored energy resulting in
a rise in serum glucose fatty acids and
amino acids.
Having access to this energy is absolutely
crucial to be able to run or
fight in response to a stressful
situation.
Especially once our short term energy
stores are low.
Cortisol helps promote the other aspects
of the stress response
by signaling peripheral vasoconstriction,
promoting an increase in blood pressure.
It also reduces inflammation and shuts
down things like the reproductive system.
Have you ever had the experience where you
were so into a sporting even or
a game competition and you didn't realize
that you actually got cut,
or otherwise minorly injured.
Do you ever wonder, how sometimes, you're
watching athletes push through
great injury in that big game, when they
feel like everything is on the line?
In Anne's case, skydiving, we did a pain
stressor test.
Where we placed Anne's hand, into freezing
ice water.
Something that reliably generates pain in,
in the middle of the hand.
In her case, after she activated a stress
response sky diving,
she was able to do something really
strange.
She was able to tolerate more pain.
Among other things,
endorphins could help us understand how
humans can deal with that.
Otherwise great pain during times of
stress.
Endorphin's are endogenous opiates
released by the brain and
body during times of stress that have a
natural pain suppressing effect.
Endorphin's suppress pain by breaking the
path of pain information in the brain.
Preventing pain signals from the lower
body from reaching the processing centers
that otherwise inform you that way.
Oxytocin is another interesting hormone
associated with stress response.
It's a neuropeptide released by the
pituitary along with
other pituitary hormones and you might be
familiar with it because,
Oxytocin has gotten a lot of love in the
media.
It's affectionately referred to as the
cuddle hormone, or the love hormone.
It's presented as a hormone that promotes
human connection and human touch.
Recent studies have associated increased
oxytocin with an amelioration or
a reduction in stress response.
While promoting human connection.
It may be that one stresses over oxytocin
helps us return to baseline.
After all, we aren't meant to be stressed
for
more than just short periods at a time.
Oxytocin may promote seeking out resources
to return back to baseline after stress.
From your own personal experience, this
might make a lot of sense to you.
What do you do when you're really stressed
out?
For many of you, you probably go to a
parent, maybe you go to a sibling,
maybe you have a best friend you confide
in or a partner.
We tend to seek out the touch, the
empathy,
the listening, the comfort of others.
And that social support helps mellow out
that stress response.
At least in part oxytocin could be
deriving that behavior.
Hormones are the great carriers of
information that signal optimization of
the body, to deal with life's greatest
challenges.
They are the players in the trenches
making a stress response happen.
Mobilizing energy, Inhibiting pain and
even, looking out for
your best interest, once stress is over.
I'll see you in the next one.
[NOISE]