Welcome back to the Physiology of Stress.
Today, stress gets nervous.
And we explore the ins and
the outs of how the nervous system is
involved with the stress response.
Previously, we addressed how the
cardiovascular system is activated when
we get stressed.
We're now going to move on to our major
system.
And discuss the role of the brain, and the
nervous system.
First, we'll talk about the brain, some of
its components.
And how to initiate our stress response.
Second, we'll talk about how our memory
and
mental performance is impacted by stress.
If you recall from the story video, Anne
performed worse on
the cognitive performance test after
jumping out of the plane.
And we're going to talk about why that
happened.
Third and lastly,
I will leave you with some awesome tools
from the Rotman Research Institute.
That might just help you make sense out of
why you seem to make so
many poor decisions.
Particularly with people that you care
about, when you're stressed.
So, how does a stress response get
activated in our bodies?
I like to think of the brain as the
kingpin system of the stress response.
It plays the crucial role of interpreting
something as stressful.
And activating the various systems to be
able to respond appropriately.
So what does physiology tell us about how
stress is initiated by the brain?
How do scientists think that the brain is
able to activate the stress response?
Well, let's take a deep dive into the
brain to familiarize ourselves with some
of the main players.
As we come around the brain, we can see
the cortex and the mid brain.
With the brain stem left out of the model
to help give us a better look.
As we come around the corner, we're
going to see each of
these brain components highlighted in
different colors.
The hippocampus is in yellow.
And it's known to be important for the
formation of memories.
The Hypothalamus, which you remember from
HPA axis, sits on top of the brain stem.
And is featured here in purple,
with connections to the pituitary shown in
blue.
It has a number of nuclei and
various responsibilities, but it's a major
player in the stress response.
With projections that activate the
sympathetic branch.
And, connecting the nervous system with
the endocrine system through the HPA axis.
The amygdala, shown in red, is commonly
the,
the go-to brain region that people love to
talk about when talking about stress.
Its role is often described as assigning
significance to a stimulus.
It rapidly identifies whether we should be
stressed out by something or not.
The amygdala is well connected to the
hippocampus and to the hypothalamus.
Making it well situated for access to
memory information.
And to activate the hypothalamus to
initiate the stress response if need be.
The prefrontal cortex, here in orange, is
responsible for a lot of different things,
and we're not going to talk about.
It's accociated with things like
personality, decision making, and
moderating all sorts of behavior.
It's also believed to regulate stress and
emotional activity.
Turning down the activation of lower level
brain regions like the amygdala.
It's thought to be, the muscle of sorts,
that is trained in cognitive behavioral
therapy, for example.
A setting where patients are taught
strategies to better manage and
influence their emotional responses.
These regions work in concert with one
another to identify that
stressful simul, stimulus.
And send a signal to get your body into
action.
So once these brain regions identify the
external stressor,
that information is passed on to the
hypothalamus.
Our one stop shop for activating the
bodies stress response.
As you can see from this great graphic,
the hypothalamus can initiate both the HPA
axis and the sympathetic chain.
We will go into greater detail of the HPA
in our next lecture.
For now, we're going to focus on my right
side.
My right side of this graph.
The hypothalamus has nerve path ways that
project it downwards into the spine, and
create what's called the sympathetic
chain.
The sympathetic chain is this really cool,
series of ladder like nerve projections,
from the thoracic and lumber spine.
If you were looking straight down into an
open chest wall.
They, they lay on the,
the very back of the chest, leaving the
spine one vertebrae at a time.
These nerve pathways synapse onto ganglia.
And then have projections out onto many
different organs in the body.
We learned earlier about how many of the
consequences of activating a stress
response, like dilating pupils and slowing
digestion, and increased heart rate.
Well many of these responses are caused by
activating this neural circuit.
The heart, which responds to both
sympathetic and
parasympathetic input, is a great example
of
an organ that is regulated by these higher
inputs from brain centers.
We also used another measure in addition
to heart rate called skin conductance,
as an indictator of how stressed how,
how stressed Anne was during the
storytelling video.
Skin conductance, often referred to as
electrodermal activity, is a measure of
how long it takes an electrical current to
pass across the surface of the skin.
We use the sensor arm band,
which is a device that has two electrodes
spaced about an inch apart on Anne's skin.
That was, that, that sent an electrical
impulse that is recorded by the device.
The amount of time it takes for the signal
to reach the other electrode,
is influenced by a lot of different
factors.
Including factors that were out of our
control when studying Anne.
But one of those factors was whether Anne
was sweating or not.
And it just so
happens that skin conductance can be a
good indicator of sympathetic activation.
Because your sweat glands are activated by
the sympathetic branch.
In some sense, skin conductance is an even
clear indicator of sympathetic arousal
than heart rate.
Because unlike heart rate, the sweat
glands do not have parasympathetic input.
So what does that mean?
It means in the right environment when you
start sweating,
it's a pretty good indicator of when
you're starting to get stressed out.
It's important to note that when
conducting a research study,
a lot of effort goes in controlling
variables.
More effort than we did in this case study
in the field with Anne.
Nevertheless, I think it still tells a
pretty good story about how
Anne's skydiving stress affected her body.
When dealing with electrodermal activity,
researchers generally look for
changes in values over periods of time.
Boiling down to a rather simple concept.
You're looking for how an external event,
like skydiving.
Changes sweating in a, in a short period
over seconds.
Or you're looking for
a general changes of arousal over a longer
period of time, like minutes.
In our case, we are looking at both.
And we are interested in how Anne's
sweating,
served as an indicator of Anne getting
stressed throughout her experience.
We see here three particular time points
where Anne's sympathetic nervous system,
turned on the sweat glands in her body.
Giving us a pretty good sense of the time
points during the skydive when stress was
being turned on.
We first arrived at the facility when we
first arrived at the facility,
you see Anne's skin conductance values
jump up and maintain.
Indicating to us that she might have been
pretty nervous during
that preparatory process.
As you also might expect, she experienced
an increase in sweating and sympathetic
activation following opening of the door,
and her big jump from the plane.
You might know from your own experience,
something really strange that happens with
memory and emotions.
And that's the, we tend to remember the
most emotionally-intense moments
in our lives.
I can still remember, in vivid detail, my
first kiss.
The higher school dance I was at, the song
that was playing.
And where my girlfriend and I were
standing on the dance floor.
For me it was really intense and exciting
moment at that time in my life.
And, and all things considered it's kind
of strange and amazing, that I remember so
many details from that moment.
Given how much I have forgotten between
now and my 14 year old self.
Studies have replicated this observation
that, that we tend to
remember experiences in which we were
strongly, emotionally aroused.
Like for those people who've experienced
an earthquake or saw an accident.
Many Americans and
others around the world, remember exactly
where they were when JFK was assassinated.
Or exactly where they were or
what they were doing when the planes hit
the twin towers on 9/11.
Stress plays a role in enhancing memory
formation.
Sympathetically enhanced memory, or
remembering more when you are stressed,
seems to be due to the increased
availability of nutrients.
As you know, the stress responses
increases the delivery of
these nutrients by increasing cardiac
output.
And increasing glucose availability
through hormones that are released.
That increase in oxygen and glucose levels
to the brain, promotes memory formation.
And it could explain why we seem so
much better at remembering emotionally
charged events in our lives.
It's pretty unlikely that Anne will forget
her skydive experience anytime soon.
Even if she can't remember what she had
for lunch two days ago.
And it has everything to do with
sympathetic arousal of the stress
response, and its impact on storage in the
brain.
When experiencing extreme and traumatic
emotional events,
it seems that there's this upside-down
u-shaped relationship between memory and
the intensity of the stressor.
Where moderate stress, like when I
received my first kiss,
leads to an increase in the likelihood of
memory formation.
Now, taken to the extreme, high arousal
events seem to
reduce the likelihood that the person will
form a strong memory.
And possibly even cause loss of brain
hippocampal cells in the process.
Why this happens sometimes, and you know
why people sometimes block out,
or, or forget, the most traumatic events
of their lives, isn't entirely understood.
But at least one theory in the literature
points to glucocorticoids like cortisol.
And the dangers it poses to brain cells in
high concentrations.
Or when present for a long period of time.
It ends up that stress and performance is
a pretty tricky topic for scientists.
And there isn't really a consensus about
how and
why certain at certain times people
perform better when they're stressed.
And at other times they perform worse.
Getting stressed certainly makes us better
at some things.
Like remembering past times that we were
stressed and getting prepared to run.
And it makes us worse at other things like
dealing with social relationships and
thinking creatively.
But what about in the case of, you know,
taking tests and cognitive performance?
As you recall from our replay of the
testing we did at SkyDive Las Vegas Anne's
cognitive performance was affected by her
stress experience.
In a cognitive performance task that
tested short-term memory,
where the task of image and word recall.
Anne remembered fewer words after she
experienced skydive stress,
than when compared to her baseline
condition the previous day.
So what's going on here?
Why do some people rise to the occasion
and perform well when they're stressed?
And others who experience the exact same
stressor, don't?
Well the, the truth is, Anne's cognitive
performance is a little bit
hard to explain, given conflicting data
and literature.
But we could still take a scientific
approach to uncover a pattern,
that might be useful.
It seems that it's through the
individual's appraisal of the stressor,
or what that stressor means to them.
That we can make sense out of the stress
making us perform well, or not.
So here's the key.
If a stressor is seen as an obstacle that
can be overcome.
It tends to motivate better performance.
When a stressor is seen as,
as insurmountable, overwhelming or
distracting.
It tends to decrease performance outcomes.
The key concept here is that when stress
leads to increased motivation and
attention, it increases performance.
However when a tension is focused
elsewhere, performance tends to decline.
This isn't terribly complicated, either
way stress mobilizes energy.
But stress that motivates focus on a task
is good for performance.
And stress that distracts focus is bad for
performance.
In our case it seems that Anne's skydiving
stress,
distracted her from performing well on
that memory task the second time.
So at the end of the day,
science matters most to us when it can
make our lives better.
So, let's apply stress to something many
of us care about.
Our relationships.
As I alluded to earlier, one of our, one
area of our lives that are often greatly
injured by stress response is the world of
social relationships.
When you find yourself in the trenches,
getting stressed with your close friend,
a family member or a partner.
You're at greater risk of doing something
that you might later regret.
The times in my life when I've said the
most hurtful things to people that I love,
are times when I was in, was in like a
different state of mind.
John Gottman of the Gottman institute,
call this phenomenon, physiologic
flooding.
Physiologic flooding is the stress
response.
The flooding of certain systems that,
interestingly, when it comes to
relationships, seems to be a bad thing.
It turns out that some of our higher-order
brain functions,
tend not to work as well when we are
stressed out.
Something called cortical inhibition.
Our most recently area involved, areas of
the brain like the, the prefrontal cortex.
Help us navigate our complex social
worlds.
And tend to not function as well when
we're under stress.
Gottman spent his entire career collecting
data on couples in his lab.
Observing times when they were connecting,
and times when they were fighting.
So one day he was doing a session in the
lab with a couple,
that was hopelessly stuck in a fight that
just was not resolving.
Both were aroused with high heart rates,
animated.
They were shouting, pointing and really
being monsters to one another.
And he was happy because he was getting
some good conflict data.
Until by accident, he had an issue with
his computer and data collection.
Embarrassed, he requested that the couple
to please pause their conflict, so
he could get the devices back online and
working again.
And that they just read a magazine, or
do something else until he alerted them to
continue.
And by the time he got the machines
working again, and
the couple continued, the most miraculous
thing had happened.
They were no longer physiologically
aroused.
And they had transformed from the ugly
monsters,
into reasonable people who quickly, worked
through their issue.
Later work in the lab repeated the same
finding.
Discovering what he refers to again,
physiologic flooding.
When his subjects and conflict had heart
rates that increase into the mid 90s.
So the point at which sympathetic input
begins,
indicating the start of the stress
response.
Those people were less empathetic.
They were less resourceful, and overall
much crappier relationship partners.
Now when we, when we asked them to pause
long enough to reduce the,
the flooding, they were much more able to
create better relationship outcomes.
So now, you're able to make sense out of
the poor choices you've made in the past
when in a stressed out state.
You may not have a heart rate monitor
handy.
But lucky for
us, we can learn to know what it feels
like in our body to become stressed.
Now that you know about cortical
inhibition and physiologic flooding.
You know when that anxiety or fear starts
creeping up, that you're body and
brain may not be in the best place for
making relationship choices.
It's a good time to remove yourself from
the situation.
Employ yourself soothing technique.
Do what you can to come back to neutral,
before reengaging.
We will learn some self, self soothing
practices in the later modules.
In the mean time, it seems that mom's old
wisdom for
counting to ten has some real scientific
support.
So that wraps up our lecture on how stress
gets nervous.
The brain plays a vital role in the stress
response.
Initiating chemical and
electrical signals that alerts the body to
respond appropriately.
It can improve our chances of forming
memories.
And sometimes, impair some of our
abilities to function.
In the case of stage fright, test anxiety
and physiologic flooding in relationships.
I can't tell you how much creating an
awareness around flooding,
has contributed to my life.
And helped me to make better choices.
I challenge you to incorporate this
knowledge into your own life.
And make a choice to help calm yourself
down the next time
you get flooded in a sticky relationship
situation.
Do a little science experimentation and
just see if you get a better result.
That's all we got for stress in the brain.
I'll see you in the next one.