[MUSIC]
[SOUND]
Stress one.
And real quickly, just because I haven't
been in here for a while.
[LAUGH] [INAUDIBLE].
Close, close.
Lights, on.
Overhead lights are on.
The camera's on.
[SOUND] Exposure is on.
Sound looks good.
Coordinate is good.
Two lights [INAUDIBLE].
Alright, Anne.
Here goes nothing.
Alright, dance, monkey, dance.
Are there any boogers in my nose?
Mobilizing energy, inhibiting pain and
leaving, even looking out for
you, and your best interest.
Let's try this over.
[LAUGH] It was almost there.
Flowing.
Okay.
I woke up this morning.
I've got a pimple right here.
I never get pimples.
I was a little nervous, for today.
>> I can't see it.
>> You can't see it?
I was going to touch it up anyway.
>> [LAUGH] When the peripheral nervous
system, refurther it.
Hm.
[LAUGH]
My mouth is dry.
I need some water, and start over on that
slide.
>> [SOUND] Duh!
[SOUND] First module is done!
>> That's awesome!
That's a keeper.
>> [LAUGH] How does it look, Dr.
Friedlander?
>> [LAUGH] Oh, man!
Welcome back, to the, physiology, of
stress,
today stress gets, hormonal and we're
going to [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGH] The brain plays a vital role in
the stress response, initiating chemical
and electrical signals that alert the body
systems to respond appropriately.
It can improve our chances of forming
memories, and also sometimes impair some
of our inabilities to fucktion, to
[LAUGH].
>> That was good.
>> But It does.
It impairs our ability to [SOUND] Jesus.
[LAUGH]
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
>> This is a better idea!