[MUSIC]
Welcome to our expert interview in
relaxation response physiology with Dr.
Herbert Benson.
Dr. Benson is the director emeritus with
the Benson-Henry Institute here at
the Massachusetts General Hospital, and
a professor of medicine at Harvard Medical
School.
A graduate of Harvard Medical School, Dr.
Benson is the author or
coauthor of more than 190 scientific
publications and 12 books.
Dr. Benson is a pioneer in mind-body
medicine and a leading researcher in,
in the study of relaxation response
physiology, and
its efficacy in counteracting the harmful
effects of stress.
A highly decorated clinician and
researcher, Dr.
Benson has received numerous national and
international awards for his work.
A best-selling author and frequently
interviewed physician,
his work has positively impacted the lives
of millions of people.
So for those reasons and for many others,
it's a great honor to now turn to our
expert interview in relaxation response
physiology with Dr. Herbert Benson.
Dr. Benson, it's really an honor to be
here with you today.
Thank you so much for your time.
>> Thank you.
Thank you for coming.
>> It's a pleasure to meet you.
So I thought that a great place to start
this morning would be right at
the beginning, and I was wondering if you
could share a little bit about your
story of how you became involved with the
study of relaxation response physiology?
>> Thank you.
It's a true honor to be part of this
Stanford series and
to be able to explain how we possess an
alternative response
within us that's opposite to the stress
response, and
to the extent that any disorder or any
condition is caused or
made worse by stress, to that extent we
have a natural,
inborn capacity to counteract that.
I'm a cardiologist by training, and early
in my career I was noting that people,
patients, coming to me to see me, had
disproportionately high blood pressures.
And I'd medicate them and I'd be
consistently over-medicating them,
and I wondered maybe there was something
different about the measurement that was
going on in their blood pressure, compared
to their every day blood pressure.
In those days so-called white coat
hypertension had not been defined.
Namely, the white coat of the health care
professional would be threatening and
a stress, and therefore raise the blood
pressure.
And that got us wondering, perhaps high
blood pressure was more
than kidney disease, which is was felt to
be due to at that time.
And this was heretical because, that the
mind would
effect the body 40 years or so ago was in
a different universe.
But it was a finding.
And then young people hearing about these
studies came to me.
Younger people, I was young in those days.
Younger people came to me and said, why
are you fooling around with monkeys?
Why don't you study us?
We practice transcendental meditation.
And if stress and high blood pressure was
beyond the pale of routine science,
meditation was in another universe, and I
refused.
I was already being told by studying
stress was unacceptable.
It wasn't science.
But these people wouldn't go away.
They kept coming back insisting that they
had lower blood pressure.
So I decided, why not give a look?
And these were days before human studies
committees,
before institutional review boards, where
we didn't have to clear it.
And I decided to do so, but we were still
careful.
We studied them only in an evening,
bringing them in through a side door when
people wouldn't see them,
and instrumented them with all sorts of
measuring parameters.
The first 20 minutes, regular thinking.
Next 20 minutes, meditation.
Third 20 minutes, regular thinking.
Off, on, off.
There were dramatic changes by that simple
act of changing their thinking.
And the hallmark of that, and
to this day, is a decrease in the
metabolic rate of the body.
It was an overall quieting response.
And in one of those wonderful,
serendipitous happenstances,
the room at Harvard Medical School in
which we were
doing these studies were the very studies
40 years before
Walter B Cannon had defined the
fight-or-flight response.
And it made no sense if this was an
opposite response,
that transcendental meditation would be
the only way to do it.
It would be as if to say there was just
one way to stress yourself.
It didn't make sense.
So we looked at, into the components that
made up transcendental meditation, and
we felt that there were two, and the first
was a repetition.
That could be a word, a sound, a prayer, a
phrase, or a repetitive movement.
The second is when other thoughts came to
mind you disregarded them and
returned to the repetition.
What these two steps do is break the train
of everyday thinking.
So we then went back to, and spent two
years reviewing the religious and
secular literatures of the world to see
whether or
not these two steps hadn't been described
before.
And lo and behold, it was ubiquitous.
Well, if this were the case, we felt we
could replicate this.
So we went back to the laboratory.
We found changes indistinguishable from
those of transcendental meditation.
Decreased metabolism, heart rate, blood
pressure, brain waves.
At any rate, this now was science.
Here was something that was predictable,
reproducible, and measurable.
And we started then with interventions
that would regularly evoke the relaxation
response and studied what we felt were
stress-related diseases.
And what we found over the decades was
that to the extent that any disorder
is caused or exacerbated by stress, by the
fight-or-flight response,
to that extent the relaxation response
would be useful.
And new technologies as the years spun out
became available for
us to then study what is going on here,
and about ten or
so years ago we started our measurements
of genes changing
their activity when people evoke the
relaxation response.
And when we compared the two groups, those
who were
regularly evoking the relaxation response,
albeit by different techniques, and
those not doing so, there were changes in
their genetic expression.
Then we took the controls.
It's part of the same initial experiment,
who had never evoked the relaxation
response, and taught them to do so.
And then they did so for eight weeks on a
regular, once a day bras basis.
This was now a prospective experiment
where the individual is off-on,
[COUGH] and what we found in those initial
and
subsequent analyses was that when people
evoke the relaxation response,
either for the first time you know, over a
short period, or
for long periods, the same gene's activity
were changing.
This was measuring all genes,
we had no hypothesis going in, so it's
really shotgun.
And what we found were there were four
categories that
are changed when people evoke the
relaxation response.
One is oxidative phosphorylation.
That is, the mitochondrial RNA activity
is, is quieted.
And incidentally, this is different from
what happens in stress,
because the same mitochondrial RNA
activity chains are activated.
What we were finding in the relaxation
response, they were deactivated.
Secondarily, another cluster of genes were
related to insulin.
Insulin metabolism and they were, that was
increased in people evoking the relaxation
response, namely putting for, forth more
insulin, more insulin being created.
And importantly, another hub site was the
site
controlling the inflammatory system, the
immune system.
And the core there was a, a molecule
called NF-kappaB, which was deactivated.
And NF-kappaB is the molecule that
controls an inordinate amount of disease
states.
Such as hypertension, such as various
autoimmune
diseases such as atherosclerosis and heart
attacks.
NF-kappaB being activated in the stress
related disorders were
deactivated by the relaxation response.
And the fourth set of genes were genes
that were
activated under stress that control
telomere length.
Telomeres, the more stressed you are, the
shorter your telomere becomes.
And what we've found is that telomere
stabilization came about
with the relaxation response and the very
aging of cells, so
called apoptosis was being decreased.
>> So where do you think this field is
headed?
What, what kind of capability do you
envision, using this knowledge of
relaxation response physiology 10, 20, 30
years from now?
>> I believe that our world probably will
become ever more stressful.
Because, we're having to adjust
behaviorally to
changes occurring at an ever more frequent
space.
And I think we need the relaxation
response to be evoked regularly so
we can take advantage of this natural
capacity within us, costing only time.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, what do we do?
We're going to have to introduce this into
our educational systems.
We have to teach this in our schools, and
they can be taught in a secular fashion.
And I think what's been built up over the
years
to carry us to this current point is the
scientific credibility of this.
And we've gotta be careful not to teach
any one technique as
being more important than others.
That is a danger.
Because once a person evokes the
relaxation response there's this
feeling that theirs is the best way, the
only way.
We see this with techniques becoming more
or
less popular or religions becoming more or
less popular.
It has to be left up to the individual and
a generic way
of evoking the relaxation response can be
easily taught.
It should be furthermore taught for
performance.
When you evoke the relaxation response
your mind is quieter.
There's less static, less noise, and you
can use visualizations as a way to
if you will, practice an athletic
endeavor.
Hitting a tennis ball.
Hitting a golf ball.
Shooting a basket.
The super athletes go into neutral, and
they evoke a visualization naturally
within themselves.
So it should be part of that training.
This should be part of military training,
for
people who where PTSD can be treated.
In fact, it should be a routine aspect of
treatment and
prevention of stress-related disorders,
and with stress being so prevalent
we should be using less drugs and less
surgeries and using this capacity.
And I'm not saying they'll replace drugs,
they won't.
There are no substitutes for the awesome
power of many drugs, but
they should be used together with the
stress-related aspect so
you don't use as much medication.
So it should be, I believe,
the relaxation response, a routine part of
our daily life.
And all we'll be doing is repeating what
people have done for millennia.
And we have actually turned away from
relaxation response
practices because we don't have time for
it, which actually compounds things.
>> The ultimate irony.
>> Because, it makes the stress worse.
So it should be, I believe,
the relaxation response, a routine part of
our daily life.
>> There are many members of our audience
who are students, and some of whom might
be interested in following in your
footsteps and embark on their own journeys
in this field of relaxation response,
physiology and mind-body medicine.
So, what advice would you give to those
students who are listening?
>> Well, congratulations on being so
young.
>> [LAUGH]
>> It, it's wonderful that you have.
>> Our telomeres are long.
>> [LAUGH] But it's wonderful that you
have a, a future in front of you.
Use it appropriately.
In other words, use it to be healthy, and
to have a sense of well being, and
to recognize both natural and unnatural
influences in your life.
And this is simply part of your education.
And I wish I were your age.
[LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] So, we're approaching the end
of our interview now.
And so, the last question I'd like to ask
you, you've given us a lot of practical
information today, but if you could zone
in on one practical element of knowledge,
what is it that you would like to
emphasize to our audience?
What's the take-home message?
>> We as humans have capacities within us
that are often unrecognized.
Be open to learning about what you can do
for yourself so
that you could help yourself and in the
process help others as well, and
I believe that stress is often very
important for performance.
And you don't want to turn away.
You don't want to become a what, me worry
type of person.
But you can learn to counteract stress
appropriately.
And I hope you choose to use it to help
yourself.
>> Well, that wraps it up for today.
Thank you so much, Dr. Benson, for your
time.
I think, I can say on behalf of all of us,
this is truly an honor to be a part of
your, your day today.
>> Thank you.
So thank you for sharing.
>> Thank you for coming.
[MUSIC]