Welcome back to the physiology of stress.
It's time to explore stress and the immune
system.
We've come a long way and
arrived at the last major system, through
which we will examine stress response.
The immune system is tasked with the
responsibility of
protecting your body from external
invaders.
And patching you up when things go wrong.
It's so important for survival that it
makes sense it should be included in
the conversation about how your body
responds during high stakes situations.
Our journey will including gaining and
understanding of the good, the bad and
the ugly of how stress impacts our immune
system.
We will then transition into the dangers
of chronic stress.
And just when you think there is no hope,
we will present a model based in science
that will give us this secret to stress.
But before we do, let's take a quick look
and
do a little quick and dirty on the nuts
bolts of the immune system as is relevant
to understanding the stress response.
Your immune system, as we said, is tasked
with protecting the cells of your body.
Stanford professor Firdaus Dhabhar has
helped us understand the role of
the immune system during stress.
He describes the immune system as the
military to your body's castle.
And it has specialized soldiers with
different skills that go into battle.
When the stress response is activated, our
good old friend, the sympathetic chain,
has fibers that extend into the bone
marrow, spleen, and lymph nodes.
These different storage sites serve as
the, the barracks, the,
the storage sites for the military
soldiers, the immune cells.
And sympathetic innervation is the siren
that mobilizes them to
action in the blood stream.
To enter into the boulevards of the body.
Then, presence of glucocortitoids, you
remember cortisol, from HPA activation,
alerts the soldiers to take their battle
stations, at the skin.
Acute, or a short term stress, in healthy
individuals,
seems to activate the immune system
placing soldiers at their battle stations.
It makes sense that we have been created
in this way, because you can
imagine that at a time that you are
attacked, let's say you're bitten or
whatever, it would be a good time for your
immune response to be on
alert to respond appropriately to combat
intruders and risk of infection.
It might surprise you to see the word
stress and good and
immune system, all in the same place.
The media has certainly done a great job
of making a villain out of stress.
And mostly, it's for good reason, which
we'll get to shortly.
But you came here, to get a more nuanced,
scientific understanding.
And the truth is, is that stress,
in the right context, can be quite good
for your immune response.
Just like acute stress recruits the heart,
hormones and nervous system to
help you confront a stressor, the stress
response also recruits the immune
system to help you survive challenges like
wounding and infection.
That are associated with a recent attacker
stressor.
Professor Dhabhar was crucial in helping
us arrive at this understanding.
That stress, can be good for us.
An excellent academic and even better
person, you will have the opportunity to
meet him for an expert interview at the
end of this section.
And formed by many years of research on
this question,
Dhabhar proposes that stress can either be
immuno-enhancing or
immuno-suppressing, based on a handful of
critical factors.
The basic summary is, is that when
psychological stress lasts longer
than a short bout and becomes chronic,
everything changes.
Almost all functional markers of immune
fuction are compromised.
You experience something called, global
immunosuppression.
All types, and all phases of the immune
response are negatively affected.
Leaving your body susceptible to illness.
People experiencing big life stressors are
more likely to get colds and,
if the chronic stress persists,
are increasingly susceptible to other more
serious infectious disease.
Each of these systems that we've discussed
are optimized during
the stress response to promote survival.
They have been designed for acute, for
short term stressers.
To help us animals either overcome a
challenge or die trying.
However, it seems that this system has
started to
go a little bit wonky on us in our most
recent human social environments.
Evolutionary stressors, like the stress
response was designed for,
like running away from a bear, are no
longer as relevant in our
day to day lives for many of us in the
modern world.
Instead, psychologial stressors seem to
have replaced physiological stressors,
as the primary activator of the stress
response.
As famed researcher Hans Selye discovered
during the infancy of
stress response discovery, chronic stress
is bad news bears.
He found that persistent activation of the
stress response led to
the atrophy of immune organs, enlargement
of the agren, adrenal gland.
And the development of peptic ulcers.
What he found was that while the stress
response can mobilize resources
necessary for survival in the short term,
if continuously activated,
the stress response itself, the stress
response itself becomes harmful.
In fact, it is estimated by Herbert Benson
at the Harvard Medical School, that 60 to
90% of visits to primary care doctors are
as a result of stress-related diseases.
Each of these systems, during acute
stress, optimize the body, to perform.
To make us, [SOUND] version, 2.0 of
ourselves.
But our bodies weren't created to maintain
high levels of stress.
And these same systems that are so good
for
us in short bouts, start creating some
real serious problems.
Increased cardiovascular tone helps in the
short term.
But creates peripheral resistance and
contributes to the development of
cardiovascular disease and cerebra,
cerebra vascular disease in the long term.
Prolonged elevated levels of Cortisol
leads the redistribution of fat stores and
disrupts metabolic processes leading to
weight gain and obesity.
Elevated cortisol levels facilitate nerve
cell death, affect memory and
cognitive ability.
Chronic suppression of the immune system
impairs normal wound healing and
puts the individual at greater risk of
infectious disease.
Unfortunately, Type 2 bi-, diabetes, being
fat, having a heart attack or
a stroke, digestion problems, and
infectious disease, and cell death, they
all contribute towards creating a greater
load on an already weakened immune system.
You can see how the slippery slope becomes
a downward spiral when it
comes to stress and the immune system.
So why should you care?
Well, you should care because chronic
stress contributes to having all sorts of
problems that none of us want to have.
Like an increased risk of adult onset
diabetes, obesity, cardiovascular disease,
which means heart attack, cerebral
vascular disease which means stroke.
Malabsorption disorders, which means
stomach problems,
infertility, immune depression, risk of
infectious disease, nerve cell death,
reduced memory and cognitive function, as
well as many other things.
As best said by famous Stanford Professor,
Robert Sapolsky, who's a leading expert on
chronic stress.
Stress related diseases emerge
predominantly out of the fact that we so
often activate a physiological system that
has evolved for
responding to acute physical emergencies.
But we turn it on for
months on end, worrying about mortgages,
relationships, and promotions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So what is the moral of the story?
How can we take this information to
transform the way that we live our lives?
We have covered so much information on how
the stress response works and
I am really proud of you for making it
this far.
You now have a depth of understanding that
allows for
us to, to synth-, synthesize and simplify
the science to make our lives better.
So with all this information, we know
enough to create
a science based model about the most
optimal relationship to have with stress.
Among the four systems of the body we
discussed,
a handful of things emerged around the
stress response.
The first thing is that the acute stress
response is highly adaptive and
it is your best friend.
You now know way too much to be fooled by
the oversimplified conversations around
you about stress always being bad.
Hogwash.
Stress is so helpful in recruiting the
resources we need,
to overcome the obstacles in our daily
life.
The stress response makes us better, and
our lives richer and more exciting.
The second theme, that you're perhaps a
little more familiar with already,
is that chronic stress is bad.
Your body optimizes stress systems to
promote performance in the short term,
but if activated in the long term it can
cause serious problems.
So, beside me is a model of how must of us
live our lives in relationship to stress.
We spend a lot of our time in the triangle
area on your left.
Stressed out, but with an itty-bitty
little triangle peak that isn't very high,
meaning, we aren't being very productive
with stress when we are stressed.
We spend very little time in the recovery
state,
mostly because we haven't been taught the
strategies we need to feel better and
to transition from a state of stress to
recovery.
And as a result, we spend a lot of time in
the evil,
chronic stress box, exposing ourselves to
the horrors we know come as a result.
Fortunately, science offers a better
model.
It tells us that we should increase the
intensity of the stress
response at the right times.
Many of us fight stress when we actually
need it the most.
And could actually benefit from more
targeted and
perhaps more intense stress responses.
Having the ability to get yourself
stressed in the right way
at the right time is crucial for success.
However, when the intense and
specific stress response has accomplished
its goal, it's over.
Developing the skill to transition from a
state of stress to a state of recovery is
crucial, extending the period of time we
spend in the recovery state.
As a result, we minimize exposure to
chronic stress, and
we put our mind and our body on an upward
spiral towards living a better life.
Now that we have such a deep understanding
of the stress response, and a model for
how it can be most adaptively supportive
to our lives,
it's time to orient ourselves towards the
parasympathetic nervous system.
The secret to stress.
And gain the tools that we need to apply
the science of stress to our own lives.
See you soon, thanks.