Welcome to the Physiology of Stress.
If you're looking for a place to learn
about what science says about stress, and
for ways to improve your relationship with
stress for
the better then you're in the right spot.
I feel honored and really excited to talk
to you about such an important topic.
As a matter of fact, how we live with
stress is so
important that I really believe that this
material has the potential to not
only improve, but perhaps to really
transform your life.
The truth is, you love stress, you thrive
on stress.
And you wouldn't survive without it.
Stress often gets a bad rap, and make no
mistake, it's for a good reason.
But in the right amount, at the right
time, in the right way,
stress is a part of what makes our lives
so rich, and makes us feel alive.
Beside me is a road map outlining the
journey we will take together.
After the storytelling video we will
understand the stress response in
the human body through the lenses of the
heart, brain, hormones, and immune system.
We will gain an appreciation about how, at
its best,
the stress response prepares our bodies to
deal with life's greatest challenges, and
at its worst, puts us at risk for chronic
disease and illness.
This knowledge will allow us to build a
science-based model that guides us, that
teaches us how to optimize good stress and
reduce bad stress in our own lives.
The final module will be jam packed full
of practical tools that can
help you to actively develop a better
relationship with stress.
My own personal goal is to inspire you,
to make stress more of your friend, and
less of your enemy.
I've distilled elements of academic stress
physiology so
that it's more digestible, and sprinkled
the material with practical tools and
information that will be relevant to your
life.
I genuinely and
sincerely hope that it can serve you in
your journey of making your life better.
So let's start with Module Two.
You just watched an awesome video story
where Dr. Friedlander launched herself out
of an airplane while we measured what was
happening to her body.
Now it's time to unpack the data and bring
it to life using Dr.
Friedlander's experience to teach us about
the stress response.
So now we're going to begin our journey
understanding stress.
Each video module in this stress section
will begin with a road map,
like this one right behind me, giving you
a quick glimpse at where we are headed.
But you guys can read faster than I can
speak, so
let's cut to the chase and get to the good
stuff.
In his lab at Harvard University studying
animals,
Walter B Cannon famously discovered the
stress response.
He found that an amazingly complex network
of nerves worked together to help animals,
and us humans deal with stressful
situations.
What Cannon, and many researchers who
followed found, was that there seemed to
be some sort of coordinated activity in
response to a stressor,
which they called the stress response, or
the ergotropic system.
Ergotropic, meaning work system,
because these researchers theorized that
the stress response prepared the body
to do something, to do work on the
external world.
Scientists also found an additional system
that seemed to
be the opposite of this work system which
they called the trophotropic system,
a fancy way of describing a growth or a
restorative system.
We will gain a deep understanding of both
of these systems in this section.
Starting with this work system more
commonly referred to
as the stress response.
So what is stress?
Walter Cannon, who was a renaissance man,
and a great researcher and athlete,
described the stress response with a
metaphor that compared the regulation in
the body, that occurs during stress, to
players on a sports team.
Each player has a separate job that they
have to
do to keep the team functioning as a
whole.
The goal for the stress team in the body,
he explained, was a fight or
flight response.
A preparation of the body to either fight
with, or flee from something dangerous.
The stress response they found was turned
on by the sympathetic nervous system,
this complex network of nerves.
So being scientists, and doing what they
do,
they set out to find out just how
important this network of nerves was.
And develop surgical techniques to remove
sympathetic nerves
in research animals like cats.
With nerves reaching out to nearly every
major organ in the body,
it's no surprise that it's often claimed,
that the sympathetic nervous system is
necessary for survival.
After all, most animals that underwent
these extensive procedures to
remove the sympathetic system actually
died.
However, once the surgical techniques
became good enough some cats actually did
survive, but barely.
They were never really quite the same.
They were no longer chasing mice, and
seemed to be perpetually lounging around.
They were able to live only within the
safety of the lab.
It seems that somehow that this system,
this, this work-stress system
is absolutely crucial for us animals to
survive in the real world.
So thanks to the work done by Walter
Cannon and
countless other researchers, we have come
to a pretty good understanding of
what this work system is and how it
functions in the body.
So let's take a quick step backwards
before we dive into the stress response.
Here we are looking at a bird's eye view
of the nervous system in each of
its various components.
The nervous system is academically at
least divided into two parts.
The central nervous system which includes
the brain and
the spinal cord, and the peripheral
nervous system which includes all of
those nerves below the neck.
Within the peripheral nervous system we
further distinguish between the somatic
nervous system and the autonomic nervous
system.
Generally speaking you can think of the
somatic system as the nerves that
control the muscles you have voluntary
control over, and
the autonomic nervous system controls
things in your body that more or
less you don't really have to think about,
like your internal organ functioning.
We'll be honing in on the autonomic
nervous system and
its two component parts, the sympathetic
system and the parasympathetic system.
The autonomic nervous system is charged
with the task
of managing the internal balance of the
body.
And the sympathetic and parasympathetic
nervous systems are often presented
as opposing systems that keep the body in
balance.
When the sympathetic branch of the nervous
system is turned on,
it's called an increase in sympathetic
tone.
And your body mobilizes resources,
prepping access to energy, and
preparing bile tissues to fight or to
flee.
In contrast, when the parasympathetic
branch of the nervous system is turned on,
it's called an increase in parasympathetic
tone.
And your body turns on the rest and digest
system, which is what it sounds like.
It allows the body to rest, restore, and
prepare for the future.
You've been practicing for
your big music recital or for your big
sporting event for many months.
And the time has finally come for
you to step onto the stage, step onto the
field and perform.
Thousands of eyes are on you.
Everyone you know and care about is there.
You feel nervous, stressed, anxious.
What if you fall apart?
What if your body doesn't remember what to
do?
What, what if you fail?
In these types of moments, you'll have
activated your stress response.
Your heart rate and your breathing rate
goes up.
You start getting goosebumps, your pupils
dilate, and
you start shaking, sweating and you get
tunnel vision.
The body has set off a cascade of
responses to prepare for the stressor.
Many other things that you can't see are
also happening, like the release of stress
hormones, increase in blood pressure, and
an increase in metabolic rate.
Stress will also turn on your brain
systems in a different way,
increasing access to memories from the
past where you felt the same type of
stressful feeling before.
At the same time that all of these
responses are turning on,
there is a cascade of body functions being
turned off.
The general theme here is that,
whatever isn't absolutely necessary to
deal with the stressor, is turned off.
In other, more scientific words, systemic
restorative functioning is turned off.
So what does that mean?
Well digesting food, for example, is
really an energetically costly process.
And being chased by a lion is probably a
bad time to use energy to
break down that food.
Activating the stress response decreases
things like digestion, and
tightens sphincters to decrease your need
to poop or to pee, and
inhibits unnecessary or momentarily
unnecessary functions like sexual arousal.
Slow thought, or energy intensive rational
thought is also inhibited.
But really, stress needs no introduction.
As a human being, you are already very
familiar with the stress response.
You've been dealing with stress and how it
feels in your body for your entire life.
Behind me is a road map of where we are
going to head in
the next four mini lectures.
We're going to talk about how each of
these systems plays a major role
in getting you stressed, sprinkling in
some practical tips along the way.
When it's all said and done, you will have
a comprehensive understanding of how
the brain and the systems of the body work
together to create this stress response.
Let's take our deep dive into stress and
see what we find.