[MUSIC]
>> So Dr.
Benson, would you show me how to elicit
the relaxation response?
>> Be delighted to do so.
First of all, if you're doing this for
medical reasons,
check with your health care professional
first so that she or he knows that you're
doing this because you might have to alter
medications, or what have you.
You can have either a secular repetition
or a religious one.
Secular terms could be the number one.
The word peace.
The word calm.
The word gentle.
Religious, if you're Roman Catholic, hail
Mary, full of grace.
And if you're Spanish, Portuguese, or
Italian, that becomes Ave Maria.
So, which would you prefer, a secular or
religious term?
>> I'll choose a secular route.
>> And which word, or sound?
>> I'll say calm.
>> Calm.
Okay, now sit up and close your eyes, and
relax all your muscles starting with your
feet.
Your calves.
Your thighs.
Shrug your shoulders around.
Shrug your shoulders and roll your head
and neck around, great.
Okay, now sit at ease without movement and
breath slowly.
And each, and breathe slowly, and each
time your breath is coming out,
say silently to yourself, we're calm.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And you're going to find all sorts of
other thoughts coming into your head.
They are normal.
They are natural and should be expected.
But when they occur, don't be upset, but
simply say, oh well, and come back to
calm.
Now I'm going to let you do this for three
or four minutes, at the end of which time
I'll ask you to keep your eyes closed but
to start thinking your regular thoughts.
But now, on your out breath, calm.
[MUSIC]
Other thoughts, oh well.
And back
to calm.
[MUSIC]
Now keep your eyes closed.
Keep them closed.
Let's start thinking your regular
thoughts.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now slowly, slowly open your eyes.
[MUSIC]
>> Was that at all
difficult for you?
>> It was, at times, difficult to come
back to the word.
But it was not a, not difficult in another
sense.
Did you notice any changes in yourself
doing so.
>> Definitely.
I feel mellow right now, and, I notice
when you gave me
the instructions to stop focusing on the
word and to think my own normal thoughts,
it was almost like I had to reach out and
pull them back towards me again.
>> Did you notice any change in your
breathing?
>> Definitely.
I slowed down.
>> Slowed down.
And, you're on camera now.
You even look younger than you looked
before because your facial musculature,
and that.
>> Is relaxed.
>> And, it, most people now have a sense
of well-being that you didn't
have when you were doing the interview
where we were talking before.
Is that part of what you're experiencing
now?
>> It's truly incredible.
>> Things are okay.
[MUSIC]