Welcome back to the Physiology of Stress.
It's finally time to put our knowledge
together to explore some
practical tools that have the potential to
totally change your life for the better.
We've had an exciting journey through the
body and
it's time to put that little cherry on top
of our physiology knowledge.
We're going to talk about three tools
commonly used to manage stress that
have been developed and well studied by
researchers.
However, keep in mind that these
techniques are just
a sampling of the unlimited number of ways
to engage your restorative physiology.
Throughout the course of human history,
we've used tools like yoga, meditation,
prayer, breathing techniques and others to
engage this restorative system,
that the techniques are, are designed to
engage.
Now we've chosen to highlight these few
particular tools because they
have a lot of scientific support, but
that doesn't mean that there aren't a lot
of equally great tools out there.
You have to decide which tools and
approaches work best for you.
The most important thing is that you have
a set of tools that work for
you, and that you use them.
So let's see what these tools are and
the research that makes the argument that
they're worth using.
Returning to our favorite science of
stress model,
remember that science gives us this
nuanced understanding of stress.
Stress is absolutely and undoubtedly an
awesome thing to have in our lives.
It prepares us to confront life's
obstacles by mobilizing the resources we
need to become version 2.0 of yourself.
A you 2.0.
Now at the same time we know that chronic
stress is really harmful to our health.
And as a result, there are two primary
ways we
can think about having a better
relationship with stress.
The first thing, is that we can leverage
stress to work for us better.
That means increasing the amplitude of our
stress response to make the biggest,
baddest, most constructively stressed
version of ourselves that exists.
The second thing we can do is when it's no
longer helpful to be
stressed it's absolutely necessary that
we transition ourselves from a state of
stress to recovery.
So that we avoid trailing off into the
chronic stress danger zone.
We're going to go into depth on three
tools that have scientific support.
Two will be in the second category of
going from stress to recovery.
And because having tools to make that
transition are so
important, that's what we're going to
start with.
So the first of these category two
techniques that we'll touch on is called
freeze frame, and it's what I refer to as
an emotional approach to stress reduction.
It was created by emotion experts at
HeartMath Institute here in California.
We did an abridged version of this
technique to engage our bodies before
discussing the physiology of the
parasympathetic nervous system.
And you can see me over here doing it.
Freeze frame involves calling attention to
your heart and
solar plexus in activating a positive
feeling.
It's a technique that is designed to
replace an unproductive emotion
with a more productive one.
Similar to all the tools that influence us
to enter into that state of recovery,
it's associated with many of the benefits
of increasing vagal tone.
Remember, use of this tool can actually
train you to increase vagal tone and
to reap all of the associated benefits.
One important thing to note is that this
tool is not the same
as relaxing and taking nap.
It involves attention, and focus to the
steps mentioned beside me.
On the right side of the screen you can
see the major steps to
the freeze frame technique.
At the end of this section,
we will have the opportunity to meet one
of the developers of this technique,
and learn directly from him how to use it.
So what's so great about the research at
HeartMath Institute is that it
is explore the lesser known but equally
important aspect of the stress experience.
Emotion.
As much as the feelings of anxiety, and
frustration, or
hopelessness are part of our experience of
stress, it's kind of amazing that many
academic conversations about stress leave
the emotional aspect out of the picture.
An entire field of research in emotion
physiology is exploring and
teaching us that the autonomic nervous
system is intimately involved and, and
responsive to emotional states that we
experience.
Work done at HeartMath demonstrates that
positive emotional states like
appreciation increase heart rate
variability and
create a more optimal heart activity that
is
disrupted during negative emotional states
like frustration.
They've found that positive emotions like
compassion and appreciation lead to
a smooth, ordered, rhythmical pattern in
heart rate variability.
As you can see beside me, the graph
depicts what you would,
you know, what would happen to you if you
were to employ the freeze frame strategy.
The jagged, incoherent activity is
characterized of
how the heart behaves when you're feeling
frustrated.
And the smooth, sine like waves,
are characteristic of how your heart
behaves when you feel appreciative.
You'll see when he does this technique on
me,
how crazy it is that changing how you feel
actually changes how your heart behaves.
And that by engaging your physiology with
breathing, and
making a sincere effort to shift your
emotional state,
it can have a profound impact on how you
feel and how you behave.
It only takes a few minutes and it can be
really effective right before
taking a test, mid-fight with your
boyfriend or
girlfriend, or as a way to freeze the
frame amid some
other stressful episode where you might
need access to better mental resources.
Psychologists, military leaders and
personal coaches all over the world employ
this technique to shift your
physiology into a more productive state so
that you can perform better.
The bottom line is they use it because it
works.
The second technique is called the
relaxation response.
I call it a cognitive stress reduction
approach because it attempts to
reduce stress by breaking the train of
everyday thinking.
Minimizing those thoughts, that lead to
provoking the stress response.
Click.
Created by doctor Herbert Benson of
Harvard Medical School, the relaxation
response is a stress reduction tool
inspired by Eastern traditions, and
designed as a synthesis of the most
important elements of historical and
religious calming strategies.
Dr. Benson is truly an inspirational
physician and
is a pioneer of mind/body medicine.
The relaxation response incorporates a
restful position of deep breathing with
a mental device, a mantra to focus on, and
a passive attitude.
It's important to note that like freeze
frame, the relaxation response is not
the same as just lying down and taking a
nap, or just relaxing in some other way.
It's an intentional more like meditation
technique
that produces benefits by breaking the
train of your scattered thought.
The research demonstrates there are
immediate short term and long term
benefits associated with activating the
vagus system with the relaxation response.
Since the very first studies that Dr.
Benson performed on transcendental
mediators in the late 1960s, one of
the hallmark features of the relaxation
response is reduced oxygen consumption.
A general quieting of metabolic activity.
A reduction in oxygen consumption and
carbon dioxide elimination is indicative
of what, what we call a hypometabolic
state.
Sleep, hypnosis, hibernation, those are
all examples of a hypometabolic state.
Because hypometabolism is a pretty rare
state for
the body to be in, the ability to
cultivate a tool that can
place the body into a quieted state is
actually pretty profound.
However, what is most unique and exciting
about the work done by Benson, and
his team at Harvard are the genomic
studies done in the most recent years.
Researchers looker at differences of the
level of genetic expression between groups
of people who regularly evoke the
relaxation response and those who don't.
They've also done prospective experiments,
experiments looking at
genetic changes in individuals who
underwent two months of relaxation,
relaxation response elicitation training.
And lo and behold, what they found was
that the consistent use of
the relaxation response not only changed
your physiology in the short term,
it actually changes the body at the level
of genetic expression.
Changes in genetic expression clustered
around the four main focus hubs that
you can see beside me.
It's incredible that changing your
behavior can change the genes your
body expresses.
And even more incredible to hypothesize
what those long term benefits might be.
You can see the four hubs beside me.
The first, improved mitochondrial
function.
It's a gene, they're gene sets linked to
energy metabolism like
the electron transport chain in your
powerhouse mitochondria cells, and
they're up-regulated in the long term
group of the relaxation response.
Its hypothesized to increase oxidative
efficiancy and to reduce or,
or to quite oxidative stress.
The second hub was insulin secretion
pathways and they were up-regulate,
up-regulated, which has the potential for
positive implications for a lot of chron,
for a particularly important chronic
disease, type two diabetes.
The third hub, was a reduction in an
immune marker, NF-kappaB,
which reduces systemic stress by slowing
the inflammatory cascade.
Which means reducing inflammation in the
body.
The fourth major hub was that there were
changes in
genetic clustering around telomere
stabilization.
For those of you who aren't quite familiar
with what telomeres are,
telomeres are the repetitive sequences
that protect the genetic material at
the end of the chromosome.
Long telomeres are associated with healthy
cells that can continue to reproduce.
Whereas shortened telomeres are associated
with chronic stress and with aging.
The relaxation response seems to have a
stabilizing effect
on telomere degradation.
Slowing aging, at the genetic level.
We're going to have an incredible
opportunity to speak with Dr.
Benson himself in the expert section of
this module,
where he will show us personally how to
best elicit the relaxation response.
Freeze frame, and the relaxation response
are two scientifically supported
techniques to help you transition from a
state of stress to a state of recovery.
If there is any place to start working on
your relationship with stress,
it's right here in that number two
category.
They have all sorts of benefits in the
short term, and
the long term that scientists are just
beginning to sort out.
The good news is, is that by using them,
you can cultivate increase to vagal tone,
and activate the recovery system that we
have within us to reduce our
exposure to chronic stress.
The good news is, is that the better you
become at transitioning to states of
recovery after stress, the better your
good stress will become.
Indigated, indicated here by the 1 bubble,
the best thing you can do to increase good
stress is to decrease the bad stress.
Reducing chronic stress allows your body
to perform its natural housekeeping
functions so that the various systems of
the body will respond optimally,
like a well-serviced car, during times of
stress.
But it doesn't stop there.
There are other things you can do to
optimize your stress response as well.
Sleep, diet and exercise all promote your
body's ability to
initiate a strong respo, a strong
fortified stress response.
Remember, in the right situation being
stressed and
physically aroused makes our lives better.
So we can also leverage science to amplify
the stress response.
In addition to general health, scientists
have discovered another clever way to
optimize the stress response by doing this
fancy thing called cognitive reappraisal.
It's a way to make your stress response
work for you better.
Really, cognitive reappraisal isn't
anything more complicated then just
changing your belief about stress.
And in this case, it's changing your
belief to a more positive one.
All right, so here's what the researchers
did.
They brought the students who were
preparing to take the GRE.
And the GRE's a really important graduate
level exam.
And they brought them into the lab to take
a pretend GRE test.
They split them into three different
groups.
One group was the suppression group.
And they were instructed that, if they
were to feel a feeling of anxiety,
which makes sense that they would feel it,
they're pretty nervous about taking this
important test.
If they feel an anxiety they were
instructed to do their best to
push that feeling of anxiety away.
A second group was a control group and
they were, they were left on their own,
they weren't instructed to do anything but
take the test.
And the third group, they were the
cognitive reappraisal group.
This special third group was instructed to
believe something different about stress.
They were told by the researchers that
stress was a good thing and
that in fact that when they feel anxiety
that means
their bodies are mobilizing resources in
order to be able to, to succeed.
And that in fact, that stress and anxiety
will help you perform better on the GRE.
Kind of miraculously, the cognitive
reappraisal group that
went through the intervention to develop
this more positive belief about stress,
actually performed better on the practice
test.
But the real crazy thing is,
is that same group performed better on the
real test many weeks later.
A follow up study explored a physiological
explanation for
how these amazing results could be
possible.
As we know, stress is a physical change in
the body.
So how is it possible that a belief could
make a difference?
Well, it turns out that when we change our
belief about what stress means,
it not only improves our performance and
lowers anxiety, but it actually changes
the stress response itself.
The reappraisal group showed similar
patterns of stress arousal as the other
groups, with one notable exception.
In comparison, the reappraisal group was
characterized by a reduction in
peripheral vasoconstriction.
The other two groups, they got stressed
and their vessels tightened up, but
the reappraisal group had vessels that
were more open and relaxed.
Skinny tight vessels provide a lot of
resistance to blood that's
trying to get through.
But relaxed, more open vessels allow more
nutrient rich blood
to flow through the body.
What you believe about stress matters, if
you want to be a high performer.
So it's about time that you gave yourself
the gift of a little belief makeover.
Preliminary research here at Stanford is
suggesting that this particular
intervention might be particularly helpful
for those of you who are anxiety prone.
Next time you're stressed, particularly if
it's a time you're about to perform,
say, a speech or step onto a sports field
or take a test.
Remember, that feeling of anxiety is your
body's way of telling you that it's
transforming into version 2.0.
And its ready to do one heck of a good
job.
This brings us to the end of our
incredible journey
exploring stress together.
We have gained a deep appreciation and
understanding of the role
the vagus nerve and parasympathetic
nervous system play in our daily lives.
And what we can do to cultivate it's
activation.
We've learned, that with just a little
vagal tone, we might just be able to be
more compassionate, more healthy, and
function at a higher level.
While I encourage you to experiment with
these techniques I don't want you
to forget that there are many other great
ways to activate this vagus system and
to optimize the relationship between
stress and recovery.
So don't be discouraged if these
particular techniques don't resonate with
most, most strongly with you.
The best tools are the ones that work for
you, whatever those tools are.
The bottom line is,
is that you need good strategies to
transition to recovery after stress.
And, you would be remiss to not capitalize
on how to make stress work for
you instead of against you.
I really hope you found this module to be
instructive, practical and entertaining.
Though stress is one of the biggest
challenges we face today,
as individuals and as a s, s, society, the
exciting thing
is that you now have the knowledge and the
tools to take responsibility for
making your life better and manage stress
in a more productive way.
I'm so excited to see what it is that you
choose to do with this knowledge.
It's been a great honor to speak with you
about a topic that I'm so
passionate about.
I extend my deepest gratitude for
the opportunity to share our experience
with you today.
Science is awesome!
Let's continue to use it and make our
lives better.