Welcome back to the Physiology of Stress.
It's finally time to put our knowledge
together, to explore some
practical tools that have the potential to
totally change your life for the better.
We've had an exciting journey through the
body, and
it's time to put that little cherry on top
of our physiology knowledge.
We're going to talk about three tools
commonly used to manage stress that have
been developed and well-studied by
researchers.
However, keep in mind that these
techniques are just a sampling of
the unlimited number of ways to engage
your restorative Physiology.
Throughout the course of human history,
we've used tools like yoga, meditation,
prayer, breathing techniques and others,
to engage this restorative system that the
techniques are, are designed to engage.
Now we've chosen to highlight these few
particular tools because they
have a lot of scientific support.
But that doesn't mean that there are a lot
of equally great tools out there.
You have to decide which tools and
approaches work best for you.
The most important thing is that you have
a set of tools that work for you.
And that you use them.
So let's see what these tools are and
the research that makes the argument that
they're worth using.
Returning to our favorite science stress
model,
remember that science gives us this
nuanced understanding of stress.
Stress is absolutely and undoubtedly an
awesome thing to have in our lives.
It prepares us to confront life's
obstacles by mobilizing the resources we
need to become version 2.0 of yourself.
A you 2.0.
Now at the same time we know that chronic
stress is really harmful to our health,
and as a result there are two primary ways
we
can think about having a better
relationship with stress.
First thing, is that we can leverage
stress to work for us better.
That means increasing the amplitude of our
stress response to make the biggest,
baddest, most constructively stressed
version of ourselves that exists.
The second thing we can do is when it's no
longer helpful to be stressed.
It's absolutely necessary that we
transition ourselves from a state
of stress to recovery, so
that we avoid trailing off into the
chronic stress danger zone.
We're going to go into depth on three
tools that have scientific support.
Two will be in the second category of
going from stress to recovery,
and because having tools to make that
transition are so
important, that's what we're going to
start with.
So the first of these category two
techniques that we'll touch on is called
Freeze Frame, and it's what I refer to as
an emotional approach to stress reduction.
It was created by emotion experts at
HearMath institute here in California.
We did an abridged version of this
technique to engage our bodies before
discussing the physiology of the
parasympathetic nervous system.
And you can see me over here doing it.
Freeze frame involves calling attention to
your heart and
solar plexus and activating a positive
feeling.
It's a technique that is designed to
replace an unproductive emotion with
a more productive one.
Similar to all the tools that influence us
to enter into that state of recovery,
it's associated with many of the benefits
of increasing vagal tone.
Remember, use of this tool can actually
train you to increase vagal tone, and
reap all the associated benefits.
One important thing to note,
is that this tool is not the same as
relaxing and taking a nap.
It involves attention, and focus to the
steps mentioned beside me.
On the right side of the screen,
you can see the major steps to the Freeze
Frame technique.
At the end of the section, we'll have the
opportunity to meet one of the developers
of this technique, and learn directly from
him how to use it.
So what's so great about the research at
HearMath Institute is that it has explored
the lesser known but equally important
aspect of the stress experience: emotion.
As much as the feelings of anxiety and
frustration, or hopelessness,
are part of our experience of stress, it's
kind of amazing that many
academic conversations about stress leave
the emotional aspect out of the picture.
An entire field of research in emotion
physiology is exploring and
teaching us that the autonomic nervous
system is intimately involved and, and
responsive to emotional states that we
experience.
Work down at HearMath demonstrates that
positive emotional states,
like appreciation, increase heart rate
variability and
create a more optimal heart activity that
is
disrupted during negative emotional
states, like frustration.
They found that positive motions like
compassion and appreciation lead to
a smooth, ordered, rhythmic pattern in
heart rate variability.
As you can see beside me, the graph
depicts what would happen to you
if you were to employ the Freeze Frame
strategy.
The jagged incoherent activity is
characterized of
how the heart behaves when you're feeling
frustrated.
And the smooth, sine like waves are
characteristic of how your
heart behaves when you feel appreciative.
You'll see when he does this technique on
me,
how crazy it is that changing how you feel
actually changes how your heart behaves.
And that by engaging your physiology with
breathing and
making a sincere effort to shift your
emotional state,
it can have a profound impact on how you
feel and how you behave.
It only takes a few minutes and
it can be really effective right before
taking a test.
Mid-fight with your boyfriend or
girlfriend, or
as a way to freeze the frame amid some
other stressful episode where you
might need access to better mental
resources.
Psychologists, military leaders and
personal coaches all around the world
employ this technique to shift your
physiology into a more productive state so
that you can perform better.
The bottom line is they use it because it
works.
The second technique is called the
relaxation response.
I call it a cognitive stress reduction
approach because it
attempts to reduce stress by breaking the
train of every day thinking,
minimizing those thoughts that lead to
provoking the stress response.
Created by Dr. Herbert Benson of Harvard
Medical School, the relaxation
response is a stress reduction tool
inspired by eastern traditions and
designed as a synthesis of the most
important elements of historical and
religious calming strategies.
Dr. Benson is truly an inspirational
physician, and
is a pioneer of mind-body medicine.
The relaxation response incorporates a
restful position of deep breathing,
with a mental device, a mantra to focus
on, and a passive attitude.
It's important to note that like Freeze
Frame, the relaxation response is not
the same as just lying down and taking a
nap or just relaxing in some other way.
It's an intentional, more like meditation
technique,
that produces benefits by breaking the
train of your scattered thought.
The research demonstrates that there are
immediate, short term, and long term
benefits associated with activating the
vagus system with the relaxation response.
Since the very first studies that Dr.
Benson performed on transcendental
meditators in the late 1960s, one of the
hallmark features of the relaxation
response is reduced oxygen consumption, a
general quieting of metabolic activity.
A reduction in oxygen consumption and
carbon-dioxide elimination is indicative
of what we call a hypometabolic state.
Sleep, hypnosis, hibernation.
Those are all examples of a hypometabolic
state.
Because hypometabolism is a pretty rare
state for
the body to be in, the ability to
cultivate a tool that can
place the body into a quieted state is
actually pretty profound.
However, what is most unique and exciting
about the work done by Benson and
his team at Harvard are the genomic
studies done in the most recent years.
Research has looked at differences of the
level of genetic expression between groups
of people who regularly evoke the
relaxation response and those who don't.
They've also done prospective experiments
looking at genetic changes in individuals,
who underwent two months of relaxation,
relaxation response elicitation training.
And lo and behold, what they found was
that the consistent use of
the relaxation response not only changed
your physiology in the short term,
it actually changes the body at the level
of genetic expression.
Changes in genetic expression clustered
around the four main focus hubs that
you can see beside me.
It's incredible that changing your
behavior can change the genes your
body expresses.
And even more incredible to hypothesize
what those long term benefits might be.
You can see the four hubs beside me.
The first, improve mitochondrial function.
It's a gene, they're gene sets linked to
energy metabolism like
the electron transport chain in your
powerhouse mitochondria, and
they were up-regulated in the long-term
group of the relaxation response.
It's hypothesized to increase oxidative
efficiency, and to reduce,
or, or to quiet oxidative stress.
The second hub was insulin secretion
pathways.
And they were up regulate, up regulated,
which has the potential for
positive implications for a lot of,
for a particularly important chronic
disease, type two diabetes.
The third hub, was a reduction in an
immune marker, NF kappa B,
which reduces systemic stress by slowing
the inflammatory cascade,
which means reducing inflammation in the
body.
The fourth major hub was that there were
changes in
genetic expression clustering around
telomere stabilization.
For those of you aren't quite familiar
with what telomeres are,
telomeres are the repetitive sequences
that protect the genetic material at
the end of the chromosome.
Long telomeres are associated with healthy
cells that can continue to reproduce.
Whereas shortened Telomeres are associated
with chronic stress and with aging.
The relaxation response seems to have a
stabilizing effect
on telomere degradation.
Slowing aging at the genetic level.
We're going to have an incredible
opportunity to speak with Dr.
Benson himself in the expert section of
this module,
where he will show us personally how to
best elicit the relaxation response.
Freeze Frame and the relaxation response
are two scientifically supported
techniques to help you transition from a
state of stress to a state of recovery.
If there is any place to start working on
your relationship with stress,
it's right here, in that number 2
category.
They have all sorts of benefits in the
short term and
the long term that scientists are just
beginning to sort out.
The good news is, is that by using them
you can cultivate increased vagal tone,
and activate the recovery system we have,
within us,
to reduce our exposure to chronic stress
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The good news is, is that the better you
become at transitioning to states of
recovery after stress, the better your
good stress will become.
Indicated, indicated here by the, the one
bubble,
the best thing you can do to increase good
stress is to decrease the bad stress.
Reducing chronic stress allows your body
to perform its natural house keeping
functions so that the various systems of
the body will respond optimally,
like a well serviced car during times of
stress, but it doesn't stop there.
There are other things you can do to
optimize your stress response as well.
Sleep, diet, and exercise all promote your
body's
ability to initiate a strong res, a strong
fortified stress response.
Remember, in the right situation being
stressed and physically aroused makes our
lives better So we can also leverage
science to amplify the stress response.
In addition to general health scientists
have discovered another clever way
to optimize this stress response by doing
this
fancy thing called cognitive reappraisal.
It's a way to make your stress response
work for you better.
Really, cognitive reappraisal isn't
anything more complicated than just
changing your belief about stress.
And in this case it's changing your belief
to a more positive one.
Alright.
So here's what the researchers did.
They brought the students who were
preparing to take the GRE.
And the GRE's a, a really important
graduate level exam.
And they brought them into the lab to take
a pretend GRE test.
They split them into three different
groups.
One group was the suppression group.
And they were instructed that, if they
were to feel a feeling of anxiety,
which makes sense that they would feel it.
They're pretty nervous about taking this
important test.
If they feel any anxiety,
they were instructed to do their best to
push that feeling of anxiety away.
A second group was a control group and
they were, they were left on their own.
They weren't instructed to do anything but
take the test.
And the third group, they were the
cognitive reappraisal group.
This special third group was instructed to
believe something different about stress.
They were told by the researchers that
stress was a good thing and
that in fact, when they feel anxiety that
means
their bodies are mobilizing resources in
order to be able to succeed.
And that in fact, that stress and anxiety
will help you perform better on the GRE.
Kind of miraculously, the cognitive
reappraisal group that
went through the intervention to develop
this more
positive belief about stress actually
performed better on the practice test.
But the real crazy thing is,
is that same group performed better on the
real test many weeks later.
A follow-up study explored a physiological
explanation for
how these amazing results could be
possible.
As we know, stress is a physical change in
the body.
So, how is it possible that a belief could
make a difference?
Well, it turns out that when we change our
belief about what stress means,
it not only improves our performance and
lowers anxiety, but it actually changes
the stress response itself.
The reappraisal group showed similar
patterns of stress arousal as the other
groups with one notable exception.
In comparison, the reappraisal group was
characterized by a reduction in
peripheral vasoconstriction.
The other two groups, they got stressed,
and their vessels tightened up.
But the reappraisal group had vessels that
were more open and relaxed Skinny type
vessels provide a lot of resistance to
blood that's trying to get through.
But relaxed more open vessels,
allow more nutrient enriched blood to flow
through the body.
What you believe about stress matters if
you want to be a high performer.
So it's about time that you gave yourself
the gift of a little belief makeover.
Preliminary research here at Stanford is
suggesting that this particular
intervention might be particularly helpful
for those of you who are anxiety prone.
Next time you're stressed, particularly if
it's a time you're about to perform say,
a speech, or step onto a sports field or
take a test, remember that feeling of
anxiety is your body's way of telling you
that it's transforming into version 2.0.
And it's ready to do one heck of a good
job.
This brings us to the end of our
incredible journey,
exploring stress together.
We've gained a deep appreciation and
understanding of the role the vagus nerve
and parasympathetic nervous system play in
our daily lives,
and what we can do to cultivate its
activation.
We've learned, that with just a little
vagal tone, we might just be able to be
more compassionate, more healthy, and
function at a higher level.
While I encourage you to experiment with
these techniques,
I don't want you to forget that there are
many other great ways to activate this
vagus system, and to optimize the
relationship between stress and recovery.
So don't be discouraged if these
particular techniques don't
resonate the most strongly with you.
The best tools are the ones that work for
you, whatever those tools are.
The bottom line is,
is that you need good strategies to
transition to recovery after stress.
And you would be remiss to not capitalize
on how to make stress work for
you instead of against you.
I really hope you found this module to be
instructive, practical, and entertaining.
Though stress is one of the biggest
challenges we face today
as individuals and as a society, the
exciting thing is that
you now have the knowledge and the tools
to take responsibility for
making your life better and manage stress
in a more productive way.
I'm so excited to see what it is that you
choose to do with this knowledge.
It's been a great honor to speak with you
about a topic that I'm so
passionate about.
I extend my deepest gratitude, for
the opportunity to share our experience
with you today.
Science is awesome.
Let's continue to use it and make our
lives better.