Welcome back to the physiology of stress.
I hope you enjoyed the activity that ended
our last session.
It's one of my favorite tools that we will
touch on in detail in the tools video
of this module.
It's pretty incredible how a simple five
minute activity can have
such a profound impact on the body.
Especially when we repeat it over time.
We're going to take our experience of
activating the parasympathetic nervous
system with this technique to guide us
through an understanding of
the physiology occuring in our bodies.
The knowledge gives us the opportunity to
shed light on how our bodies work and
the possibility of using this information
in real life.
So let's get curious and find out if any
of this science can make our life better.
So now we're going to take a deep dive
into the physiology of
the parasympathetic nervous system.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As we talk about parasympathetic
physiology,
I want you to keep this model in the back
of your mind.
We're learning about how your body's
intrinsic capability to relax and
recover is so useful and powerful, which
becomes the foundation for
the tools we learned about in the last
video module on management tools.
Of course, when stress is helpful, we
want to maximize our stress response,
which you can see in that pointy triangle
there.
But, when it's no longer productive to be
stressed,
it's absolutely necessary to activate our
parasympathetic system and transition
to a state of recovery, where we minimize
our exposure to chronic stress.
So what happens to our physiology when the
parasympathetic branch is activated.
What changes did you experience at the end
of that last video?
Not surprisingly, the parasympathetic
response is basically everything that
stress isn't.
When you engage in a short activity, your
heart rate slowed,
your rate of breathing went down, and your
pupils constricted.
Continued parasympathetic activation means
that metabolic activity is quieted.
There is reduced oxygen consumption, and
an increase in digestion and
other restorative functions.
Other great things happen to your body
too.
Your thinking often becomes clear, and
it's easier to manage relationships and
social situations with increased
parasympathetic tone.
So generally speaking, it's accurate
enough to think of the sympathetic and
parasympathetic branches as opposing ends
of a single dial.
Like when we exercise.
When we exercise, initially there's a
removal of the parasympathetic brain.
And as exercise intensity increases at
around 100 beats a minute or
so, the sympathetic system starts kicking
in.
That same coordination happens in the
opposite direction,
when we sit down to pray or meditate at
the end of a long day.
That sympathetic system previously
activated from daily stressors turns off.
And the parasympathetic system starts to
turn on.
But in reality the autonomic nervous
system is more nuance than just on or
off, as depicted by the diagram next to
me.
It allows for something called the mutual
coactivation as well as coinhibition.
Of the sympathetic and parasympathetic
branches.
What this means is that it's possible to
have both branches activated at
the same time.
As it occurs, for example, during sexual
arousal.
In the case of sex, the parasympathetic
system is activated to help direct blood
flow to, well, you know where, and the the
sympathetic system.
Well, its job is to bring the body to
orgasm when the time is right.
So, you can see that's an example where
both systems are turned on at
the same time.
Perhaps less interesting, but still an
important example is that
both branches can be turned off at the
same time.
Which happens during anesthesia, for
example.
The respective branches can work in
concert with another as well as
independently of each other.
So how's this recovery happening in the
body?
The vagus nerve, or the 10th Cranial Nerve
deserves a big thanks for its hard work.
It's often overshadowed by the glory of
the stress response.
But this complex vagus nerve is incredibly
important to our survival and
is often wildly under-appreciated.
The Vagus isn't just a single bundle or
pathway.
It's a complex, multi-branched,
bidirectional nerve system.
What this means is that the vagus nerve
can be highly specific in the organs that
it innervates, and that includes afferent,
meaning ascending sensory nerves,
as well as efferent, meaning descending
motor nerves.
The activity of the vagus nerve can be
measured indirectly through a measure we
call heart rate variability.
As it turns out, while you may be used to
a heart rate monitor that
averages heart rate over 15 or more
seconds.
Heart rate actually varies upwards of 10
to 20 beats,
up and down as we breathe in and out.
Breathing in inhibits the activity of the
vagal communication with heart,
causing the heart rate to increase.
And breathing out restores the vagal tone
and heart rate is reduced.
This variance in beat to beat interval is
known as heart rate variability and
as an indicator of vagal tone, or how
turned on does vagus system is.
So now that we know all about the vagus
nerve and
parasympathetic tone, let's uncover some
of the benefits that
researchers have associated with greater
vagal activations.
It turns out that increasing baseline
levels of vagal tone could do you a lot of
good in life.
For example, research suggests that higher
levels of
vagal tone might just make you more
compassionate.
Work at Stanford Center for Compassion,
Altruism, and Research, and
other similar organizations around the
country, have been exploring empathy and
compassion from a scientific prospective.
And vagal tone seems to be right at the
heart of it.
The studies beside me can be further
explored in the resource section at
the end of our section materials.
They suggest that vagal tone is an
indicator of higher compassion and
offering of social support.
It seems that somehow, the vagus plays a
role in creating an internal environment
that leads to a greater propensity to give
and to, to care for others.
Research also suggests that having more
vagal tone and
being more compassionate isn't just good
for those people around you.
Compassion is associated with improved
immune function and
is a predictor of overall health and well
being.
So it seems pretty good for you too.
If that isn't enough, it seems that
cultivating increase of vagal tone in
loving kindness meditation can improve
your ability to manage negative emotions,
and cause an upward spiral in positive
emotions,
making you feel better more often
throughout the day.
So here's the, the moral of the compassion
story.
The study of compassion is a budding field
with increase of vagal tone,
right at the center of the science behind
the benefits.
Compassion could be leading to better
immune function,
better social connection, and more
positive feelings.
I want all of those things in my life.
Give me some of that.
If I've done my job well, you're in awe of
the complexity and high degree of
influence that the vagus nerve has on our
physiology and on our lives.
How incredible is it that our bodies had
developed such a adversital and
effective system for dealing with so many
of our problems.
Lucky for us our journey doesn't end at
the appreciation of
the science behind parasympathetic nervous
system.
We're going to use this science to make
our lives better.
I'm looking forward to seeing you in the
grandaddy of them all,
the stress management tool section.