The last module, space.
I was going to try to describe what it's
like to be in space.
But, who am I kidding?
I've never been to space.
Although, if given the opportunity, I'd
take it.
Do you think that Stanford would foot the
bill for that one?
Mm, probably not.
Anyway, I realized that it would be much
more compelling to
hear from astronauts who have actually
been to space,
thus the radio app episode that you
hopefully listened to.
In the resources, I've also linked an
interview with Chris Hadfield,
who last year returned from a 144 days in
space
commanding the International Space
Station.
He's the famous Canadian astronaut who
performed and
filmed a version of David Bowie's Space
Oddity while in space, in a space station.
The music video's great.
It gave you the chills.
But I'm kind of geeky about space.
I've provided a link to the music video in
the resources as well.
But since 20 million of you have already
seen it, it may not be new to many of you.
With the environmental conditions covered
by the experts,
I'm just going to talk about one little
physics thing, and then the physiology.
I'll make it short and sweet for this
final module.
Microgravity is a condition where people
or objects appear weightless.
It's sometimes referred to as zero
gravity, but
that's technically not accurate.
A small amount of gravity can be found
even way out in outer space.
Gravity is the natural force of a
celestial body that
pulls an object towards its center.
The bigger and closer the object, the
stronger the gravitational force.
The reason things appear weightless with
our astronauts on
the International Space Station is not
because they're so
far from Earth that the gravitational
force is minimal.
The space station is in orbit only about
200 to 250 miles from Earth.
Gravity there is about 90% of what we feel
here on Earth.
So, what gives the astronauts the
appearance of weightlessness is
that they're actually in constant free
fall.
But, everything else around them is also
in constant free fall.
Here's an example.
If you were to jump off a cliff and
released a ball in front of you at the
same time, and
I'm not recommending that you do this, the
ball would appear to be floating in
front of you, traveling at the same speed
as you plummeted to your death.
In the vacuum of space, objects fall at
the same speed because there's no air
resistance to slow any objects down.
Since everything is falling at the same
speed,
it gives the appearance of floating.
So if the space station is falling, why
doesn't it hit the Earth?
Well, it is also traveling really fast,
about 17,500 miles an hour.
It's trying to go straight because of its
momentum, but
Earth's gravity is pulling it down.
The result is the compromise of the blue
orbit line illustrated to my right.
It's moving at a speed that matches the
Earth's surface curve, so
it never makes contact.
If it were to go too fast, it would spin
out of the orbit.
If it were to go too slow,
it would be pulled towards the Earth, hit
the Earth atmosphere, and burn up.
Fortunately, for
the moment, it's right in that sweet spot
of speeds to keep it in orbit.
What do you think?
Is it possible to achieve microgravity on
earth?
You probably already have.
Have you ever driven a bit too fast over a
hill and
it feels like the car is lifting off the
ground?
Ever been on a roller coaster?
Descended in one of those really,
really fast express elevators that leaves
your stomach in your throat?
You're experiencing a brief moment of
weightlessness in those moments.
Also, NASA's figured out a way to achieve
slightly longer
weightlessness here on Earth.
They've created a special research plan
affectionately referred to
as the Vomit Comet for obvious reasons.
It can simulate microgravity by flying
repeated parabolas in the sky.
A schematic is pictured to me on the left.
As the plane goes up, it experiences
almost two Gs, but
when it reaches the top of its arc and
starts to come down, people in
the plane experience a microgravity
environment for 20 to 30 seconds.
Astronauts train in the Vomit Comet,
researchers and
students do short experiments, and
directors in Hollywood use it to film
parts of their space movies.
What do you think?
Should that be the next Corey story video?
Barf bags for everyone, especially me
apparently.
Let's talk about what happens when
human bodies are exposed to the almost
complete vacuum of space.
We'll start with an easy one.
As you can imagine, breathing is a
problem.
It's not that gas exchange doesn't occur,
it's that it occurs in the wrong
direction.
Because gases travel from high to low
pressure, and
there's essentially no breathable oxygen
in space, the oxygen would be
sucked out of your blood through your
lungs into space very rapidly.
It would take about nine to 12 seconds for
that deoxygenated blood to get from your
lungs to your brain,
causing you to blackout, and a couple more
minutes after that for you to die.
So my practical tip for you on this is,
keep your spacesuit on.
An even greater incentive to keep your
spacesuit on, and in working order,
is the risk of rapid decompression.
Because of the low ambient pressures,
without a spacesuit, fluids and
gases in the body begin to expand,
causing the body to blow up to about two
times its size within about ten seconds.
Also, rapid evaporate of cooling will
cause frost to
form on any exposed body fluid, mouth,
lungs, sweat, etc.
Rapid decompression is not pretty, so
let's move on.
Weightlessness leads to Space Adaptation
Syndrome, or space sickness.
No longer having the force of gravity
pulling on your
inner ear vestibular system really messes
with you.
About 70% of astronauts experience nausea,
vomiting, and
vertigo for up to 72 hours upon arriving
at the space station.
Eventually, the body resolved the conflict
between what is seen and
what is being felt, and will start to
relearn which way is
up based on visual queues, like where your
feet are.
Fluid shifts happen rapidly in
weightlessness.
As we discussed in the G force module,
your body's used to
having your blood pulled down toward your
feet with the force of gravity.
We have a lot of mechanisms that allow us
to keep that blood flowing back up to
the heart and brain.
But what happens when all of sudden, that
force is reduced, like in negative Gs,
or removed, like in weightlessness?
The fluids get redistributed back up to
our heads and
torsos, causing bulging neck veins, puffy
moon faces, and nasal congestion.
When I was asked to consult with NASA, it
was for
a research study that was trying to come
up with exercise countermeasures or
equipment that would help with the fluid
shift problems in weightlessness.
The study design was to have volunteers
lie in a bed for one month, with 15%
head down tilt to mimic the effects of
fluid shifts that take place in space.
The participants were allowed to get up on
one elbow to eat three times a day,
but that was it.
Exercise, reading, talking, whatever had
to be done in the head down position.
Can you imagine for a month?
That's real dedication by the
participants.
Apparently, that was not the first time
NASA had used a protocol like that, and
they had no problem getting volunteers.
So, thank you to all of you out there who
contribute to science in so many ways.
Fluid shifts don't just give you a puffy
face.
The fluid shifts can impact vision by
changing the shape of the eyeballs and
pressing on the optic nerve.
It can also affect possibly taste,
although we don't know why, and balance.
Sleep is also challenging in space.
Circadian rhythms are disrupted by the
90-minute day-night cycle in space.
And nausea and soreness can make sleeping
difficult.
It's also light and loud on the space
station with lots of fans and
motors running.
Also, when sleeping in weightlessness,
there is no plopping down on the mattress.
You may as well sleep on the ceiling.
An astronaut just needs something to clip
themselves onto so they don't float away.
But many choose to sleep in secured
sleeping bags in
the private sleeping room.
Sleep dee, sleep deprivation is a major
problem for
astronauts, and sleeping pills are the
second most common drug tape,
taken on the Space Station after pain
medication.
Once you've been up in space for a while,
you have to worry about some
long-term changes that may not be good for
your health.
First, let's talk about muscle.
Muscle is responsive to the forces placed
upon it,
that's why strength training causes muscle
hypertrophy.
So, look at me standing here.
I'm not really doing anything except
keeping myself from falling down.
But in order to do that, I'm using muscles
in my feet,
my calves, quads, torso, abdomen, and
back.
Now imagine me floating around this, the,
the space station all limp.
I'd no longer be using any of those
muscles.
As a result, when astronauts go up in
space, their muscles atrophy quickly.
If they don't exercise regularly, they can
lose up to 20% of their
muscle mass in key areas like back and
legs within five to 11 days.
Yikes.
Bone is also laid down in the direction of
mechanical stress.
But when weightless, all of a sudden,
there's minimal skeletal loading.
Bone can be lost at a rate of
approximately 1.5% per month,
if counter measures aren't taken.
After a three to four month trip into
space,
it used to take astronauts two to three
years to re,
regain their bone mass after returning to
Earth, and some never fully recovered.
Also, all the calcium that is taken out of
the bone during the resorption or
breakdown period ends up circulating
around the body,
causing calcification of other tissues and
sometimes kidney stones.
The fluid shifts that occur in space can
lead to orthostatic intolerance, or
an inability to maintain blood pressure
when you get back to Earth.
The body has forgotten how to keep the
blood up against gravity,
that can result in fainting, if an
astronaut stands for ten minutes or more.
This problem is exacerbated by a loss of
total fluid in space of about 20%,
because there's no need to maintain blood
pressure to
the same degree without any gravity to
overcome.
The orthostatic intolerance can last for
weeks upon returning to Earth.
And finally, a big concern about prolonged
space travel and
exposure is increased radiation.
Without the protective field of the
Earth's atmosphere,
astronauts in space station are exposed to
radiation from cosmic rays at
a magnitude of ten times that of Earth.
Unfortunately, high dose radiation damages
bone marrow, lymphocytes, and other immune
markers, resulting in suppressed immunity
and increased susceptibility to viruses.
This can cause a spread of infection
within normally healthy populations in
the confined living quarters in space.
Increased radiation has also been linked
to higher incidences of
cataracts in astronauts.
It also may put astronauts at greater risk
of diseases like cancer,
since we know radiation can cause
chromosomal mutations.
Also, rare strong solar flare events,
which are unpredictable, could
give a one time massive dose of radiation
to astronauts that could be fatal.
The issues associated with muscle and bone
loss have gotten better over the years.
Everyone is now well aware of the problem,
and
it can be at least partially prevented
with regular exercise while in space.
Astronauts are required to exercise at
least two hours a day to prevent bone and
muscle wasting.
But special exercise equipment is
required.
If you think about it, you can't just run
normally on a treadmill in space.
One stride forward, and you'd be floating
around the room.
So as you can see in the picture to my
left,
astronauts are secured down with bungee
cords, so there's some resistance to
their running that both loads the skeleton
and holds them onto the treadmill.
But, who's to say you have to run on the
floor in space?
Or, for that matter, which is the floor
when you're in space?
It's all the same.
Astronauts on the space station also have
access to important resistance
training equipment.
Even exercising two hours a day isn't
enough to keep the astronauts from
losing bone.
So engineers are in the process of
experimenting with new compression suits,
pictured to my right.
They're designed with built in elastic
strap that go from the shoulders down to
the ankles.
The hope is that the constant loading of
the spine and
legs will keep some of the bone and muscle
wasting from taking place.
And as far as I can tell from the picture,
the suit has the added benefit of making
the astronauts look like superheroes.
Put on the suit, add a cape, go to outer
space.
You're good to go, Wonder Woman.
And finally, some of the discomfort,
nausea and insomnia can be treated
by various medications, such as pain meds,
anti-nausea patches, and sleeping pills.
As we get closer to the possibility of a
man trip to Mars and
doing more distance space exploration,
research into the risks,
health consequences, and counter measure
becomes more critical.
The trips of longer duration would magnify
many of
the risks described in this module.
Despite all the risks and possible
disasters I listed in this module,
many people would still jump at the
opportunity to go into space.
There's a majesty and a mystery about
space.
A feeling of something bigger than
ourselves that unite us for our faith and
our spirituality.
And the feeling that we're all connected
to each other and to the cosmos around us.
You get that sense of awe when you listen
to astronauts talk about their time and
experience in space.
I've included some of those links in the
resources section for you.
But you don't have to go to space to
experience that sense of awe.
I get it, when I look at your bodies, and
all your different shapes and
sizes, colors and ages.
We're all connected in the amazing
capacity of our
bodies to deal with the stresses that the
world can throw at us.
We've talked in this class about cold,
heat, altitude, stress, age, and
even outer space.
And through it all, we've seen how our
bodies not only adapt to survive but
to make us better and stronger.
Or as Corey likes to say, version 2.0 of
ourselves.
We've thrown a lot of information at you
in this class, and I hope you
will be able to use some of it to make
better and healthier choices in your life.
But even if you forget many of the details
over time, I hope a sense of
appreciation and respect for your body
will remain with you throughout your life.
Your body does so many things for you
every moment of every day.
Make sure you give it a few things back.
Physical activity, good nutrition, rest,
laughter and
gratitude, and of course, a little
environmental or
physical challenge here and there, just to
keep it interesting.
Thank you all for making this online
experience one that we'll never forget.
And I mean that in a good way.
We'll have one more weekly check-in posted
next week to say farewell.
But for now, bye.