I'm a bit sad because we've come to the
last of the sections.
I'm also really proud of you for making it
all the way to the end.
It's not easy to complete an online course
and you're almost done it.
Way to go!
This week we will be talking about
variable pressure environments,
g-forces, diving, and the microgravity of
outer space.
Except for maybe scuba diving, not a lot
of you out there have
probably experienced the environments that
we'll be talking about.
Raise your hand, how many of you have
flown a fighter plane?
Okay.
Not so many out there.
But in some ways, that's what makes this
section so cool.
It's unique.
Microgravity, I mean,
how many of you wanted to be an astronaut
when you were a kid?
Despite having three different topics,
this section will be our shortest of all.
After all, unlike aging, stress, or
altitude, there are no whole lot of
practical tips I can give you for when you
happen to be in outer space.
But the physiology is still fascinating.
And who knows, maybe someday, Mars will
just be a commuter flight away for
some of you younger folks out there.
That reminds me.
When I visited NASA in Mountain View to do
a little consulting work,
I walked by a door to a room that said,
Mars exercise physiology lab.
Wow.
I don't know
what was going on behind that door, but I
bet it was really interesting.
I think I want that to be my next business
card.
Anne Friedlander, Mars Exercise
Physiologist.
What do you think?
To my right is the outline for this
section.
You've already seen our vomiting
adventures in the skies, so
we'll start off by talking about how your
body deals with G-forces.
Then we'll move onto modules about diving,
and then onto space, the final frontier.
To boldly go where no man has gone before.
[LAUGH] Okay.
I think I just dated myself, but I've
looked at the age demographics for this
class, and more than half of you should
knew, should know what that comes from.
Yes?
Anyhow, we didn't have quite enough
funding to send Corey into space for
this project, but fortunately, Radio Lab,
my favorite radio show, did a great
episode called The Dark Side of the Earth,
that tells a thrilling story of what it's
like to be in space.
We've provided that link so you can listen
on your computer or
even better, download it onto your phone
and listen to it while you go for a walk.
Then come back to Module 5, we will
explain the physiology of space.
We had a lot of fun filming the story for
this section.
As you saw from the video, some of us had
a bit more fun than others.
Let's put it this way.
You didn't see me getting out of the plane
saying,
that was probably the coolest thing I've
ever done.
[LAUGH] But it was a once-in-a-lifetime
experience, I hope, and
really fascinating.
Even if you have never flown,
you may actually experience G-forces more
often than you think.
Let's take a look.
The force of gravity will pull on a free
falling object causing it
to accelerate towards earth at 32 feet per
second.
If we move quickly in a particular
direction we can create our
own acceleration that can be quantified in
multiples of gravity, or G-forces.
The arrows on the man to my right
represent the direction of forces felt, so
the opposite that the person is moving.
If we go up rapidly, then the additional
force pulling down on us adds to
gravity and its called positive G-forces,
depicted as the plus Gz on the man.
Because of the aerodynamics in a plane,
pilots experience positive G-forces not
only when they accelerate upward, but
also when making a sharp turn because the
plane tips to its side.
It's sort of like putting water in a
bucket and spinning it around.
The centripetal acceleration holds the
water in
the bucket just like that same force
pushes down on the pilot into the seat.
If you experience twice the acceleration
of gravity, you're pulling 2Gs.
3 times, 3 Gs, etc.
If you were to dive down suddenly in a
plane,
then the force is subtracted off gravity,
and it's called a negative G.
You can also have side to side G-forces,
like when you go around
a corner quickly in a car on a non-banked
road, or forward and back, acceleration.
The Gx to my right, Like when taking off
in a plane or
testing your 0 to 60 acceleration in your
new Toyota Camry.
The main problem we face with G-force is
that the Gs force blood into parts of our
body away from the direction of movement.
We'll talk more about the implications of
that blood movement a bit later.
Before we had airplanes, there was nothing
that could accelerate the human body fast
enough to create the feeling of G-forces,
so it wasn't until World War One,
when pilots started mysteriously fainting
in the air,
that doctors started investigating the
phenomenon.
As planes got faster and started changing
directions more rapidly in the air,
things started getting worse for the
pilots.
People started talking about the G-force
phenomenon and
it was estimated that humans could
withstand a maximum of
18 Gs because that was air force pilots
seemed to be able to survive in a crash.
It was also the force that the cockpit was
designed to withstand upon impact.
In the mid 1940's, an Air Force physician
named John Stapp began to suspect that
maybe it wasn't the G-forces that was
killing the pilots in the crash, but
the crushing of the cockpit.
So he set out to understand the physiology
of G-forces hoping to
improve cockpit safety.
He started strapping dummies into
self-built rocket powered, a self-built
rocket powered sled called the Gee Whiz,
that was capable of accelerating along
a track very rapidly and then coming up to
a ridiculously abrupt stop.
Eventually, the dummies weren't good
enough and
he started strapping himself into the
sled.
As explained in a Nova article by Peter
Tyson, quote, by the late summer of
1948 Stapp had done 16 runs himself and
withstood up to 35 Gs.
He lost dental fillings, cracked a few
ribs and
twice broke a wrist, but he survived.
But that wasn't good enough for Stapp.
He decided that he really needed to know
what pilots would
experience when they ejected at high
speeds.
So he built an even faster sled, the Sonic
Wind.
In his article, Tyson goes on to give a
description of
Stapp's final run in December of 1954 in
the Sonic Wind.
He says quote, Sap deci,
Stap decided to pull out all the stops,
firing nine solid fuel rockets.
His sled accelerated to 632 miles per
hours in five seconds,
slamming him into two tons of wind
pressure.
Then came to a stop in just over one
second.
A witness said it was absolutely
inconceivable anyone could
go that fast then just stop and survive,
but Stapp did.
He was just barely conscious.
The jolt burst nearly ev, nearly every
capillary in his eyeballs.
He was blinded, but his retinas did not
detach.
He slowly regained his bearings.
And within a day, his vision was back to
normal.
During that final run, he experienced a
record breaking 46.2 Gs.
For an instant, his 168 pound body had
weighed over 7,700 pounds.
Now that is dedication to science.
I don't think we're going to take Corey
quite that far.
A link to the Nova article where I got
some of this story is in
the resource section at the end.
Sometimes we handle G-forces better than
others.
Let's look at why.
As we said a couple of slides ago,
G-forces are related to acceleration, so
change in speed, not speed itself.
That's why you feel like you're being
pressed back into the seat when you
accelerate onto the freeway, but
not when you're cruising along steadily at
65 miles an hour.
Also, how g-forces affect your body is
dependent on
the magnitude of acceleration, the
duration, and the direction.
Magnitude is obvious.
The more the acceleration, the more you
feel on your body.
But duration is key as well.
Plop down in a chair, it can be up to 10
Gs.
A cough can be up to 3.5 Gs.
A firm slap on the back can be 4 Gs.
Also, think about how much Stapp could
survive for
an instant, greater than 46 Gs.
But he'd never be able to handle that,
close to that, much, for sustained time.
You NASCAR fans out there probably know
that NASCAR drivers sus,
sustain two to three Gs around the corners
of the racetrack.
That isn't that much for a couple turns,
but
it's very physically demanding during a
three to five hour race.
Your body has to do a lot of work to
constantly fight that pressure and
keep the blood going up to your head and
not pooling in the lower extremities.
So whether you think NASCAR is a sport or
not, it does require physical fitness.
And then there's direction.
Forward and back, or horizontal, is not as
hard on us as up and
down direction, that can create major
blood flow and pressure issues.
There's a roller coaster in South Africa
that claims to
give riders a 6.3G experience.
Riders can tolerate that because it is in
the forward direction, and is only for
a couple of seconds.
There's a link to the resources that shows
you that roller coaster as well.
And what do you think is harder for us to
sane, sustain?
Going up quickly, so positive Gs.
Or, down quickly, negative Gs.
Negative Gs are harder.
We're used to walking upright and
fighting the affects of gravity on blood
flow anyway.
So we have some mechanisms like tightening
up our vessels, or
clamping down our muscles that help get
blood back up to our hearts and brains.
On the other hand,
we don't usually deal with a problem of
too much blood rushing to our heads.
There's not a lot physiologically that we
can do about it.
That's why we get so red faced and
puffy when we hang upside down on the
jungle gym.
So what are the tolerable limits for
sustained G-forces in humans?
Depends on a number of factors, but a
normal person is thought to be able to
tolerate between four and five positive Gs
and two to three negative Gs.
Fighter pilots both because they are
preselected to be able to
sustain high G's and because they train to
get used to them,
can sustain eight to nine in the positive
direction but
again only about two to three in the
negative direction.
We just don't have a lot of tolerance for
blood rushing into our heads.
With G-suits pilots can still get to about
eight or
nine but they can sustain them for longer.
A G-suit pictured on this handsome young,
yet small,
man to my right, [LAUGH] pressurizes the
lower body to
keep blood from pooling away from the
brain when the G-valve is activated.
So the suit senses some change in
G-forces.
The suit is easier, but not quite as
effective as maintain the butt clinch or
G strain maneuver that you saw instructor
Jad Dennis talk about in the story video.
For the G strain you tighten down your
lower body and compress your diaphragm
against a closed globus to increase blood
pressure and volume in your core.
Which, by the way, is something that I
completely forgot to do as I was trying to
figure out how to fly the plane.
And we know what happened to me sadly.
For training, physical fitness is
important in order to
withstand the repeated pressures that are
put upon pilots.
Weight training of the lower body and core
that increases the forces that pilots can,
pilots can develop when needed for the G
strain, or hook maneuver, is critical.
With regular exposure, pilots have some
circulatory and
heart changes that allow them to maintain
blood pressure, and
the G strain maneuver just becomes
automatic for them.
With the G suit, good hook maneuver, and
regular flying,
a high-end pilot can maintain nine Gs for
around 30 seconds before passing out.
By the way, here's a little factoid for
you.
The famous Blue Angel Navy pilots
regularly pull high Gs, but
they can't wear G-suits because they
stabilize their flying arms on their legs.
Their flying maneuvers are so tight,
within 18 inches of each other's planes,
that they
can't risk the suit automatically
inflating to counter a G-force, and
thus moving their arms at all, which could
cause them to clip the next plane over.
It's amazing precision.
Now the challenges of G-forces.
First on the list, tunnel vision and grey
out.
Blood flow to the eyes ceases before blood
flow to the brain, so
your vision gets affected as an early
warning sign.
Vision is lost from the outside in because
the peripheral vision is weaker in
humans with the greatest number of photo
receptors in the center and
lowest on the edge.
A grey out occurs when a person is on the
verge of fainting.
Vision fades and light and color reduce to
a gray washed-out blur.
There'll often be a loss of peripheral
vision and
a sort of tunnel effect, which is caused
by a drop in blood pressure to the brain.
G-LOC, or
G Loss of Consciousness, is the next step
as more blood drains from the head.
Basically, there's not enough oxygen to
sustain metabolism of the brain.
Normally, if you're on the ground and you
faint, it causes you to fall over,
thus getting more blood and oxygen back up
to your brain.
It's a bit more problematic if you're
flying an F-16 at 1,500 miles per hour, or
2,400 kilometers per hour.
Next is the wobblies, G-induced vestibular
dysfunction, GIVD, which results
from force migration of crystals into the
posterior semicircular canal of the ear.
It gives a false sense of angular motion
which leads to dizziness, nausea, and
swir, a swirling sensation.
Do you remember when Corey first got out
of the plane?
He was wobbling all over the place,
because he had done some seriously radical
maneuvers up in the air.
It took about five or ten minutes to
recover from that.
Nausea can come from the wobblies, and
Corey did almost get sick as we were
walking back to the airport.
But for those of you who got, get motion
sickness, you know that nausea can also
come from a disconnect between what your
eyes are seeing and your ears are feeling.
Some researchers believe that the throwing
up response is because that sort of
disconnect and confusion in the brain,
before we had cars and trains and
planes, used to be associated with eating
a toxin.
So your body is trying to purge you of
that toxin.
You also can experience nausea when
recovering from G-LOC or
even when blood drains temporarily from
your head.
If any of you have fainted, you know that
nausea frequently follows.
Your brain does not like to be without
blood flow.
Okay, but here's the question.
Why does motion sickness get worse with
age?
Or does it?
I have lots of friends who used to love
roller coasters and
now can't ride them with their kids
without hurling.
I've seen TV episodes depicting this
dilemma for parents.
I used to be a maniac when it came to
rides at the county fair, and
yet I vomited in the plane for this story
video.
So what is it?
Some people theorize that as we get older,
fluid in the ears get thicker, so crystal
stick out of place more.
Maybe it's just that we are not used to
throwing ourselves around as much, so
we get out of practice.
Clearly our pilots from our Air Force
combat adventure were no
spring chickens and they weren't having
any trouble at all, but they still fly for
a living so they're used to it.
Anyway, I looked, but haven't found a
satisfactory answer.
So, if any of you bright people out there
have an idea about aging and
motion sickness, I'd love to hear it.
Moving on.
Retinal damage can be caused by the
rupture of delicate vessels in
the eye with sudden backward motion.
This can lead to red-out, which is a
dangerous condition that
results from too much blood pressure in
the head and eyes.
Whereas positive G induced grey out or
blackout is usually only temporary,
negative G induced red-outs are especially
dangerous because they
can cause retinal damage and maybe a
precursor to hemorrhagic stroke.
The theory is that the red in the visual
field occurs not as a result of
blood flow to the eye, but as a result of
the blood filled lower eyelid being
pulled into the visual field as a result
of the negative Gs.
Last on the slide, long term effects.
The long term effects aren't too bad.
They include most commonly neck pain from
the constant strain and
pressure on the neck.
Also many pilots report bruxism, which is
grinding the teeth and clenching the jaw.
On the good side, there also may be a
beneficial outcome on bone density,
because of all that increased spinal
loading, with the high G-forces.
A 2001 study found that Australian fighter
pilots who routinely felt forces of
between two and six Gs experienced an 11%
increase in
bone mineral content of their spines over
the course of their training year.
Okay, that's it for this module.
If you want to see some pilots go through
their G-force training check out
the short video that I've inserted in the
resources.
It illustrates these concepts well
including the vomiting and
is fun to watch.
Next up, scuba and free diving, excellent.