When we go up in altitude, we experience
low pressures.
But when we go down underwater, we
experience high pressures.
Of course we increase the pressure a whole
lot faster when we dive underwater,
because water is almost 800 times denser
than air.
Underwater, it can be beautiful and
tranquil, but
it can also expose us to a whole new set
of challenges, including breathing.
That's a big one.
Temperature control, viability, and
boyensey.
There are are a couple of typical ways to
get under water and
we'll talk about each of them briefly.
First is scuba diving.
Where you bring your air with you and you
keep breathing under water.
The second is free diving, where you hold
your breath for
extended periods of time while your under
water.
Now even though the surrounding
environment can be the same between these
two types of dives, the stresses on the
body are quite different.
For example, when you scuba dive, you
continue to breathe, so
your lungs essentially stay the same size
as you go deeper and deeper.
In contrast, when you free dive as you go
down the pressure increases,
your lungs get squeezed becoming smaller
and
smaller because' there's no new air coming
in to balance that pressure.
As you can imagine the risks and
sensations are not the same between the
two sports.
In 1943, Jacques Cousteau and Emile Gagnan
invented the aqua lung, or
more commonly called the self-contained
underwater breathing apparatus.
Scuba.
Although not the first underwater
breathing device, it was the most popular.
And it revolutionized underwater
exploration.
Since then, there have been many advances
in the equipment but
even so, a well-equipped diver today can
still carry between 65 and
70 pounds of gear in the water.
The picture to my right shows the basic
equipment that you
need to deal with the underwater
challenges.
A wet or dry suit to deal with cold
temperatures, mask for
visibility, Fins for mobility.
Weight belt for buoyancy.
And of course, tanks and regulators for
breathing.
The tanks can be filled with compressed
ambient air, or
nitrox, which is a mixture of gas with
higher oxygen and lower nitrogen content.
Nitrox has the advantage of reducing the
risk of nitrogen narcosis, and
allows a diver to stay under water longer.
However, nitrox also increases the risk of
oxygen toxicity for given depth.
We'll talk more about that physiology
later.
Trimix tanks add a third inert gas to the
mix for deeper dives,
to limit the negative effects of both
nitrogen and oxygen under high pressures.
The breathing devices are usually
open-circuit, meaning the bri, the diver
breathes in from the tank and out into the
water, creating bubbles of the unused gas.
However, there's certain applications like
the military, for
example, where they don't want bubbles.
And they want to be able to stay down
longer.
In those situations, they use
closed-circuit breathing.
And that's an area that equipment
regulation is much trickier, and the CO2
produced by our bodies has to be carefully
scrubbed or removed, otherwise the diver
can start to hyperventilate and get
delirious while they're down underwater.
On the surface of the ocean, the pressure
is one atmosphere, or
760 millimeters of mercury.
As you descend deeper and deeper your body
experiences the continued pressure of
the one atmosphere plus the pressure of
the additional water above.
When you reach 30 meters or
100 feet the pressure that your body feels
is about four atmospheres.
There are a variety of things that happen
due to these increased pressures.
First relates to Boyle's Law which says
the volume of gas is
dependent on the surrounding pressure.
So as you go deeper air in the stasis and
sinuses and the ear canal get compressed
causing a feeling of pressure and pain.
Divers must equalize the pressure in these
spaces by variety of
methods like plugging the nose and blowing
lightly.
The change in pressure is not a problem if
you can equalize,
but if you have a cold or allergies that
prevent equalibration it can result in
a great deal of discomfort and even a
ruptured ear drum.
Also, air needs to flow freely in and
out of the lungs when changing depth,
especially when surfacing.
So never hold your breath.
As the pressure decreases on the way up
the air in the lungs can expand,
if not expel, and can either block
circulation or damage lung tissue.
Henry's Law says that the amount of gas
that dissolves into a solution is
dependent on the pressure of the gas.
Therefore as the pressure increases, more
nitrogen and
oxygen dissolve into the blood.
This can be problematic both while you're
underwater and
when you come back up to the surface.
We'll talk more about that on the next
slide.
The underwater environment presents a
variety of challenges.
As we talked about in the cold section,
cool water can draw heat away from the
body rapidly.
The cooler the water, the more thermal
protection is needed, and or
the shorter the dive should be.
If shivering starts, it's a warning sign
of approaching hypothermia and
the dive should be ended.
Although many people think of SCUBA diving
as a lazy floating activity,
it can be quite physically demanding.
Between hauling all that equipment around,
fighting possible currents,
and covering distance against the
increased resistance of water,
a fair amount of work needs to be done.
Caloric expenditure for recreational
divers has been estimated around 250 to
300 kcals for 30 minutes of a dive time at
let's say, 30 to 60 feet of water.
That's a low to moderate activity level
and
should be accounted for in pre and post
dive caloric intake.
Also remember that it's harder to keep
yourself warm if you run out of
calories and become hypoglycemic.
Numbers 3 through 5 on the list to my
right result from the increased amount of
gases dissolved in blood and tissue at the
higher pressures.
Oxygen is obviously critical to our
survival, but just like anything else,
water, chocolate cake [LAUGH], too much of
a good thing can cause serious problems.
Even if a diver has normal compressed air
in the tank, so at 20% oxygen,
at 130 feet, she will be breathing the
equivalent number of oxygen mol,
molecules per breath as 100% oxygen on the
surface.
With normal air is not usually an issue
until a diver reaches about 200 feet.
But with the higher O2 content of nitrox,
oxygen toxicity can happen at shallower
depths.
High systemic oxygen levels affects the
central nervous system.
It can cause tremors, seizures, ringing in
the ears, nausea and tunnel vision.
Can also lead to drowning or decompression
sickness if
a diver tries to ascend too quickly in
response to those uncomfortable symptoms.
Number four, high levels of nitrogen
dissolved in the blood can
interfere with nerve signalling, which can
cause nitrogen narcosis.
Nitrogen narcosis is also called rapture
of
the deep because the symptoms mimic
alcohol intoxication to a certain extent.
Euphoric feelings, lapses in
concentration, loss of good judgment.
Simply enjoying the feeling is a bad idea
and
can lead to risky decisions that can put
you and others at risk.
If you start feeling the symptoms coming
on, move to shallower water.
Decompression sickness is the more
dangerous cousin of Nitrogen Narcosis.
As the diver descends nitrogen not only
gets absorbed into the blood, but
also into the tissues like fat, tendons,
and cartilage.
As the diver goes back up, the nitrogen
reverses its path, and comes back out.
If the ascent is slow enough, nitrogen
comes out in
small bubbles that enter the bloodstream
and are harmlessly excreted by the lungs.
However, if the ascent rate is too fast,
large bubbles form that
can block circulation, compress nerves,
and form dangerous chemical reactions.
Sort of like opening a bottle of
carbonated soda, and
the bubbles suddenly appear.
You've probably heard of divers getting
the bends.
This is caused by one form of
decompression sickness,
where nitrogen bubbles block the small
vessels of joints causing pain that
can be partially relieved by bending the
affected joints.
First aid for decompression sickness
ranges from
breathing 100% oxygen taking aspirin,
drinking fluid and resting for
minor cases to full re-compression in a
chamber for more serious cases.
Re-compression causes the bubbles to
redissolve into the blood and
tissues until the person can be
depressurized more slowly.
Clearly the best treatment is prevention.
There are many dive tables and computers
that let divers determine how much
nitrogen is being absorbed, how long it is
safe to stay at certain depths,
how quickly they can come up, and how soon
they can either dive or fly again.
Think for a moment.
Why do you think divers need to be wary of
both subsequent diving and flying?
See if you can figure it out in the check
for understanding questions.
Okay, that's it for scuba.
Take a little mini break if you need it,
and
then come back for the exciting world of
free diving.