Free diving is a technique used with many
types of activities.
Basically, it means going under water
without the assistance of
any breathing devices.
Until the past century, it was the only
way to explore or
to retrieve items from under water.
Retrieving natural sponges, among other
treasured sea life,
was big business as far back as at least
Plato.
Currently, people free dive for recreation
and competition.
For recreation, proponents say it has
advantages over scuba that include
requiring less gear, no distracting sounds
or bubbles, cheaper, less prep time,
greater mobility under water, and less
risk of decompression sickness.
Free diving competition is complicated
with many categories ranging from static
apnea in the pool, basically how long you
can hold your breath without moving,
to extreme depth diving with and without
weights, with and without fins, et cetera.
The current depth record recognized by the
AIDA regulatory board in
the no limits category is 214 meters.
That's 702 feet.
Like with scuba, free divers experience
dramatic pressure changes as
they dive down to depths equivalent or
even lower than scuba divers.
Similarly, during the dive the
non-compressible spaces like the nose,
trachea, sinuses, ears, and even the mask,
need to be equilibrated.
However, the major difference is that with
scuba there is
air coming in from the tank to fill those
spaces as the gas gets compressed down.
In free diving there's no additional air
coming in except for
what is available in the compressible
spaces like the lungs.
As the diver goes down farther and
farther, the lungs compress both due
to the pressure and to give up additional
air to those other stiff spaces.
At great depths the lung can compress
below residual volume, which is the size
they'd be right now if you blew out all
the air you could possibly blow out.
As you can imagine,
it takes awhile to get used to the feeling
of extreme compression.
So how do people hold their breaths long
enough to descend 702 feet and
then make it back up again?
Well, training, which we'll see in the
next slide, but
they also get a little help from Mother
Nature.
If you're not going to keep breathing
you'd better A,
use as little oxygen as possible for
non-vital functions.
And B, provide your important tissues like
brain and
heart with as much oxygen as possible.
The diving reflex is very prominent in
water man, mammals like seals and
otters, but it exists to a lesser degree
in other mammals including humans.
When we put our face in cold water our
heart rate can drop 10 to 25%.
That's lowering our metabolic rate.
We are innately prepping ourselves for
a possible period when oxygen may be
limited.
How neat is that?
The cooler the water, the stronger the
response.
However, if our core gets too cold and we
start shivering, that negates the effect.
Unless of course we go so, we get so
cold that we actually go into a state of
suspended animation,
like kids falling into a frozen lake that
we talked about in the cold lectures.
Anyway, as part of a diving reflex we also
get peripheral vasoconstriction,
which directs more blood to the critical
tissues like the brain and the heart.
As the diver goes deeper and pressure
increases two other things happen.
First, the spleen, which serves as a
reservoir for
extra blood, contracts to release those
extra oxygen carrying red blood cells into
the circulation and to increase the sheer
volume of blood in the system.
Second, a very interesting thing called
blood shift happens to
prevent the increase in pressure from
crushing the chest cavity.
As a diver goes down his lungs get
compressed in
proportion to the pressure change.
At 50 meters the lungs are about one sixth
their normal volume.
It was thought by physiologists that free
divers would not be able to
go below 50 meters without crushing their
lungs and ribcages.
However, they were proved wrong in 1961
when it was accomplished by
free diver Enzo Majorca.
Researchers later discovered that the
blood shunted from a diver's extremities
by vasoconstriction, and from the spleen
finds a new home in the chest cavity,
occupying the space created when air in
the lungs is compressed.
The blood plasma fills the alveoli,
which are the small air sacs in the
diver's lungs where gas exchange occurs.
Plasma is essentially an incompressible
fluid.
So it helps prevent critical damaging
compression as the divers descends.
Wow.
Our bodies are freaking amazing.
Now the blood-plasma shift is not without
risks.
Although most is reabsorbed when the diver
leaves the high-pressure environment,
fluid and blood leakage into lungs can
occur.
But still, as a temporary emergency fix,
it's pretty sweet.
By the way, another less serious side
effect of the vasoconstriction and
spleen contraction is more central blood
volume, which increases blood pressure.
Your kidneys adjust to that by clearing
fluid.
So just like when people are in the cold
and have to pee more, so
too do divers say they haven't have an
urge to pee underwater.
In the longer term, it can also lead to
dehydration.
Free divers train to increase their breath
holding ability in several ways.
They work on reducing their metabolic rate
through relaxation techniques
like meditation.
Lowering metabolic rate decreases oxygen
requirements during the dive.
Second, divers practice building their
tolerance to CO2 in the blood.
The drive to breath is far more strongly
regulated by the build up of CO2 than
the lack of O2 in most people.
Therefore, if you can tolerate more CO2
buildup, you can hold your breath longer.
Training involves a rather uncomfortable
process where you try to
override that incredible urge to breath at
the end of holding your breath.
This works because even when you're forced
to take a breath by the CO2,
you still have a fair amount of oxygen
left in your lungs.
However, ignoring that primal survival
instinct to
breathe is both challenging and can be
dangerous.
Third, a person's lung capacity is
generally considered pretty stable and
highly correlated with chest size.
However, there are some things that divers
can do to expand the capacity of
their lungs.
Mainly involves working on the compliance
of the rib cage by
loosening connective tissue and packing
more air into the lungs.
The fourth box to my right is pre-dive.
Before dives experienced divers will pack
their lungs with more air called,
not surprisingly, lung packing, or less
obviously, glossopharyngeal insufflation.
Basically it involves inhaling a full
breath, then expanding the ridge cage,
rib cage, raising the shoulder blades,
tipping the head back, and
then forcing more into, air into the lungs
using a kind of gulping motion.
By the way, I'm not recommending that you
try it because it can cause lung damage if
you don't know what you are doing.
Anyway, experienced divers can increase
the volume of the air in
their lungs significantly by using this
technique.
And finally, we come to hyperventilation,
or forcing air deeply or
rapidly in and out of your lungs.
This is something we tend to do
instinctively when we are going to hold
our breath in the pool, for example.
It does help us hold our breath longer but
not for the reason you might think.
Contrary to what many believe it doesn't
increase the oxygen in
our systems significantly, but it does
decrease the CO2 in our blood.
Remember how I said earlier that our urge
to breathe is governed more by
high CO2 than low O2?
Well that applies here as well.
The problem is that if you blow off your
CO2 you can black out
underwater from lack of O2 before the CO2
response causes you to breath, so
it can be dangerous for divers to
hyperventilate.
Therefore, experienced divers may take a
couple of deep breaths before diving but
many will do no hyperventilation at all.
If you're interested in testing the
control of ventilation on yourself,
I've included a mini experiment for you to
try at the end of this section.
It's fun, requires only a brown bag, and
can be completed in a few minutes.
Try it.
It's a good illustration of physiology.
Fun with science.
Ready, last slide for diving.
Risk and safety for free diving.
One of the biggest risks is blackout.
In extreme diving and
competition, divers are trying to push the
limits of tolerance underwater.
If they misjudge and don't make it back to
the surface before their oxygen runs out,
they can black out underwater.
Usually this happens near the surface
because they haven't quite made it
all the way back up.
It's much more rare for
it to happen in deep water unless
something goes terribly wrong.
Because of the blackout risk,
free divers never go down without a safety
diver watching them continuously.
If the first diver passes out, the safety
diver will cover their mouth and
nose to prevent inhalation and
pull the diver to the surface; where they
will automatically start breathing again.
Second on the list is respiratory squeeze.
When tissues are squeezed in response to
the increasing pressure,
whether they're compressible or
non-compressible, they can get damaged and
start to leak fluid and blood.
Trachea, lungs, sinuses, nose, even the
space covered by the mask,
can all suffer barotrauma and damage.
Although getting squeezed rarely results
in permanent damage,
lung squeeze was thought to have
contributed to the recent free diving,
diving death of Nicholas Mevoli in
November 2013.
The good news is that free diving doesn't
have the same risks as sc,
scuba in terms of gas toxicity and
decompression issues.
The short duration underwater and minimal
available oxygen reduce these risks.
It takes significant training in order to
free dive long enough and
deep enough to get decompression sickness.
However, nitrogen can accumulate over time
in the blood during many repeat dives,
so appropriate precaution should still be
taken in that situation.
That's it for the physiology of high
pressure environments.
Next up, microgravity.
In some ways, you can't get more different
than talking about being
way underwater with high pressure to way
outerspace with minimal pressure.
On the other hand, the buoyancy that we
feel drifting underwater may be as
close as most of us can get on Earth to
feeling what its like to float in space.
The physiology however is very different.
So, watch module five to learn what
happens in our bodies in that wild and
crazy environment.
First though, get a feeling for what it's
actually be in space by listening to
the excellent Radiolab podcast story that
we linked in module four for
your listening pleasure.
Again, feel free to download the podcast
to your phone and
listen while you're taking a walk.
Enjoy, see you soon.