As humans, we exist within a varied and
changeable environment.
We are the most adaptable
animals on Earth.
Below your conscious awareness, trillions
of cells are communicating
to precisely adjust to the stresses
experienced daily, or
during a once in a lifetime extreme
adventure.
In this class,
you will experience different environments
through story videos and
learn what changes occur in your body at
the systemic and cellular level.
You will gain a new appreciation for
the amazing capacity of your body to adapt
and to survive.
You will learn practical tips that will
enhance your own personal experience and
physical performance in extreme
environments.
Your body is awesome.
Welcome to Environmental Physiology.
[BLANK_AUDIO]