Like subconsciously sort of thought of
being good at math like either you were or
you weren't and then coming to this class
I've recognized oh,
okay, that's kind of the mindset I've been
in my whole life and
I feel like that's the environment that
I've been in for like 18 years,
this class really allowed me to see that
that's really not how it is, and that.
I'm like working now to try ove towards a
growth mindset, so
that is sort of the big thing that I took
away.
>> My take away was mostly, because at the
beginning of the course I talked about and
like wrote a lot about how I hated math
and had, like,
absolutely terrible experiences and like I
don't take that back now, I like still
did, but I sort of have reframed them in
the sense of like that wasn't me, uh...
Being bad at math.
It was more in maybe the practices that I
encountered or
sort of getting stuck in a rut early on
and
having that dictate the rest of the course
of my mathematics education unfortunately.
But it's a new leaf so.
>> Great.
And said, now math.
And I can in with this fixed mindset just
like math itself,
you know, made me scared, confused.
And I was kind of in denial.
And even during our first few classes,
when we had to do math equations as
a class, the first time we did that I was
really, really, really scared.
And then these are my footprints through
the, this class, and
I feel like this is me after, and so
whenever someone mentions math now I'm
actually interested in what they're
talking about and what they have to say or
what they're going to say about math and I
feel like this class has made me want to
give math definitely a second chance, and
so...
I'm not dreading the math class that I
have to take at Stanford as much as
I I was before.
And I feel like I'm definitely leaving
this classroom with a growth mindset not
only towards math, but towards all other
subjects.
>> So when now when I meet difficulties I
don't feel like it's just the fact that I
don't have the talent, it's just that I
really have to persevere and
give it another shot.
>> Just reading about it maybe I wanted to
have a rough mindset.
That like seems like something I should
have, like I should work for,
so like learning that it was stronger in
like women and
minorities, which is like I'm both of
those, so like...
I realize like, I have to like, really
like, work at it to give it like,
to have the girls mindset.
And Just like, telling myself things like,
like not to blame myself that,
you know like, it's not like, It's not
something that's internal like,
something about me that like, makes me
struggle.
It's helps me to cope with
>> Difficulties a lot better.
>> So I guess I kind of did like a graph
of the different concepts and
how they related with me.
So like the bottom was my interest in
these different topics, and
I struggled with coming up with this
title.
I settled with mind blown [LAUGH] ...
Because I guess coming in like, for
me really realizing that I had like, a
really strongly fixed mindset.
And like, through this course like, being
able to like,
evaluate my past experiences and stuff,
that I'm still doing now.
It like, did a tremendous amount for me.
Especially like, this quarter
particularly.
>> And other things like which I race and
gender and stuff that I was like very
interested in and it like offered me a
whole new way to think about it.
>> Even if we're stuck, the opportunity to
see where you're stuck at and
what's preventing you from moving on is,
is better than just being stuck and not
knowing because then you can take a step
back and go okay, what's preventing...
And to me like, I'm taking a Math 19
course at Stanford and when I
first went in, I was like okay, well, I
was scared like Jackie from calculus and
I was like, I'm not sure if I'm ready for
this.
But taking a step back, even when I don't
understand what the professor is trying to
give, like teach us, I'm taking a step
back and
realizing that maybe it's not me who
doesn't Understand.
>> Maybe it's the way she's presenting
information and I
just need to take a step back and realize
that even if I'm stuck in this spider web,
because I know that I'm stuck and because
I know it's making me stuck I have
the ability to go and make myself unstuck
by say, by going to like TA session.
>> Alright guys, so this our, kind of
like, concept map in a way, so
we kind of
>> want to switch places with me?
>> Sure.
[LAUGH] So
we basically grouped it around that
there's a bunch of spider webs amongst our
midst and our mind and that's keeping us
from reaching our true potential and
with this class, it was kind of like Raid
in that It melted away these kind of
thoughts that we had to show that we can
really achieve not anything,
well probably anything, but a lot of
things.
[LAUGH] So it's kind of like fixed risk
growth.
How standardized testing effects your
learning.
Traditional learning and whether we have
bad teachers and mathematicians.
So, these are the spiders who are spinning
the webs around us