[MUSIC].
Welcome to the first course of How to
Learn Maths.
This course is for teachers, parents,
administrators, anyone who teach or
helps people learn maths.
But a similar class is going to be
released for
students in this school year, probably in
the fall or just after the winter break.
The version you will take is nowhere near
as, polished or zappy.
The student version is going to have some
different cool animations and
graphics and, different ways to engage the
students.
Different questions and interviews and so
on, but the ideas are going to be similar.
But I wanted to introduce you first to
those ideas.
So who am I?
At this point we have 20,000 people
enrolled in the course.
And I know some of you know me well, some
of you have read my book or
recent books or research work.
And many probably most of you have no idea
who I am.
So, I am a professor of mathematics
education at Stafford University.
But before being a professor and during
that time taught mathematics or
maths as we say in the UK you will hear me
say both math and maths in this course.
And I have taught maths at many different
levels.
So, in, in a city in London I taught the
age range of ages eleven to eighteen as we
do in England.
And I taught in Camden Town for
those of you who know the area in schools
with more than 250 languages spoken.
In the U.S.
I've taught maths to seventh and eighth
grade students and
also to undergraduates at Stanford so lots
of levels of math.
So, I've said that this course is for
teachers and parents,
that's because its not a course on how to
teach with the detailed ideas for
teaching although there are some of those.
But its really a course with short input
from me, most sessions are about 15 or
20 minutes long.
I think I said in the description they'd
be ten to 15 minutes but
I got a bit excited about the ideas that I
could show you.
And so, I'm going to show you some
research ideas that have
recently emerged that i think could be
really helpful for every body.
So, this course is some what experimental.
Your my first time in trying this and were
in it together.
I would welcome input on what is or isn't
useful to you.
Which of the ideas would be most useful
for
the student of course which is the one
I'll work on next.
I'd really like us to be a community of
learners and
the intro video that you can see on how
the course works.
Tells you about the forum and the other
places that we can connect, and
there's going to be some live chat
sessions to.
So, it's hard to design a class for such a
broad range of people.
But my hope is that even if I give you one
or
two key ideas, they can change something
you do in the classroom.
Or in interaction you can have with your
own children that may
actually make a huge difference for them
in their mathematical trajectory as
you'll find out from the ideas I'll show
you.
I'm going to be helped in teaching this
course by
some really interesting individuals who I
interviewed for the course.
And they're going to be sharing their
experiences of using maths out in
the world, and of, learning maths.
So, we have Michelle Sandburg who's a
pediatrician.
Sebastian Thrun, he designed the self
driving cars for Google.
He's also a Stanford professor, and the
CEO of Udacity, an online company.
Chris, who's a software engineer, at
Udacity.
Emily is a team leader at Apple, she leads
a team of engineers.
And Sophie is a film maker and they are
going to come in and
out of the course as you will see.
I have also introduced Carol Dweck who is
the guru on mind sets and
you will be seeing some of her.
So, it would really help me in moving
forward if I can collect some data from
you about who you are, your motives for
taking the course.
I am going to ask you now to stop and
complete the survey that I'll will direct
you to.
And this survey's really important so
I'd really appreciate if you would
complete this.