So in a moment we're going to think about
ways of making maths environments great
spaces for learning from mistakes.
But first I want you to think about, about
why mistakes are so helpful.
So, first, the first reason, pure and
simple is that the students learn most in
those moments, as I've said.
Now that means that it's really important
that they are given difficult,
challenging work, work that they can
access, that's going to be a challenge for
them, not work that they can get all
correct.
They may fe-, they may feel good about
getting work correct, but
as Carol Duex says, it's really cheating
them.
Of the important learning experiences, so
in a study I conducted in England I
followed students through two schools over
three years, and
in one of the schools students are taught
traditionally with demonstration and
practice and exercises and in the other
school students were given big
open problems to work on and solve, so
that's...
Approaches also known as PBL, or Problem
Based Learning.
They didn't really know how to solve them,
and sometimes they were given choices of
problems, they were encouraged always to
choose the ones that were difficult for
them, and then they just came up with
ideas.
So they were learning math to solve
problems, and if they needed some new
math methods The teacher would teach it to
them in the context of the problem.
So the typical method in classrooms is
students taught methods,
then they solve problems.
But in this classroom students got big
open problems, and
then they learned the methods to help them
solve them.
The students started at these two schools
at the same levels in maths achievement,
but the students at the problem based
schools,
ended up scoring at significantly higher
levels on the national exam.
And I was able to follow up and find the
students eight years later, and
they also ended up in more professional
jobs.
Now I wanted to know why.
That was really interesting to me.
And I interviewed many of the adults.
And when I interviewed them they talked
about how they'd really taken their
problem solving approach into their jobs
and lives.
And there's a paper in the reference
section that gives you more detail on all
of that.
But this is one of the young adults I
caught up with from the problem-based
school.
Talking about seeing a maths problem at
work.
So I asked him.
What happens if you don't know how to do
something with maths when you're in
your work?
And actually this was a young woman.
And she said, I, I keep on going until I
do.
Because I wouldn't.
If something is.
If I can't do it, then it annoys me.
I need to see something through, really,
until the end.
So I need to understand how I've done it.
And if I don't immediately understand it,
then I will just keep on going at it until
I do understand it.
So this student I'm going to quote from
now is actually,
this interview came from during their time
in school.
And for this boy, I asked them to reflect
on the exams and
how they got on with the exams.
Because they never did exam-like
questions.
They only did these big projects.
They exam like questions a few weeks
before the national exam ad, so
I asked them what happens when you go into
the exams.
And he said, I tend to go into them
anyways just thinking that I can do them.
Yeah, I there wasn't any time I thought,
well this is this, this is this,
I just worked it out from the knowledge
that I had.
So the students at Phoenix Park as I call
the school never as I said, they didn't on
exam [UNKNOWN] questions and they didn't
do tests either in the school.
So they only saw those kinds of questions
in the run up to the end of school at 16.
So both of these quotes I think you'll
probably agree show an attitude and
an approach to math That came about from a
learning culture in
which students were rewarded for
experimentation and for trying things.
Not for correct answers, but for having
ideas and trying things out.
And that meant that they did better.
They did better in the National Exams, and
they did better in life.
So, what did it take to get them to have
that wonderful confidence and
that persistence that helped them in life?
What it took was an approach to maths
learning that was about problem solving,
trying things out, uncertainty, making
mistakes and
feeling good about them, because teachers
valued them.
And as I said, the references on that
study are in the reference section.
So, this seems a good point to stop and
listen to some of the interview I
conducted with Carol Dweck, especially for
maths teachers and parents.
And after entry I'm going to get you to
write down some of
the key ideas that you heard and would
like to take further.
>> My first piece of advice is to present
math as somehting that is learned it is
a learned set of skills And that when kids
strugle or
get confused they should understand that
with more effort and practice and
help from teachers, they will continue to
learn from these skills.
math is typically seen by students as
something you have or
you don't, your good at it or your not.
That's not true.
Everyone can get better at math when they
work on it.
And we don't know how good you're going to
be in the future if you work on it now.
It's really important for teachers to show
students the progress they've made.
I think psychologically when a student is
confused or struggling,
it feels as if there's no progress being
made, as if they're back at square one.
So, a great thing for teachers to do is to
keep track of the progress that students
have made Over the whole year or over that
unit and to show it to them all the time.
You've learned these things before and you
will learn them again.
Also, I think it's important that when
teachers give
specific feedback to students, they show
the student how to use that feedback.
To become better at this kind of problem
and to be become better t math.
The basic idea is that you can learn to be
better and better at math and
the teacher's feedback should always be
conveying that message.
One thing that we're studying now is the
word Yet...
So if teachers say, no,
not quite yet, you're still learning,
you're on that learning curve.
You're just not there yet.
And I think it's a very hopeful message
that keeps that time dimension,
that learning curve in the picture.
I think we've made a huge mistake in our
child-rearing practices.
In our education system.
We tell kids they should feel good when
things were easy for them, and
they got everything right.
That's a cause for celebration.
Not in my book.
In my book it means, you're not learning
as much as you could.
If it was easy, well, you probably already
knew how to do it.
If you didn't put in effort, you weren't
growing those math neurons.
We should make kids feel cheated.
If the work is too easy for them, or
if the teachers gloss over their errors
and don't give them good feedback.
We should have kids asking for harder
work, wanting the challenging problems.
I want challenge to become the new comfort
zone, not easy.
Being the comfort zone.
I'll never forget at the beginning of my
research career when a little boy
said- should I start that again.
I'll never forget at the beginning of my
research career when a little boy said,
mistakes are our friend.
I was really struck by the beauty of that
message and all children should feel
that mistakes don't condemn them, mistakes
are not things they should flee from,
mistakes are a natural part of learning
And often give us clues about what we
have done wrong, what we need to learn,
and what we should do next.
There's a wonderful relatively new brain
imaging study where
they looked, it's actually an EEG study,
they looked at...
Fixed mind set brains solving problems and
making mistakes.
And when the student was in a fixed mind
set and
made an error, they fled from that error
as quickly as possible.
But when they looked at growth mind set
students making errors, they Focused in
on the error, they processed it deeply,
and they corrected it.
So they got it right on the next trial.
That's what we want.
We want an error to be something that you
glom on to, and learn from.
We have Found that teaching a growth
mindset is really, important for
math achievement.
Math is a,
a subject where a lot of kids have a fixed
mindset, and a lot of kids struggle.
Teaching a growth mindset,
makes them understand, it's not a fixed
trade it's a learned set of skills.
It particularly helps kids who are
laboring under
a negative stereotype to keep telling
themselves, I can grow my math brain.
Maybe my group didn't do as well
historically.
We weren't encouraged.
There were stereotypes, but I can grow my
math brain.
Through hard work, practice and good
mentoring.
In a fixed mindset, students hate effort.
Now for me, effort is the secret of life,
but for them effort means you're dumb.
They think if you're good at something you
shouldn't have to work hard.
Well one thing we know is that math makes
you work hard.
So teachers and parents should keep in
mind that in a fixed mind set,
those students are feeling dumb,
every time they struggle, every time you
tell them they got something wrong.
We need to change that whole framework,
that whole mind set because when you teach
a growth mind set They begin to understand
that effort is making them smarter and
mistakes are important parts of learning.
So, that effort needs to be experienced as
worthwhile,
enjoyable, productive.
I would say to a child who's getting a lot
wrong, and
getting discouraged, stop, let's see what
is it that you don't understand?
Let's analyze it, let's see what you need
to understand.
And also many students will go, I know, I
know, I know it, when they don't.
And how do you break through that?
So you could say well I think we're having
two different conversations.
You think we're having a conversation
about whether you're good at this or not.
But we're really having a conversation
about how some kids have had
experiences and opportunities in the past
to learn this and
some kids haven't had that opportunity.
I'm trying to give you that opportunity.
So take it away from evaluating ability.
And get it into opertunities to learn.