So, the big point is that tasks need to
give students the space to learn and
to see that maths means learning, not just
performing.
So, what does that mean?
Even a small change can make that
difference.
For example a really classic math problem
you'll see in textbooks is,
find the perimeter of this shape.
Now, if we changed that question to can
you construct two
rectangles with a perimeter of 26?
We change completely what the students do
and
the first one, they're coming up with an
answer.
And the second one, we're asking them to
make choices and
this invokes the thought process for
students.
They also change from thinking, I'm
finding the answer, to I'm think,
learning and growing.
Even though this is assessing the exactly
same mathematics..
Now, I wouldn't say that finding two
rectangles with a certain area is
a great task by any means but
it illustrates the process of moving, from
performing to growing and thinking.
So here is a great task that can be very
different depending on how it's presented.
And this illustrates my point as well I
think.
So first I'm going to present the task in
a way that is
oriented towards a growth mindset.
So in this task I'm going to ask you to do
you're going to,
you'll see case one, two and three of a
shape growing.
And my question for you that I want you to
think about and
write about is how do you see this shape
growing.
How would you describe the growth.