So an other amazingly effective
intervention in 2006
researchers asked this time seventh grade
students.
And they asked half of the seventh grade
students to write a short
written reflection of this beginning of
school about their personal values.
They did this at the start of seventh
grade.
They wrote about their values, and what
they meant to them, and
why they're important.
The other half, randomly, were asked to
write about values that other people had
and why they thought they might have those
values.
What was incredible from that was the
minority students who
completed the writing, so it's about their
own values,
closed the racial achievement gap over the
next year by 40%.
So, we know that students with the
greatest detachment from their schools and
the least trust that people believe in
them in a school environment.
That's minority students.
It can be girls in man's environments in
similar ways.
It's those students that gain the most
from these interventions that
really target social belonging.
So I asked you a moment ago to think of or
a while ago,
to think of what we could do about
stereotypes.
Now I want you to design something that's
more targeted.
I want you to draw from the ideas you've
just heard about messages and
writings tasks and think about something
you would do with a class of students.
You don't have to be a teacher to think
about this and do it.
It could be similar to what you've heard,
that you've adapted in some way.
But try and plan something of your own
that [INAUDIBLE] an activity that you
think would help in mathematics class.
Maybe you prefer a particular group, maybe
it's for all students.
Remember as you're doing this that the
researchers planned a really tiny
intervention, a one sentence or
a writing task to look at something very
targeted, what they call wise feedback.
That doesn't mean it's the best thing for
teachers to do as you design an
intervention.
You can think of anything at all.
So after you've written this, and maybe
you'll write a paragraph I think for this,
[INAUDIBLE] your paragraph's going to be
sent around to three other people who
are going to comment on it.
And you're going to get it, the comments
back.
And your going to get three other people's
paragraphs to look at.