[MUSIC].
Across the United States, students are
failing algebra, or
to put in another way, we are failing
students.
In urban districts, as many as 70% of
students are failing introductory algebra
classes and around 40% of students fail
the same class over and over again.
There's a reason for this situation.
Algebra, in most schools and definitely in
the vast majority of all textbooks,
is taught in a way that goes against all
the knowledge we've gained from
research about effective teaching and
learning of algebra.
Students are set off in the wrong path
from the beginning.
And many students and
adults will tell you algebra is just an
act of maneuvering meaningless symbols.
In algebra, as in the number and
arithmetic work that we've looked at,
students resort to memorizing facts.
Which sends them down that terrible
pathway that I've talked about that for
many ends their chance of learning maths
well.
This is a serious equity issue with
failure rates among students in
urban districts, particularly minority
students, reaching shocking proportions.
Jack Humphrey points to the need for a
change across the whole system,
teachers, administrators, districts and
parents are all needed in this.
In fact we know parents have an important
role to play.
Researchers know that the students who are
in homes where parents are supporting them
in their algebraic reasoning, are those
who do a lot better.
And often that's hard for parents who're
juggling many jobs to make ends meet and
don't have places, and students don't have
places to sit and work quietly at home.
The algebra for all initiative, which came
in to many states across the US, and
states that all students take algebra in
eighth grade has not helped failure rates.
In fact, it's worsened them as algebra
continues to be taught in
the same inequitable [INAUDIBLE] and
inaccessible way that misses the most
important ideas of algebra.
Many students fail and then fail again and
again.
It's, not surprisingly, you, you know, we
should all try taking a dry,
meaningless algebra course after we failed
it the first time.
It really becomes almost impossible with
the fixed mindset ideas
students have received.
Andrew Hacker, who's a writer for the New
York Times, caused a firestorm recently,
when he wrote an article saying we
shouldn't make all students take or
pass algebra.
It ends the careers of thousands of great
people who don't need it, but
their college careers end because of it.
And he argues that it's not necessary in
life, and
that he's never used it in his life or
career.
I think if algebra continues to be taught
in the way that it has been then I
agree with him.
But if algebra was introduced and taught
with meaning and
excitement then we wouldn't need to argue
that the requirement be dropped as
everyone would enjoy and benefit from it.
As Bob Moses, this famous civil rights
campaign of
the 1960s has argued Algebra is the new
civil right.
So, why is it important besides being the
main gate keeper to a world of
high achievement?
Beyond that, why is this subject
important.
Now, I'm going to ask you to answer that
through this quiz first,
why should students learn Algebra?
Or shouldn't they?
Give you a response to that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]