So now we're going to learn about
stereotype threat.
My dean, Claude Steel, he's dean of the
Stanford graduate school of education.
He's a world renowned psychologist and he
conceptualized and
started a whole field of work on what's
called stereotype threat and
over the decades Claude and his colleagues
have discovered that
many people suffer from stereotypes Women
in maths, African American and
academic, students in academic settings,
white students, around sporting ability.
So they have many studies on stereotype
threat and
they have many studies on girls and maths.
Showing that if women take a test and
beforehand just mark off their gender in a
box, they underperform.
If they don't mark off their gender,
there's no underperformance.
A group of psychologists at Princeton
conducted an experiment with white and
African American students who were given a
golfing task.
When the white students were given the
task and they were told that it,
the golfing task measured natural athletic
ability,
they golfed allot worse than the white
students who were not told anything.
When the same messages were given to black
students, it didn't affect their
performance, as poor athletic ability
isn't a stereotype they suffer from.
In the early studies they reminded people
of gender differences by getting them to
mark gender on a form.
Later they found that they didn't even
need to do that, because stereotypes are,
as they say, always in the air, which is
why they call it stereotype threat.
There's always the threat of that
stereotype, and
researchers have found the gender and
math stereotype to be established in girls
as young as five years old.
So they talk about the fact that young
girls are put off from engaging in
math before they have even had a chance to
engage in maths because of
the stereotypes in the air.
So Claude concludes in his book.
The stereotype threat affects all of us in
subtle and not so subtle ways.
But they're all damaging, and I really
recommend reading the entire book.
This student that I'm going to, play for
you now, really showed for
me the, that subtle, in-the-air effect of
the stereotype.
>> I would say that I've felt
discrimination from classmates as
a female.
I think that not so much of high school
but here I feel it.
Like not directly but subtle things like,
oh, like they won't ask me for
my help or they just will like kind of
bulldoze over what I'm saying so
not anything direct, but subtle things.
>> I'm constantly amazed by how many
students are given gender messages,
whether subtle or not so subtle, math
isn't for you.
And here's another one of my students
talking about that.
>> In fourth grade, I remember being so
curious about why
a square was a rectangle, but a rectangle
wasn't a square, and
really caring about those sorts of
problems, and then as soon as
people start telling you math isn't your
thing, then it's all downhill.
>> So as students come to math classrooms
and
doing math work with some serious
stereotypes in the air about gender and
about race, and these combine with general
views.
That only some kids can be good at maths
and
that maths is about a natural ability that
only some people have.
And we're going to look closely at that
one idea of natural ability in
the next sessions.
So we're beginning to see part of the
reason that mathematics education is in
a poor state.
Some messages can send students off the
rails even if they aren't about
gender or race.
People have told me recalling really in
very sharp detail how once in seventh or
eighth grade they asked a question and
the teacher said to them, that's a baby
question and
how they decided at that point the maths
was not the subject for them.
So the first session in the student
version of this class will be
about countering these stereotypes and
bolstering students and
negating those messages that they may have
heard, and really helping them believe and
know that they can be really good at math.
So a quick shortish question now for you.
What do you think you can do, as a
teacher, or as a parent, or whatever
role you have, to counter these damaging
stereotypes.