Now we're going to watch Cathy Humphries
teach this with her class of students.
Ans as you watch this video,
I'm going to ask you to reflect afterwards
when in this clip do you hear and
see mathematical wonder and curiosity and
appreciation from the students.
Where does it happen in the teaching?
>> Also, what teaching decisions did you
see Cathy make that
generated the student's interest and
engagement in this work?
[BLANK_AUDIO].
>> So, what I've got right here is a, is a
10 by 10 grid.
And, what I'd like you to do mentally is
figure out without
counting one by one, how many squares are
in the colored in portion.
>> In what portion?
>> How many unit squares?
>> In where?
And without talking, without counting
one by one, stop writing.
Wow.
Lots of people have an idea.
Would you talk to each other just about
what you got?
[CROSSTALK]
Can I please have your attention?
>> [CROSSTALK]
By the way, what do,
do we all want to say the answer?
>> [CROSSTALK] Yeah!
>> Well how /g, what is it?
>> [CROSSTALK] 36!
>> 36 squares, but did anybody pick what
was maybe 40 first?
>> [CROSSTALK] First?
'Kay, did anyone pick what was maybe 38
first?
A few people, okay.
And we.
So, when you talked it over in your group,
those of you who thought 40,
what were you thinking?
>> All right, Stephanie, what were you
thinking?
>> I was thinking that one side is tied,
and
there's 4 sides even, 5 times [INAUDIBLE]
is 40.
>> OK, how many were thinking just like
Stephanie?
>> All right, what about the 38 people,
what were you thinking?
>> Mindy.
>> I was thinking that the top 2 10 equals
10 which equals 20 out of the other two to
get where 9 is the [UNKNOWN] 18.
>> Aah.
Okay.
Alright.
So now let's just see some different
methods.
You know how we like to gather different
Let's see some different methods for
getting the 36.
So let's see.
Let's have Charmaine.
Charmaine what's your method?
Well [UNKNOWN] started out with 40
[UNKNOWN] 18 times 4.
And then I subtracted 4 from that because
there would be 4 squares overlapping.
And so that got 26.
>> Raise your hand if you understand how
and show me how you did it.
[NOISE] And the 4 was for.
>> The four squares that overlap.
>> Okay, and this 4 was for?
>> 4 sides.
>> And this 10 was for?
>> 10 squares on each side.
>> Okay.
Another way to do it?
Owen.
>> All right, how I got it was,
I just put one side was Obviously going to
be ten towards ten, and then, I did,
like the bottom one, and that was
[CROSSTALK] Could you go up and show us?
I think that might help us.
>> So I'll use a pointer finger as the
pen.
>> The pointer's in the top drawer if you
want to use it.
Top, cent, right center.
>> [NOISE] Oh, here it is.
>> There it is.
>> All right, I found it.
Anyway, so [NOISE] I like I know this has
10, so I just did like 10,
and then this one, this one's the
overlapping one, so then this would be 9.
Then this one would be nine too because
this one's overlapping but, and then for
this one it would be eight because these
two, this one is being used by this one,
and this one is being used by that one.
>> Colin, I really like.
>> What you showed visually what you did.
How many understood Colin's method?
Wow, great, okay, thank you.
How about a different method?
Wow, there's a lot.
Alright, let's see it's hard to choose,
Joe.
>> I I did.
The top.
>> When you go up like Colin did?
>> I added, I know that this one, this is
10 and so is that.
So I added those two.
And at first I thought this was like 9
right there so
I thought about it for a while.
And that's 8 and so I added those two and
that's.
16 and add it to 20.
>> [NOISE] So, Joseph look at this and
tell me if you think that represents what
you did.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
And the 10 and the 10 stand for.
>> This one and this row right here.
How many boxes are in that row and
[INAUDIBLE] 10.
>> Okay.
How many unit squares are in the top and
here at the bottom, and then where'd you
get the eight?
>> like, this row, except it didn't have
listed.
>> How many understand Joseph's method?
All right.
Are there any other methods?
Oh, lots of people, but how many had Joe's
method that they wanted to explain?
A lot of people.
>> Can anybody think of
another way to [SOUND] Melissa.
>> Okay.
[INAUDIBLE]
square is 100 units.
Because 10 times 10 there's.
Okay, that, and then there's [INAUDIBLE]
[SOUND] there's 8 by 8 that aren't shaded,
so that's 64, and you subtract 64 from
100.
>> What do you think of that method?
[CROSSTALK] Okay, so that would be, so
Melissa though, help me now.
You've got 10 times 10 first?
>> Yeah.
>> And then you subtracted 8 times 8.
>> Oh...
Okay and
other methods.
Tina.
[CROSSTALK] Alright any other methods that
you think you could do it?
Because there was one more in period one.
Exactly [COUGH] [CROSSTALK] Zach Morris?
Yeah I know Zach.
Alright here's what I'm going to do.
This is the backwards.
Rather than having you guess what
Zachary's method is,
which doesn't make any sense at all, I'm
going to show you Zachary's method.
You see if you can see why it makes sense
with the picture, okay?
Here's what Zachary did, and Dana I'll
call on you.
[NOISE]
4 times 8 plus 4.
Why does that make
sense with the picture?
>> [INAUDIBLE] [CROSSTALK] [CROSSTALK] ,
[INAUDIBLE]. >> Kayla, why does that make
sense with the picture.
>> Because there, there are 4 sides.
>> You want the what?
>> No, [INAUDIBLE] ,um, there are 4 sides.
[INAUDIBLE] [LAUGH] Okay.
There's like four sides, and, there's --
wait.
Okay.
And there's, there's 8 right here,
8 right here and 8 right here.
Yeah.
And that times 4 And it'd be plus 4
becuase 1, 2, 3, 4.
Yeah.
>> Anybody want to comment to her?
>> [UNKNOWN] [CROSSTALK] Okay, for the one
side if you said
that there were eight there so you have
two left over in the.
Corner, and then if you put eight on each
other side there would be one in each of
the three corners, or the two corners, two
other corners.
So, we'll basically do like eight times
four, and
then you're going to have laps until you
add one.
Is that same you said?
>> Yeah, that's what I was trying to say.
>> I thought you said it very well.
Just show us again with the eights.
>> It's coming from the filling.
>> Well, like, these, this, this comes
from eight right here.
>> So this whole side length, but what's,
what's the part that you're making out?
>> The filled in [INAUDIBLE] All the
corners, okay.
[CROSSTALK] Okay, okay, thank you very
much.
All right.
Okay so Kay wanted to come in on Zach's
method.
>> On Zach's method I think it's because
[INAUDIBLE] only that
it's [INAUDIBLE] times 4 and not 9 times
4.
>> What's the difference?
I really like that fact that Kay is
connecting two methods to each other.
How is Tina and Zach's method alike and
how are they.
>> They different.
Say it again, okay, and then I'll call on
somebody else.
>> well, I think it's pretty much the same
[INAUDIBLE] 4 times 8
[SOUND] [INAUDIBLE] plus 4, pretty much
the same thing as 9 times 4.
>> Alright, and, and any other comments
about the two methods?
Sarah?
>> Well, the only thing Tina did,
was she well because 4 times 8 plus 4, is
the exact same thing as 9 times 4.
Only you're saying, instead of having said
9 for
the, instead of having the, instead of.
I'm distracted, Mindy, by your hand being
up right now.
Please listen to Sarah.
>> Okay.
Instead of having the 9 4 being multiplied
with
the other 8 4's times 4, he added it
after.
[INAUDIBLE] So Sarah's thinking about this
numerically.
She's really, she knows that these two are
equal, and, she's saying what, like what,
what the person did first or second.
>> So an, another way I'd like you to
think about it is
what's Zack doing that Tina's not doing.
What's Tina doing that Zack's not doing?
How would those look in the picture?
so, Christa go ahead.
>> Well I think, kind of /g,
like it's what I was saying before, he
just took the corners away.
And he took the corners away and added
what was left.
And [CROSSTALK].
>> Okay stop for just a second.
So Zack took both of the corners off.
>> 1.1 is [UNKNOWN].
And Tina just took, she didn't take
anything.
She just kind of put it there and she kind
of decides minus 1 corner for each side.
>> Now we have Tina here to defend
herself.
Is that right Tina?
>> yeah.
>> Kind of right.
Alright, I'm going to, oh boy.
>> Charmagne.
>> I think my method is also kind like
Tina's and
Zachary's because, well, I was counting
the sides and then I subtracted four, but
he didn't count the sides and he added
four.
>> okay.
Other comments about how
those methods are alike and different?
Let's see.
[NOISE] going to ask you to do and turn
that off.
I want you to visualize a square in your
mind, and
use whatever method you want, do I want
you to use whatever method you want?
Yeah, I want you to use whatever method
you want, but I want you to
shrink the square in your mind, down to a
6 by 6, and then use one of those methods.
But instead of there being ten unit
squares on one side, now there are six.
Use one of those methods, and
see what you think the total number of
squares, let's keep our hands down.
It's kind of intimidating to have people
that think so fast.
>> Six by six.
[SOUND]
'Kay.
Now, lets just say that I don't care about
how many there are.
Lets say that what I care about is how
people would do it.
>> So, what I want to know is, and not
Charmaine, but someone else.
If the square, if the big square was a six
by six,
what would Charmaine have done to get
the total number of unit square in the
border?
[NOISE]