So, students will often write this; 230
plus 320
equals 550 minus 150 equals 4.
Which violates the equals sign.
That both sides at all times need to be
equal.
One elementary teacher I know spent a
really useful half hour asking his
third grade students to come up with
definitions of equals.
And then they discussed the different
ideas, which really helped to
set them off on a good path that won't
cause them to slip up later in algebra.
The fact that the equal sign means
equivalent is an important idea in
helping students make sense of algebra.
So, also we need to represent algebra in
multiple ways, and
where possible, multiple forms.
So, we can represent that symbolic
expression visually,
graphically, through words, and a great,
it's a great principle for algebra.
In fact, one of the greatest algebra
books, calculus text books, sorry,
that I have seen used this, what they
called the principle of 4.
So, these were calculus text books
developed by faculty at Harvard,
the Harvard Calculus Consortium.
And the principle of four was,
every situation should be described in at
least four ways.
From words, a picture, a graph, a table,
and symbols.
And then a really good teaching approach I
studied, where they had
a similar principle, the students color
coded the different representations.
For example, if you have an expression x
plus three, you could say,
well, this is my plus 3 in the, in the
line, in the graph.
This is the plus three in the visual of
the cases.
This is the plus three in the expression.
Everything's color coded.
And that's really helpful in teaching
important connections.
And you can see this color coding in the
picture from that school.
Connections and different representations
lead to deeper learning, and
a focus on the structural not only the
procedural role of algebra.
Even a multiple representation of one
form, the symbolic form,
can unleash incredible understanding.
So, here's a fairly standard algebra
question, not really my favorite type,
but with an added twist.
So, try this question now.
There are three piles of rock, A,
B and C, where B has 2 more than A and C
has 4 times as many rocks as A.
The total number of rocks is 14.
Find the number of rocks in each pile
using x.
And do the problem in three different
ways,
using the x in three different positions.