So I understand that we want students to
do well in exams with a time limit,
later probably if you're an elementary or,
or a middle school teacher, but
what not to do is make them anxious when
they're learning by timing them.
What we should do is make them comfortable
with numbers and with all of maths.
And if the anxiety or fear is taken away
They will work much more quickly.
The other point I want to make is that
timed tests and other speed pressures
misrepresent math as a subject that's all
about working on factual questions fast.
That isn't math, it's not the mathematics
that mathematicians work on
It's not the mathematics that's needed in
the workplace.
And in later sessions we're going to hear
from top math users,
people in Silcone Valley who work in
technology, people in medicine, in film,
people are team leaders.
It's really important to listen, I think,
to the ways people use maths now.
But many, many students in the UK and the
US and beyond develop the strong
impression that those who are best at math
are those who can do it quickly.
That's damaging and wrong.
And it puts off those students who think
deeply and carefully.
Cathy Seeley the former president of NCTM
has written a great book on
this called Faster Isn't Smarter.
So speed is the enemy of a mistakes
friendly culture, and
we should really use it in moderation or
not at all.
So what can we do to change the culture of
maths classrooms and maths times and home.
Here's some strategies I can think of to
help students value mistakes.
Later I'm going to ask you to add some of
your own in the forum.
So If you're a teacher start classes the
norm that you love and want mistakes.
And don't just say, I love mistakes.
Mistakes are good, We learn from mistakes.
But give students time and when make- when
they make a mistake ask them to present it
for everybody to see it.
One of the best teachers that I've ever
worked with regularly did
that with students.
I saw her right at the beginning of the
year when.
Say to one of her students, oh would you
go and present that on the board.
And he said, well I got it wrong.
And then she explained that, you know,
it's really great for
us to see mistakes because if one
student's made others will have to.
And we can all learn, and the student said
oh, okay, and got up and showed it.
And after that And other messages from the
teacher,
students became really willing to take
risks and to make mistakes publicly.
And in the last session, we'll see some of
those students at work.
For parents and for other helpers, the
ideas are the same.
When I have tutored people in math, I've
always started by saying,
by the way I just want you to know that I
love mistakes the most.
They are the time that your brain grows,
when you really learn so
it's really great to make mistakes.
Mistakes, and people immediately relax and
breathe a sigh of relief and
are much more willing to jump in to
problems and persist longer.
So the second advice is, don't just praise
mistakes but
talk about why they're important.
Maybe at the start of the year or
at other times talk to students about
brain growth and about some of the ideas.
I presented in this session and the last
session.
And at the end of this session you're
going to have an opportunity to brainstorm
the ways you can talk to students about
the brain and the importance of mistakes.
The third point is to give work that
encourages mistakes.
If students aren't making mistakes in
their math work,
they're not doing work at the right level
for them.
So try and always push the boundaries.
Keep them at the edge of their
understanding at all times.
And this may require talking to them about
what's most helpful for them.
For example, you can tell students that
when they get a question right that's not
really producing learning.
And if you're getting all questions right,
you're probably not doing work that's
challenging enough.
And as Carol has said, students are
missing out and
they're not getting the chance to make
mistakes.
For parents, you know by now that I think
one of the biggest helps you can
give your children is to dispel myths.
And now that comes in the ways that you
help and guide them.
So first of all, encourage mistakes at all
times.
And importantly, don't share with them
your own painful experiences of math in
school if you had those.
Research has found that as soon as mothers
told their daughters that they were bad at
maths in school, which mothers often say
to help their daughters feel better,
their daughters achievement immediately
went down.
If you're not confident with math
yourself, the best thing to say is great.
We can learn this together.
I don't know this either.
You can help me with this.
And whenever they come home with math
homework, greet it with cheers.
Say yay, I'm so excited, math homework.
I love working on math, especially math I
can't do.
So my own daughter who is in fourth grade
really lacks confidence in math.
She had some terrible experiences early on
in school with.
Fixed mindset messages.
But this was a classic example of an
interaction I had with her.
I recently went into a third grade maths
class with her.
And together, we watched the teacher put
up two questions.
One of which she got correct, and the
other she got wrong.
And she immediately went, oh, you know?
I should have added the one, not taken it
away.
And then she said, oh gosh.
I am so bad at maths.
I'm even worse than third graders, I'm
terrible.
And, and so I said to her.
You know what just happened there in that
question that you got right?
Nothing happened in your brain.
But in the question that you got wrong,
and that you thought about.
Your brain grew at that time, that was
really great.
And I could see her like really thinking
about that.
So my fourth bit of advice is to grade,
particularly for
teachers, to grade differently, or not at
all.
And I'm going to talk more on this next
session.
But the way you grade and give feedback to
students is really important.
So a cool thing to do when you grade, if
you give grades,
is to give students their papers back and
highlight mistakes but really positively.
Give them gold stars or comments or
whatever.
And then always let them correct their
mistakes and get the points or
even more, get double points.
Because it's such a great, those are the
great learning moments.
more, I'm going to talk more in assessment
and grading in the next lesson.
The final piece you're going to be
surprised about,
of advice is to dissociate math from
speed.
The new common core didn't do enough in my
view to make the content of
the curriculum the content that our young
people will need, but
they did something really important, and
they said that it's only useful to be
learning content if you're also learning
what they set out in the mathematical
practices to solve problems, to reason, to
be persistent, and so on.
But of course that takes longer as there's
a need to go deeper, which is great, and
I think teachers would have been really
helped in my opinion if the content had
been slimmed down.
Although that's just my, my opinion but
for parents it's just as important not to
use speed, not to use things like flash
cards or other speed math practice.
So we're in the resources section.
I'm going to give you some alternative
phone Apps and programs that will help
with math fluency without putting kids
under that negative speed pressure.
And if you're in a school where you're
made to give time test to kids.
Then try and advocate just for losing the
timing.
Because researchers have found that the
exact same tests without the timed
component don't create anxiety.
Even better, try and replace those tests
with teaching strategies that
will actually help teach fluency, rather
than just test it.
And then the next sessions I'm going to
show you a great teaching strategy for
parents or teachers that teaches number
fluency and
conceptual understanding together.
Of course, it would've helped teachers to
work in these ways if
the content was not so packed, but rushing
through content because there's so
much of it doesn't help, and the most
successful schools have studied
the teachers got together and worked out,
what are the big ideas in this year?
What are the core ideas?
And they really planned for those, and
I didn't worry if students didn't get
through all of the smaller methods.
And those students did better than those
who like go through everything.
So of course covering every thing doesn't
that students are learning everything.
So it's not always, if it's too fast, it's
not that helpful.
So take the time, take the time to present
maths as a subject that's interesting,
make it visual, connected, and deep.
Presenting maths fast doesn't help.
If you have students who have finished in
class, encourage them to go deeper.
I often ask students just to, if they've
finished,
to think of other questions that are
similar and work on them.
And that's a great thing for them to do.
So the first time I showed the release
items or
the Common Core to a group of teachers
they freaked out.
They were saying my students won't be able
to do this.
The problems were more open, they require
thinking.
They don't have A B C D choices.
The students will be able to do those
problems.
not because we've crammed them with more
knowledge, but
because we've given them the belief that
they can succeed.
And the mistakes are no important part of
their work and their learning.
So I wouldn't need to stop now and take
one of the released common core questions.
So here is an example of one of the
assessments.
I'd like you to do the assessment and also
reflect on the thinking involved,
what students would have to do to do the
assessment.