So, I use math every day, every minute of
my life.
But not the way math is usually thought of
as big formulas.
But math is a way to look at life.
I mean, I go to a supermarket and buy
things, I use math.
I drive to work and look at my phone to
see what the congestion level is, and
I use math to understand how long the
commute will take me.
And I use math in my own research, when I
build robots that navigate Streets.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I emulate the human brain's information
processing, and
it's known that the way we process
multiple sources of information is
somewhat reminiscence of some of the more
abstract math, like bases and statistics.
I find it extremely empowering because
[UNKNOWN] is geometric, time is geometric,
space is geometric.
We operate in time and space all the time.
And to understand how space interacts with
us and time and
people, math is just a great concept.