Mathematics is in crisis, here in the US,
in the UK,
and in many other countries across the
world.
Large numbers of people hate and fear
maths.
And as we saw in the very first class,
math ends people's chances for
college in the US.
Hundreds and thousands of people.
There are also not enough people
graduating from colleges with
the mathematics needed to help society.
And this is causing a serious shortage in
many really important fields.
Including science, medicine, technology.
So it seriously threatens the future of
countries.
Children and adults everywhere are
traumatized by math.
And this can affect their whole life.
Do you remember Vivian our British
scientist, and her trauma?
Many people have that and more.
So, I just mentioned Race to Nowhere.
And their Real Link are developing a new
film largely about math.
And they'd also like to collect stories
about people's maths experiences for
the film.
So, they've asked me to ask you to record
your story, if you have one, about maths.
You know, whether it's one of math trauma,
or trying to bring about change,
of good teaching, you can record your
story and send it to them.
And you can visit that on their website.
They have an iPhone app, so the website is
racetonowhere.com.
And these are the words that Vicky sent
me.
She asked for peoples' math stories, and
she said.
We want to hear how your situation or that
of your child or
student changed for the better or worse.
Was it a realization in yourself?
An adult that believed in you?
A teacher or student that suggested you
look at math another way?
Or if nothing changed, what do you wish
had?
We want to change our math education
system for the better and
your voices are critical to this change.
Keith Devlin is a Stanford mathematician.
And he's written a range of wonderful
books on maths, learning, and living.
And this is a quote from Keith,
who like Paul Lockhart, who we read
earlier in the course.
Asked us to think about music to highlight
what's going on in today's classrooms.
So Keith says this.
Mathematical notation no more is
mathematics than musical
notation is music.
A page of sheet musics represents a piece
of music, but the notation and
the music are not the same.
The music itself happens when the notes on
the page are sung or
performed on a musical instrument.
And it's in its performance that the music
comes alive.
It exists not on the page, but in our
minds, and
the same is true for mathematics.
Mathematics is a performance.
It's a living act.
It's a way of interpreting the world.
Imagine music lessons in which students
work through hundreds of hours of
sheet music, adjusting the notes on the
page, or
seeing checks and crosses, but never
playing the music.
Student's wouldn't, wouldn't continue with
the subject because they wouldn't ever
experience what music is.
And that's the situation we have a, a lot
in math classrooms.
Clearly, we need to change the way maths
is taught.
And that is in the hands of teachers,
parents, and administrators.
This may require being brave and
courageous, as most people don't
understand how maths is learned well.
But they still hold very strong opinions.
And many people have serious
misconceptions, including administrators,
which is the reason I wrote the book I
wrote, What's Math Got To Do With It.
Some of you may know about the attacks I
experienced when my research results
were published.
Two mathematicians who worked tirelessly
in the US pushing the idea that
students should not engage actively in
mathematics.
Targeted me in my work.
I won't go into that now, but I put the
details on the Stanford website.
The best thing I ever did was speaking up
against their behavior and
standing up to them.
That website was read by 50,000 people,
and
I was inundated, really overwhelmed by the
support I received from teachers,
mathematicians, Academics, parents, and
others.
And that taught me many things, the power
of community and
of us working together, to stop bullies
and other people who stop change.
And the, also the importance of different
forms of media.
And just of speaking out.
The Twitter community helped a lot in
really de-powering those two guys.
So if we want to break the cycle of maths
failure, and
spread what we know about effective math
learning, we may have to be brave, and
communicate in many different forms and
ways.
In my work in recent years,
I've really come to realize how much
teachers have suffered over recent years.
Partly, some of them, from the same two
men.
But more than that, since the No Child
Left Behind initiative,
teachers have had their professionalism
stripped away from them, and
many have been forced to do what they know
to be wrong.
I've seen schools, where teachers have
been ordered to teach traditionally with
desks in rows, and then on days when they
ask the students to work in groups, for
an activity, the students center them.
You're not allowed to do that.
How de-professionalizing is an experience
like that?
In the last year, I've work in one school
district in depth,
Vista Unified, with the director of maths,
Kathy Williams.
And that's been great.
I've learned a lot from that in-depth work
with teachers.
And I work particularly with middle school
teachers, and shared some of
the ideas with this course, and other
ideas, we worked on maths together.
They went back to their schools and
started using inquiry tasks, and
just saw the effect on their students,
which made them so excited.
I could see them becoming, getting,
getting the energy back that they had had
taken away.
And in one meeting with high,
just one meeting with high school
teachers, I showed some,
a video of students working together in
amazing ways to solve a complex problem.
They were I and P students.
And the teachers looked at me with some
pain in their eyes, and
one of them said to me, are we allowed to
do that?
Because people told us we were harming
children.
So at the end of that meeting, they were
getting their old I and
P books out of back of the cupboards and
planning excitedly again.
Sunday at Vista High School was one of the
teachers I met with for just a few hours,
and she was teaching geometry to students
the course they had to pass to graduate.
All the students were in their last year.
And at the end of the year, she reflected
that one of the ideas she'd learned at
our meeting around the way to give
students feedback and
telling them that you believe in them, had
changed everything in her class.
All of the students passed the course and,
they were coming up to her at graduation
to tell her what a difference she'd made
to them.
So these different interactions and
stories with teachers make me very happy
and sad, happy to be working with them,
sad that these professionals who knew ten
times as much about student learning,
than the people who were telling them what
to do, had had their own creativity and
autonomy taken away from them.
And what gave it back was a few ideas from
research.
Research of what we know works.
And ideas that they knew were really
productive.
And I think we really need to open spaces
up for important ideas.
And certainly, in the US, we're in a good
time to do that now.
And maybe these new forms of technology
can really help with that, too.
Mathematics is a human activity, a social
phenomenon.
It's a set of ideas and concepts that help
illuminate the world.
It can be seen in the design of buildings,
the rhythm of raindrops,
special effects in movies and the social
networks that connect us.
And mathematics is all about illuminating
relationships,
such as those we see in shapes, in nature.
And it's a diverse and multidimensional
subject.
It's also a powerful way of expressing
relationship and
ideas in numerical, pictorial, graphical,
verbal, and symbolic forms.
So let's together introduce students that
we're on about exciting and
beautiful maths.
It's a really important thing to do.
So this is the end of the course, and I
want to end with a, a final question and
a couple of things for you to do the
question is to ask you, if there is
any particular way I can be helpful to you
in supporting any changes you may.
Maybe we have a follow-up course on how to
teach in these ways.
I recognize this course wasn't that it was
just about sparking a few ideas.
Maybe keeping the forum open, maybe giving
you updates through monthly webinars.
I'd like to know how to help you and
here's a question for that.