All of these interventions are
psychological interventions.
They're not about content and they're not
about pedagogy.
But pedagogy and content are extremely
important, and
we're going to be thinking about those for
pretty much all of the later sessions.
But just to give you a chance to think
about that a little bit in
this first session, there are many things
going wrong in mathematics education.
For me, one of the best short descriptions
of what's going on was written by
a mathematician called Paul Lockhart.
He was a [INAUDIBLE] is a mathematician
who's also taught maths in K12 schools,
and he was so exasperated [INAUDIBLE] by
what he saw in schools.
He wrote something really beautifully
written called A Mathematician's Lament,
and I'm going to ask you to read some of
that at the end of this class.
So I want to say something first about
teachers.
it, I'm sounding very critical of
mathematics education but
I'm not at all critical of teachers
because teachers have had to
work in ways that are educationally
damaging for some time.
So I don't blame teachers for the bad
state we're in.
They've been living and working for
decades in a culture driven by
ridiculously long list of content
standards.
And those standards made them feel they
have no time to stop and
create engaging activities for kids.
And nonstop testing of very narrow content
and multiple choice tests.
There's hope now in the United States with
the onset of the common call that
that's changing.
On top of that, they've really felt like
their professionalism has stripped away.
Even when they do take an extra step and
do something great, I've heard stories of
administrators coming in and
shutting them down, and that's why it's so
important that everybody,
administrators, parents, teachers, learned
about good mathematics instruction.
Of course there are great administrators
and teachers who've been able to
ignore the pressure and done what they
know to be right with the kids.
But that's hard to do with all of the
directives and it happens very rarely.
For me, mathematics is a living act.
It's a performance, a way of interpreting
the world.
And we urgently need both to address
stereotypes and myths and
to bring mathematics back to the real
mathematics.
The mathematicians used and that's out
there in the world.
Teachers, administrators, and
parents, all of us can do this, especially
if we work together.
Everyone has a role to play.
And in later sessions we're going to
[INAUDIBLE] learn more about how to
do this.
But I'm going to ask you to stop by
reading at least the first five pages of
Lockhart's Lament.
And now, I'll just end by saying that I
look forward to seeing you in the next
session.