[MUSIC].
So welcome to the second session.
Most people believe that people are either
good at maths or they're not or
you need to set brain to be good at maths.
And one of the hardest challenges teachers
and parents face is
dealing with that myth, that only some
students will have to be good in math.
And the student version of the course,
this session, will be an intervention to
shift their thinking about this.
And I found that when I've shown students
what I'm going to show you,
they've really changed in their learning
paths.
So first of all,
why is the idea that only some students
can be good at math so prevalent?
Particularly will talk more about the US
and the UK and countries in the west.
So, these days, I'm spending far too much
time watching teenage TV shows because I
have two daughters.
And I have been amazed by the messages
about math that
students are literally bombarded with.
Math is hard, they see over and over
again.
And scenarios such as this one,
that two of my students helped with, are
just shown repeatedly.
I can't count the number of times I've
seen something like this in one of
the shows.
[SOUND].
>> So what are you working on?
>> [SOUND]
Algebra.
>> As well as scenarios like that.
A funny one I saw recently, had a caveman
who was called Cavey.
And he was sitting, finishing all of his
English homework, and
he was saying, oh I'm really happy to do
this, I love literature.
And then his friend goes over to him and
said, huh, you still have math to do, and
hands him his math homework.
And he goes berserk, jumping up and down,
angrily beating his stick, so
that's another image for kids, and those
ideas that math is hard, or
even worse you see kids telling other
kids, I just can't do math,
which is a totally fixed mindset messages.
These are given to students all the time
through the media and these messages
make kids feel a number of things.
So, I have a question for you now.
What I would like you to do is to write
down in the forum, where you think,
besides television, kids get these
negative messages about maths.