[MUSIC].
When Carol Dweck published this book in
2007, it quickly became a New York Times
best seller, and it really started a
revolution in education.
I don't know of any research volume that's
had such an impact, and
in there she reported that there are two
ways of thinking and
people fall into one of two groups.
There are those people who have a fixed
mindset and those people believe that you
have a certain amount of intelligence that
you really can't change, so
math's ability is a gift.
And then there are those who have a growth
mindset,
who believe that math's ability and
smartness grows with experience.
So it turns out that these two beliefs
have huge implications for learning and
for students.
Those people with a growth mindset, it
turns out are persistent,
they learn from mistakes, and they're
encouraged by other people's success.
But those were the fixed mindset hate to
fail thus it tells on
that they are not smart and they will
avoid challenging work at all costs.
Now these mindset beliefs effects students
from across the achievement spectrum.
In fact high achieving goals all are from
the worst hit by fixed mindset, thinking
and that's affects them really badly when
they come to choose courses and careers.
Students can have these mindsets from the
time they are about 3 years old, and
one of the reasons is that many parents
praise their children for being smart.
Now they do that with the best intentions,
but when they do that and
they say oh, you're so smart, children
think, oh, good I'm smart.
But when they later fail, and they will,
they think oh, I'm not so smart.
So it's important always to praise what
students have done, not them.
Say wow, that's great that you've learned
that, or
it's great that you've learned to do that.
And Carol's book has many more ideas on
that.
And as she mentions in her interview, they
found that the praise given to babies in
the first three years of their life
predicts their mind set five years later,
so it's really important.
And it turns out that praise can impact
students immediately.
In one of Carol's studies they did
experiments with 400 fifth graders, and
they were asked to take an easy, short
test, and
almost all of them performed well.
And half the children were praised for
being really smart.
The other half were complimented on having
worked really hard.
Then, they were asked to take a second
test and they were told they
could choose one that was pretty simple
and that they would do well on or they
could choose one that was more challenging
but they might make mistakes on it.
90% of those praised for effort chose the
harder test, but
of those smart, the majority chose the
easy test.
So, let's look at some of the really
interesting data on mindset in students.
So this graph shows what happens when
students received an intervention.
It turns out students for
four months declined through seventh grade
but the intervention stopped that.
And those that graph shows only what
happened from a mindset intervention.
The students have the same math teachers
and the same curriculum.
So that intervention and
all sorts of other useful advice, is on
the Brainology website.
So, a question I want you to answer now,
which is slightly different to the last
one,.
Some of, many of you may have seen the
data I've just shown you on mindset before
as Carol's book is so popular, but maybe
not all of it before.
And I want us to stop and think now, and
think about if student.
If schools took on this mindset evidence
seriously, what would they need to change?
So write about schools now, even if you
wrote about schools before.
And make your answer local to your own
situation or
the schools you know in your districts and
country.