So I want now to tell you
about some interventions that have been
conducted that have had amazing effects.
And they give us insights into things that
we can all do to counter stereotypes.
So a range of studies have been conducted
by people like Jeff Cohen at Stanford,
David Jeiger at the University of Texas,
and their colleagues.
They were all in the references.
The first one I found amazing,
they divided students into two groups in
English high school classrooms.
And everybody got diagnostic feedback on
an essay, which was critical, really good,
but really good feedback.
Half of the students randomly also got a
sentence.
Which was this, I am giving you this
feedback because I believe in you.
The teachers didn't know who got that
sentence.
What they found was those students
achieved significantly better in
the essay, they made more improvements.
They also achieved significantly better a
year
later particularly the black students.
So white students improved, but
African-American students they made
significant improvements, from that one
single statement.
So they've looked at praise and feedback
carefully and
they've pointed out that, you know, you
can't just over praise students.
Especially stereotype groups, because that
just makes them perceive that,
the a lower standard is being applied to
them and it backfires.
But when these African-American students
are encouraged to see criticism of
a reflection of two things.
Their teachers high standards and their
teachers belief in their potential,
their performance in really important
subjects improved in important ways.
So I'm not suggesting here that we can
just add I believe in you to feedback and
everything will be well.
I'm showing this data as much as anything
to show you how powerful
single messages can be that we give to
kids.
And I think that's really important for
teachers and for parents.
So I'm going to get us to stop now and
pause and think about the effect of that
particular intervention.
Why, or how,
do you think one message, one sentence,
could impact students a year later?