As well as the huge implications we've
seen for all students achievement,
there are serious implications of mindset
work for equity.
So we know that after mindset
interventions, African American students
show the sharpest increase in grades and
in valuing school.
We also know that a growth mindset
eliminates any gender gaps in performance.
Even in the highest SAT levels,
the very top level where there still
gender differences, we know that if
we only look at growth mindset students,
those gender differences disappear.
We know too at the end of eighth grade, or
the research showed us that at the end of
eighth grade when they follow students,
there was only a gender gap in maths
amongst fixed mindset students.
Interestingly, Carol Dreck and
the other researchers, studied, as well,
calculus at Columbia.
So at the University level.
And they found that in calculus classes,
first of all,
stereotyping was alive and well.
Women have been through university math
departments can probably identify
with that.
But they found that the stereotype
messages that the women received only
effected those with a fixed mindset and
when they received those messages their
confidence eroded and they abandoned plans
to pursue STEM subjects,
whereas those with a growth mindset were
able to deal with those messages and
continue pursuing the STEM subjects.
So seeing maths as a gift not only makes
students vulnerable to lack of
confidence but vulnerable to stereotypes,
too.
And having a growth mindset is what we
want all students and teachers to have.
So, the big message, intelligence is
malleable.
But, students, teachers, schools,
parents tend to treat math learners As
though it's relatively fixed.
So some questions for you now.