[MUSIC].
Welcome to the first class of How to Learn
Maths.
This course is for teachers, parents,
administrators, anyone who teaches or
helps people learn maths.
But, a similar course is going to be
released for students in this school year.
Probably in the fall.
Or just after the winter break.
The version you'll take is no where near
as polished or uh,zappy.
The student version is going to have some
different cool animations and graphics and
different ways to engage the
students,different questions and
interviews and so on.
But the idea's are going to be similar.
But I want to introduce you first to those
ideas.
So, who am I at this point we have over
20,000 people enrolled in the course and
I know some of you know me well, some have
read my book or researched book or
researched work.
And many probably most of you have no idea
who I am,
so I am a professor of mathematics
education at Stanford University.
But before being a professor and
during that time, I've taught mathematics
or maths as we call it in the UK.
You'll probably here me say both maths and
math in this course.
And I've taught maths at many different
levels.
So in inner city London and public schools
I taught.
The age range of ages 11 to 18 as we do in
England and
I taught in Camden town for those of you
who know the area in
schools with more than 250 different
languages spoken.
In the US I've taught math to seventh and
eighth grade students and
also to undergraduates at Stanford so.
Lots of levels of maths.
So I've said that this course is for
teachers and for parents,
that's because it's not a course on how to
teach with the detailed ideas for
teaching, although there are some of
those.
But it's really a course with short input
from me.
Most sessions are about 15 or 20 minutes
long.
I think I said in the description they'd
be 10 to 15 minutes but
I got a bit excited about the different
ideas I could show you.
And so I'm going to show you some research
ideas that have recently emerged that
I think can be really helpful for
everybody.
So this course is somewhat experimental.
You're my first time of trying this and
we're in it together.
I, I would welcome input on what is or
isn't useful for you as well as letting me
know in the forum Which of the ideas will
be most useful for the student course.
Which is the one I'll work on next.
I'd really like us to be a community of
learners in the intro video that you can
see on how the course works, tells you
about the forum and
the other places we can connect.
And there's going to be some life chat
sessions, too.
So it's hard to design a class for such a
broad range of people but
my hope is that even if I give you one or
two key ideas they can
change something you do in the classroom
or an interaction you can have with
your own children that may actually make a
huge difference for them in
their mathematical trajectory as your find
out from the ideas I'll show you.
I'm going to be helped in teaching this
course by some really interesting
individuals who I interviewed for the
course, and they're going to be
sharing their experiences of using maths
out in the world and of learning maths.
So we have Michelle Sandburg, who's a
pediatrician.
Sebastian Thrun who designed the
self-driving cars for Google.
He's also a Stanford professor and the CEO
of Udacity, an online company.
Chris who's a software engineer at
Udacity.
Emily is a team leader at Apple.
She leads a team of engineers.
And Sophie is a filmmaker.
And they're going to come in and out of
the course, as you'll see.
I also included Carol Dweck who's the guru
on mindsets.
And you'll be seeing some of her.
So, it would really help me in moving
forward if I can collect some data from
you, about who you are your motives for
taking the course.
I'm going to ask you, now, to stop and
complete the survey, that I'll direct you
to.
And this survey is really important so
I would really appreciate if you would
complete this.
So teaching is really complex and
intellectual work even though people often
don't think that.
If you think about, just for a moment,
what happens when you're in a whole,
when a teacher's in a whole class
discussion.
And the student asks a question or
says something and the teacher needs to
come back with a comment or a question.
In that moment they have to hear what the
students have said and
make sense of that in terms of their
thinking, and
think about what their mathematical
trajectory is, what's helpful for them.
At the same time thinking about the
journey of the class and
where they are and what they need to hear.
And in that split second they have to make
those decisions and
come back with a question or a response
for a student.
That is a very, very hard thing to do, and
teaching is one of the hardest jobs in the
world.
It's also one of the most important, and
what we now know is that small moments,
small conversations and messages to
students can make a huge, huge difference.
And I'm going to come to those, some of
those, in a moment.
But first I want us to look together at
some data.
I want to share with you now some data
that I learned in this past year and I,
I was pretty shocked by.
And that's this, currently in the US 50%
of students are in 2 year colleges.
70% of those students are placed into
remedial maths classes.
Basically, repeating the maths they took
in high school.
And only 1 in 10 students complete those
courses for
the other 90%, they actually leave
college.
That, they don't get through that math
course and
that's the end of their college career.
So that data is, I thin pretty shocking
and
it tells you about the wide spread
problem.
And I want you to think now about what do
you think is the top reason for
that problem, and I've just put four
reasons down.
This I'm going to get you to just choose
one, or
you can choose more than one from the
list.
So this is your first question, that's
actually a multiple-choice question,
even though there aren't going to be many
multiple choice questions at all in here.
But this one works for that.
So I want you to just look at the choices,
pick as many as you like,
trying, you know, trying to make it 1 or
2.
Why you think there's such a terrible
problem in mathematics education?
There's so many students end their career
with maths.
So is it the teaching methods that are
taught in schools and colleges?
Maybe you think students lack foundational
knowledge that trips them up, maybe you
think students don't have the ability for
that high level maths or perhaps Algebra
is the stumbling block, its just a very
difficult subject for many.
So, choose from those.