So, I can think of a few reasons.
Let's see if they match yours.
Or maybe you have better ones.
I would say that algebra is a language for
expressing the world, and we need it,
particularly in the new world we're living
in.
Also, algebra is a tool for solving
problems, although many don't think of
it that way, because of the way it's
introduced to them.
And then, the, my third reason is that
Algebra helps us think abstractly.
And that learning to think outside of
numbers with abstract ideas is
really critical.
It is going to be at the center of many
careers in this new age.
And jobs that don't even exist now,
that we can't even think about, are going
to be based on this abstract thinking.
But the failure rates in algebra,
failure that sets a student on a low-level
pathway, is completely changeable.
And in this session, I'm going to set out
important core principles for
teaching algebra that come from research
evidence, and
that apply to all levels of algebra from
elementary to college.
I'll set out those principles first, and
then we'll look at some examples of those
principles in action in classrooms.
[MUSIC]
So, one of the clearest and
most repeated research results is that
students have great difficulties,
moving from what's described as procedural
algebra to structural algebra.
And here's the difference between those
two.
Procedural algebra involves representing a
letter as
a single unknown number that students
find.
Most algebra textbooks bombard students at
the beginning of their learning,
with questions like, find x when 7x plus 4
equals 32.
A structural approach to algebra involves
using symbols, such as letters,
to express generality in a situation.
So, the big idea of algebra and the
concept that will help students more
than any in work and life, is this idea of
generalization.
So, when students work with growing
patterns, as we have looked at before, and
they're asked to describe grows, they can
be introduced to the use of
algebra as a really useful tool that helps
them solve that problem.
So, a question for you now is, how do you
see this shape growing?
Can you find the number of square in case
100, or in case n?