So teaching is really complex and
intellectual work, even though people
often don't think that.
If you think about just for a moment what
happens when you're in a whole, when
a teacher's in a whole class discussion
and a student asks a question or
says something, and the teacher needs to
come back with a comment or question.
In that moment, they have to hear what
their students have said.
And make sense of that in terms of their
thinking, and
think about what their mathematical
trajectory is, what's helpful for them.
At the same time, thinking about the
journey of the class, and
where they are and what they need to hear.
And in that split second they have to make
those decisions and
come back with a question or a response
for a student.
That is a very, very hard thing to do, and
teaching is one of the hardest jobs in the
world.
It's also one of the most important.
And what we now know is that small
moments, small conversations, and
messages to students can make a huge, huge
difference.
And I'm going to to come to those, some of
those in a moment.
But first, I want us to look together at
some data.
I want to share with you now some data
that I learned in this past year and I,
I was pretty shocked by.
And that's this.
Currently in the US, 50% of students are
in two-year colleges.
70% of those students are placed into
remedial maths courses.
Basically, repeating the maths they took
in high school.
And, only one in ten students complete
those courses.
For the other 90%, they actually leave
college.
That, they don't get through those maths
course and
that's the end of their college career.
So that data is, I think, pretty shocking
and
it tells you about a widespread problem.
And I want you to think now about, what do
you think is the top reason for
that problem?
And I've just put four reasons down.
This I going to, to just choose one.
Or you can choose more than one from the
list.
So this is your first question that's
actually a multiple choice question,
even though there aren't going to be many
multiple choice questions at all in here.
But this one works for that.
So I want you to just look at the choices.
Pick as many as you like.
Try and you know try and make it one or
two.
Why you think that there's such a terrible
problem in mathematics education that so
many students in their career with math.
So is it the teaching methods that are
taught in schools and colleges?
Maybe you think students lack foundational
knowledge that trips them up.
Maybe you think students don't have the
ability for that high level maths or
perhaps algebra is the stumbling block.
It's just a very difficult subject for
many.
So choose from those.