In the reference section, I've included a
list of some great puzzle books.
There's something slightly separate as we
talk about parent help.
I've developed uh,a written article about
how to help with Maths homework.
I wrote it for UK parents, but the
messages and advice apply to all parents.
And there's a link to that in the
reference section.
I've played you lots of videos of
Sebastian [INAUDIBLE] talking about Maths
already as I think is very insightful.
And now I have one last one to play you.
At then end of the interview with
Sebastian I asked him, what advice he
would give K12 teachers preparing
students, and this is what he said.
Someone told me once that, if you are K
through 12 teacher and
you're teacking kids in Maths.
Something like 65% of the jobs that your
kids will take haven't even been
invented yet.
So it's really hard to prepare kids.
And obviously we live within an utterly
outdated curriculum.
The curriculum goes back to any number of
years.
And for various bureaucratic reasons,
we are just unable to change even the most
basic things.
And we also try to force every student
into the same schemes if they're all
like robots and have to learn at the same
speed.
Which is, specifically for
Maths, is really a problem because Maths
is such beautiful thing.
If you give people the time that they
need, some are very fast,
some are very slow.
You can get pretty much every kid there.
>> Mm-hm.
>> For me the,
the critical thing in Maths [INAUDIBLE]
not applying formulas, like the most, or
least interesting component.
The most interesting thing is, think like
a mathematician.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And think like a mathematician is a
very intuitive thing.
It's the skill that you can look at a
problem, and
make assessment when a number's involved,
when a quantity's involved.
It's the skill of making a baking recipe,
understand how to scale it up to more
people.
It's the skill, how to pack a truck.
When you want to move somewhere, and how
the moving distance affects the,
the size of truck you're going to rent and
the way you pack it, turns out.
If you move short distance, you pack it
different if you move long distances.
And these skills in daily life, really,
really good mathematicians to me
have really insightful answers for those
skills.
It's the skill of thinking first
principles.
Most of us think by analogy as Elon Musk
tends to say.
But if you say, okay, the problem is
solved this way over here has to be
solved exactly the same way over here.
With a understanding that there's
assumptions behind it.
It's a skill of being able to say, well,
does it have to be this way?
What are the assumptions?
In my own work right now in education we
make this assumption that we
teach all of the students at the same
speed.
And it has a huge impact on, on, on, on
learning.
What if you just let that go instead and
you can teach students at their own speed.
What if, what would be the outcome, and
how could we,
structure the material differently.
It's the skill of logical thinking of
saying,
okay if that's the case,maybe the
following assumptions are also wrong.
Maybe the teacher doesn't have to be in
the entertaining the kids.
Maybe the teacher can be interacting with
the kids on their own turf, and
then really be relentless about digging in
and seeing if he can find a better mode.
Again, I think what we teach in Maths is
pretty irrelevant.
It's the skills that kids pick up, how to
look at life, and
the ability to apply those things to real
life situations.
I think any particular formula is probably
uninteresting but
the ability to think abstractly.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
Matha to me is just a training course to
be a citizen, how to think in the world.
And were the numbers of people, of
relationships, of time, of space and
so on.
So we can get people that kids that
feeling of how to deal with these things
and empower them and take away the fear
everywhere.
And that's irrespective of the job
description, again no job has,
most jobs have not been invented yet that
teachers teach kids on.
>> You also asked Sarah Flannery a similar
question and
this is some of Sarah's reflections.
>> Some of the things that I use in my
work all the time and
I don't know how to answer this question
well but,
it's to prepare people for the basic tasks
of making sense of data.
Understanding how to visualize data in
different ways.
Being able to estimate I think people
don't don't understand how to do
that enough and being confident about
looking at things in different ways.
And cross checking their work and
you know not being afraid to use intuition
to move forward and get something done.
But then, you know, taking a step back and
being realistic and
checking your work [LAUGH].
And as I said, I think another way to
prepare people, is,
communication speak skills and the ability
to express themselves and their ideas.
Because if you look at employers, every
job in any field is asking for
good communication skills and good
problem-solving skills.
And so, to that end, you know, do puzzles,
because you get all of that out of it, and
you get confidence.
>> So thinking about what both Sebastian
and Sarah said, what do you
think are the implications of their ideas
for teaching if we were to take them on?