So recently a New York Times columnist
Peter Sims, wrote a really compelling
piece about the critical role of mistakes
in innovation and design thinking.
And he analyzed the differences between
more and less successful entrepreneurs and
he found that the successful ones
Basically make more mistakes.
And they learn from those mistakes, and
that learning sets them on the path to
huge success.
But another New York Times columnist and
bestselling author of
the book Better By Mistake, Alina Tugend,
has written, correctly in my view,
that we are raising a generation who are
terrified of blundering, of failing,
of even sitting with the discomfort of not
knowing something for a few minutes.
I was really stunned last year in a
teacher workshop I was running when
Carol Dweck had given up some time to join
us.
She said many things that were helpful and
we will hear from her in this lesson but
one of them was every time students make a
mistake in maths they grow a new synapse,
and that really hit me as very important.
So what we're finding from research is
that when students make a mistake, and
I'm thinking this is a kind of core
mistake, not an error such as
a numerical slip, when they make a mistake
about an idea in math, two sparks happen.
First when they make the mistake, and then
again when they think about the mistake.
And that brain growth that comes from
those sparks in
the brain doesn't happen when people get
work correct, so this was stunning to me.
And the reason is it turns out that making
mistakes its the most useful thing to
be doing.
The, the very much useful thing in maths,
but
students often feel really bad, crushed
even, if they make a mistake in maths.
They think it means that they're not a
math person, but
it turns out it's really the most useful
thing they can be doing.
Jason Moser and his colleagues published
an article in Psychological Science,
which I'm putting in the references, and
they reported the evidence of
significant brain changes when students
make a mistake.
They also found that the brain growth that
happens was different greater in
growth-mindset individuals than in
fixed-mindset individuals.
So again, the greater response of the
growth mindset people and
the brain growth they've showed, they were
more aware of
mistakes with greater reaction and a
greater accuracy afterwards.
It's really amazing and that paper is in
the reference section.
So that evidence points to 2 things for
me, the new science of the brain,
showing us that brains actually change
when people make a mistake.
And, again, the importance of a growth
mindset is it was the growth
mindset people's brains who grew the most.
So we're going to talk more about this new
evidence of what it means for
math learning, but before we do that I
want to stop here and ask you a question.
And that is, what is your reaction to the
information or
mistakes that I have given you so far
because I think it's pretty big?
So I'm going to ask you to write a
paragraph at least and submit that and
then you will get somebody else's
paragraph.
So this will be a kind of peer assessment
and you will be asked to give them
a comment on their submission and you will
get a comment on yours.