So this is what they make me think about.
I was in a high school geometry class
recently in California,
in a great school with lots of great
teachers and ideas.
But, as the teacher tried to get students
to reproduce the exact accurate words on
the next line of the proof.
I just wondered at how the students could
make sense of this in terms of
their lives outside the classroom.
Where very little depends on the precise
adjustment of a single word.
Of course, precise wording is important in
mathematics, but
it seems high school geometry classes are
about little else.
And their far from that exciting mode of
time and
space in geometry in action that Sebastian
and Sophie described.
And for Sophie the fact that her geometry
class was so removed from the world was
the reason she felt forced to both suspend
reality and disengage from maths.
This reminds me of a great quote by a
sociologist and
newspaper writer Hilary Rose.
Who recalls that as a young child she
loved to explore patterns and
numbers and shapes.
But has sense of mathematical wonder ended
in school.
And this is what she said.
Thinking about it, it was those so
called practical problems that irritated
me the most.
It was obvious to me that many of the
questions simply indicated that
the questioner did not know enough about
the craft skills involved in
real world solutions.
Lawn rollers being pulled up slopes,
wallpapering rooms by calculating square
feet and inches.
These were tedious and as far as that
highly practical child could see, stupid.
I knew that the price I paid was to lose
my sense of confidence that
school maths and everyday maths were part
of one world.
I haven't talked, in this course much
about the difference between
questions that really are in the world and
involve the world, and are great.
And those that I would call pseudo context
such as those that are used in
most word problems.
Where people are meant to read the words
but
not really engage with them as though they
are real.
And they fill Maths textbooks.
But I have a paper written just on that
which is in the references and
a chapter of my book.
And Dan Meyers' website has hosted a
discussion around these
pseudo-context problems.
As well as how to redesign tasks and
modelling tasks using multimedia.
So these links are all good resources for
those.
So I think its important to reflect on the
geometry of time,
space, light, film making and so much
more.
And to replace the artificial unreal world
of geometry classes with one that's all
about life.
So that's my thought about geometry's role
in transforming students' maths
experiences for the better.
I know we would need a whole course to
work out how to do that and we,
you need a lot of time to work on how to
do that.
The same is true for Algebra and for the
number work but, as this course is about,
hopefully, sparking ideas and empowering
you to make those changes.
Hopefully these are helpful.
And here's another idea or really, a
research finding,
to really provide students with maths that
represents the world.
We should be separating Algebra and
Geometry.
This is really a conversation for
the US viewers, because the US is the only
country I know of that does this.
Maybe there are others, but in the US,
students take a year of Algebra,
then a year of Geometry when they forget
most of the Algebra.
Then a year of advanced Algebra that
spends a big time in that course going
back over the Algebra from the first
course.
I found it hard when I first moved to the
US to even know where some important and
really good topics and
problems would fit between, with within
these artificial distinctions.
And the distinctions certainly don't
represent the world.
Two studies have been conducted recently
with large numbers of students, and
one study by Degross and colleagues, they
studies 2,161 students.
Half of them went to the traditional US
approach of Algebra, Geometry.
And half of them went through an approach
where the subjects were taught
together that they're starting to call the
international approach in the U.S.
In a second study James Tar and colleagues
studied 3,258 students also.
In the traditional approach and the
international approach.
In both studies the students working with
the integrated curriculum of
the international approach scored
significantly higher on
every achievement measure that was given
to them.
And those studies are also in the
references.
So, we've talked about many different
ideas in this course,
we'll I've talked about them hopefully you
have talked some to.
And now I'd like us to stop and reflect on
those ideas.
I have two questions for you that I'm
very, very interested in the results of.
So, this could take awhile but,
please complete the questions carefully,
they could really help.
Students and and teachers and parents.
So the first big question is to think
about the student course that I'm
going to release directly to students.
And think which of the ideas we've talked
about would be useful for them.
So I'm going to show you the main ideas of
the course and ask you to vote for those
that you think would be most useful for
students and make comments if you wish.