So, a really interesting study on this was
done by Barbara White and
John Frederiksen.
And they conducted a research study with
12 classes of students learning physics.
Students were divided into 2 groups.
There was a controlled and experimental
group.
Both groups were taught force and motion.
But the control group spent portions of
each lesson discussing the work,
while the experimental group spent the
same amount of time engaging in peer and
self assessment, and the results were
dramatic.
The experimental group outperformed the
control group on three different
assessments, and
the greatest gains were made by those who
were previously low achieving.
After the low achievers spent time
discussing assessing themselves and
others on these different assessments,
they started behaving like the highest
achievers.
And the researchers concluded that low
achievers are often thought of as
lacking ability or, being slow, but what
they actually found was that they were
often low achieving just because they
don't know what's important, and
what they're meant to be paying attention
to.
And the seventh graders in this study
scored higher levels then
AP Physics students on tests of high
school physics so
the impact of that, self and peer
assessment was dramatic.
So one the best assessment for
learning sites I know of comes from a
collaboration between the UK and the US.
The show center at Nottingham University
and the Mars Collaborative and
I'm going to give you a link to their
site.
And what I want you to do for this
assignment is go to their site,
go to the lessons part of the site and
you'll find a whole range of formative
assessment or assessment for learning
lessons from grade 6 to high school.
And the way the materials work on this
site very nicely is that they
provide a whole lesson, and
they provide a pre-assessment the students
take at the beginning of a unit.
Then the teachers know how and where to
direct questions, and help improve them.
Then there's a lesson, and I'm going to
get you to look at those.
There are a few examples, and
I've selected three different ones that
probably would be most helpful if
you're an elementary, middle, or high
school teacher.
Choose the one for your grade level, or
just one that you're interested in.
So for the elementary teachers,
I think the grade six lesson called
optimizing security cameras would be good.
For grade there's a lesson on classifying
solutions to systems of equation.
For the middle school teachers and
the high school teachers, I think solving
quadratic equation lessons is good.
So, go to those lessons now, and what I
want you to do is read all of the teacher
guide and the introduction before the
lesson and suggested lesson outline.
And then do the student work and
then after you've done that, I'd like you
to reflect a bit on.
What you see in that Formative Assessment
Lesson, what resources you see that
might be valuable to you in your thinking
as a teacher or parent or administrator.
So, the question for you is,
what resources do you see in that
Formative Assessment Lesson,
what ideas do you see that might be
valuable to you whether you're a teacher,
parent, or administrator, anybody, and how
might they support a growth mindset.