So, it's quite likely that many of you put
10a plus 12p for
that expression, because that's how it's
taught in most textbooks.
But research tells us that using the first
letter of objects leads to
a classic misconception in algebra.
It leads students to think that we're
adding 10 apples and 12 pears.
But a doesn't stand for apple.
It stands for the number of apples, which
could be any number, such as three apples.
They aren't ten apples, the cost is ten
times any number that's represented by a.
So, instead if we said 10v plus 1 w.
Where v represents the number of apples w
represents pears,
it stops that misconception at the
beginning.
In algebra, we can represent variables
with any letters.
They don't have to be x and y, with any
objects really, but
they shouldn't be the first letter of the
object.
So, the big problems I see in algebra,
really come from the fact that textbooks
are disconnected from research evidence.
And algebra is introduced in exactly the
wrong way that sets up later failure.
And this is as Bob Moses has said, the new
civil right.
If we really want to erase the severe
inequalities of the school system as
Jonathan Kozol has described them, and a
principle that I presume we all hold,
then we need to change the teaching of
algebra.
So, how do we do this?
My first principle of teaching and
learning algebra,
which I've just talked about at length,
involves starting students with engaging,
meaningful problems that lead to both
exploration and generalization.
And we're going to be looking at some
soon.
Teach algebra as a problem solving tool.
Somewhere along the way, something
Important flipped in the teaching of
algebra and it stopped being seen as a
problem solving tool, and
instead became the end point, the thing
you solve for.
Nick Fiori notes this reversal when he
says, problems have become a resource for
practicing algebra instead of algebra
being learned and
used as a tool for exploring problems.
Teach algebra is a sense making
experience.
If it doesn't make sense then the work
should be stopped,
instead of paring on down a negative path.
So, as the equals sign is often taught in
a very misleading way,
from early on in school, and can lead to
some of the confusion.
In earlier school experiences, the equal
sign is often used as an announcement of
a result rather than to express a
symmetrical relationship.
And by that I mean, both sides of the
equal sign need to be equal.
Often, the equal sign is taken to mean and
this gives, with a sort of left to right
direction.
So, this example comes from a great
chapter Carolyn Kieran wrote on
Algebra learning.
An example is this.
Daniel went to visit his grandmother who
gave him $1.50,
then he bought a book costing $3.20.
If he has $2.30 left, how much money did
he have before Visiting his grandmother.
So, try that problem.