So, our summer school students were hugely
enthusiastic about the five weeks.
And their two main reasons they gave were
collaboration and inquiry.
Not because they were fun, but
because they apprciated that those two
aspects of the class helped them learn.
So, here's just a few of the students
talking about that.
So in interviews in response to the
question did talking about math help you
and how?
These are some responses from students one
of them said I used to
use only one way the teacher taught me and
not really understand it.
Now, I use different ways until I can get
it.
In normal school you don't get to do this
but it helped me understand things more.
So, they're talking about talking.
It helps me see how they see it and to see
if I could understand it.
And when we can see the problems in
different ways,
we would understand it better.
One of the great, most eloquent students
we interviewed was
a young African American girl who told us
it's like the way,
the way our schools did it is like, very
black and white.
And the way people do it here, it's like,
very colorful, very bright.
You have very different varieties you're
looking at.
You're can look at it one way turn your
head and
all of a sudden you see a whole different
picture, which is great.
In response to a question on what really
helped you about the math's approach
the students talked about inquiring.
They talked about that concept of
generalization.
So, here's one saying.
I've learned that after finding a patent
you can stretch it in many ways instead of
just staring at it.
I've learned to think beyond the answer to
the problem and
another one saying when I'm done I can
think of something harder to do.
These students refer to the fact that when
students who are faster finished a problem
we would ask them to extend it or
adapt the problem to make a new problem,
which they loved doing.
Another one saying generalizing helped me
to look beyond the problems and
make challenges for myself.
Patterns were very helpful because
sometimes the question was asking about
the huge numbers.
So, then I would just start with some
smaller numbers, find a pattern and
predict the answer without just taking a
lot of time and
effort to do the one big problem.
And this is one of the student's notebook
pages just reviewing the week before.
So, the summer school is a great
experience we saw huge change in
the students in engagement and in their
ways of approaching mathematics and
in algebraic understanding.
And one of them said to us at the end of
the summer if math was like this every day
I'd want to do it all day and all week.
In the fore we went to observe the
students back in their regular math
classes we went to 15 of them and in
everyone we saw them sitting in
rows working through worksheets solving
for x in silence.
So, these students what they had really
wanted in from that showed that they
learned from this intervention was to be
given hard challenges.
They actually really like to get the hard
work particularly the ones who are in
low tracks in their schools.
They wanted to gain understanding through
discussion.
They want to be able to stretch problems
and
determine mathematical pathways, which is
the inquiry piece.
And, really, they want to add some color
to their mathematical landscapes and I'm
going to quote from the same student again
when we caught up with her in the fall.
And she reflected saying, I would say the
only way to describe summer school is
very colorful and then this class is just
still, ugh, black and white.
And you just want to ask can I have a
little bit of yellow?
So, I'm going to end this lesson just by
restating her plea,
to bring the color into algebra teaching.
To make it more inquiry based,
based on the core principles of algebra,
generalization, relationships,
exploration, not just on procedural
algebra.
And in the last session we're going to
bring together allot of
the different ideas we've learned in
different sessions, so.
Here are my principles again in case they
are useful for
you around the teaching of algebra.
And in the reference section there are a
lot of resources for
great algebra problems and tasks to use.
So, I'll look forward to seeing you next
session.