[MUSIC].
So the fourth section I want to talk about
is the way we group students in schools.
Earlier this year in Denver, Colorado, I
asked 800 teachers and teacher leaders.
You may have been there.
How they thought students received fixed
mindset messages in schools?
Where do they come from?
And the number one reason chosen, which I
agree with, was the ability
grouping that's used in schools, whether
we call it tracks or sets.
And I think that's right.
The biggest fixed mind set message we give
to kids is to tell them you're low,
high, or middle ability.
In England, many students don't just think
of themselves as low or
high, they think of themselves as a number
and students will tell each other and
parents, I'm a level four, or even worse,
I'm a nothing.
There's a paper written about that in the
reference section.
Now not many countries are, are as extreme
as that in the labeling.
But whenever or however ability grouping
happens to students,
whether they're grouped within or across
classes.
They start to develop fixed ideas about
their potential, and
those fixed ideas don't normally stop at
math.
In my daughter's school in England,
they used to put students into ability
groups at age 5 for maths.
And the kids came home after that happened
saying, oh,
all the clever children have gone into a
different group now.
So they get ideas about each other's
ability,
not just about their math potential.
They get very fixed messages about their
intelligence.
So one of the main messages we get from
the brain and the mindset research is
that when students think they're in a low
group, everything begins to unravel.
Even kids in top groups get fixed mind set
messages.
You're the smart ones, and that's damaging
for them.
It may feel good for a while but it will
hold them up in their later work.
As students with a fixed mind set just
can't learn as well as we've seen.
Now, intuitively I think it makes a lot of
sense to group students according to
notions of ability or what they know at
that time.
Teachers can target material to students
more accurately, and that seems good.
But let's look at the evidence because
there's really been a lot of evidence on
this topic.
And what we know is, the countries that
group students by ability, the least and
the latest are the most successful in the
world, Finland, Japan, lots of countries.
When teachers in England put students into
ability groups,
researchers found that one-third of the
children were put into the wrong group,
even just looking at achievement.
We also know that about 88% of students
put into groups at ages four and
five stay in those groups for the rest of
their school career.
And in very careful experimental studies
of students who go through tracked or
mixed achievement groups the studies find
no advantages and
significant disadvantages for students in
tracks and sets.
So let's look at a couple of those
studies.
The first one was conducted in the US by
Carol Burris, Jay Heubert, and Hank Levin.
So in that study they followed students
over three years when they were in
tracks in middle school and then they, the
schools untracked and
they continued to follow students for the
next three years.
And when they were doing that, all of the
students were
taking the highest level work in those
untracked classes.
And what they found was the untracked
students achieved more,
they took more advanced courses, and
they passed the state exams a year earlier
then the students who worked the tracks,
and those advantages were across the
achievement range.
In England, researchers followed 14,000
children through years four and six.
Comparing those taught in sets with those
grouped heterogeneously over the period of
a year.
And those taught in sets, or tracks,
scored at lower levels on tests of
reasoning, and again that came from
across.
The achievement range and the references
for those, that is,
in the reference section.
And then, finally, the National Research
Counsel in the U.S.,
has made a number of reports about
tracking.
They recently reported with the Institute
of Medicine.
They gave a report that concluded both
formal and
informal tracking viability be eliminated.
And alternative strategies should be used
to ensure appropriately challenging
instruction for students who vary widely
in their skill levels.
So studies that are more in depth have
also been conducted,
I've conducted them and others, where
students are being followed through
grouping systems over years, different
grouping systems.
And they produce exactly the same as human
results, with higher results for
students in mixed groups, but they also
show more why that happens.
So I want to pause for a moment and ask
you the question.
Why do you think tracking / setting,
results in lower overall achievement for
students in these different studies?