Some people argue that open inquiry
approaches are only for
high achieving students or students from
more wealthy homes.
The most of the Phoenix Park students
lived on a housing estate,
I think like a project in the US, that the
police wouldn't go onto at night.
And they came to the school mathematically
weak and
significantly below the national average
in their maths achievement.
They left the school significantly above
the national average.
The students at Phoenix Park, even though
they learned through open problems,
still learned standard mathematical
methods, but they may/g, they learned them
through an inquiring relationship, which
meant they learned how to use them.
And this stayed with them into their work
lives.
When I caught up with both sets of
students as young adults about 24,
I found that the [UNKNOWN] students were
in more professional jobs that were
higher on the social class scale,
even though they were living in a much
poorer area of the country.
Their inquiry relationship had clearly
stayed with them and
insured their success.
The interviews of both sets of the
[UNKNOWN] were very interesting and
they were in the paper.
Called psychological prisons, in the
reference section.
But here's one of the young adults
speaking in a way that's pretty typical.
I ask, what happens if you don't know how
to do something with maths in work?
And she said, keep on going until I do.
Because I wouldn't, if something is, if I
can't do it, then it annoys me.
I need to see something through really
until the end.
So I need to understand how I've done it.
If I don't immediately understand it,
then I will keep on going at it until I do
understand it.
The other school students I've seen
develop this sort of relationship were in
the INP program IMP is a high school
curriculum and
the only one that I would describe as
inquiry based in the US.
It's won awards, and was sponsored by the
National Science Foundation, but
has largely been eliminated because people
campaigned for
it to be replaced by procedural
approaches.
Some schools and some states still use it.
And lots of them use it with great results
and
the graduates from that program are very
interesting.
Like and like you know, there similar to
the Phoenix [INAUDIBLE] students.
Chris software engineer at Udacity, who
you've already heard from.
Told me, one of my very first meetings
with him, that the only reason he could do
his job now, was because of the way he'd
learned maths through IMP.
And this is Chris talking about that.
>> I managed to spend my seventh eighth,
ninth and
tenth grades through middle school and
first half of high school in
a math program called, The Interactive
Math Program,
which was developed by a guy here I think
in the Bay area.
That, and it was inquiry based math which
I didn't know anything about at the time.
We talked back then a lot about deep
learning and
shallow learning and it's pretty
controversial you know a lot of
parents you know yanked their kids out of
the program because it was so weird.
I loved it and it was just based on
problems.
You know we had problems of the day, and
problems of the week that all you know
culmanated into the problem of the unit.
And they presented, you know, these
problems, you know, like, that we have to,
you know, try and solve, and we'd have no
idea how to solve them.
And two months later,
all of a sudden, out of nowhere, we had
all the tools we needed to solve them.
And that turns out to be exactly what I do
from day to day.
Which is and learning the skills, and
having the courage to just sit down and
try to figure out how to solve something.
And then after that learn the vernacular
that is incorporated you know,
into that, you know.
Though, I was pretty lucky I think to have
that guidance early on.
And that certainly set you know, built the
framework for
which I pretty much, accomplish things in
life.
>> Mm-hm.
>> When I follow students through IMP
classes,
I saw the inquiry relationship develop.
They also did well on standard tests.
One of the boys I asked in an interview
what he thought about math said this,
"Math is really beautiful, and it has
these patterns in it that are amazing".
Most art is just made of up patterns
anyway, and so
I've written a lot of poems about it and a
lot of songs.
You can tell it's Californian.
Involving it.
Polyrhythms is one thing that kind of
interspersed music and math for
me, because it's like patterns that take
multiple measures to
repeat because they don't fit evenly over
four bars.
And it's exactly like a fraction because
if you take a fraction high enough,
there's going to be common denominators.
And so seeing how patterns can be
interesting and artistic.
And math intersperses a lot for me that
way.
When I've shared that quote with people
and
they said, wow, that is such an unusual
view of maths.
But actually, it sounds very similar to
mathematicians talking about maths.
And there's a very simple reason for that.
It's because Toby had a school approach
where he was working like a mathematician
rather than the usual approach which is
unlike the maths of mathematicians or
the maths of the world.
So, teachers can build that relationship
with their students.
So can parents as we'll hear in a minute
and they'll be sure to
build that relationship from kindergarten
up, by asking students to be curious,
to take risks, to turn, to learn math
through problem solving.
So the maths we want in classrooms is
really multi dimensional.
Uni dimensional mass is mass that has 1
dimension often its
reproducing matter that the teacher's
shown here.
Multi dimensional math is about teaching
the maths the mathematician work with and
all of its dimensions.
So it might include asking questions.
A really important part of a
mathematician's work is coming up
with a good question.
Connecting methods and ideas using logic
and reasoning.
Using, adapting and applying procedures.
Using intuition, making sense of
situtations.
I've written something for
people in this course, that I've been
meaning to write for a long time.
Which is really a summary of what I've
told you explained about maths teaching.
As a one page document that you can
download and keep it, it's helpful.
It's sort of what I think needs to be
happening with students in maths
classrooms, and it comes from research and
experience, and I thought something very
brief might be helpful for you to use with
parents, administrators, and others.
Parents have a very important role in
building this relationship too, and
I want to introduce you now to another
high level math tutor,
that we haven't met before, and she is
super interesting.
For parents, teachers, anyone.
So, her name is Sarah Flannery.
And at the age of 16, she won the Young
Scientist of the Year Award in Ireland,
for a new idea she developed in
mathematics and cryptography.
She has a great autobiography in which she
talks about how she came to develop.
What I see is a perfect mathematical
inquiry relationship.
And she got that from her parents.
Her book's called "In Code".
In it, she says that working on math
puzzles with her family did more for
her than all the years of math classes in
school put together.
So here's Sarah talking about math.
>> My parents definitely let me see that
mathematics was this beautiful subject.
I think a lot of people never even hear
those two words in the same sentence.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So
they gave that to me, and they gave me,
through these different puzzles where even
I thought I couldn't start out on them.
They showed me, no, you have lots of tools
and techniques and
ways to visualize and get started.
And you can do it and, and then they
talked a lot about
the mathematicians themselves and their
lives,.
We did a lot puzzles at home.
We had a blackboard in the kitchen and,
you know, when I talked to my dad about
those times he said, that we hound him for
puzzles and my dad says that he collects
puzzles like someone might collect jokes.
You know, and when I read your book and
I see you talking about the benefits of
doing long problems, or
of working in groups, or of understanding
when it's important to, you know,
to estimate, to visualize, understand the
problem that you're working on.
You get all of that from puzzles, or the
absolute range and
variety of the puzzles that my dad managed
to dig up and find for us.
>> What sort of puzzles did you work on as
a child?
>> Well, I mean we worked on all sorts of
things.
Some that you could just work out in your
head by thinking.
And there's the two jar puzzle where you
have you know, two jars of
different sizes and then you try to get an
amount of water that is a size,
that is not one of the jars you've been
given.
You know, and there's typical examples
where you've a jar of size 3,
and a jar of size 5, and you have to get a
size 4.
But that's the kind of puzzle that can be
extended, and once you've solved it for
one and you like it.
And anybody can do it.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And you can do it in different ways.
You can think of it in your head, you can
really, actually, physically do it, or
you can you know, write out cases, and so
on.
And you know, my dad would give us these
puzzles, and
pick a number that, you know, pick one
that wasn't easy, you know.
So if you have a 3 gallon and a 5 gallon,
it's easy to get 2.
But you know, what you do to make, to make
it all the way to 4,
and then he might ask us, well, what other
measurements can you make out of that.
And then he would know that, you know, if
you picked relative primes or
something, you took 5 and 8, then you
could have the puzzle again and
you could do the same exploration over
again.
You know, other puzzles are like, I won't,
I won't go into them all, but
say, say there's a rabbit, there's a
puzzle about a rabbit.
Where you have to figure out how long it
takes them to fall out of
a hole given a certain you know, it crawls
up 3 steps everyday but falls back 2.
And so you have to figure out how many
days does it take to get out of
a 30 foot well.
For example and
that's a puzzle where I don't want to ruin
it but if you think about it you, it
teaches you to not rush ahead too quickly
once you think you've got something.
So make sure, it [UNKNOWN] you to remember
the real world even if
you think you've got a procedure or and
it's funny like that one is,
you know, 3 minus 2 is not always equal to
1 or whatever you, it's.
>> Yeah.
>> Then other ones were things about magic
squares and so
on, where again, my dad would just give a
puzzle.
And it was about numbers and manipulating
numbers, so you could get a,
you know, get a grasp on it.
>> Mm-hm.
But then, he could extend it into
something where it was teaching you
about rotations, and transformations, and
generalize the problem.
And just make you feel like you were
starting to understand what it might be to
do a proof, what it might be to, you know,
to just see more and
more of the subject that is mathematics.
And then he would, you know, put in an
interesting fact about, well,
there's magic squares, and such and such a
square in Germany, or it's in this.
You know painting by Brecht is it, or I'm
forgetting that stuff.
[LAUGH] But I'm struck by it even when I
talk to my dad's you know,
back on those lovely memories I do have of
doing puzzles as a child you know.
Another thing my parents also did which is
not related directly to mathematics but
that you also get through puzzles,
is they tried to make sure that we could
express ourselves well.
>> Mm-hm.
>> [LAUGH] It's a service now by saying
that but,
you know, if you can express yourself
well.
>> huh.
>> Then that's part of
not only learning how to ask good
questions but in,
in figuring out a way of, you know,
organizing your thoughts.
>> Right, right.
>> Being systematic, but then.
>> You know, it's in a really important
thing,
which is not just about mathematics, but
that you can get through puzzles, and
something that will, see, you know, see
you in good stead for
the rest of your life, you know.
>> So I'd like you to write briefly, what
surprised you about Sarah's reflections.