[MUSIC].
So the second piece we're going to think
about is the tasks that are used in
math classrooms or at home.
The task chosen for math lessons are
hugely important for
the development of mindset.
If they're short and
closed with 1 right answer, like most math
questions that are in math classrooms.
And students are constantly either just
getting them right or wrong,
then it's really hard to develop the idea
that math is about growth and learning.
And if you're constantly getting them
wrong,
it's really hard to believe that you can
really do math.
So instead, many students, just from the
tasks they get, come to believe that math
is more about performance and performing,
than it is about learning and growth.
So my colleague Rachel Lambert told me
recently that her son who's six,
came home from school one day and said he
hadn't enjoyed his math class.
And when she asked him why, he said, math
is too much answer time and
not enough learning time.
And I thought that was really interesting,
that even a six year old got
the sense that math classes were not about
space for learning.
Instead they're often about performing.
And the more math classes I visit, the
more I can see that math
classrooms offer maths more of performance
subject that a learning subject.
So what do I mean by that?
A great example of a teacher changing a
problem from one that had
opportunities really only for performing
to one that was a great invitation for
learning within the task.
I'm going to show you now.
She didn't use that framing.
She talks about letting students own the
task in her adapted version.
But look at the opportunities for growth
and
learning in the first, in the second
version of her task that we'll see here.
So the next question for you is, what
ideas did you get
about quality growth mindset math tasks in
the posting you just read?