[MUSIC].
Hello, and welcome to the last class.
So, in this session, I want to review
where we've been.
And think about what could be really
helpful for
you in your journey onwards from this
class.
We also have a few ideas to think about
and some great videos.
So, first, I want us to think a little bit
about geometry.
Because we spent a whole session on
algebra, and
we both thought a lot about numbers.
This is going to be very small, but I
really wanted you to hear a little from
Sophie and Sebastian as they both talk
about geometry in their lives and
work, and they're both very interesting.
So, after each one, after hearing Sophie
and
Sebastian, I would like you to write a
short, two sentence reflection.
What does this prompt you to think about
in terms of geometry teaching in
school and how it could be better?
>> I don't know why geometry didn't work
for me.
I mean, it, for some reason, it was,
I guess it was more abstract than anything
I'd ever done before.
And even the equations of algebra still,
they still seemed accessible,
whereas geometry sort of, it was like you
had to suspend your notions of reality.
Because there were no, there's no such
thing as you know, perfect sphere, or
you know, something, something.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it was not, and
there was nothing, there was nothing
grounded in geometry.
It was these abstract notions, and, and it
was so, [LAUGH] so
easy to space out, right?
I don't know where I'm going with this.
so, which I you know, that sort of is a
good segway.
I mean that the abstraction of geometry
made no sense to me.
And that was my great ah-ha in life, where
suddenly I saw real geometric expressions,
in the real world, you know, in my work.
So, you know, I'm a, I'm a film-maker, and
I went through a process of [UNKNOWN] of
working my way up through the ranks, and
I was a camera assistant for a period of
time.
And as a focus puller, it's your, your job
is to, to,
to figure out the distances between here
and there.
And then if a person walks, or you're on a
dolly or
a crane, you have to figure out what the,
how that distance changes.
With all these sort of geometrical
maneuvers [CROSSTALK].
Really mathematical, and of course you you
don't get to take your tape measure out
while you're shooting or while you're on
this crane or this dolly.
So, you know, you sort of have to use
intuition, but
you also you know, you can start doing
quick math in your head and
go uh-huh, uh-huh the isosceles triangle
[INAUDIBLE].
And I knew all that math, and I had
studied it, and
it was it was, it was somewhere deep in my
brain.
But suddenly I was like, ooh yeah, yeah, I
know where we are.
I know how close we are to that next
number.
Or that you're going to go far then close
based on this sort of, this parabola.
And, and to me that was so exciting.
But I was like, why didn't somebody take
me to a film set when I was 15, and show,
show me this we, you know, and there's
something sexy about a camera, and lights.
And you know, this, this equipment, and
that, that was, that was fun, right?
That was really, that was geometry in its,
in its best.