So, one I thought of was my daughter gets
$3 of pocket money or
allowance if you're in the U.S.
But for every chore she does I add a
dollar.
So, A represents the number of chores in
that expression.
Algebra learning should be about enabling
learners to employ their
natural powers and using algebra to make
sense of the world.
And the most fundamental concepts
generalizing in relationships,
which should be first and foremost.
So, the best way to introduce Algebra as
the leading Algebra researchers state is
through patent growth.
And we again see some examples in a
moment.
Jere Confrey, who's another leading
researcher who studies algebra learning,
calls for a number of things in the
teaching of algebra.
Identifying situations that the students
are excited to investigate.
Motivating that, through the need to
explain, predict and
model, which is the starting road to
Calculus.
Varying representations with visuals,
graphs, tables, descriptions and
making algebraic manipulations some think
that helps solve a problem.
Where, when students are manipulating,
that manipulation also has value for them.
And allow students to use problem solving,
communications, new technologies to engage
in rich modeling situations.
Another research finding that illustrates
for
me how disconnected the algebra textbooks
are from research evidence is this.
I'd like you, in this question, to
represent the cost of apples and pears.
If we know that apples cost $0.10 and
pears cost $0.12.
So, write an expression for that.