So mistakes are important, not only the
huge learning opportunities but
they're critical to setting up attitudes
to maths that are about resilience,
resiliency and the belief that you can do
it.
How great would it be if your child or
your class of students come in with a
belief that they can do any maths and
that they're eager to be given complex
problems, such as those in
the common core and not to be put off if
their first idea doesn't work.
This is a poster that I used to think was
really good when I saw it in classrooms,
and this is what is says.
So the message is good, but not as good as
it can be,
I think, given what we now know about
mistakes.
So your assignment now, is I want you to
design a better poster.
So, as the words that matter you can just
type them, but
I welcome all [INAUDIBLE] creativity at
all time.
So, if you want to create a poster or post
some ideas on paper what I
want to do is photograph it and upload
that photograph.
And we'll feature some of the good ones on
the site.