As you probably know, there's a new
curriculum coming into place for
most states in the United States, and
the most important part of that new
curriculum called the Common Call.
In my view, is a section called
Mathematical Practices, and the first
standard of the mathematical practices you
will see in their big conceptual is this.
It says mathematical practice one, make
sense of problems and
persevere in solving them.
And that practice is being assessed even
in the tests that are being released.
And they're causing students and teachers
to be pretty shocked,
because students have to really think
deeply and persevere.
And they're very different from the
previous multiple choice fill in
the bubble tests that we used across most
states in the United States.
So students will not develop assistance
unless they're given more open and
challenging problems.
And teachers and students can really break
out of that didactic contract and
that's really important.
But the students have to develop comfort
with mistakes.
If making a mistake shakes their
confidence they're likely to give up, so
in a minute we'll think about way to do
that, ways to help them in those ways.
But we still think about why mistakes are
important.
We thought about learning, we thought
about persistence, and
the third important reason that I want to
talk about is life.
[MUSIC]
Peter Sims,
the New York Times columnist again, and
these are his closing comments on
his article on how to create entrepreneurs
and design thinkers.
And he said invention and
discovery emanate from the ability to try
seemingly wild possibilities.
To feel comfortable being wrong before
being right,
to live in the world as a careful
observer, open to different experiences,
to play with ideas without prematurely
judging oneself or others,
to persist through difficulties and have a
willingness to be misunderstood,
sometimes for long periods despite the
conventional wisdom.