So the research conducted by Carol Dweck
and
her colleagues on student mindset has been
really interesting and important.
And there's going to be an interview with
Carol later, especially for
math teachers and parents.
But first let's look at some of
the recent things that have been learned
about the brain.
And the key finding that everyone is
talking about,
is what is referred to as brain
plasticity.
So, people used to think that some people
had the brain for math or other subjects
and some didn't, but recently there have
been stunning examples of brain growth.
Now, the brain isn't actually made of
plastic, but the idea of neuroplasticity
refers to the life long capacity of the
brain to change and rewire itself.
In fact there have been stunning examples
of the brain's ability to
create new neurons and connections in
recent years.
So when learning happens, the synapse
fires.
Electric currents fire and create new
neurons and connections between neurons,
and the paths of a synapse are like
footprints in the sand.
They can become firm paths if they're
traveled a lot, but
without use, they wash away.
And the brain is so flexible, its changing
by the minute.
It's losing and gaining connections.
You may even be gaining or
losing, hopefully, the former synaptic
connections right now.
So, let me introduce you now to the life
of a London cab driver.
All London drivers have to learn 320
routes that help them remember and
learn the 25,000 streets and 20,000
landmarks and
places of interest within a six mile
radius of Charing Crossing in London.
So it's extremely complex, and
they have to pass a test which is called
The Knowledge.
All Black Cab drivers have to have passed
It takes between two and four years to
pass the All London Knowledge.
And once you're licensed, you can work
anywhere in the greater London area.
Here's a photo of London's streets.
As you can see, there's no grid structure
in London.
So what the researchers found is that the
taxi drivers go through a training period,
and by the end of their training period,
the hippocampus had grown.
When they retire from being a black cab
driver later in life,
the hippocampus shrinks back down again.
They also found that compared to the
brains of London taxi
drivers with London bus drivers, and
the London bus drivers don't have to learn
such a complex set of routes, and
found the hippocampus of the taxi drivers
was bigger than the bus drivers.
So the region of the hippocampus that had
grown is the, is specialized in acquiring
and using complex spatial information in
order to navigate efficiently.
So a second example of brain growth was a
nine year old girl who had half of
her brain move, removed.
She was having fits and they literally
took out one hemisphere.
And at first her left side, her whole left
side was paralyzed, but
she amazed doctors.
As within weeks she'd grown connections
back and
eventually in a very short time developed
all of her functions back.
And that was because of the incredible and
fast growth of her brain.
And then the third example, that was
interesting.
Researchers at the National Institute of
Mental Health found that after a 3
week intervention, 3 weeks of working
differently,
participants in the experiment changed the
structure of their brains.
So, we now know that all students, maybe
except, you know, those with a very
specific learning disability, but all
other students can achieve at the highest
levels in maths, in all levels of school,
okay, right up to the end of high school.
And other countries that believe this
about students do a lot better than we do
in the US or the UK, so countries such as
Japan.
So here's the irony, children can develop
half a brain or
change their brain significantly yet,
we think kids can't develop a few neurons
they need to learn algebra.
Many people think that some kids are
capable or smart or high ability or
what you want to call it and some are not.
Now we all know that students come into
math classes with some of them
finding work easier, some finding it
really challenging, but
that doesn't reflect their potential for
future work.
What it tells you is that students have
been having different experiences since
childhood and some of those experience
have been causing synapses to fire and
some haven't.
So as teachers our job is really to
disrupt the trajectories of students who
haven't had challenging experiences, and
it's to provide all students for
the richest and most challenging
environment possible.
If our brain can change in three weeks,
think what students can do over the course
of a year with the right materials.
So to recap, brain research tells us a
number of things.
It tells us every child can excel in
mathematics in school from elementary to
high school.
It tells us about the potential of the
brain to grow,
no matter where students start from, and
that potential is huge.
It tells us that every new learning
experience is, changes your ability.
Even though we think of students of having
a certain ability or not being high or
low, every experience can change that
ability.
So we use fixed ability language all the
time, high and low kids, and
we need to rethink that.
So scientists know that kids can develop
the wiring to learn any maths in school,
but many teacher and parents still believe
in a kind of natural ability.
And a number of schools, probably most
schools,
are still set up on outdated models of
fixed ability thinking.
So if you wanted to take on this new
evidence on brain growth and
ability, how would it change what you do?
In your classroom, if you're a teacher, or
in your interactions as a parent, or
another helper, or
in your school if you're an administrator,
or leader who's planning schools.