So, we found that those differences in the
task lead to different forms of
engagement and different learning
opportunities with a visual version,
helping students see the meaning of
variables, and understand functional
growth as a function, instead of just
looking down the columns of the table.
They also differ on this learning
performing dimension with one
really encouraging growth and learning.
The other appearing to have one
performance answer that can
quickly be found.
So you can make that change from a
performance task to
a growth mindset task or a learning task
with any math task.
And in fact my student Dan Meyer has been
compiling some great versions on his site,
and that's a link to that site here.
So, I'm going to give you a peer
assignment now which is
something you'll do and you'll see a
peer's work and, and
give a comment on that and you'll get a
comment back to yours.
And my assignment is, I want you to come
up with an example of your own,
a task that starts off as closed and
short.
And encouraging fixed mindset thinking,
I'm sure you can just think of one of
those easily.
And then, a way of adapting that to make
it more of a growth mindset task.
So I'd like you to write those down, write
about that process.