So we're going to be talking about all of
these ideas in the sessions that follow.
Now the data I've just shown you is about
a serious crisis, but
in one very large section of the US
population, but it doesn't end there.
That's a crisis for students in two year
colleges there are students that don't get
into two year colleges, and for them, the
problem are probably worse.
And then the four year college system.
We also have plenty of students who are
really harmed by mathematics.
I released this book for parents and
the public a couple of years ago, with a
US version and a version for the UK.
And this prob, that book took me on a
journey that I hadn't been before,
during which I met a huge number of highly
professional and educated people.
Many of them women, who were absolutely
terrified of maths.
Now I've always known that far too many
people have a terrible time with math.
But these people really showed me the
depth of trauma and
the severity of the reaction.
So when that book came out I was in feed
on about 40 different radio
stations across the U.S and BBC stations
across the UK.
And the presenters almost all of them
shared with me
their own stories of trauma.
It was kind of interesting.
I I was introduced as this mathematics
education professor, but early on I
said that I know that mathematics is very
traumatic for lots of people.
And as soon as I said that the session,
the interviewers we opened up and
the sessions became more like therapy
sessions.
As these different people shared their
tales of trauma.
So we're going to listen to one of them
from the US.
This was Kitty Dunne reporting on
Wisconsin Radio.
>> Well why is it that, why is math such a
scarring experience for so many people?
Is it something about the people who are
into math, just, aren't, they're, maybe,
just, don't know that much about teaching,
and engaging kids?
Because it's two sides of the brain?
Or what, what's going on there, that, that
happens?
I mean, for me, I mean, I still remember
the name of the author of my algebra book,
because it's, like burned into my head.
>> Oh dear.
>> [LAUGH] [LAUGH] You know what I mean?
>> Yeah.
>> And so, I, I guess, I don't know, how,
why is it that there are a lot of great
English teachers.
You don't hear of a too many kids with
scarring English class experience.
>> No, that's right.
I mean, math really plays a unique roll in
our children's lifetimes and
being that subject that can crush their
confidence.
So what was notable to me was really how
much it had hurt people what a kind of
scarring experience it was for them.
But in case you think, well journalists
and reporters are kind of
artsy media types I want to introduce you
now to an amazing woman.
Called Vivienne Parry, OBE,
that's Order of the British Empire, a
medal that is given to you by the Queen.
And she's a pretty incredible person.
She's a scientist, a top scientist.
She's Vice chair of counsil for University
College of London.
Member of the Medical Research Council.
She presents BBC TV science programs, and
she's author of, several books.
So I asked Vivian to introduce me, when I
gave a talk at the Royal Institution in
London a couple of years ago.
This is a picture of the Royal
Institution.
We're going to listen now to Vivienne's
introduction of me in that talk.
>> Well the reason that I think I'm here
telling this is
because I did a program for radio for
about Dyscalculia.
And have myself tested, and was shammingly
bad at maths and
a couple of two or three weeks ago Lenny
Henry and I did a program together.
Where we talked about our awful, awful
maths experiences at schools.
And when I did this program, I said that I
was reduced to
sobbing in the corner because Mrs Glass,
my math teacher made me stand there.
Because I couldn't do my seven times
table.
And do you know, five women called the BBC
Action Line and
said was it Mrs.Glass of Rookesbury Park?
[LAUGH] , [SOUND].
And you know ladies and gentlemen, it
surely was.
[LAUGH].
And ever since then, one of the things
that we, were both saying was that.
We always thought that people who could do
maths were clever, so
that if you couldn't do maths.
It must mean that you weren't clever, and
both Lenny Henry and
I have this secret shame, well not with my
secret.
All our lives about being bad at maths,
and I was always afraid that Mrs.
Glass would jump out.
When I was at the BBC, tap me on the
shoulder and
say that's it Parry, you've had your lot,
we've discovered you.
So, math really, has an enormous effect,
on children's lives.
And it can, bad teaching can, blight their
lives.
So, I am delighted to introduce Professor
Joe Bo.
>> So this is Vivian describing maths in
her life.
She says, This has pursued me through my
whole life.
It's so undermining of your whole being to
be so
bad at maths, you just feel so stupid.
So here's this top scientist who feels so
awful about her maths relationship,
she told me that even if she was getting a
medal, her OBE from the Queen.
She was worrying, because I'm not good at
maths, I'm an impostor.
So this fear and trauma with maths is very
damaging, it's very widespread and
it cuts across achievement levels and
success levels in the population.
You may yourself have this sort of
relationship with maths, and
if you do I hope this course will really
help with that.
So I'm going to ask you a question now,
which is,
how surprised are you by the information
and data I have just presented?
How does this connect, if at all, with
your own students or
your own reason for taking this course?
So this is the first time of many that you
are going to be asked to write a response.
This time it's just for me and the other
teaching assistants to read.
Sometimes it will be seen by others, but
I'll tell you about those times.