So in the Cathy video we watched,
we saw a task that could definitely be all
about performance.
One divided by 2 3rd, if that 2 3rds, if
that was given to students as a question,
definitely they could just see that as one
quick answer that they meant to show.
But Cathy transformed that task by asking
students about different ways they
could make sense of 1 divided by 2 3rds,
and that opened it up.
You know?
Along with the culture of her class, it's
all about learning and
explore, and exploring.
And that opening encouraged opportunities
for a growth mindset.
So at Stanford, we've been collecting good
resources for
tasks at different grade level.
And I've put Alice into the Wiki section,
and it's an ongoing process.
We are constantly looking and adding to
it, but if you have task or
resources such as book references that you
think are really great.
Or it might be web pages,
please put it under the Wiki section that
will be there headed, Great Task.
And then, at the end of the class we can
send out the stats to everyone.
[MUSIC].
So the third section I want to talk about
is something very important which is
the way you assess and grade and give
feedback to students.
That's a really important place for the
encouragement of a great mindset.
For many students, they receive multiple
choice tests, or
closed questions, that tell them how well
they're doing or how badly they're doing.
Compared to others, usually.
But really give them no information about
the path for growth and improvement.
So, two professors in the UK, Paul Black,
who is my PhD adviser, and Dylan William.
To get to the master analysis of all the
studies that have taken place on
what sometimes called formative assessment
or assessment for learning.
So, the difference between formative and
summative assessment is Summative is
an end of unit assessment that shows
performance.
Formative assessment in this, is an
assessment that informs learning for
the student and the teacher.
And can also used be used summatively.
But from the meto analysis of studies that
looked at the impact of assessment for
learning.
Black and William found that if scores
were to use that more often.
It would raise the ranking of a country
such as the US.
Which sits in the middle of the pack and
international assessments to a place in
the top 5.
So really, that one change could have a
massive impact on the way students learn.
So assessment for learning is based on the
principle that students have a full and
clear sense of where they are going, and
what, and
what they have to do to be successful.
That may sound obvious but I’ve found that
students in math classes rarely know
where they are in their learning path.
Either what they’re learning beyond the
chapter title.
Sometimes I go to students in math classes
and
I say, Oh, tell me what you’re working on,
and they’ll say, Oh, chapter three.
And I'll say, oh, so what are you working
on exactly?
And they'll say, oh, I'm sorry, question
four and
they really can't tell me more than that.
So assessment for learning is about how we
should know where they are and
also how they can be successful.
So it's really about communicating three
things, where students are,
where they need to be , and a way to close
the gap between the two.
Most students in math classrooms really
get nothing from an assessment result
other than a rank or
an evaluative statement about where they
are compared to others.
Like, a grade such as B or D.
That information for students,
particularly for
those who are getting D's and are under
performing.
Is really damaging for them as it's a
constant knocking their self esteem.
So a really interesting experimental study
was conducted by Butler, and
he compared three conditions.
Well first of all he compared just two
conditions, he gave students grades.
And then in the other condition they gave
students diagnostic feedback.
And what they found was the students who
had no grades, but
they got diagnostic feedback did
significantly better in the future.
Then they added a third group and they
said, Oh, why don't we give them both?
So they gave grades, grades and feedback
and just feedback and
they found, that again, it was the
students who only got feedback.
Who outperform the others and those who
got grades and
feedback did the same as those who just
got grades.
Because it turned out that once you give a
grade, the student just looks at that.
They thought it might be the best of both
worlds to get both.
But they found that the very best thing
you can do for
students is to ditch the grade and give
them diagnostic feedback.
And that feedback, helps them understand
how they can improve.
So assessment for learning makes use of
diagnostic feedback.
And its main focus is on helping students
become aware of where they are and
where they should be in ways that help
them bridge the gap.
And that awareness is often built through
self and peer assessment.
Teachers set mathematical goals for
students, not list of chapter titles or
contents.
But, details of the important ideas and
how they are linked.
And they can be given a statement, sort of
very clear and
communicate the point of the work that
they are working on.
For example the students could have the
statement,
I have understood the difference between
mean and median and
know when they should be used.
Very clearly tells them the point of that
lesson or piece of work.
The students then assess their, or their
peers, work against the statements.
And as time goes on, something really
important happens.
Students start to take more responsibility
for their learning as they become aware of
what they should be learning, and what the
important ideas are.
And in studies of self-assessment in
action,
researchers have found students are very
perceptive about their own understandings.
And they don't over or underestimate it.
So a question for
you now, think of some key things in maths
that people need to work on.
Could be for a future class of yours or
something that your children work on at
home.
And think of a way of writing one or
two statements to show students what's
important to know.
For example, if I was teaching students
through area models to
understand fractions, I might give them
this statement.
I understand that fractional parts of a
whole always have to be equal in size but
not in shape.
And that would be a statement that they
could take and
think about how well they've understood
that.