So, the function you just worked on is one
of linear growth.
And if we look at a table of the values,
or we plot the values on a graph,
we can see that the growth is constant and
the graph is linear.
I don't ask students to make tables and
plot graphs, as it leads them to look down
a table and work out a pattern, and
make [INAUDIBLE] make it into an algebraic
expression,
with really little understanding of what
that expression means.
instead, this this article which is really
great, I recommend reading it,
shows the way two people saw it visually.
The people who arrived at the algebraic
generalization in
this way can also tell you what that n
represents,
whereas those who work it out from a table
usually can't do that.
Not surprisingly, as they haven't had the
opportunity to see the n visually.
And so, in this case, you'll notice that,
that n doesn't represent one single
number, it represents any case number.
So, in procedural algebra, the answers are
numbers.
In structural algebra, students are
learning to work with and represent, and
act on algebraic symbols.
And the result is an, another algebraic
expression.
So, when I say act on,
I mean things like simplifying, factoring,
finding equivalence and so on.
So, students start algebra usually finding
a single value x or for n.
A lot of times, so, they get a lot of
practice and that, and
then they move to the more important work
in algebra, where the x or the n,
or whatever the variable represents any
number.
This is a huge conceptual shift, and
it's not surprising that many students get
stuck in the first idea.
So, the research in algebra tells us that
students should start algebra with
exploration of patterns, leading to
structural algebra and
variables representing a single number
that can vary, not a single solution.
Finding, using situations where there's
one single solution can be
introduced later when students have
learned about the main ideas in algebra.
So, these are two very different ways of
working, and
they develop two mindsets around algebra
and what algebra is.
The one we want and we desperately need
kids to develop is a generalizing mindset.
And that comes from work in structural
algebra.
But most school textbooks start students
in procedural algebra with lots of
solving for x.
Not only does this lead students away from
a generalizing mindset, but
it's deadly boring often and meaningless
for most students.
Instead of sending them down that
unhelpful pathway from the beginning,
we urgently need to start students on a
path of generalization and
relationship exploration through rich and
engaging problems.
So, to illustrate the difference, try
these two questions.
Here's the standard way students were
introduced to algebra.
Evaluate the following expression for the
given values, 4x plus 1,
when x equals 1, x equals 2, x equals 3.
Or, we have a different question, describe
how the shape is growing.
Can you use x to represent the number of
blocks at any stage?
Now, that second example may take slightly
longer, but it's all about connections and
a meaningful understanding of algebra.
Students need that extra time to
understand generalization and
to start on a path which will take them to
calculus and beyond the college.
[UNKNOWN] administered an assessment to
see whether students could use
algebraic letters as a generalized case
after they had learned algebra.
And what he found was, 73% of 13 year
olds, 59% of 14 year olds, and
53% of 15 year olds, could only treat
letters as a particular number.
So, they got stuck in the procedure,
procedural algebra that there were
introduced to at the beginning.
So, why do students find it so hard to
move past this?
It's not because they're not capable of
generalization.
And John Mason, who is a great writer
always he and his colleagues put it well.
They say, expressing generality is
entirely natural, pleasurable, and
part of human sense making.
They also state that every learner who
starts school has
already displayed the power to generalize
and abstract from particular cases.
And that is the root of algebra.
So, the classic procedural introduction to
algebra has a big impact on
students' thinking.
And the lack of teaching of generalization
through exploration means that
students are immediately led to miss the
point often.
Carolyn Kieran found that when students
were asked to express the meaning of a +
3, they couldn't, because there is no
equal sign, and
no number on the other side.
So, as an illustration of what they hope
students would see that,
try yourself think of a real situation
that can be represented by a + 3.