So everybody worked on this, and then we
got everyone to just come up and
put one of their solutions on the board,
which they were happy to do.
And they became excited.
They were totally engaged by the activity,
which actually is a great one, because it
practices a number of operations, but it
does that through an enquiry approach.
So that was a low-stress beginning, for
them coming up to the board, and
we gradually got them more used to it.
We wanted them to have voice, so we gave
them all blank notebooks.
And we asked them the decorate them, make
them their own.
And that was their place for their
mathematical voice, their ideas.
And we didn't write in their notebooks, as
it was meant to be their place.
But we left feedback for them on post it
notes.
And you can see an example of that here.
We started most days with the number talk
which you know about.
And those just blew the kids away.
They had not known that number problems
could be solved in so many ways.
So our research tells us that students are
much more successful in algebra if
they've learned about ways to break
numbers apart, as we talked about.
If they know, for example, that 13 is the
same as 5 plus 8 and
they're fluent in those ways of thinking
Well, 13 equals 5 plus 8.
Then it helps them learn about algebraic
expressions, such as a equals b plus c.
We collected a lot of data to understand
how this different math approach for
the students impacted their learning.
So this is a list of the different data we
collected.
So we had their summer school
applications.
Which had data from their teachers.
Lesson observations.
All the lessons were observed.
Students completed lots of surveys and
reflections.
We interviewed students.
35 during the summer, and 15 in the fall.
And then we analyzed all their class
materials, posters, work.
What they produced.
And then we also had results of MARS
assessment.
So, we haven't intended to give a post
test,
as these students came from different
grades, different schools.
They hadn't worked on the same things.
But we found out that all students had
taken the MARS assessment at the end of
their previous term.
That's an assessment that comes from the
Mathematics Assessment Resource Service.
It's just normal, average, sort of normal
school like test but it's much better and
more conceptual than other school math
tests I've seen.
So the end of five weeks we gave them the
same questions, the algebra questions, and
the students scored with a 24% increase
which was significant,
a significant increase.
And that was great.
Or their intention was less to improve
content as to teach them to
engage in maths with a positive inquiry
relationship that they could take forward.
So, probably the greatest sign of a change
in engagement during the five weeks for
me was their change in behavior.
At the beginning they shuffled in to the
first class, they had their hoods up.
They sat down.
They didn't want to talk.
They only were interested in talking about
social issues.
Not maths.
But by the end it was amazing.
They were jostling at the door to get into
the room and then rushing to get at
the problem or the [UNKNOWN] they had
worked on for 90 minutes the previous day.
And continue on with it.
It was really great.
So, we saw a couple of surveys from the
first day.
Here a.
Two of the same students giving their
response after the five weeks.
So we asked, how does this class feel
compared to
other math classes you've been in?
And she said, it's a lot funner and more
interesting.
And I'm actually learning something about
math.
And we asked, has it been more or less
useful?
And she said more.
Because, in a regular math class, you have
to do everything the teacher's way.
And sometimes, I don't get it.
And in here, I could do the problems
whatever way I want.
And that was super-important to many of
the students,
that freedom to work on problems the way
that they wanted to.
And then the,
another student saying, this is way better
than any other math class I've been in.
You participate more, and you work
together." So
that was interesting because those two
things, participate more and collaborate,
were the two biggest things that came out
as powerful for most of the students.
So one activity we worked on was a famous
activity called the painted cube.
Here's the activity for you to do.
This is along activity, but if you have
time, stop and
work on it now, because it's great.
And try and describe the function that
come out of this.
You can see, it on a graph, if you want to
plot it on a graph,
you'll see that it isn't linear.
And it's kind of exciting to see that
function.
So every time I use this problem with
students from seventh grade up to
Stanford freshmen.
They see the problem in many different
ways.
It's really fascinating.
And I can't show you the video of my
seventh and eighth grade students.
But I have some really nice video of my
freshmen class working on this problem,
which we can look at now.
And my question for you is,
what features of this problem do you think
enabled the learning that came out?
Which aspects of algebra are being worked
on here?
This is like, how we like to work on math
together.
You've been really great at following some
of these norms we developed.
And, the different posters show
some of the math problems.
[CROSSTALK]
[INAUDIBLE]
>> What?
I know.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> And so we'll be
having more/g.
>> [LAUGH]
[INAUDIBLE]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
,
[SOUND]
, [INAUDIBLE].
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And, we found that there
was the same equations that
you guys all found.
But then Joe came by and asked us to
explain how we got our center cube.
And Alonna, Alonna didn't really, like, do
a good job of explaining, so
like, if you imagine this is a three by
three cube sugar block,
she said that you would knock off.
>> Faces, until you are left with a cube
inside.
>> It sort of goes with the onion thing.
Like, if you have let's say, a four by
four cube.
I'm going to take off this slice, this
slice, a slice from the top,
a slice from the bottom, and a slice from
each side.
And then on the inside, there's a cube
left.
I don't know.
It, it's hard to show.
>> [UNKNOWN]
>> Yeah, I just made this as a visual way
to represent it.
And to show all the different, types of
cubes that are represented.
And so, like, this is one way.
Layer.
This is two layers and
this is three layers.
But you can see like even the cubes on the
inside.
And so this, this would be like the cube
that doesn't have any sides painted.
And then these would be the eight corners
that, that have three sides painted.
These would be the faces that have one
sides painted, one side painted, and
then the pink would be the two sides
painted, and so
it's just, like, representing 3D on a 2D
space.
>> Mhm.
And just to help with visual,
visualization,.
The computer really helps.
This is.
So
this is just a demonstration using
mathematical [UNKNOWN].
and, so this a 2 by 2 by 2 and it's pretty
transparent so you can see the corners.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Looking at the corners, you can count the
faces.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
There's a face on the bottom and it's
helpful to see that those
properties really don't change, you know,
then number of faces is staying the same,
even as I increase the number of number of
total cubes.
So the number of corners is going to be
constant, the number of faces is
going to be constant, and even the number
of edges is going to be constant.
It also helps in visualizing the, the idea
that there's a an inside cube.
So.
>> Yeah, so,
this isn't quite accurate then I guess.
yeah, okay I'm confused about,
about the drawing [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] But it really helped you.
>> Yeah, but, but the drawing helped us to
visualize it.
>> Okay so don't, try not to repeat things
other people have said,
see if you can add something different or
different ways of seeing it?
>> Okay.
So first, we did like the 3 by 3,
and then we wrote what we found there.
And then, we did the 4 by 4 but we didn't
actually have enough like cubes, so
sad day for us.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So we actually like,
we didn't count things.
We had to like find patterns, and so once
we started like Like, how we saw?
Yeah, okay.
So, like, for the three by three, we had
six, one color, and then 24 for the four.
So, we actually found that it was 6 times
1, and then 6 times 4, is how we got it,
because you have, for the one color, these
are the ones that like.
Are just in the middle of the face.
So like here, you got like no color face.
And so like we're looking for the middle
because you
can't count the edges cause we just want
the middle of the face.
So it's a defining area, that's going to
be this times that.
So, you have five, right, and then because
you can't count this row or
this row, it'll be five minus two.
And then, same thing up here, so you have
five.
And then you can count this or this, and
then that's going to
be 5 minus 2 then, so it's just going to
be n minus 2 square.
[CROSSTALK] [CROSSTALK] So,
I think we should describe how like the
inside, just slicing off a layer.
>> I agree.
Like [INAUDIBLE].
>> Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
>> I don't know because, I think, if we go
up one more.
>> Mm-mmm
>> This relationship..
>> [CLEARS THROAT] Yeah, yeah, I don't, I
not quite sure how to put this...
[CROSSTALK]
>> But, if, yeah, this, like if we, if we
use a basic...
>> of two.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> This represents, like, two to the zero,
two to the one, two squared, and
two cubed, the amount it changes by.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, and I figure, like, there's
some blank coefficient times,
in [SOUND]
>> Square the nq.
The n to the first.
Or n to the zero.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And I'm trying to find the coefficient
for each one of these.
>> Got it.
Hmm.
>> Yeah.
I don't know if that,
like makes any sense.
[CROSSTALK]
>> [UNKNOWN] Just to do a,
like, number five?
Yeah, and then again.
>> Now two, this one likes works.
>> You know this one is A right,
>> Yeah Are we doing five?
>> Given the cube with N sides we'll have
two exposed, three exposed.
The side is zero.
>> The two is so hard though because they
are all overlapping.
>> Well two is just, I'm good But
I think the rules also, kind of turn into
like the general [INAUDIBLE].
>> I didn't do that.
But I didn't, I didn't that way round,
cause others abusing [INAUDIBLE].
>> [INAUDIBLE] [CROSSTALK].
>> No, you, four separate rules are fine,
you just want know how to find, like each
color.
>> Yeah.
or any given cube.
So you can have two.
Do you want to switch seats right now?
>> and minus two times six.
Yeah, And three exposed.
>> I'm so glad you left it because I
didn't have mine and I thought oh.
>> Which one is that?
Well it's like N, but I feel like you can
make this formula a lot of different ways,
but I feel like N over two, so that's
eight.
Or it's just n times 6.
Because so here it's a [CROSSTALK]
>> That's 12, right?
Or is it just N times four?
>> They're right here.
>> One. [INAUDIBLE] >> So, I dunno if this
makes sense but
does N minus two, times four, times three,
work?
>> Wait, five cubed, what's five cubed?
125, right?
>> So that would be two.
>> So that would be 25 times 5.
>> That does work.
Why does that work?
>> Yeah.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Because so there two.
>> Where'd you get the three from.
>> The three?
Because, the way we did it was like, we
added, we took one whole.
>> The three faces.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> And then four, where's the, four?
Because there's four different things.
>> Yeah, four different things.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Oh, 3, 8.
>> We should try it with 5 afterwards,
because -- there should be 69 ones with 2.
So --
>> What do you mean we should try it with
5?
>> I think you guys -- like if we come up
with a formula for
the one -- the final ones with 2 --
>> Mm-hmm.
>> -- we could try it -- like -- you can
probably narrow it down to
like there has to be 69.
>> Like basically, all the...
>> There is?
>> ...other stuff in there, like for
five, right?
>> There has to be 69 what?
>> Ones with two.
For five, and just basically all the other
stuff we know, like,
there has to be eight, there has to be...
>> Three times twelve.
Wouldn't that be...wait.
Where'd you, I'm just confused.
Where did you get the 69?
>> Oh, okay.
So...
>> because for two, we got the formula,
and
minus 2 times 4 times
>> Mhm
>> Yeah.
Oh for [INAUDIBLE].
I don't know like, it seems like, like,
we can like figure out all the other
things and
then figure out what the two would be for
five.
'Cuz like we came up with stuff for all
the others right?
>> Right
>> Maybe I did this wrong.
So like, for five.
There's going to be