Hello everyone!
And welcome to our Fireside chat.
As you'll see, we have a lovely warm,
toasty fire here, and Holly and
I are going to sit and get nice and cozy.
And, first of all I want to introduce you
to Holly.
This is Holly Pope, she's a graduate
student at Stanford doing a PhD with me.
And Holly was match coach in Pittsburgh
before she came to Stanford.
So just a few words about the course
before we start going through
some questions.
I wanted to say first of all
that this course has really been an
amazing experience for me.
So many people have told me of ways it's
helped them, it's been really great.
The questions you sent in for this
fireside chat just showed me
How much we're together in our mission and
knowledge and values.
Those are really the questions I would
expect to be asked.
Probably, the ones I would have written if
I were you.
So as well as people telling me how
helpful the course has been,
I've been super impressed with the act,
the submissions people have sent in for
the tasks and activities in the course.
So really big congratulations to you guys,
we've achieved the first nuke in math's
teaching and learning.
So that's great.
So, a couple of things just for info for
you,
we have about 40,000 people registered for
the course, which is long-going and
about 300 questions were sent in for this
fireside chat so
we're not going to answer all of those,
you'll be pleased to know.
We've looked at the ones that were most
voted on that seemed to be most,
wanting to be asked.
So I'm going to hand over to Holly now and
we're going to
>> Chat through some of the questions.
>> So thanks for having me here, Jill.
>> It's a pleasure.
>> The first question that I want to ask
you comes, is what comes next?
A lot of people wanted to know what comes
next after this,
how do I bring this home with, what are
some things that I could do?
To get materials and so on.
>> Yeah, sure.
So I think the first thing to talk about
is the student course which
is the course I have been talking about
through this course.
>> Uh-huh.
>> And, what I've been thinking about that
was this.
This course, the course for teachers and
parents was a huge amount of work,
preparing it, teaching it, managing it
much more than I thought it would be.
I think I worked through about twelve
weekends straight in
the run-up to the course.
My kids were complaining, but anyway.
So one thing I want to do, and
think about the student course is plan, is
not move at quite such a fast pace.
So it's very carefully planned, and it's
really a good experience for the student.
So I want it to be very good and I manner
the time it takes for that.
So the co, the student course will be
sometime next year next academic year.
So the other thing I've been thinking
about the student course is ideally,
if I were the teacher giving the students
intervention to help them change in
the views about themselves and about
maths.
Then I think this summer or right at the
beginning of the school year is probably
the best time for that ideally, or maybe
the end of the previous school year.
>> Yeah.
>> So I'm thinking what I would like to do
with the course is have it available for
this school year but late in the school
year maybe spring and
then keep it going through the summer and
into the fall.
So that people can choose to have students
take it this summer or
the fall of maybe spring of this year.
So people also asked how the, how,
how they can register students, when
they'll, when they'll know it's ready.
So we'll send an email out to everybody in
this course when the student course is
getting ready and is ready.
>> Yeah.
>> So the other thing I'd like to mention
is, I would
really like to do research around the
course and find out if it's helpful for
the students who do this course which
would be a short intervention for them.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, what I wanted to ask is, if
there are any teachers or
districts that would work with me on that
research it would be really good to know.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So maybe I could work with whole
districts where some of
the kids take the course.
And there's an e-mail which I also sent
out for people to write reflections on
the course, which is jo, jomathscourse
sorry, jomathscourse@gmail.com.
>> That's jomathscourse@gmail.com.
So maybe if you could send an email to
that, if you are somebody that
would like to help with the research, with
a student course, that'd be great.
>> That's a good idea.
Very good idea.
>> So resources for problems in inquiry
based activities.
A lot of people wanted.
>> Yeah the, the resources.
So I've, there are a number of things.
I guess a number of people asked, can you
send us more inquiry based activities.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Project based work.
Are there good curriculum out there?
Are there more examples of number talks?
Some people asked whether I could send the
lesson plans that we used in our summer
school teaching that I talked about in the
course and the materials and the syllabus.
So loads of things.
And other people ask whether we could give
more a confirmative assessment,
which is very important.
And so many many things that would be
helpful for teachers.
And so what I'm doing now is I'm working
on a new website which is called Youcubed.
>> That's exciting.
>> Yeah youcubed.org and it's not up right
now but it will be by the end of September
and on that website we're going to put
lots of helpful things for teachers.
>> Oh, that's good.
>> So
lots of activities and some of the videos
from the course I think too.
>> So people asked whether there was going
to be a how to do this course and
I did say this in, in the course we just
had that.
It was really just about sparking ideas,
and
it left open the whole question of how do
you teach in these ways,
what are the detailed things you have to
do in classrooms.
So, I think that would be a great follow
on course, and I'm thinking about that.
So, and I think as well this course will
run again.
>> but I'm not sure at this point whether
it's going to be free again or
whether there will be a small cost, stand
for discussions.
But the other thing I wanted to mention
was a number of schools and
teachers have told me that they've
downloaded some of the videos and
they've used them either with kids or with
parents.
So some schools in the US have been using
them at back to school nights.
>> Oh, that's a good idea.
>> Yeah.
And you can do that.
All the videos are downloadable.
So, people have asked me if it's okay to
download them and
what I've said is, it's okay with me to
use them in schools and
with parents and other but not to put on
websites.
I don't really want them to be posted up
on websites.
>> Right, right.
>> Really so those are the you know,
the students course, the follow up course.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And the youcubed site which is going to
be a site where we can put up a lot
resources to, for people to keep working
these ways.
>> And there is also the Wiki from the
class Wiki that has some resources on it
that people can refer to.
>>That's right, you reminded me of that.
So we have got a lot, this, under,
under the Wiki there is a tab called Great
Tasks or something like that, Good Tasks.
So under that is a lot of references to
tasks,
to books full of tasks, So other good
websites and apps and
all sorts of things so yeah, I'm glad you
mentioned that.
That, that's already on the site and under
the Wiki.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> So, the next burning question [LAUGH]
no pun intended was about teaching
untracked groups.
>> Huh
>> Or sets.
And, and set groups
>> Huh
>> As people refer to.
>> them in England.
Do you have any, suggestions on
implementing those ideas?
>> Yeah, so, I mean I think a lot of
people asked kind of how to questions.
Partly to ask if they could be in the
follow up class,
like "How do you teach un-tracked groups"
and we can't in this session just
explain all these complex Things that
teachers need to be doing.
But I wanted to say a couple of things
about the question of un-tracked groups.
And, so I gave,
I showed the evidence in the class about
the success of heterogeneous classes and
groups, and I've worked with a lot of
schools that have un-tracked.
And What, what I know from that is it,
the work of teaching in [UNKNOWN] groups
is not, it's not eas,
it's not an easy shift you can't just
untrack and teach in the same way.
>> Right, right.
>> So teachers do need time and
training to Know the methods for teaching
an on-track classes.
And that training takes time, I mean I
work closely at the moment with the school
district Vista, school district Vista
Unified, school district in San Diego.
And there's a director of mathematics
there, and she and
I have been working with the teachers over
quite a few sessions every year to
help them learn to teach in un-track
groups.
They wanted to un-track, which is great.
And, we've been teaching them.
So, one of the very useful strategies, and
something people can look at is,
complex instruction, that's a pedagogical
strategy for having group work be equal.
Some of the schools I've worked with that
have been very successful have
used complex instruction.
There are complex instruction books that
can be bought, and some of
my articles have a lot more detail about
how to teach through complex instruction.
>>That's good.
>>Another thing I was going to say is
There's different ways of teaching
un-tracked groups.
And it's important that kids, can go to
different places, mathematically,
and be pushed in different ways, it's not
that you un-track and
then everybody gets the same experience,
really.
And I've seen schools work in different
ways,
the [INAUDIBLE] instruction school I
started, which I called Railside Mm hmm.
>> Have students working with a math task
and they all stay together in
fact nobody moved on to the next one and
so it finished but
they really push students pretty much
forward as they worked on activities.
They were kind of,
the tasks themselves were more open than
your sort of standard math questions.
>> Mm hmm.
>> And.
Kids who came in, sort of, at a higher
level and maybe being faster, whatever.
What they found was often those kids were
very narrow,
like they could be fast,
>> yeah,
>> but they were fast on procedures and
when they were pushed to maybe explain
some thing or
help others understand or represent in
different ways they found that hard so
They all stayed on the same task, but kids
were pushed in different ways.
So everybody was challenged all the time.
Without going up higher though.
Whereas the, school I started in England,
which used project based tasks,
the whole premise of that approach was
kids have these open ended projects.
And different kids could take it in
different places, so
what you saw is higher achieving kids
really took them up to high levels,
you know, you could go anywhere with them,
really.
So, I think the thing I wanted to just
stress is that,
you need to change the task that the kids
are given.
And I don't think un-tracked groups really
work really short
procedural math questions.
>> Right, right.
>> Those are focused on one way of
thinking.
They need to be more open and in the way
that I talked about task.
But I think you know that there's training
that needs to be done and
really support, teaches me support.
If I'm moving from tracks into groups
because they're different.
>> I agree, yeah.
>> I also have found though,
that I mean we worked with schools in
England that we didn't have more support
and they put kids into untracked groups
and
they gave them bigger problems
>> And
the teachers were so surprised at how well
it went.
So they were saying to us wow, when I gave
this different kind of problem, it was
that kid who would have been in the bottom
group, and he came up with the idea.
And they really could see how kids were
being much more engaged, and
certainly these schools are working within
Vista, the teachers were saying to
me last week that it's the first time
they've taught kids from all levels, and
it had just been wonderful is the way she
described it to me.
>> Oh, wow.
Wow!
>> So, it's definitely great if there's
training involved, but also I think you
can faith that when you un-track grouped
kids, if you give them problems that
are really more open, that they'll raise,
they'll rise up to the challenge.
>> Right.
So, so
basically, having multiple entry points
but a high expectation.
>> Mm-hm, yeah I think that's.
>> And so that will help them.
>> I mean I do, some people ask always
about the high kids,
are the high kids held back.
>> Yeah.
>> And I should note that you know,
that is not what's found in resesarch when
schools are untracked.
What we find is that the high achievers do
really well, actually.
Better than kids in high top tracks in
other schools and you know it's good,
it turns out,
one thing is the level of discussion kind
of rises to the higher kids.
It doesn't fall to the lower achieving
kids.
But the other thing is they get more kids
to explain.
We all know as teachers,
when you're explaining something, it's a
much deeper level of understanding.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> So, you know can be really good for
the, all kids So the other thing I
guess my book has some more detail If
people are moving to one track groups.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So my book which is called What's Math
Got To Do With in, in the U.S. and
The Elephant in the Classroom in the U.K.
both give much more
detail descriptions of the schools that
are working in one tracks ways.
>> Okay.
So another question about procedural
knowledge.
How do you teach procedural knowledge
through an inquiry-based approach?
>> Yeah.
>> And for upper-level classes.
>> Mm-hm.
Yeah so I think there were a few questions
about that.
>> Yeah.
>> We saw how do you teach the more
procedural aspects of an algebra course
for example.
>> Mm-hmm, mm -hm.
>> From people who really liked more open
tasks but couldn't see all the ways that
those procedural bits of knowledge could
fit in.
>> Right.
>> So, I, I guess I have a couple of
responses to that.
One thing is there are more procedural
parts that need to
be learned in the current curriculum,.
>> Mm-hm.
>> This like collecting like terms and you
know,
all sorts of things with algebraic
expressions really but,.
>> All of procedural knowledge can be
taught conceptually.
>> Yeah
>> In fact, what researchers are finding
now is that you need to
hold all knowledge conceptually, even if
procedure,
>> Hmm
>> isn't held conceptually, it's.
>> Hm
>> Really hard to use it anywhere.
>> Right.
>> So I don't see this distinction between
procedure and, and
conceptual knowledge because you need to
hold those procedural ideas conceptually.
>> Mm hmm.
>> The other thing is though how well kids
do,
when they don't, when we don't focus on
procedures.
So.
>>at Phoenix Park, one of the schools I
worked in I talked a lot about in
the course, they worked on big projects
all the time.
For three years, projects that took their
interests,
the teachers would give them ideas and
they would take them all of these ways.
They didn't cover all of that procedural
>>knowledge that people see in the exams,
but they still did better on the national
exam than kids that practiced on those
procedures and better than average even
though they came in on much lower levels.
So what the teachers did in that school,
is they were hooked on projects for
three years and literally four or five
weeks before the exam they
gave them exam papers That learning of,
you know
thinking that because they'd been thinking
all the time in their maths approach.
When they were given, like, solve these
two sim,
solve these simultaneous equations.
Do you call differently in the U.S.?
>>Systems of equations.
>>[chuckles] Oh, yeah, that's beyond my
level.
[laughs]
>> Then--
>> I'm elementary.
[laughs]
>> I know.
I know [INAUDIBLE] elementary classrooms,
which is a good thing.
So they worked it out because they went
into all those procedural
questions thinking "I know how to do it so
I know nothing is going to stump me." So
So first of all I think when kids will
learn in much more depth and
they learn to think and they're always
reasoning,
problem solving, those procedural
questions are not difficult for them.
But the other thing is,
even when we want to teach those bits of
content that we just can't see a way.
In the bigger activities, there are ways
to do that conceptually too.
Collecting like terms, algebraic
equivelants, those things seem very,
you know, hard to develop through big
activities, but whatever the Mathematics.
There are ways to make them more engaging
for kids.
The Shell center which the reference is
on,
the Wiki, for Shell center, has great
activites and
one of them for example is called
interpreting algebraic expressions.
And they give to kids.
There are four expressions that are shown
in four different ways, table --
through a table, through a picture,
through words and through symbols,
and there are cut-out sheets that teachers
can use with lots of them on And
kids get a set of them, and then they have
to go and find their partners, and,
you know, so I might have this picture,
and I'd think "What is the algebraic
equivelent of this?" And I'd have to go
and find somebody else who has that.
So you can get kids moving around,
thinking about equivelance, or
they can do it on the table, I mean,
however teachers want to do it.
But, there's really nothing that can't be
taught conceptually.
I think our biggest friends in
teaching conceptially even with more
procedural content representations.
I am always asking kids can you represent
this, can you show it in another way?
And then just always asking about sense
making.
Why does it make sense?
How can you, why can you do that?
>> Right.
>> Why does it make sense to do that, why
would we want to do that and why.
>> Yeah.
>> Asking those questions
changes something from being very
procedural to being much more conceptual.
>> I agree, I agree.
Good advice.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So another question that
comes up which is big in the United States
is how do these ideas fit in with
what's needed to score well on the SATs
>> Mm-hm.
>>And to get into competitive colleges?
>>Mm-hm.
>>Um, and is there room for competitivenes
in this.
>>Mm-hm.
>>View of math?
>> education.
>> Yeah, so you probably got from
watching my course that I'm not a big
fan of competitive math teaching.
>> Yes.
>> And my answer to that questions is
there room for
competitiveness in this view of math
education?
There's room sure but is there a need for
it?
no, I would say not and I think.
>> Some kids thrive on competition and if
you make things into a race or
a competition where we stack people up in
terms of who won,
it can engage kids for sure.
Particularly boys it seems.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Are more engaged by that approach but
There are a lot of kids who are put off by
that kind of competitive approach.
And I think with math in particular, where
people are already,
there's already a lot of opportunity for
people to get stressed.
You know, I'm not a fan of
competitiveness, and
I don't think competitiveness in the
classroom makes
people better prepared
>> Either to do well on things like SAT's
or to get into college.
>> Right.
>> Those kids who do well are kids who
feel comfortable with math and
with numbers and feel secure in their
understanding.
So I would say we teach for
understanding then that's the best
opportunity kids have to do well.
On tests and just thriving competitive
environments as well.
>> I think that's good advice.
Do you have any more concrete examples of
steps to
take with students of various ages to
shift their mindset?
Yeah, that's a really good question, and
lots of people I think, in the course,
really like the mindset ideas, and
understood their importance, and
asked "How can we really shift kids?" So,
there are good resources out there, and
websites, Brainknowledgy is the website
that has a student intervention course.
And that's one thing that can be done.
I think that course that schools pay for
and that students can go
through in intervention, it really teaches
kids the same as I taught in this course.
>> Mm hmm.
>> That the brain can grow, that it's you
know, muscle, that it grows and gets a.
People can get smarter the more work they
do.
I think as well as if you want to be more
math focused,
playing them some of the videos from the
course might be,
I mean they weren't designed for students
and classrooms, but
I think some of the mindset videos
>> Might be useful to show kids.
Particularly, I think the key messages for
kids to shift their mindset is the one of
the brain growing and how the brain grows.
And the new evidence we have on brain
growth.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Ability grows.
Very important to keep stressing the
message that math is about effort.
>> Yeah.
>> It's
not about some people being smart and some
people being not.
>> And I think the mistakes message is
really good for
kids too that, you know, when you make
mistakes, your brain grows.
>> I agree.
>> And we can keep reinforcing these
messages.
I had a conversation with my daughter,
I've been having a few lately [LAUGH] on
that very topic last night, when she was
on her math homework, and she got stuck.
And she was saying "Help me!
Help me!
I don't know what to do, I don't know what
to do!" And
I knew that she was able to, you know,
make progress.
It wasn't
>> Like I left it floundering, but
I said "Ay!
I can't help you, even if it's hard, and
you make mistakes!
That's so great for you!
Cause your brain will grow!
I don't want to deny that opportunity to
you, for
your brain to grow, as you make mistakes
and struggle."
>> Yeah, what kind of a mother would you
be?
>> Exactly!
[NOISE] [LAUGH] Anyway.
So there were lots of opportunities to
keep giving kids >>So these messages about
brain growth and about effort.
Yeah.
>>So what are your
thoughts on natural ability, I mean is
there such a thing or?
>>Yes.
So some people asked about that I think
because of most very strongly saying this
there's no such thing as math people and
non-math people.
>>Yeah.
>>Um, surely some peop, there are people
out there who can.
Win the Fields medal or whatever.
So I guess what I think about that is,
scientists know that,
you know, there's some things that come
genetically, but
they're very small, and the amounts are
very small.
And it's massively outweighed by all the
things that happen in the environment and
in the home and in the school.
so, I w- -- the way I think about it is
that people think math
is somehow a gift or somewhat in a, a
massively out -- y'know,
in -- out of proportion to that amount
[INAUDIBLE] , which is very, very small.
So, to me, it doesn't matter, really,
whether people are Born with some
advantage or not.
What matters is
>> Right.
>> when we get kids to us we know that all
of them can achieve and that,
and that, because achievement is about
learning and hard work.
>> Right, right.
>> So, I think, I mean, when I talk about
everybody can learn and grow.
I, I know, of course when we teach math.
In classes.
There are kids who are faster than other
kids.
So one thing is faster doesn't mean
better, of course, maths
classrooms are often based on idea that
they're fast that means they're better.
But also You know, what matters is, we
take those kids,
even those who are struggling who, who
don't seem to have much of an idea.
>> Mm hmm.
>> And
know that those kids can get to where we
want them to get to.
>> Right
>> And to very high levels.
I mean one of the studies I referenced in
the course was
a three week intervention which changed
the structure of people's brains.
So.
>>you know it just doesn't make sense to
think why this kid hasn't got the brains
to do it.
That's really old fashioned thinking, so--
>> And it's damaging.
>>And it's very damaging, yes.
So I don't think it's even worth thinking
about is there's such a thing kids who
are-- I mean what's important to know is
how these kids do is
in your power as teachers No matter where
they come in.
And one of the, one of the best teachers
I've ever seen, [INAUDIBLE]
always talks about, he never thinks about
who's going to do well on a task or
who can do a task before he gives out a
task.
So whereas other teachres are saying well,
so and so will get this or this kid's
going to kind this easy or challenging or
they're not going to get it.
He always.
>> Resist that?
And says I don't know that.
And so I give out this task, because kids
constantly surprise me, and
he just doesn't hold that idea.
And it's really, you can see the teaching,
how productive that is for the kids.
>> Yeah, yeah.
A lot of times you just have to believe
that they can do it, and
show them they can do it.
>> Yeah, some of the people are saying
the hardest thing to give up,
I've had tweets of people saying the
hardest thing to give up the smart word.
>> because their so used to saying
>> Yeah.
>> Oh you're smart, you can do this.
>> so, you know, these are shifts in the
way we think it's really important not to
say people you are smart you can do this
but.
>> Right.
>> We can say to them,
you know, it's great that you're learning
this and you'll be able to learn it.
And some schools still use the smart word
but
they use it in a way of everybody can get,
can be smart.
And there are many ways to be smart, and
everybody can do it.
And we have to learn to be smart,
smartness is about effort.
I mean I think, the smart is so, the word
smart, or
bright if you're in England, probably.
Is so related to a fixed view, that I just
choose, I think it's
better just to nix the word all together,
and not bring it in in any way.
But, yeah, these are hard changes for us
to make, and
it's really great that people are working
on it.
I had to change the way I spoke to my
kids.
>> [INAUDIBLE] more of that mindset.
>> I agree, I had to change the way I
spoke to the steppies that I teach,
the student teachers, I had to, I had to
be more careful about the words I chose.
So, it is hard to change.
The next question, people want to know how
to handle administrators and parents.
What do you do when administrators are,
are
>> Forcing you to teach, or
pressuring you to teach in a traditional
manner, even though you know...
>> Yeah, that's a really tough one.
It's a good question.
And I, I work with a lot of teachers all
year, and some of them will say to me,
you know, my administration is telling me
to Have the kids in rows,
have them work in silence, or
-- some of them -- one of the teachers I
work with is doing a number talk, and
the principal came in and says, "Oh, this
is too easy; we've gotta stop this." So
that's the hardest thing, if you really
are doing this important changes that
we know are needed from research and you
have people from above telling you not to.
So What do you do?
I think we have to teach administrators
the same as
>> yeah
>> teachers.
I mean, I, there were, I opened,
I tried to get administrators to take this
course and some of them, some did.
>>uh huh.
>>um But also we should, I think we should
give them things to read and do.
There are lots of good short articles.
I have a short article on time tests as
some people asked how do
we Convinced our administration about
timed tests.
>> And parents.
>> And parents too can read articles about
timed tests and
about the need to teach for understanding.
There were good, short articles.
We could get them to take my course,
maybe.
>> Yeah.
>> That would be a good thing for
administrators and parents.
And the website [UNKNOWN] that I'm putting
out.
We also have a section for administrators,
and a section for
parents, cause we do need to educate
everybody in this.
It's not, enough.
And I think we've suffered in mathematics
education from not bringing parents and
administrators along.
When the reforms in the 1990s were really
big, and
schools
>> Parents were easily, managed by people
who want reform, and so
>> yeah
>> And encouraged to oppose them because
we didn't work with parents.
So, it's really important, and the.
>>The parents who want time tests and-
well administrators and
parents- I'm thinking we have to get them
more knowledgeable about that.
I know there were some other questions
about time tests.
>>There are.
They wanted to know how important it
is for students to memorize multiplication
tables.
>>Oh yeah.
>>Is that important?
Is there need for automaticity or
what we call "automaticity?"
>> So I think that automaticity- that word
is in the common core.
Lots of people want automaticity, so
automaticity is good.
If you can be quick with math facts it's
not a bad thing,
but >>How necessary is it and how much do
we sacrifice in pushing for that?
>>Mm-hm.
>>So being quick with math facts being,
knowing your times tables.
I don't know my times tables actually.
I was in the progressive era in England
where they got rid of times tables and
I never learned them as a child.
>>Mm-hm.
>>But I can, you know, work them out
pretty quickly it's never held me back,
that I didn't Memorize time tables.
And [UNKNOWN] does not come from giving
students timed tests.
What we know from timed tests is the fast
kids stay fast, and
the slow kids stay slow.
What encourages [UNKNOWN] is comfort with
numbers, and understanding.
You can do lots of great things with
mental math practice, and
number talks, as I've said, are ideal for
practicing mental math.
>> When kids, it's great to practice
that, I'm really not saying kids
shouldn't have an opportunity to practice
things like multiplication facts.
But not to practice them under timed
conditions
>> Yes.
>> And also not only practice them, but
also to understand the numbers.
So Number talks are great.
But there's other number work that can be
done too.
It's really good.
Work with the hundred square as we called
it in England.
And I think
>> Yeah.
The hundreds chart.
>> The hundreds chart, thank you.
It's hard to be bilingual, you know.
>> I know.
>> I'm working on it still but.
And there are lots of, actually, there are
good apps, most of the apps that I see for
phones and other things are pretty
procedural practice, you know,
which is fine, if kids are enjoying them.
But also you want kids to work with number
sense.
And, understand so that...
There's actually a really good new app
that's just come out that Keith Deblin was
working on, Could wuzzit trouble.
W-U-Z-Z-I-T.
How do you say that?
Wuzzit trouble.
And that's nice because it's an app that
encourages logic and problem solving but
also practice with numbers, factors of
multiples, so.
Though great ways for kids to practice.
>> Mm hmm
>> Ken kens I like a lot.
>> I do to.
>> If you don't know
what ken kens are, google them.
They're really nice number, number
problems that kids have so teach for
number sentences is the most important
thing for automaticity.
Comfort with numbers understsanding
numbers, number sense.
>> [INAUDIBLE] math facts is fine, but
we don't need time test, they're not what
encourages that in the best way.
>> So, thanks for
taking the time for sitting down to talk
with us about these questions were asked.
>> Yeah!
It's been great, and
>> We didn't answer all 300 as I said.
>> Yeah.
>> So I'm sorry if
your question didn't get answered.
We went for the ones that had the most
votes.
>> Yeah.
>> And those people needed to know the
answers too, but I hope it's been helpful,
and thanks again for taking the course.