So last year I taught a Freshman seminar
at Stanford.
It was called, How do People learn Math?
So, in the description I said, we were
going to look at why math is so
traumatic for people, why is it so
inequitable?
I had 15 slots, but I got about 70
applications from students, and
Reading those applications, all from
Stanford students was
amazing because they all wrote pretty much
the same thing.
That I used to be great at maths, I used
to love maths until dot, dot, dot.
And you can see some of their words here.
Those dot dot dots are what I want to talk
to you about in this class.
I'm now going to play you some brief, very
brief, video reflections on maths,
just from around six Stanford freshmen.
So they're each very short.
But you're going to get some different
ideas from these clips from the students.
And at the end I want you to make, a kind
of concept map of the ideas.
What were the big ideas you heard?
Maybe you put big ideas in one space.
And smaller ideas coming off those.
If you're going to draw a concept map, you
need to take a photo of it and
upload it to send it in.
If you can't or don't want to do that, you
can just write the ideas in the text box.
And if you don't know what a concept map
is, here's one on a totally unrelated
topic just to show how different ideas
relate in one of those.
For high school it was mostly just like, I
would've thinked like, basically for
the most part they gave you the formulas,
and you just have to plug that in.
>> For me at least, I always had trouble
with math in the sense that,
it never quite reached me, I always found
there was a disconnect in the classroom,
for example Why would someone go to the
store and buy 300 apples?
I would never do that.
So I would always think of math as like,
this fairy tale land.
Which I would never use.
So I think that there's a pretty big
disconnect for me.
At least in that sense.
I was kind of, discouraged as a kid,
growing up.
>> Now when I think about math, I kind of
cringe and
feel anxiety just thinking about.
Those feelings I felt when trying to do
that math this quarter.
So.
>> I hate it a lot.
It's boring and dry, and it's a lot of
work.
>> The first thing that comes to mind when
I
think of math is just a series of formulas
and equations.
>> I feel very stupid, like I don't
belong.
>> And that academic world, when I think
about math,
it basically drives me away from pursuing
higher education.
>> So the class I taught to the Stanford
freshman was a kind of intervention to
change their relationship with math.
So that class gave me the idea for putting
a similar class online.
So, what are the reasons for
the big problems we have in maths
education and beyond?
Because, I say beyond, the problems don't
stay in classrooms poor math
performance really predicts desperate
shortages for the future for the numbers
who can work in science, innovation
technology, [UNKNOWN], and so on.
And we'll be going through some of these
reasons in the class generally, but
today I want to focus on these.
One, very big reason is the myths and
stereotypes that are in and
around mathematics education.
And in the [INAUDIBLE] version of this
course, this very first session is
going to be knocking down some of the
damaging myths that students suffer from.
So I think the most pervasive myth, and
damaging, is that.
Only some people can be good at maths.
That idea is absent in the more successful
countries in the world, such as Japan, and
I'm going to show you how wrong that idea
is in sessions two and three.
Another idea, girls have less potential to
do well in maths.
I cannot count of the number of women who
tell me.
About somebody telling them, to be nice
and
to help them, maybe math isn't your thing.
You're good at other things.
Here's a couple of my standard students,
just relating, and talking about that,
the particular kind of messages that hurt
them.
>> I Think a lot of people said to me
>> Like we know math isn't your thing, but
that's okay because something else is your
thing.
And while that's true, I think personally,
it was pretty detrimental for
my experiences in math, especially in high
school.
>> Growing up it was always me in a class
full of a lot of males.
And so the teacher tended to favor these
students who were good.
And so they didn't talk to me at all.
And when I looked at that.
When I looked at my sophomore, year, my
junior year.
Just, being excluded.
Like, I wasn't worth talking to.
That felt the worst.
And it just.
Totally was different from, like say,
an English course, where they would talk
to every student.
In like, my math courses, completely
ignored, and I just felt not important.
So, when I think about math, I generally
tend to think about my past experiences.
>> Especially my sophomore year in high
school, where I felt the lowest.
And it just totally drove me away from
pursuing anything in math.
I feel very dumb and like, inadequate when
I think about that topic.
And I don't feel good enough.
>> So now I want to introduce you to one
of the first math users we have on video.
Sophie Constantino is a filmmaker.
And I met her when she came to film my
freshman class.
And she's the co founder of Citizen Film.
She's a documentary film director and
cinematographer.
And Sophie told me that she uses maths all
the time in her work, but
she used to hate it in school.
So we'll listen to Sophie now.
>> Probably my early math days I was.
You know, just slogging along trying to
figure it out and I got that sort of
message, well it's okay, girls aren't
really as good at math as boys are, so
you know, maybe you're just going to
struggle with that one.
>> And, and as a kid who thought I was
good at everything,
I think that was hard I wasn't You know I,
I'm not good at memorizing.
So once I had to do times tables you know,
I was, I was sort of,
doing the math backwards in my head.
Cheating.
It's like, it's like,
memorizing Shakespeare.
It's like, why?
>> Mm hm.
>> I don't get it.
Is there a reason I'm doing this?
>> Yeah.
>> So I, you know, I sort of had a.
Resistance and frustration with that and I
think by the time I was yeah, fourth grade
I was you know good at English, not so
good at math and I sort of accepted that.
I kind of want to blame it on my mother
but
I think that it was her way of sort of
empathizing with my struggles.
Like you know Don't worry it's, it's an,
you know, sometimes girls just aren't as
good at that.
>> Students experience racial stereotyping
too.
If you'll ask an American or a Latina or
Latino in today's schools it's very
likely that you're made to feel that you
can't perform well in math.
Those are negative and very harmful
stereotypes.
What are called positive stereotypes also
occur.
And put pressure on kids.
And have a negative impact.
As we'll hear about in a minute.
If you're Asian you may experience the
pressure to achieve highly in math.
Because you're expected to be naturally
good at it.
And those messages are also damaging.
So this is one of my students, KK.
An Asian-American student talking about
the negative effects of that stereotype.
>> When I was growing up, I was always
like, I'm Asian-American and
I suppose people would think that I'm good
at math in the terms of the classroom and
also the teachers, but I guess when I was
younger I was more hesitant to
fulfill the stereotype, so I wanted to be
the anti-stereotype.
>> So we've now heard four people talk
about messages they've received.
Three students and Sophie talked about it.
Messages in general about low achievement
and
messages that were related to gender and
race.
And I want to ask you the question now,
what do you think are similar or
different other negative messages that you
think students hear, or
maybe you heard as a learner?
It doesn't matter if the message is
similar to those you just heard.
I'd just like to hear about what damaging
messages are out there.
So I want you to write briefly about that,
couple of sentences at most.
And, you're going to be asked to look at
six other people's submissions and
your submission will be sent out too.
I'm not asking you to comment on other
people's submissions, just to seen them,
to get some sense of what's out there in
terms of these messages.