[MUSIC].
Hello and welcome to our fourth session.
This one's going to be a little longer
with about 20 minutes from me and
also some videos to watch.
And some lessons for you to look at.
So allow yourself plenty of time.
Because this session is really going to
discuss some particular strategies that
teachers and parents and
others can use to promote a growth mindset
in their students.
So I've shown you data already,
showing the impact of a growth mindset
intervention for students.
And those interventions are available at
mindset works, and
this is the web address for that.
But the effect of such interventions won't
last if students return to
math classrooms where they're bombarded
with fixed mindset messages.
I've been approached by school principals
who tell me that their teachers have
read Carol Dweck's books.
They love the ideas, but they don't know
what it means for their math teaching.
Well, it means a lot for maths teaching,
because it's teachers and parents who can
really make a difference and change
students from a fixed to growth mindset.
Just to illustrate the power of parents,
Carol Dweck told me the other day that she
got a letter from the parent of
a boy who'd been asked in class to write
down what he was smart at.
And instead of answering that question, he
wrote that he really couldn't answer
the question because everything he was
good at, he worked really hard for.
That's the child of a parent giving him
growth mindset messages despite
the messages he gets in school.
Teachers are also extremely powerful in
the mindset students develop as
they communicate messages about mindset
constantly.
So messages come from grouping structures,
from the tasks students work on,
from assessment and grading.
The way mistakes are managed, the norm set
in a classroom.
And I want to thank my two graduate
students Sarah Kate Selling and
Kathy Sun for the ideas I'm going to show
you now, which we've developed together as
ways of helping teachers and others
develop a growth mindset in students.
So this picture shows you the different
areas that are going to be worked on.
We've already talked in the last lesson
about mistakes.
And they're a big part of a growth mindset
culture.
But here are some ideas for
the rest of this session about the other
aspects that we featured in that picture.
[MUSIC]
So the first one I want to talk about is
the norms that is set in the classrooms or
around homework at home.
And the norms that teachers set up or the
parents establish around what math is and
how we work on math is super important.
And it's really important to set up norms
that are all about a growth mindset.
So instead of talking a lot about this,
we've already talked about a lot of the
ideas in the last session.
Instead, I want to show you a video of one
amazing teacher.
So Cathy Humphreys is the teacher.
And she and I wrote a book together,
that includes lots of great examples of
her teaching in middle school.
And in the book there are lesson plans,
she, she shows her lesson plans.
She talks about how she was thinking about
the lesson.
She, then, reflects on the lesson.
And Many teachers have found it very
helpful to watch these teaching examples
and read Cathy's thoughts.
So, Cathy has a really strong focus in her
classroom on a particular norm
that's about encouraging students to be
sense makers.
Nothing goes in her classroom unless the
students can make sense of it.
So there are different things within.
The norm of sense making.
She encourages different ways to make
sense.
We have different representations,
encouraging students to draw and
to visualize and to show things in
different ways.
She also develops a culture of
collaboration and shared work.
Students really make sense of mathematics
when they talk about it.
And when they reason mathematically with
each other.
Something else she does, is she gives
public space to the sense making norms.
So she holds whole class discussions.
Now, when teachers have those whole class
discussions, it's chance for them to
really instantiate norms of what they
think is important with all the students.
What math is and what's important in the
class.
And Maggie Lambert wrote about that in,
in her book which I put in the reference
section.
So, in Cathy's class, mistakes are really
valued and shared for
everyone to think about and this is an
extract from Cathy's writing in the book.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I'm going to ask you to
watch the video now, and
afterwards I'm going to
ask you to write in the forum
what teacher moves did you and
find interesting that Cathy
used to support the students'
learning in this ten-minute
time.
>> What would this one be?
[SOUND] Without, without doing a role that
you know,
like, see if you can make sense of
[INAUDIBLE] what one,
one divided by two [CROSSTALK]
[INAUDIBLE].
>> What's one and a half [CROSSTALK]
>> It's one and a half [CROSSTALK]
[INAUDIBLE] makes sense.
[CROSSTALK] [INAUDIBLE] Hi, let's hear
what some people have to say.
Leslie.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Yeah.
Say what you think it is.
>> I think it's six.
>> And you think it's six because?
>> Because a third goes into one three
times, and
then three times has to do with it.
>> Alright other thoughts about this?
[UNKNOWN].
>> I got one and a half.
[SOUND] [INAUDIBLE] of two.
>> I can't hear.
>> I got one and a half because I
[INAUDIBLE].
>> You, you used the reciprocal of three
half, of two thirds.
>> Yeah.
>> Why?
>> Because on the other one, we could
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Yeah, and so see what's, what, here's
what I,
here's where I'm going with this today.
But before classing, you're going to have
a rule.
And some people already know the rule, but
I don't care about the rule right now.
What I want to know is can anybody make
sense of this, of what,
alright, let's just, so right now we have
two different answers.
We have the answer six, and Lesley is
saying it's because you divide it,
there's three one thirds in one.
And then, 2 times 3 is 6.
And then we have the other theory, that
the [INAUDIBLE] get your hands down.
The other theory that the answer's one and
a half, but
we don't know why, except that the rule
works.
So the rule working is not good enough
today.
Alright.
So why does it make sense?
What?
Does Leslie's answer make sense?
Does one and a half make sense?
I want to know why it makes sense.
[SOUND] Okay.
I've got almost one hand up in every
group, but not quite.
I want every group to come up with what
makes sense, some reason why.
[CROSSTALK] [INAUDIBLE] Put those heads
together.
>> [CROSSTALK] 2 3rds [INAUDIBLE] and half
of 2 3rds is one 3rd.
2 3rds plus 1 3rd is 3 3rds is 1.
Right?
>> [INAUDIBLE] [NOISE] [CROSSTALK]
[INAUDIBLE] Excuse me.
This is really interesting.
The side of the room that I talked to,
about half of the people thought
it was six, and about half the people
thought it was one and a half.
And then, I found Sam willing to make an
argument for one half.
So Sam would you go to the board and draw
a picture?
And you can erase the other pictures so
far.
[NOISE] And would you erase the other
arithmetic
too, so we start [INAUDIBLE] any problem?
>> [SOUND] [COUGH].
>> Well if you have, if you have this,
that's, it's not even clear.
That's, if that's one whole.
And if these, [SOUND] if these two parts
are shaded, then, that's two thirds.
Right?
That and this one doesn't count now, so
that's two thirds and this is the other
one third.
And so if you draw, this is a whole.
[INAUDIBLE].
See that's the whole right?
And if you change these two, put them here
[SOUND] like it was.
And then you still have these, and you
still have the 1 3rd left.
And 1 3rd is half of 2 3rds, and so you
just add one half.
And that's what I was thinking.
>> Now, remember what the day that we
talked about,
convince yourself, convince a friend, you
convince a skeptic.
Anybody want to [INAUDIBLE] let's see if
anybody can
challenge Sam or push on his thinking a
little bit.
>> Okay.
>> I thought you were, okay well that's
exactly what I was thinking.
And that's how I convinced our table to
get a couple people here
[INAUDIBLE] thought it was six, and then I
pretty much convinced them [INAUDIBLE].
>> Zack or Ben I need one of you to talk
about what Michael might have said that
convinced you?
>> [COUGH] Everything.
>> One and a half [INAUDIBLE] the
beginning.
>> [CROSSTALK] He was discovering.
>> You are the skeptic?
Okay, now really, this would be really
great.
What made you change your mind?
>> It made more sense to me than 4.
>> Can you explain it?
>> I think so.
>> Okay, would you try, please?
because if you can explain what somebody
else said,
then you're one notch further up in your
ability to understand it.
Well, there's 2 3rds, and 2 3rds goes into
one, one whole time with,
and there's still a little half left over,
or a little 1 3rd left over.
And so you try to fit it in there
[INAUDIBLE].
So one half of it fits.
So, [INAUDIBLE] one and one half times.
>> Anyone, one, want to comment to Ben?
>> Well yeah, I agree with you and Sammy
and Michael.
>> So I just thought of it line/g
[INAUDIBLE] where [INAUDIBLE] like mine.
>> Could you show your line [INAUDIBLE]?
So, the more ways we have it, then we're
going to have to hear from the six people
because there's gotta be maybe some people
still that are thinking the answer is 6.
>> [SOUND] [INAUDIBLE] One, then, okay, so
right here is our 2 3rds mark.
And, and so, so from like here to here, it
goes through that one time,
one full time like Ben said.
So that's like, certainty of one.
And then here is 1 3rd left and
1 3rd [SOUND] is one half of 2 3rds.
So, times 2 3rds equals [INAUDIBLE] two,
oh wait.
>> 1 3rd or 2 3rds.
>> Well, well, 1 3rd is a half of 2 3rds.
>> How would you write that, one minus one
half of 2 3rds?
>> I think [SOUND] I would write
[CROSSTALK] 2
3rds divided by [CROSSTALK] I'm not sure
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Maybe you could get help from someone
in the class.
>> Oh I can?
So, hey Sheryl.
>> 2 3rds, you write 2 3rds times one
half.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Then you get one
[INAUDIBLE] [SOUND] Um, [INAUDIBLE].
So, then, that 2 6th is also equal to 1
3rd, and that's that part, 1 3rd.
So that 1 3rd is like a half of the 2
3rds, so
then you can consider it one and a half.
>> Sheryl?
>> I have another way of thinking, like as
in the number [INAUDIBLE] say.
>> You can go up.
>> Okay, so the problem is one
divided by 2 3rds equals blank.
And then, also, you know how you go the
inverse.
So you can go either way.
So then you can do this times 2 3rds
equals one.
And so, that is going to be 3 over 2,
which is also one and a half.
>> Why does that make sense?
Or does it make sense?
>> I don't, I don't really understand,
like, to me it's like,
I still think it's 6 because.
>> Wait, Christine.
And I know you had your hand up and I, I
want to call on you about why it's 6,
but this, what method is Sheryl using
here, for this one?
Okay.
Since people aren't remembering,
[INAUDIBLE] remember when yesterday we
talked about that fan that before we
[UNKNOWN] number sentences?
Can anybody, well, okay, and so
you chose another number sentence to show
what that would be true?
Okay.
Christine, and you still think it's 6?
>> Yeah, because me and Alisha kind of has
the same method iii.
>> You and who have the same answer?
>> Alisha.
>> Okay.
>> And like, we [LAUGH] we multiplied the
numerator by the denominator and
then multiplied that by the whole number,
which equals, because 2 times 3 equals 6.
>> [CROSSTALK] Could you go up and show
what you did?
[SOUND] Is this the kind of problem you
had two different answers to?
>> No, no.
>> Some problems could have more than one
answer or a range of answers, but in this
case we agree that there has to be, so
the question is which, which is the most
sensible way of interpreting this problem.
>> 2 times 3 equals 6 [SOUND] and 6 times
1 equals 6.
>> And why does that make sense, Christie?
>> I don't, [LAUGH].
>> Leslie, what do you think about.
>> Well.
>> What do
you think about our original answer?
>> I thought it was 6.
But then I don't think it could be that
big.
>> [LAUGH] Why don't you think it could be
that big?
>> Well, because you're doing 1 divided by
2 3rds.
And it'd be less than 6.
I don't know any other way to do it.
>> So you're trying to figure out and
you're trying to figure out something to
do with numbers?
>> Yeah, I was thinking about Cheryl's
method.
I, I don't really understand it that much
but like I kind of was looking at it and
it makes sense now.
>> Okay.
You've got two people who
are just about having a fit over here.
Would you call on a few people?
>> Amy?
>> Well if you multiply 6 by 2 3rds,
it wouldn't equal 1.
>> Oh, you're checking.
>> Yeah.
>> The inverse operation.
[INAUDIBLE] You know,
how you wrote two times three [INAUDIBLE]
because the line means divide.
So it would be 2 divided [INAUDIBLE].
>> [INAUDIBLE] Okay, so the, the line
separating [INAUDIBLE].
>> Okay, so I'm going to stop this right
now because here's something that really,
I think, is the biggest danger in math is
that you follow rules,
you do things with numbers, it's kind of
like waving your magic wand.
>> As much [UNKNOWN] I say about cartoons
like that.
Where this mathematician is doing
something on the board and there's all
this things that he's done and then in the
middle, let's see, how does it go.
In the middle there's this thing where you
kind of wave your magic wand, and
that way you prove your answer.
But, so that's what I don't want you to
do.
I want you to make sense of it.
And I want to back to what Lesley said
about how 6 is too big to be sensible.
So let's see what would be a situation
that would, this would make sense?
2 3rds is kind of hard.
Let's see.
I have a yard, oh gosh, let's see.
I have a foot of lumber, and I need to cut
off 2 3rds of it.
I need to cut my lumber into 2 3rds of a
foot sections.
So how may 2 3rds of a foot sections will
I be able to get out of there?
So if you visualize that piece of lumber,
I cut off the 2 3rds of a foot,
how much I've got left is at [INAUDIBLE]
makes sense then.
>> Now, so it could be six, [UNKNOWN] so
I really like the way that you were
reasoning about that.
What would it be then?
How many pieces of lumber, how many
two-thirds of a foot sections could I get?
Leslie?
>> I think one and a half.
>> OK, and why do you think one and a
half?
>> I think [INAUDIBLE] I've got a foot of
lumber.
>> [INAUDIBLE] I should have said a
[INAUDIBLE] you
usually don't have lumber in one foot
sections, but anyway.
>> [INAUDIBLE] one third glass, and one
third packing paper.
>> Okay, so if I have a, here's my foot of
lumber right.
>> And I cut off my, I cut off my 2 3rds,
and so
I get rid of that and then I've only got
this little piece left, so
I've only got one, two, thirds of a foot
section, this one.
And then this part is how long?
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> One third of a foot, and that's half of
what I made.
So one and a half is the correct answer.
Now, Christine, does that make any sense
to you?
>> Yeah, well it does make sense
[INAUDIBLE] five maybe less
[INAUDIBLE] thought it was too big, but
like I was like the,
I know the probability's confusing but
wouldn't it,
like, the foot of lumber, like, divided by
3, is 12 divided by 3 is 4.
>> Where are you getting 12?
>> Because twelve inches in a foot.
>> Oh, so you're thinking twelve inches in
a foot, yes?
And so each third would be four inches.
>> Four inches.
>> I agree with that.
And 2 3rds of a foot is how many inches?
>> 8 inches.
So I cut out 8 inches and I've got how
many inches left?
>> 4.
>> 4, and 4 is half of 8.
So that's another way to prove it.
Okay.
Now,
I'd like you to copy this down [SOUND]
because this is
called a traditional algorithm for
dividing fractions.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> There's more than one way to divide
functions.
This is the traditional algorithm
[INAUDIBLE].