When researchers gave that problem to
students,
they found that it really helped them in
forming different expressions.
And they learned how to manipulate
algebra, and
how to set up algebraic expressions that
they wouldn't have got if
they'd just been asked to represent the
situation in one way.
So, finally, my other principle is to
integrate the mathematical practices into
the teaching of algebra.
The great thing about the new common core
in the US is the writers realize that we
can't we just set out this content
anymore.
We need to get student working in
mathematical ways and
they call these mathematical practices.
The idea of practices also came from a
group I was in, it was a group made up of
a lot of mathematicians and a few
mathematics educators.
And we were working to produce advice for
the government on the most fruitful
directions on future research.
Deborah Ball chaired that group.
And one of the directions we nominated was
mathematical practices as
many people knew that it was these
practices that separated those who
were successful in maths from those who
weren't.
And the mathematicians were really
passionate about that.
And it turns out that these important
practices that are now to be
addressed across the content in the US and
are going to be assessed.
Have some real, really particular
importance in algebra.
So, one of the great books to
read about all of this is Mark Driscoll's
Fostering Algebraic Thinking.
And he nominates doing and undoing as a
central practice in algebraic thinking.
Doing and undoing means being able to
reason both forwards, but
also backwards with operations.
So, an example of that type of thinking
might be,
first finding the number of blocks in pile
seven in a growth pattern task.
And then giving students a number of
blocks, and
asking them, which pile would have that
many.
So, I'm going to show you some examples of
these principles through classroom video
and a teaching intervention where I was
one of the teachers teaching algebra to
disaffected 7th and 8th graders.
And that so I'm going to start that by
asking you to do a problem now.
You may know it, but do it anyway.
And for this problem I don't want to leave
the visual lo, long for a reason.
This isn't one way you would give this
visual out to students.
So, I'd like you to figure out, mentally,
without counting one by one.
Without talking without writing how many
squares are in the colored portion.