So the reason that tracking, setting,
often result in lower achievement in many,
and I'm going to go through some of the
things that I found from research.
So the first reason is the messages that
they give to students and
the first, this is a really big issue,
as the students go into ability groups
they develop more fixed mind sets,
more of an idea that they, they are or
they are not a math [INAUDIBLE] person.
So in high groups, students get the idea
that they have the math gift,
a strongly fixed mindset message.
And even fixed ideas that you're smart,
will hurt and limit brain group, growth.
The kids in low groups, the fixed messages
are ones that stay with them for life, and
you can read about this in one of my
papers on psychological prisons,
which was one of the terms that the
students used,
when he was reflecting back on his school
experience.
So, those messages are huge.
And then, another huge piece is the
teacher expectations that go in
different ability groups, even when
teachers try or
don't want to have different [INAUDIBLE]
expectations.
And those, what's now a really old study
which we wouldn't be able to
repeat these days but when researchers
gave all students in
an elementary school an IQ test, then they
randomly chose 20% of the students and
told the teacher that those students, by
name,
would be academic spurters that year and
they would move ahead.
And what they found was, at the end of
that year, those that randomly group,
groups, group of students achieved at
significantly higher levels than
the other students, with everything else
being the same.
And that just shows the huge importance of
teacher expectations.
So the third reason is the work they’re
given.
Students in lower groups are generally
given easier work, but
it’s often too easy and will limit their
achievement.
They don’t even get access, even to the
higher level content that others do.
And for a long time in education we
thought it best to give students work that
they can get correct and feel good about.
But we now know that's wrong and
the prime goal it's all times must be that
students feel challenged.
Unfortunately, it's well-known that
students in groups from the second group
downwards get work that's insufficiently
challenging and
really denies them that learning
opportunity.
And then one of the ones I talk about in
my book are the borderline causalities.
It really seems to me that a decision that
is incorrect so much of the time about
which groups students go into, it may come
down to them not feeling very good on
the day of the test or whatever, can
determine a child's entire future.
And that really doesn't seem good.
And then, the other reason that I found is
that in ability groups teacher tends to
teach in the middle of the group, they
assume that everybody is more or
less the same, because they've been
grouped together.
And everybody gets the same work at the
same pace.
Where as in mixed group,
teachers have to recognize that these
students are from all over the place.
And they have to give them different
opportunities to work and
what you find in those mixed groups, that
high achievers really take off
because they have opportunities to work at
their own level.
There are different ways of having
teachers give these
different opportunities to students in
different lessons.
They can use more open work or more
differentiated work.
You may remember in the Japanese lesson,
we watched the way the teacher gave
different options for
the students there's more detail about the
way those can work in my book.
But before I invite you to the forum, I
just wanted to share with you
some words from Michelle Obama, which I
recently saw that she spoke.
This is what she said to students at Savoy
Elementary School.
She said to them, "Because the truth is --
and
this is important; I want you all to
listen up -- no one is born smart.
Do you understand that?
No one is born smart.
No one is born knowing how to read, right?
No one is born knowing how to do math, no
one is born knowing how to
play the flute -- all of that comes with a
lot of hard work." And
she also talked about the importance of
mistakes and failure.
She told students about preparing for
greatness.
And you can,
there's a link to that speech if you want
to watch the First Lady's speech.
So I have a question that I want you to
discuss in the forum.
You may well teach in a school that has a
lot of ability grouping, most teachers do.
So I want to give you space now to react
to the research data and
ideas I've shared.
It'd be particularly great to hear from
people about things that are working well.
If you have stories around.
Ways of challenging all students maybe in
groups, maybe through detracking.
You may want to talk about conversations
you've had with administrators or
constraints you may face in moving to
these approaches.
You may have had frustrations or things
you'd like to change in your schools.
So it's a very open question.
I'd like you to go to the forum.
And if you have questions to ask,
there is a small group of us who are going
to try and answer questions.
So be, feel free to put down questions and
I just invite you to chat with your
colleagues in this course about some of
the ideas that I've shared around
grouping.