So last year I taught a freshmen seminar
at Stanford.
It was called How Do People Learn Math.
So in the description I said why we're
going to look at why maths is so
dramatic for people.
Why it's so inequitable.
I had 15slots but I got about 70
applications from students.
And Reading those, applications all from
Stanford students was amazing because
they all wrote pretty much the same thing,
that,
I used to be great at maths, I used to
love maths, until dot dot dot.
And you can see some of their words here.
And there is dot, dot, dots what I want to
talk to you about in this class I am
now going to play you some brief very
brief video reflection on maths just from,
from around six time professment so
they're very short, but
you're going to get some different ideas
from these clips from the students.
And at the end I want you to make a kind
of concept map of the ideas.
What were the big ideas you heard?
Maybe you put big ideas in one space and
smaller ideas coming off those.
If you are going to draw a concept map,
you need to take a photo of it and
upload it to send it in.
If you can't or don't want to do that, you
can just write the ideas in the text box.
And if you don't know what a concept map
is, here's one on a totally unrelated
topic, just to show you how different
ideas are related in one of those.
>> For high school it was mostly just like
algorithmically like, basically for
the most part, they gave you the formulas
and you just had to plug that in.
>> For me, at least,
I always had trouble with math in the
sense that it never quite reached me.
I always found there was a disconnect in
the classroom.
For example, why would someone go the
storm by 300 apples,
I would never do that.
So I would always think of math as,
kind of like this fairy tale land which I
would never use.
so I think that there's a pretty big
disconnect for me,
at least, in that sense.
I was kind of discouraged as a kid growing
up.
>> Now when I think of math, I kind of
cringe and
just feel anxiety just thinking about
>> Those feelings I felt when trying to do
that math this quarter, so.
>> I hate it a lot.
It's boring and dry, and it's a lot of
work.
>> First thing that comes to mind when I
think of math is just a series of formulas
and equations.
>> I feel very stupid, like I don't
belong.
>> In that academic world when I think
about math,
it basically drives me away from pursuing
higher education.
>> So, the class I taught to the Stanford
freshman was a kind of intervention to
change their relationship with math, and
that class gave me the idea for
putting a similar class online.
So what are the reasons for the big
problems we have in math education and
beyond, because I say beyond, the problems
don't stay in classrooms.
Poor math performance predicts desperate
shortages for the future for the numbers
who can work in science, innovation,
technology, medicine and so on.
And we'll be going through some of those
reasons in the class generally, but
today I want to focus on these.
One very big reason is the myths and
stereotypes that are in and
around mathematics education.
And in the student version of this course,
this very first session is going to be
knocking down some of the damaging myths
that students suffer from.
So, I think the most pervasive myth and
damaging, is that.
Only some people can be good at maths.
That idea is absent in the more successful
countries in the world, such as Japan, and
I'm going to show you how wrong that idea
is, in sessions two and three.
Another idea, girls have less potential to
do well in maths.
I cannot keep count of the number of women
who tell me About somebody telling them to
be nice and to help them.
Maybe math isn't your thing.
You're good at other things.
Here's a couple of my Stanford students
just relating and
talking about that the particular kind of
messages that hurt them.
>> So, I have, I had a really negative
math experience.
Mostly it started for me in fifth grade
when we were taking a standardized test
and the teacher accidentally gave me the
eighth grade version of the test and so
for three days I tested with the eighth
grade version of the test and
sort of that set me off and
I never really came back from it I think a
lot of people have said to me.
Look, we know math isn't your thing, but
that's okay because something else is your
thing.
Look, we know math isn't your thing, but
that's okay because something else is your
thing.
Look, we know math isn't your thing, but
that's okay because something else is your
thing.
>> And, while that's true, I think
personally it was pretty detrimental for
my Experiences in math, especially in high
school.
>> Growing up it was always me in a class
full of a lot of males and so the teacher
tended to favor the students who were good
and so they didn't talk to me at all.
And when I looked at that, when I looked
at my sophomore year and
my junior year I just.
>> Being excluded, like,
>> Hm.
>> I wasn't worth talking to, that felt
the worst, and
it just totally was different from, like,
say an English course where they would
talk to every student.
In, like, my math courses, completely
ignored, and I just felt not important.
So when I think about math, I generally
tend to think about my past experiences.
Especially my sophomore year in high
school where I felt the lowest and
it just totally drove me away from
pursuing anything in math.
I feel very dumb and like inadequate when
I think about that topic and
I don't feel good enough.
>> So, now I want to introduce you to one
of the first math users we have on video.
Sophie Constantano is a filmmaker and
I met her when she came to film my
freshman class.
And she's the co-founder of Citizen Film.
She's a documentary film director and
cinematographer.
And Sophie told me that she uses math all
the time in her work, but
she used to hate in school.
So we'll listen to Sophie now.
>> Probably my early math days I was You
know,
just slogging a long trying to figure it
out and I got that sort of message, well,
it's okay girls are really as good in, at
math as boys are.
So, you know, maybe you're just going to
struggle with that one and, and
as a kid who thought I was good at
everything, I, I think that was hard.
I wasn't You know, I'm, I'm not good at
memorizing, so
once I had to do times tables, you know, I
was,
I was sort of doing the math backwards in
my head, cheating.
It was like, like memorizing Shakespeare,
it's like why?
I don't get it?
Is there a reason I'm doing this?
So I, you know, I sort of had a resistance
and a frustration with that, and
I think by the time I was, yeah, fourth
grade, I was,
you know, good at English, not so good at
math, and I kind of accepted that.
>> Like I don't want to blame it on my
mother, but I think it was her way of
sort of empathizing with my struggle, is
like, you know, Don't worry it's, it's,
you know, sometimes girls just aren't as
good at that.
>> Students experience racial stereotyping
too.
If you're African American or Latina or
Latino in today's schools it's very
likely that you're made to feel that you
can't perform well in math.
Those are negative and very harmful
stereotypes.
What are called positive stereotypes also
occur and put pressure on kids and
have a negative impact, as we'll here
about in a minute.
If you're Asian you may experience the
pressure to achieve highly in math,
because you're expected to be naturally
good at it, and
those messages are also damaging.
So, this is one of my students, Kaykay,
an Asian american student talking about
the negative effects of that stereotype.
When I was growing up, I was, I'm always
like I'm Asian America and
I suppose people would think that I'm good
at math in the terms of the classroom and
which and also the teachers, but I guess
when I was younger, I
was more hesitant to fill the stereotype,
so I wanted to be the anti-stereotype.
>> So we've now heard four people talk
about messages they've received,
three students and Sophie talked about it
Messages in general about low achievement,
and messages related to gender and race.
And I want to ask you the question now,
what do you think are similar or
different other negative messages that you
think students here?
Or maybe you heard as a learner?
It doesn't matter if the messages are
similar to those you've just heard,
I just like to hear about what damaging
messages are out there.
So I want you to write briefly about that.
A couple of sentences at most.
And you're going to be asked to look at
six other people's submissions and
your submission will be sent out too.
I'm not asking you to comment on other
people's submissions.
Just to see them,
to get some sense of what's out there in
terms of these messages.