[MUSIC].
So now we're going to learn about
stereotype threat.
My dean Claude Steele, he's dean of the
Stanford Graduate School of Education,
is a world-renowned psychologist.
And he conceptualized and
started a whole field of work on what's
called stereotype threat.
And over decades Claude and
his colleagues have found that many people
suffer from stereotypes.
Women in maths, African-American in
academic, students in academic settings,
white students around sporting ability.
So they have many studies on stereotype
threat, and
they have many studies on girls and maths,
showing that if women take a test and
beforehand just mark off their gender in a
box, they underperform.
If they don't mark off their gender
there's no underperformance.
A group of psychologists at Princeton
conducted an experiment with white and
African-American students who were given a
golfing task.
When the white students were given the
task and they were told that it,
the golfing task measured natural athletic
ability,
they golfed a lot worse than the white
students who were not told anything.
When the same messages were given to black
students, it didn't affect their
performance, as poor athletic ability
isn't a stereotype they suffer from.
In the early studies,
they reminded people of gender differences
by getting them to mark gender on a form.
Later they found they didn't even need to
do that because stereotypes are,
as they say, always in the air.
Which is why they call it stereotype
threat,
there's always the threat of that
stereotype.
And researchers have found the gender and
math stereotype to be established in girls
as young as five years old.
So they talk about the fact that young
girls are put off from engaging in
math before they even have a chance to
engage in maths because of
the stereotypes the air.
So Claude concludes in his book, the
stereotype threat affects all of us in
subtle and not so subtle ways, but they're
all damaging.
And I really recommend reading the entire
book.
This student that I'm going to play for
you now really showed for
me that, that subtle, in the air effect of
a stereotype.
>> I would say that I've felt
discrimination from classmates as
a female.
I think that not, not so much in high
school but here, I feel it.
It's like not directly, but subtle things,
like oh, like, they won't ask me for
my help, or they just will, like, kind of
bulldoze over what I'm saying.
So not anything direct, but subtle things.
>> I'm constantly amazed by how many
students are given
gender messages whether subtle or not so
subtle, math isn't for you.
And here's another one of my students
talking about that.
>> In fourth grade, I remember being so
curious about why a square was a rectangle
but a rectangle wasn't a square and really
caring about those sorts of problems.
And then, as soon as people start telling
you math isn't your thing,
then it's all downhill.
>> So as students come to maths classrooms
and to any
math work with some serious stereotypes in
the air about gender and about race.
And these combined with general views that
only some kids can be good at maths.
And that maths is about a natural ability
that only some people have.
And we're going to look closely at that
one idea of natural ability in
the next sessions.
So we're beginning to see part of the
reason that mathematics education is in
a poor state.
Some messages can send students off the
rails even if they aren't about
gender or race.
People have told me recalling really in
very sharp detail how once in seventh or
eighth grade, they asked the question and
the teachers said to them, that's a baby
question.
And how they decided at that point that
maths was not a subject for them.
So, the first session in the student
version of this class will be
about countering these stereotypes.
and, and [UNKNOWN] students, negating
those messages that they may have heard,
and really helping them believe and know
that they can be really good at maths.
So a quick shortish question now for you.
What do you think you can do, as a teacher
or as a parent or whatever
role you have, to counter these damaging
stereotypes?