I've taught you lots about an inquiry
relationship that students need.
I've seen this relationship.
I've seen it in many fortunate adults such
as those I've interviewed.
But also in two sets of school students
that I wanted to tell you about.
So, in the UK I studied students in two
schools over three years,
who were taught math completely
differently.
So, I collected a lot of data on their
learning experiences and
their achievement, including the results
of their national exam in England.
One of the, one school taught
traditionally,
watch me demonstrate methods and then
practice them.
The other taught an inquiry approach to
maths.
Both sets of students started in three
years at the same levels.
Now, I'm not going to go through the
study, but there's a book on it and
also papers that are downloadable from my
website but I will say a few things.
At the school I called Phoenix Park, they
were taught in heterogeneous groups, and
they were given big problems to solve.
If they needed some mathematical method
they didn't know to solve the problem,
they were taught it within the problem.
They were constantly challenged to ask
questions,
take problems in their own directions and
be curious about math.
The students left that school not only
better problem solvers, but
they also did better on the traditional
national exam.
In the other school that I called Amber
Hill,
they were taught the standard method
through demonstration and practice.
But the students were bored by maths and
they didn't understand most of the methods
they were taught.
As an example of this, in their national
exam, which I was able to go and analyze.
There was a question on simultaneous
equations or
systems of equation as they're called in
the U.S.
And things partly weren't taught that
method.
But in the exam, twice as many Phoenix
Park students felt that question right.
Only 26% of the Amber Hill students solved
the problem.
The rest of them used a confused and
jambled version of the procedure.
So, they tried to use it, but not
successfully.
The Phoenix Park students were much more
successful by looking at the situation and
the numbers and, and making sense of it.
So, these interview quotes will give you a
sense of how students who weren't taught
through standard questions and didn't
practice on the questions for three years.
Like those in the traditional school ended
up doing better on the national exam.
So, this is Adrian from Phoenix Park just
reflecting on the exams when he said I
tend to go into them anyway just thinking
that I can do them.
Yeah, there wasn't any time I though well
this is this, this is this.
I just worked it out from the knowledge
that I had.
Contrast that with these two students from
Amber Hill,
a traditional school who practiced
endlessly on these questions.
And they said very illuminating things to
me in an interview.
They said, one of them said, it's stupid
really,
because when you're in the lesson, when
you're doing work, even when it's hard.
You get the odd one or two wrong, but most
of them you get right.
And you think well when I go into the exam
I'm going to get most of
them right because you get all your
chapters right, but you don't.
And this boy who was very interesting also
said, you can get a trigger,
when she says like simultaneous equations
and graphs, graphically.
When they say that and, you know, it
pushes that trigger.
Tells you what to do, and
I asked him, what happens in the exam when
you haven't got that?
And he said you panic.
So, my question for you, what do these
three responses from the students tell you
about why the Phoenix Park students did
better on the national exam than
the Amber Hill students?