So here are my top two reasons.
You can see that they might match with
yours.
So, the first one, I believe is the
testing culture.
The students who are in our schools now
have grown up in the testing culture for
the last decade, which has inflicted a lot
of damage and
that damage comes in many forms.
But one of them is the clear message that
students in schools get that success is
about doing well on tests.
And if success is defined in that way for
students, then, they really don't see
mistakes playing a role.
Now, of course, we want our students to do
well on tests.
But it turns out that having them do a lot
of tests is not how we get there.
In fact, it's probably the opposite of how
we get there.
Students who do well on tests are those
who've learned to feel comfortable with
math, and who've developed the belief that
they can do it.
The students who went to Phoenix Park that
I quoted above, who left school with
fabulous attitudes, to maths that helped
them in their work and life...
And scored higher on the national exam.
They actually scored higher than the
national average,
even though they came in significantly
lower, and
had never taken a test in high school up
until 3 weeks before the exam.
So, again quoting from Alina Tugend in the
New York times.
If students are afraid of mistakes, then
they're afraid of trying something new,
of being creative, of thinking in a
different way.
They're scared to raise their hands when
they don't know the answer, and
their response to a difficult problem is
to ask the teacher rather than try
different solutions that might - gasp be -
wrong.
They are, as one teacher told me, victims
of excellence.
So teachers have had to work in this
culture for a long time, and
they've suffered, as have kids and more on
that later.
But what is important is that that culture
is changing.
People are realizing what a bad place we
were in after the decade of
multiple choice testing and constant test
preparation.
But I would say that even if the state
testing is changing,
teachers also need to stop or change the
testing they do in their classrooms.
Countries and
schools that are successful don't test
summatively, except at the end of a year.
But in the US it's typical to be given a
math test every week,
especially in high school.
And that means that once a week, kids get
bad messages for many of them that
are harmful especially if, especially if
their grades are are D's and F's.
But not only those kids.
And in later lessons we, we're going to
think in detail about ways of
replacing those summative assessments with
formative assessments.
And my second reason for
why students feel bad about mistakes, is
the role of speed in math classrooms.
In many classrooms, too many classrooms,
speed is valued subtly and not so subtly.
And one of the main messages coming out of
neuroscience is that mathematics should
never be associated with speed.
Researchers have conducted a number of
studies in recent years showing that
timed tests and
other timed mathematical performances
cause the early onset of maths anxiety.
And I think the use of timed tests in the
US is one of the most harmful things in
the system.
These tests are used with the very best
intentions by teachers and policymakers,
but they're often used without the
important knowledge that we have now,
from neuroscience, that timed tests cause
math anxiety in students from
across the achievement range.
So Beilock and her colleagues, Sian
Beilock, have conducted brain scans to
study the ways in which anxiety effects
individuals, and that's shown when
[INAUDIBLE] students compute with math
facts such as those required in
timed tests they recall information that's
held in their working memory.
And the more working memory an individual
has the greater potential they have for
academic success.
And Beilock and colleagues have found that
when people are stressed,
that stress just blocks their working
memory.
So the facts with which people are
familiar can't be recalled.
You may recognize that situation from any
public situation you may have been in,
when you've had to work with some familiar
math,
like you might have had to work out a tip
or something in a restaurant, and
you've looked at it and you felt that your
mind has gone blank.
And that's the impact of stress blocking
the working memory.
So Beilock and colleagues found that math
anxiety impacts those with
higher rather than lower amounts of
working memory,
exactly those students who have the
potential to take maths to high levels.
So there's a paper and references that
summarize the neuroscience on
time tests that I wrote and came out in Ed
Week last summer in the references.
So one of the things I did is I asked
second and fourth grades students.
So I asked teachers of those students to
get them to write down how
the time tests made them feel.
And the students reflection showed that
the test prompted anxiety in at
least a quarter of the students in each
class.
And that anxiety was not correlated with
test success.
And, in fact some, of the students who
completed all 50
questions correctly were those who
indicated the most severe anxiety.
Talking about being scared, when they were
asked to take the test.
So these are the responses from the fourth
graders and
the second graders to the question today.
This assessment made me feel.
So here are the fourth graders.
Worried that I won't finish.
Nervous.
I know my facts well, but it just scares
me that my, I might get a bad score.
I feel nervous because I don't like tests
that much.
Nervous because I'm afraid I won't finish
or I'll make a mistake.
I feel nervous I know my facts but it just
scares me.
I feel pressured.
So those were some of the fourth graders.
Now the second graders, not quite a good
on their spelling.
But responses were.
Not great, upset, nervous, that I'm
terrible at math and unhappy.
So some US districts use time tests
because of words such as automaticity,
that's used in the new common core state
standards.
But there are much better methods of
teaching automoticity that also give
students conceptual understanding of
mathematical operations.
And help them develop number sense.
And number sense is so critical to young
children that its known to be
what separates high achievers from low
achievers in maths.
And in a couple of sessions we're going to
learn a great strategy for
developing number sense and automaticity
together.
Importantly, many strong mathematical
thinkers, deep thinkers,
are put off by math because of speed
emphasis.
But in my experience, mathematicians are
some of the slowest people I've met.
And I don't say that to be insulting to
mathematicians, but
the reason they're often slow is because
they're thinking deeply.
And I wants us to hear now from one of
France's greatest mathematicians
Lauren Schwartz who won the field medal in
math which it's like the nobel prize for
mathemeticians and Mrs Schwartz's
reflecting on her time in school.
I was always deeply uncertain about my own
intellectual capacity.
I thought I was unintelligent.
And it's true that I was, and I still am,
rather slow.
I need time to seize things because I
always need to understand them fully.
Even when I was the first to ans-, answer
the teacher's questions, I knew it
was because they happened to be questions
to which I already knew the answer.
But if a new question arose, Usually
students who read as good as I
was answered before me and towards the end
of the 11th grade I
secretly thought of myself as stupid and I
worried about this for a long time.
I never talked about this to anyone but
I always felt convinced that my imposture
would someday be revealed.
The whole world and myself would see that
what looked like intelligence was
really just an illusion Now that ever
happened.
Apparently no one ever noticed it, and I'm
still just as slow.
At the end of the eleventh grade I took
the measure of the situation and came to
the conclusion that rapidity doesn't have
a precise relationship to intelligence.
What is important is to deeply understand
things and their relations to each other.
This is where intelligence lies.
The fact of being quick or slow isn't
really relevant.
Naturally, it's helpful to be quick, like
it is to have a good memory.
But it's neither necessary nor sufficient
for intellectual success.
So, my question now is which of Schwartz,
Schwartz's reflections on
his school math experience stand out for
you as significant?
And why?
I'd like you to write about that.