[MUSIC].
So my first point was that mistakes are
helpful for learning, but
the second thing I want to talk about is
persistence.
When employers complain about students
coming out of the education system,
the chief thing they complain about is
lack of persistence.
That young people will try, and then very
quickly give up.
And this quote comes from Ray Peacock,
who is the Director of Research at Philips
Laboratories in the UK.
And this is what he said.
He said, lots of people think knowledge is
what we want, and
I don't believe that because knowledge is
astonishingly transitory.
We don't employ people as knowledge bases.
We employ people to actually do things or
solve things.
Knowledge basis comes out of books, so I
want flexibility and continuous learning
and I need team-working, and part of
team-working is communication.
When you're out doing any job in any
business the tasks are not
forty-five minutes max, they're usually
three week dollops or one day dollop or
something, and the guy that gives up, oh
sod it, you don't want him.
So the things therefore the flexibility,
the team work, communications and
the sheer persistence.
Now I'm sure for the teachers in the
course the lack of persistence amongst
students is a big concern for you too.
The students want to be spoon feed in math
lessons and many teachers tell me
that they've learned how great it is to
give open challenging tasks.
But when they give them out, the students
say they can't do them.
Now what students are doing in those
moments is reflecting the math's culture
that's been imposed on teachers in the
last decade or
so of doing lots and lots of equations
that don't require any deep thought.
Questions for which they've already been
told what method to use.
So it also reflects what French scholar
Guy Brousseau termed
the didactic contract.
And he pointed out that what often happens
in classrooms is this.
Students get stuck on a question and they
call the teacher over for help, and
they want to be led step by step through
the work.
But that takes out the cognitive demand of
the problem, and the trouble is,
kids don't expect to struggle and they
want to be helped with each step.
And teachers in their turn feel an
implicit contract that says they
should help students who need help.
So both the teachers and the students work
within this contract, and
they work together to empty the
interaction of learning.
And that's what's called the didactic
contract, and it's been
widely recognized and a lot of work done
on it in France and across the world.
So my question for you now is, do you
recognize this contract?
Think if you can, about a particular
situation as a parent or
a teacher and talk about the presence or
absence of this contract in your
interaction with a math student.