Mathematics is in crisis here in the U.S,
in the U.K and
in many other countries across the world.
Large numbers of people hate and fear
maths.
And as we saw in the very first class,
math ends peoples' chances of college in
the U.S.
Hundreds and thousands of people.
There are also not enough people
graduating from colleges with
the mathematics needed to help society.
And this is causing a serious shortage in
many really important fields
including Science, Medicine, Technology.
So it's seriously threatens the future of
countries.
Children and adults everywhere are
traumatized by math and
this can affect their whole life.
Do you remember Vivian, our British
Scientist and her trauma.
Many people have that and more.
So I just mentioned [UNKNOWN], and
their company Reel Link had been
developing a new film, largely about math.
And they actually liked to collect stories
about people's maths experiences for
the film.
So they've asked me to ask you to record
your story, if you have one about maths.
You know whether it's one about math
trauma, or
trying to bring about change, of good
teaching.
You can record your story and send it to
them.
And and you can visit that on their
website and they have an iPhone app.
So the website is racetonowhere.com.
And these are the words that Vicki sent
me.
She asked people for math stories she
said, we want to hear how
your situation or that of your child or
student changed for the better or worse.
Was it a realization in yourself?
An adult that believed in you?
A teacher or student that suggested you
look at math another way?
Or if nothing changed, what do you wish
had?
We want to to change our math education
system for the better and
your voices are critical to this change.
Keith Devlin is a Stanford mathematician
and
he has written a range of wonderful books
on math's learning and living.
And this is a quote from Keith who like
Paul Lockhart,
who we read earlier in the course.
Asked us to think about music to highlight
what's going on in today's classrooms.
So Keith says this: Mathematical notation
no more is
mathematics than musical notation is
music.
A page of sheet music represents a piece
of music, but the notation and
the music are not the same.
The music itself happens when the notes on
the page are sung or
performed on a musical instrument.
And its in its performance that the music
comes alive.
It exists not on the page but in our minds
and the same is true for mathematics.
Mathematics is a performance, it's a
living act,
it's a way of interpreting the world.
Imagine music lessons that make students
work through hundreds of hours of
sheet music.
Adjusting the notes on the page, receiving
checks and crosses, but
never playing the music.
Students won't, wouldn't continue with the
subject because they wouldn't ever
experience what music is.
And that's the situation we have a, a lot
in math classrooms.
Clearly we need to change the math is
taught.
And that is in the hands of teachers,
parents and administrators.
This may require being brave and
courageous as most people don't
understand how math is learned well but
they still hold very strong opinions.
And many people have serious
misconceptions including many
administrators.
Which is the reason I wrote the book that
I
wrote called What's Math Got To Do With
It?
Some of you may know about the attacks I
experienced when my research results
were published.
Two mathematicians who worked tirelessly
in the US,
pushing their view that students should
not engage actively in mathematics.
One of whom refers to African American as
Pickininers/g,
to give you a sense of who they are,
targeted me and my work.
I won't go in to that now, but I put the
details on this Stanford website.
The best thing I ever did was speaking up
against their behavior and
standing up to them.
That website was read by 50,000 people and
I was inundated, really overwhlemed, by
the support I received.
From teachers, mathmeticians, academics,
parents and others.
And that taught me many things.
The power of community, and of us working
together to stop bullies and
other people who stop change.
And also the importance of different forms
of media.
And just of speaking out.
The Twitter community helped a lot in
really depowering those two guys.
So, if we want to break this cycle of math
failure and
spread what we know about effective math
learning.
We may to be brave and communicate in many
different forms and ways.
In my work in recent years,
I've really come to realize how much
teachers have suffered over recent years.
Partly, some of them from the same two
men.
But more than that, since the No Child
Left Behind initiative,
teachers have had their professionalism
stripped away from them.
And many have been forced to do what they
know to be wrong.
I've seen schools where teachers have been
ordered to teach traditionally,
with desks in rows.
And then, on days when they ask the
students to work in groups for
an activity.
The students said to them you're not
allowed to do that.
How deprofessionalizing is an experience
like that?
In the last year I've worked in one school
district in depth.
Vista Unified, with the director of maths,
Kathy Williams.
And that's been great.
I've learned a lot from that in depth work
with teachers.
And I worked particularly with middle
school teachers and shared some of
the ideas from this course and other
ideas, we worked on maths together.
They went back to their schools and
started using inquiry tasks and
just saw the effect on their students
which made them so excited.
And I could see them becoming, getting,
getting the energy back that they've had
taken away.
And in one meeting with high, just one
meeting with high school teachers.
I showed some video of students working
together in amazing ways to
solve a complex problem.
They were INP students.
And the teachers looked at me with some
pain in their eyes and
one of them said to me.
Are we allowed to do that, because people
told us that we were harming children?
So, at the end of that meeting, they were
getting their old INP books out of
the covers and planning excitedly again.
Sandy at Vista High School was one of the
teachers I met with for just a few hours.
And she was teaching geometry to students
at the course they had to
pass to graduate.
All the students were in their last year.
And at the end of the year, she reflected
that one of the ideas she learned at
our meeting around the way to give
students feedback.
And telling them that you believe in them
had changed everything in her class.
All of the students passed the course and
they were coming up to her at graduation
to tell her what a difference she made
to them.
So these different interactions and
stories with teachers make me very happy
and sad.
Happy to be working with them.
Sad that these professionals who knew ten
times as much about student learning than
the people who were telling them what to
do.
Had had their own creativity and autonomy
taken away from them.
And what gave it back was a few ideas from
research,
research in what we know works and ideas
that they knew were really productive.
And I think we really need to open spaces
up for important ideas.
And certainly in the U.S, we're in a good
time to do that now.
And maybe these new forms of technology
can really help with that too.
Mathematics is a human activity, a social
phenomenon, it's a set of ideas and
concepts that help illuminate the world.
It can be seen in the design of buildings,
the rhythm of raindrops,
special effects in movies, and the social
networks that connect to us.
And mathematics is all about illuminating
relationships such as those we see in
shapes, in nature.
And it's a diverse and multidimensional
subject.
It's also a powerful way of expressing
relationships and
ideas in numerical, pictorial, graphical,
verbal and symbolic forms.
So let's together introduce students to
that world of exciting and
beautiful maths.
It's a really important thing to do.
So this is the end of the course.
And I want to end with a co, a final
question and a couple of things for
you to do.
The question is to ask you if there is any
particular way I can be helpful to you in
supporting any changes you make.
Maybe we have a follow-up course on how to
teach in these ways.
I recognize this course wasn't that.
It was really just about sparking a few
ideas.
Maybe keeping the forum open; maybe giving
you updates through monthly webinars.
I'd like to know how to help you, and
here's a question for that.