My graduate students at Stanford and I
taught algebra to a much more
diverse group of kids than you just saw,
racially, socially, academically.
I have great videos, I'm not able to put
them up yet,
I'm going to get new permissions.
But I will take you through the teaching
approach.
And our design principles.
And show you how it impacted the kids.
[MUSIC]
So, we taught a course which we called
Exploring Algebra and it was offered as a
five week summer school to seventh and
eighth grade kids, who were what I would
describe as disaffected.
They were typically diverse Bay Area group
of kids.
This is a chart of their ethnicities.
So summer school math is taught in the
long summers that they have in the US.
Usually most of the kids have been made to
come by parents or by schools who may
require a summer school class to go on
with the curriculum at the school.
So our kids came from 33 different classes
in their middle schools.
90% of them had been made to go to the
class and
their prior achievement in the last math
class was very mixed.
So 40% of them had got an A or a B, 20% a
C and 40% a D or an F.
So that was a pretty heterogeneous group
which we were happy about as we wanted
that to be part of our teaching.
So with 40% of them getting As and Bs, you
may wonder why I call them disaffected.
That's because in the survey that we gave
out on the first day of class where, where
students told us that they've been made to
come, there were typical descriptions.
We asked them how they felt about math and
these were pretty typical.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we taught four classes of about 30 kids
in each and my co-teachers were
Emily Sheehan, Tesha [UNKNOWN] Irving,
Nick Fiori and Jennifer DiBrienza.
And we had four teaching principles.
To engage students as active inquirers and
capable learners.
To teach algebra through mathematical
practices, generalizing, reasoning,
organizing, representing.
To develop a collaborate mathematical
community and to give opportunities for
student voice.
There were four 90 minute sessions a week
over five weeks.
So our main task that we gave were algebra
generalization tasks, and
I'm going to give you links and places in
the resources where you can lots of those.
They both engaged students actively on the
first point, and
they got straight to the core of algebra,
relationships and generalization.
And they encourage mathematical practices.
The students were really excited to learn
algebra in this way and
to see it as a tool that helped them.
So this statement about teaching students
as capable learners we had no ability to
repeat and we wanted them all to work on
hard problems.
And to give them messages that we believed
in them.
So we typically gave problems that had a,
had a low entry bar.
Everybody could start on it but extend it
to high places.
A good example of this is the pattern
growth task, where we saw the work of
the three boys in the fourth class when we
talked about tasks.
Anyone can describe a pattern in engaging
the task.
But that one extended to quadratic
functions.
The border problem that you've just seen
also has a low entry and a high ceiling.
So does the painted q problem we're
going to look at in a minute.
So the students all told us that their
previous math experience had
meant working silently through workshop
worksheets.
And we encourage them to discuss
everything, to work in pairs or groups.
Sometimes we strategically group students,
sometimes we let them choose where they
worked.
So we wanted to have whole class
discussions and
that meant students need to become
comfortable presenting from the front.
W hich is pretty scary for middle school
kids if they haven't done it before.
So we set out to nurture that by giving
them very easy ways to come up to
the front at first.
For example earlier on we gave them the
four fours activity which is one I
like a lot so I'll give you this now.
Can you make every number between one and
twenty using only four fours?
And you can use any operation.
For example we might say this.