So it turns out that a comfort with
mistakes is [INAUDIBLE] extremely
important for life and for success in
life.
For design and for invention, but also for
a way to, as he says, live in the world.
So we've talked about the importance of
mistakes.
Let's think for a while about why students
often feel so crushed when they make
a mistake, because it's hard to create a
mistake-friendly culture without
understanding the student resistance.
So I would like you to just list two
reasons here.
It can be two words.
So in as few words as possible.
Why do students, do you think, often feel
so bad about making mistakes?
What are your top two reasons?