So when we use this task, when we were
teaching algebra to some seventh and
eighth graders, a group of three students
saw it grow in two different ways,
as you can see from a picture of their
work.
With one of the boys, saw it growing as
cubes adding onto the bottom row
each time, and the other one saw it as
cubes adding onto each column.
Now there are other ways of seeing the
growth that you might have seen.
Some people see it as growing square, for
example.
But as students worked on that task, and
we also asked them to work at how many
cubes were in the 100th case,
they really had to think about the shape,
and the form, and the number of cubes.
And as they worked on that, they came to
develop and
understand a quadratic function.
So that's really big.
They weren't just given a function to
manipulate, but
they are actually forming it.
They were seeing it visually and
understanding its components.
And as the students worked on the task,
the first thing they realized was that
they'd seen it in different ways and
they talked about that and that deepened
their understanding of the function.
They then work to try and work out how the
shape was growing.
When I've worked in workshops and I've
given this task to
teachers with the same wording, asking
them to find the hundredth case,
thinking they would work in similar ways
to the students.
Instead they made a table, put in the
numbers,
could see that the function was growing as
an n plus 1 squared.
Function put in the number for the 100th
case and came up with an answer.
Then, when I asked them what their n
represented, and
their n plus 1 squared, they really didn't
know what their n represented.
And I realized that that's changing the
presentation of asking people,
how do you see the shape growing and
how many cubes were in case 100,
completely changed the task.
So now, when I do workshops with teachers,
I might ask for the 100th case but
I always start just by asking that, how do
you see the shape growing, as I asked you.
[MUSIC]
At Stanford we developed a framework for
what we thought were the essential
features of growth mindset tasks.
And this is that framework.
The last one the goals and opportunities
for
feedback, I'm going to talk about in a
minute.
But I want you now to stop and look at
that task's framework and think and
write about the different dimensions we
have in there.
And think about how the two versions of
the task,
one where we asked students to find the
100th case and
one where we ask them to see how the shape
is growing, differ on that framework.