So I know the idea that we need students
in different groups is very deep in US,
UK, and possibly other cultures.
And changing the heterogeneous grouping
requires big changes in teaching, but
if we keep telling students that they're,
that they're not good in maths or
that they have the math gift, it's really
going to be hard to break the cycle of
failure that we see in these and other
countries.
[MUSIC].
So the final piece is around messages.
Teachers and parents give messages to
students all of the time about mindsets,
and in the first session we saw the power
of one sentence in
changing student's learning trajectories.
You, you remember that's saying that I'm
giving you this feedback because I
believe in you and how that's changed the
student's learning.
Now teachers and parents can give messages
very explicitly by designing a lesson or
a conversation, and they can also give
them constantly as they interact.
So what I want to do now,
I'm going to show you the rest of the
interview I did with Carol Dweck.
It's about eight minutes long.
There's a lot in there to think about, and
as it's the end of this session, the final
task that I want to give you is to
really think about what you heard in the
lesson and from Carol.
And design something different you're
going to do with your students,
school students or your own children.
So think of ways to communicate positive
messages about growth mindset.
Maybe in your first class,
maybe it's something that will go through
your teaching with them.
Be creative.
Don't just think of things to say, there
might be a really good way to
get that information across, maybe a video
or an activity.
And I want, I want everyone to do is to
write down their ideas in a paragraph or
two and then those will be sent out and
you will get back three other
people's idea, so you can look and comment
on those.
And I'm also giving you, some resources
for great websites on, teaching for
a growth mindset.
So, I look forward to seeing you in the
next session.
>> When students are in a fixed mindset,
where everything and everybody is judging
how smart they are they see effort and
difficulty as meaning they're dumb.
But when they're in a growth mindset,
they come to understand that effort and
difficulty.
These are the times that they're getting
smarter.
These are the times that their brains are
growing new connections and
they're really, really learning.
We have a long line of research showing
that the self-esteem movement was wrong.
Praising kids' intelligence and talent is
harmful.
It puts them in a fixed mindset, it makes
them afraid of difficult tasks,
it makes them less resilient and less
persistent when they hit errors.
They only care about looking smart and
never doing anything that would contradict
that.
Parents think the greatest gift they can
give to kids is this gift of
praising intelligence.
It isn't.
It saddles them with a big liability.
Instead, what should you do?
Praise the child's process, the strategies
they, they use, the effort they put in,
the persistence they show, their focus on
doing the problem.
This gives them a growth mindset.
[COUGH] And it tells them what they can do
when they're struggling.
Those same things, it tells them how to
overcome obstacles,
not just why they succeeded but what they
can do to be successful in the future.
This is the greatest gift we can give to
kids.
We published a study recently showing that
mothers praise to
their babies one to three years of age
predicted the child's mindset and
desire for challenge five years later.
So that praise is powerful.
Recently, Stephanie Freiburg, a professor
at the University of Illinois did a big
growth mindset intervention at a Native
American Reservation where she grew up,
actually the whole school was transformed
in terms of the growth mind set.
Kids were asked to spend and
required to spend six hours a day in
school growing their brains.
And the, the educators explain that it's
because we care about you.
We want you to have six hours a day
growing your brain.
The younger grades, after one to one and a
half years of that growth minds
that message, went from the bottom of the
district to near the top of the district,
in terms of their reading readiness, and
reading Ccmprehension.
The higher grades gain substantially in
reading and math, but
it wasn't just a growth mind set message.
It was a growth mind set message that was
tailored to the communal values of
that culture.
So they weren't just told that they could
grow their intelligence,
they were told they could grow their
intelligence and
thereby help their families and their
communities better in the future.
So originally, the students were told,
listen,
you can get smarter, but in that culture
it wasn't an inherent value.
In a lot of mainstream culture you tell
kids you can get smarter and
they are riveted.
They're thrilled, they're in, but here,
it's really it was
a really strong value on helping your
family and contributing to your culture.
And when the growth mindset was framed in
terms of getting smarter in order to
contribute more to your family and
culture, it really took off.
Recently we did an intervention with the
Kahn Academy.
This was led by one of our graduate
students, Dave Panesku,
where before each fractions problem, kids
received either the standard kind academy,
no, nothing before the problem or a growth
mindset message.
Remember, the harder you work, the smarter
you get in math.
Or remember, when you work hard to solve
this problems your math grain,
brain will grow.
We also had a third group that received
encouraging statements.
Like this one's hard, do your best, or if
at first you don't succeed, try again.
Now that may sound a lot like growth
mindset, but
just exhorting kids to try is not the same
as teaching them that when they try.
They grow their math brains and become
better at math problems.
So, what happened?
First, we found that when the growth
mindset message was
before each fraction problem, the students
solved more problems.
Than the kids in the other two groups.
The encouragement alone did not do better
than nothing.
Also that improvement in a number of
problems solved continued on future units,
where they were no longer receiving those
growth mindset statements.
Also, the students who received the growth
mindset statements,
mastered many more, or significantly more
units after that fractions unit.
Even though they were no longer getting
that growth mindset message.
So, it means that the message that working
hard at math grows your math brain.
Not that it means you're dumb like in a
fixed mind set, but
it grows your math brain.
Teachers and parents should spend time
listening to
the fixed mind set messages they have in
their head.
The things they tell themselves about
themselves,
they things they're thinking about kids.
Don't get defensive, we all have those
thoughts, but start to hear them.
Don't evaluate them, just start to hear
them, and
eventually start talking back to the with
growth-mindset messages.
But it's very, very important to
understand,
we all have some fixed-mindset ideas, and
we need to be aware of them in
order to change our talk and practice to
truly reflect a growth mindset.
[BLANK_AUDIO]