I think that for students in today's
traditional math classrooms it's
really hard to stay curious.
How can you be mathematically curious when
all you're doing is having to
remember lists of methods?
That's really very hard.
But curiosity is a natural quality of
people that should be nurtured from birth,
nurtured mathematically.
But it disappears from students in math
classrooms, and
they really get the idea that there's no
roll for curiosity, only for answers.
So in my thinking about these parts of the
mathematical inquiry relationship we
want students to have, I see some
interesting interrelationships.
So even though some scholars have
contrasted intuition with understanding,
my work that I'm doing with these
high-level math issues shows me intuition
and understanding are interrelated in very
interesting and important ways.
Raymond Wilder, an American mathematician
and topologist I think, agrees.
He points out that without intuition,
there's no creativity in mathematics.
But also that the intuitive component is
dependent for
its growth on the knowledge component.
And that really fits with the people I've
been interviewing who's
intuition clearly grew out of
understandings.
And then their understandings grew out of
the intuition.
The mathematician's Burton interview
linked interestingly with
mathematical connections suggesting that
intuition really draws from
mathematical connections.
And those are often missed in classrooms
as well.
It may be that students' lack of connected
awareness of math and
lack of opportunities to work on the
connections partly prevents their
development of intuition.
So there's an important iterative process
in understanding and intuition.
And I would say that there's a kind of
helix.
Related to that also is mathematical
curiosity,
something with such inherent value.
Everyone agrees that curiosity is a
wonderful thing.
But, I don't think [INAUDIBLE]
mathematical curiosity remains in
students, if they don't feel good about
themselves in maths.
I'm going to play you another short
extract from one of my students Sammy.
She didn't know at all that I was
interested in, or
would be talking about curiosity in this
course.
But when we interviewed her, she talked
about how her curiosity ended.
>> I think, that if, if somebody could,
given me positive feedback about math or
said, you're good at math or you can do
this, that I think my experience would
have been a little bit different because I
remember before that testing debacle in,
in fourth grade, I remember being so
curious about why
a square was a rectangle, but a rectangle
wasn't a square.
And really caring about those sorts of
problems, and then,
as soon as people start telling you, math
isn't your thing, then, it's all downhill.
>> In the first class, I shared that very
few students feel good about maths.
And one of the teachers in our teaching
program at Stanford recently concluded,
after one year of teaching, that math has
beaten my students down really,
really badly.
And I know exactly what she means.
Of course it isn't math per se,
that's beaten the students down, it's
their experiences in math in school.
And that suppresses curiosity.
So I really see two kind of interrelating
helixes, understanding and
intuition on the one hand, competence and
curiosity on the other.
There are a number of components of an
inquiry relationship that
students need that are separate from the
knowledge we focused on for decades.
But it is clear to me that there were two
parts to mathematical competency in
today's world, knowledge and an inquiry
relationship.
So now I'd like you to choose a word that
represent, for
you, the most important aspect of the
relationship you think students need.
It might be one of the words we've talked
about, like inquiry or curiosity or
maybe a different one.
Choose the one that's most important for
you and
when we get some responses, we'll show you
a word cloud.
[MUSIC]