Okay so this is Kathy writing about
the Dot Card Number Talks.
[MUSIC]
Okay.
Now we're going to look at a number number
talk.
And as you watch this video, you're going
to see Kathy enact a number of practices.
Or what we might call teacher moves that
are really important in number talks.
So keep a note, or a mental note of what
you think they are.
Because after the video, I'm going to ask
you to write them down and
also comment on someone else's submission,
so
this is going to be like a peer assessment
type of writing.
>> We're going to try a different number
talk this time and
this time it's with numbers and it's
going to be multiplication.
Okay, so get ready to think.
And the
problem
is.
And if your thumb is already
up you might try to see
if you could see it a different
way.
Okay, so I'm seeing most
people's thumbs.
Is anybody willing to share what they
think the answer might be?
[SOUND].
Okay, Joe, what do you think?
>> 720.
>> Does anybody have another idea about
what the answer might be?
>> Okay Shay?
>> 725.
>> I change mine.
[LAUGH]
>> Hold on.
Does anyone have a dif,
an idea, a different idea about what the
answer might be?
Okay, so Joe, what's the matter?
>> What I, I realize what I did.
I I think Shay and I probably both got to
750, but she accurately subtracted 25,
and I subtracted 30.
because I was confused by the rounding I
was doing, from 29 to 30.
>> That's good.
That's good.
You were, so I'll have you, actually, so,
you're saying that you want to disagree
with this answer then?
>> Yeah, yeah, I want to disagree with my
answer, yes.
>> Okay, so you're agreeing that the
answer's 725.
>> Yes.
>> Okay, so
let's go through your method then, Joe.
And you can show us what you did wrong.
>> What I did was I rounded 29 to 30 to
make a friendly number.
>> Okay, so we're doing 25 times 29, but
you decided to do 25 times 30 to.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Because.
>> To, because 30 is a friendly number
and, and easier to multiply with.
>> Okay, alright.
>> And then what I did was I broke
25 up into 10 plus 10 plus 5.
So what that does is you can multiply 30
by each of those numbers, so
that turns into 300 plus 300 plus 150.
>> So you multiplied 30 times each one of
those numbers?
>> Yes.
>> 10 plus 10 plus 5.
Okay, and then?
>> So 30 times 10 is 300.
Plus 30 times 10, which is 300.
Plus 30 times 5 which is 150.
>> Okay.
>> So I added those up and that equals
750.
>> Okay.
>> And then I knew because I rounded 29 up
to 30 I had to subtract a number and,
I think I just got a little confused.
Instead of subtracting the 25, which is
what we're, I'm really doing here,
multiplying by an extra, you know, adding
an extra 25 in the multiplication.
>> How do you know you're adding an extra
25 in the multiplication?
>> Because I'm doing 25 times 30, which is
25 times 29 plus 25.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you added too many 25s.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> And you want to take away one.
>> And I want to take away 25, which
would.
>> So you got.
>> Yeah.
>> And then you got.
>> That would be 725, but I accidentally
did minus 30 in my.
>> But you almost did.
>> Confusion, and that would have.
[CROSSTALK]
>> That's an interesting mistake, though,
minus 30.
>> Yes, it is an interesting mistake.
>> Where do you think the 30, what were
you thinking?
Do you think you were this?
>> I think I just yeah, I got confused, I
think,
about which number in the original
equation I was adding an extra of.
>> Yeah, that's really complicated.
Did anybody have the same,did anybody else
round up to 30?
Oh really?
Okay, do you want to talk about what you
did?
You don't, Geraldine.
Who does want to talk about what they did?
Okay Joe and then.
>> Yeah similar to Joe 25 times 30 was
first initial reaction to create two
friendly numbers but, you know,
knowing there's, there's ways in math that
we kind of make, like, quick shortcuts.
>> Yeah.
>> So knowing that 30 makes it more,
more, [INAUDIBLE] for me to actually do it
sometimes in my head.
So I just cut the zero off and made 25
times 3.
So I made it into quarters almost.
So three quarters.
>> So you were thinking three quarters.
>> Yeah, so that way, because I know in
the future I will then add the zero,
knowing that, that rule applies to all
equations multiplied by a zero at the end.
>> So when you did 25 times 29, you, you
did.
>> I did the same thing at 25 times 30.
>> Times 30, but then you were thinking of
quarters.
>> Yeah, 25 times 3.
>> So, were you thinking of 3 times 25?
So you were thinking of 3 quarters?
>> Yeah.
That means 25s, yeah, rings, you know,
quarters amounts in my head.
>> Okay.
So 3 quarters, And you knew that was.
>> 75.
>> Like cents almost.
Yeah.
>> And then.
>> So now, I mean,
now I kind of halved the equation already,
because knowing the rule, the zero rule.
When you multiply something by zero, you
just add on the zero.
>> When you multiply.
>> So, you know, I just kind of did Joe's
method, but
instead of breaking it down, decompose it,
I just tried to simplify the, the
equation, and then apply the rule of zero.
>> Okay, let me rewind you.
Did you, I think I heard you say, when I,
when you multiply by something by zero,
you add a zero.
Is that what you meant?
>> Yeah, anything, anything you multiply,
or is known.
>> Go ahead.
>> Any, any, because anything by 10, 20 or
30 you can, you know, cut zero off and
just multiply by the 3 or 2 or 1,
depending on the, the number it is, and
then once you get that number, you just
add on a 0 at the end.
>> Oh, so you weren't multiplying by 0,
you were multiplying by.
>> 2, yes.
>> A multiple of 10.
>> Multiple of 10, yes.
>> okay.
>> So, I guess what I'm trying to say is
that I definitely broke it down.
>> Okay.
>> So
that I was multiplying by yeah, the tens.
>> Okay.
So, the 25 times 3,
the 3 quarters, helped you know, helped
you think about about the 750.
>> Yeah, just to make it more friendly of
a equation.
>> Okay, then that's what we're after.
And so, what did you do then?
>> Yeah, well, you know, same realization,
realization that Joe had is that,
you know, because I round up, I'm round, I
multiply one more 25 than necessary.
And so I subtract that 25 away from 7,
750.
So, 750 minus 25, just so that, similar to
Joe,
is similar to 75, 25 times 30 minus 25.
>> Okay.
Very, very similar.
Okay.
>> Very similar.
>> Who did it a completely different way?
Okay.
Vivian, you want to go?
>> I took 25 times 20.
So, I guess, basically, I took apart 20,
29, and made it 20 and 9, first.
And so I did 25 times 20.
>> Okay, so you, you took, you multiplied
25.
>> Yes, and I, I did it kind of similar to
Julio.
And then I, I just took the 0 off with the
rule of the, rule of tens, so,
like, I took it off and did 25 times 2 and
I got 50.
>> Okay.
>> And then I added the 0 back that I had
taken away, so I got 500.
>> So if 25 times 2 is 50 then 25 times 20
is 500.
Okay?
>> And then from there, I applied the
quarter, the quarter rule.
So I knew that four would make 100, So I
knew that five.
>> You knew that four?
>> Four 25s.
>> Four 25s would make a hundred.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Okay.
>> So, fours groups of 25, if you add them
together it will make a 100.
So, I saw that there were two groups of 4,
so that's 200.
So, I had 700, 500 plus 200 is 700.
>> Okay.
Rewind for a second.
Where did you see the two groups of 4
quarters?
>> In the 9.
>> Yes.
>> So, when you broke up the 29, you broke
it into.
You were thinking about 29 as?
>> 20 and 9.
>> 20 plus 9?
>> Mm-hm.
>> Okay, and then.
>> And then I broke the nine up into 4, 4
[CROSSTALK].
>> okay, so then you broke the 9 up into
4s, 4.
>> 4, 4, and 1.
>> Plus 4, plus 1.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Okay, now I'm up with you.
Then what?
>> Yeah.
And so I knew that each of the 4s would
represent 100 because I
was multiplying it by 25.
>> So I knew 4 times 25 is 100, 4 times 25
is 100, that would make 200, so
I added that 200 to the 500.
>> Okay.
So this really represents, for you, 4
times 25.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And this represents 4 times 25.
And then, the 1?
>> 25 by just [CROSSTALK]
>> 25, 1 times 25, okay.
And so going back here then, this 9
actually means 9 times 25?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Whew. Okay, now what?
>> Well as I said before, I took the 200
from the 4 times 25, plus 4 times 25,
added to the 500.
>> Okay, so you knew this was 100 and 100,
so
you knew that was 200, and you add that
to.
>> To the 500.
>> The 500 you had here?
Okay, 500, okay.
>> And that gave me 700.
>> Okay.
And then there is that one 25 left.
>> That I added onto it, and I got 725.
>> Okay.
How are we doing on time?
Have us think about some of the properties
we talked about.
And so I, you've broken up numbers in a
lot of different ways, and
so I, what I'd like, I'm going to do is,
I'm going to draw a picture for
what I think Joe saw first up here, a
diagram.
And if this is 25.
Joe Joe, as you, you, you saw the 29.
But then you added one more on there.
So you multiplied 25 times 30.
And then you subtracted the 25?
>> Yeah.
>> So this part went out.
And this was 25 plus 1.
Does anybody know what property that is?
What Joe did, how you would write it
algebraically.
Talk to each other real quick.
See how you would write this
algebraically.
[CROSSTALK]
Too bad we don't
have the mics on
every table.
Is anybody willing to say what property it
is, and how it works?
>> We thought it was the distributive
property, because.
>> You want to say why, Kellen?
>> Yeah.
He, since Joe added 1.
>> Hang on, let me just write it up here.
>> He's now taking his 25 and multiplying
it by both 29 and 1.
>> Okay, so how would you write that?
Do you know?
>> 25 times, and then with parentheses.
>> Okay.
>> 29 plus 1.
>> 29, which is the original problem.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Plus 1 that he added.
Okay.
>> And then he's distributing the 25
across [CROSSTALK] multiplied by 29.
>> 25 times 29?
One, 20.
Okay, good.
What about one more.
Let's see I just oh, let's see, Julio, you
said three quarters, Joe,
Vivian, how, how would you write Vivian's
using the distributive property?
Talk that one over.
And pre, draw on the desk, like,
pretend with your finger, how you would
draw a picture for this.
>> [CROSSTALK]
>> Wait, say that again.
>> 25 times [INAUDIBLE],
she broke the 29 into 20 and 9, so
it would be 25 times 20, and 25 times 9.
>> [CROSSTALK]
>> Is anybody willing,
that, that we haven't heard from yet,
to talk, explain this for us?
Stephanie, great, thank you.
>> So explaining what would be the
equation, or the picture?
[CROSSTALK]
>> Yeah, well, you could do the picture or
the equation, either one.
We can do both separately, if you'd like.
>> Okay.
So first, it would, so
the, it would be 25 and then the 29 would
be broken up into 20.
Plus 4 plus 4 plus 1.
>> So 20 from.
Oh, this is badly out of whack.
[LAUGH].
It's more like that.
4 plus 4 plus 1.
So you're saying that this is oh well.
[SOUND].
Is that what you're saying?
>> Mm-hm.
>> Stephanie?
Okay.
So this whole thing is still 29, but those
are the separate pieces.
Okay, then how would we write it
algebraically?
Somebody else.
[INAUDIBLE]
Okay Erin, try.
>> I guess it would be 25 times.
>> I feel like I need a different color
pen somewhere.
Okay.
I'm going to write it over here then.
>> Okay.
>> So, 25 times.
>> Times the quantity of 20 plus 4 plus 4
plus 1.
>> What do you think?
Yep.
Good.
We are done with our number talk.
Thank you very much.
[NOISE]
[MUSIC]