So one of the best ways to teach number
sense is a pedagogical strategy that's
been really growing over recent years.
It's kind of a grass roots movement called
Number Talks.
Sometimes they're called Math Talks.
And they were started by Ruth Parker and
Kathy Richardson.
You may use these already but I know many
people don't.
And we're going to try one together in a
moment.
The way they work is, in a classroom you
would ask students to work out
a problem mentally in their heads, without
written work, without writing.
And when they've answered the problem
students are asked to just put up
their thumb.
No hands because when students are putting
their hands up as soon as
they're finished it's intimidating for
people who haven't finished.
And I'm going to just show you the way a
number talk is introduced.
Just the first piece now with the use of
thumbs.
So this was a number talk that Cathy
Humphreys gave to our elementary teachers
at Stanford.
And we're just going to watch the
beginning here to see how a number talk
is started.
>> Okay.
So on this card, there are some shapes.
And when I put the card up,
I'd like you to figure out how many there
are without counting one by one.
So take a quick glimpse at them.
And when you're, when you do think you
know how many there are,
then put your thumb up to show me.
Ready?
>> So
before we watch a couple of different
number talks,
I want to try some of the mathematical
ideas with you together.
So the first thing I'm going to ask you is
just simply to write down the answer
without using pen and paper.
Try not to use a, the traditional
algorithm but
work out and write down the answer for 18
times 5.
[MUSIC].