Okay, so this is Cathy writing about the
dot card number talks.
Okay.
Now we're going to look at
a number number talk.
And as you watch this video, you're going
to see Cathy enact a number of practices,
or what we might call teacher moves that
are really important in number talks.
So keep a note or a mental note of what
you think they are,
because after the video I'm going to ask
you to write them down, and
also comment on someone else's submission.
So this is going to be like a pair
assessment type of writing.
>> We're going to try a different number
talk this time.
And this time it's with numbers, and it's
going to be multiplication.
Okay?
So get ready to think and
the problem is [NOISE] and
if your thumb is already up you might
try to see if you could see it a different
way.
Okay, so I'm seeing
most people's
thumbs.
Is anybody willing to share what they
think the answer might be?
Okay, Joe.
What do you think?
>> 720.
>> Does anybody have another idea
about what the answer might be.
>> Okay, Shay?
>> 725.
>> I changed my answer.
[LAUGH]
>> Hold on.
Does anyone have an idea, a different idea
about what the answer might be?
Okay, so Joe, what's the matter?
>> What I, I realized what I did.
I I think Shannon probably both got to
750, but
she accurately subtracted 25, and I
subtracted 30.
Cause I was confused by the rounding I was
doing from 29 to 30.
>> That's good.
That's good.
You were, so I want I'll have you,
actually, so you're saying that you
want to disagree with this answer?
>> yeah, I want to disagree with my
answer, yes.
>> Okay.
And so you're agreeing at the answer, 725?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, so
let's go through your method then, Joe and
you could show us what you did wrong.
>> What I did was I rounded 29 to 30, to
make it a friendly number.
>> Okay, so we're doing 25 times 29.
But you decided to do 25 times 30 to
>> Mm-hm.
>> Because?
>> Because 30's a friendly number and
>> Okay.
>> And it's easier to multiply with.
>> Alright.
>> And
then what I did, was I broke 25 up into 10
plus 10, plus 5.
So, what that does is you can multiply 30
by each of those numbers, so
that turns into 300 plus 300 plus 150.
So you multiplied 30 times each one of
those numbers.
>> Yes.
>> 10 plus 10 plus 5, okay, and then.
So, 30 times 10 is 300, plus 30 times 10
which is 300,
plus 30 times 5, which is 150.
>> Okay.
>> So I added those up and that equals
750.
>> Okay.
>> And then I knew, because I rounded 29
up to 30 I had to subtract a number, and.
>> I think I just got a little confused.
Instead of subtracting the 25 which is
what I'm really doing here,
multiplying by an extra, you know, adding
an extra 25 in the multiplication.
>> How do you know you're adding an extra
25 in the multiplication?
>> Because I'm doing 25 times 30, which is
25 times 29 plus 25.
>> okay.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you added too many 25s.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> And you want to take away one.
>> And I want to take away 25,
which would yield
>> So, you got
>> Yeah.
>> And then you got?
>> That would be 725.
But, I accidentally did minus 30.
>> Than mine.
>> But you almost didn't.
>> Confusion and then that would've.
>> That's an interesting.
>> That's why I thought it was.
>> Mistake though.
Minus 30.
>> Yes it is and.
>> Where do you think the 30.
What were you thinking?
Were you thinking.
>> The thing I just.
>> This?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I got confused, I think about,
about which number in the original
equation I was adding an extra of.
>> Yeah, that's really complicated.
>> Did anybody have the same experience?
Did anybody else round up to 30?
Oh really?
Do you want to talk about what you did?
You don't, Geraldine,, who does want to
talk about what they did?
Okay, Joe and then.
>> Yes, similar to Joe,
25 times 30 was my first initial exaction
to create two friendly numbers.
but, you know, knowing there's, there's
ways in math that we cut,
we take quick shortcuts,
>> Yeah.
>> So knowing that 30 may sit, where, to,
or for me, to actually do it sometimes in
my head, so I just cut the zero off and
made 25 times 3.
So I made it into quarters almost.
>> So three quarters.
>> So you were thinking three quarters.
>> Yeah, so that way, because I know in
the future I will then add the zero,
knowing that that rule applies to all
equations multiplied by a zero at the end.
>> So when you did 25 times 29, you, you
did...
>> I did same thing at 25 times 30.
>> Times 30.
But then you were thinking of quarters.
>> Yeah, 25 times 3.
>> So were you thinking of 3 times 25.
So you're thinking of three quarters?
>> Yeah.
That means 25 is yeah, rings, you know,
quarters in my head.
>> Okay, so three quarters.
And you knew that was 75.
>> 75.
It's like I said it's almost yeah.
>> And then.
>> So now, I mean now I cut it to half the
equation already because knowing
the No-Zero Rule.
>> When you multiply something by a 0 you
just add on the 0.
>> When you multiply.
>> So you know, I just kind of did Jones'
method, but
instead of breaking it down and
decomposing it I just tried to simplify
the equation and then apply the rule of 0.
>> Okay let me rewind you.
I, did you, I think I heard you say when
I,
when you multiply something by 0 you add a
0?
>> Yeah, well anything, anything you
multiply, well I just know in...
Anything by 10, 20, or 30 you can, you
know, cut the zero off and
just multiply it by the three or two or
one, depending on the number it is, and
then once you get that number you can just
add on the zero at the end.
>> Oh, so you weren't multiplying by zero.
You were multiplying by a.
>> Two, yes.
>> A multiple of ten.
>> Multiple of ten.
>> okay.
>> What I guess I'm trying to say is
that I definitely broke it down so that I
was probably by, at the tens.
>> Okay.
So the 25 times, times 3,
the three quarters helped you know, help
you think about the 750.
>> Yeah.
Just to make it more friendly of an
equation.
>> Okay.
Then that's what we're after.
And so, what Did you do then?
>> Yeah, well you know, same resident,
realizing that Joe had,
is that you know because I round up, I'm
rounding, I am multiplying one more 25
than necessary, and so I have to track
that 25 away from seven, 750.
So 750 minus 25, just so
that similar to Joe, it's similar to 75,
25 times 30 minus 25.
>> Okay.
>> There's very similar, Okay.
Who did it a completely different way.
Okay, Vivian, want to go?
>> I took 25 times 20.
So I guess basically I took apart 20, 29
and made it 20 and
9 first
>> And so I did 25 times 20.
>> Okay, so you took, you multiplied 25.
>> Yes, and I did it kind of similar to
Julio in that I just took the 0 off with
the rule of 10s, so like I took it off and
did 24 times 2 and I got 50.
Okay.
>> And then I added the zero back that I'd
taken away.
So I got 500.
>> So if 25 times two is 50, then 25 times
20 is 500.
Okay.
>> And then from there,
I applied the quarter, the quarter rule.
So I knew that four would make 100.
>> So I knew that
>> You knew that four
>> Four 25 would make 100, okay.
>> So four groups of 25, if you add them
together will make a hundred.
So I saw that there were two groups of
four so that was 200.
So I had 700.
500 plus 200 is 700.
>> Okay rewind for a second.
Where did you see the two groups of four
quarters?
>> In the 9.
>> And the nine.
>> Yup.
>> So when you broke up the 29,
you broke it into you were thinking about
29 as
>> 20 and
nine
>> 20 plus nine
>> hm.
>> Okay.
>> And then I broke the nine up
into four four
>> Okay so
then you broke the nine up into fours?
>> 4?
>> 4 4 and 1
>> Plus 4 plus 1.
>> Mmhm.
>> Okay now I'm up with you.
Then what?
>> Yeah.
And so I knew that each of the 4s
would represent 100 because I was
multiplying it by 25.
>> So I knew 4 times 25 is 100, 4 times 25
is 100, that would make 200.
>> So I addd that 200 to the 500.
>> Okay, so this really represents for you
4 times 25, and
this represents 4 times 25, and then the
1?
>> 25.
I just [CROSSTALK] 1 and the 2.
>> 25 times 25.
Okay, and so going back here then this 9
actually means 9 times 25...
>> Yeah, okay.
Whew.
Okay, now what?
>> Well, as I said before I took the 200
from 4 times 25 plus 4 times 25,
add it to the 500.
>> Okay so you knew that this was 100 and
100 and that was 200, and
you added that to.
>> To the 500.
>> The 500 you had here, okay, 500,
okay...
>> And that gave me 700.
>> Okay.
>> And then there was that one 25 left.
>> And that I added onto it, and
I got 725.
>> Okay.
>> How are we doing on time?
Have us think about some of the properties
we talked about.
And so I You've broken up numbers in a lot
of different ways.
And so I, what I'd like, I'm going to do
is I'm going to draw a picture for
what I think Joe saw first up here.
A diagram.
>> And if this is 25 Joe, Joe as you, s-,
you saw the 29, but
then you added one more on there?
>> Oh, Yeah.
>> So, you multiplied 25 times 30 and then
you subtracted the 25.
>> Yeah.
>> So, this part went out and this was 25
plus 1.
Does anybody know what property that is?
What Joe did?
How you would write it alegebraically?
Talk to each other real quick.
See how you would write
this alegebraically.
[CROSSTALK]
[INAUDIBLE]
Too bad we
don't have the mics on every table.
Is anybody willing to say what property is
and how it works?
>> We thought it was a distributive
property, because.
>> You want to say why, Kellan?
>> Yeah.
He, since Joe added 1.
>> Hang on, let me just write it up here.
>> He's now taking his 25 and multiplying
it by both 29 and 1.
>> Okay, so how would you write that?
Do you.
>> 25 times, and then with parenthesis, 29
plus 1.
>> 19, which is the original problem, plus
1 that he added.
Okay.
>> And then he's distributing the 25
across the [CROSSTALK] multiplied with
the 21-
>> 25 times 29?
[CROSSTALK] 120.
Okay, good.
What about one more.
Let's see, I just.
Oh, let's, let's see, Julio uses three
quarters, Joe.
Vivian, how, how would you write Vivian's
on using the distributive property?
Talk that one over.
And pre-, draw on the desk,
pretend with your finger how you would
draw a picture for this.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Wait, say that again.
>> Wait, I didn't say that.
>> 20 and 9, so it would be 25 times 20,
plus.
>> 20.
>> 25 times nine, although [INAUDIBLE]
[CROSSTALK] [CROSSTALK] [INAUDIBLE]
>> It would really be 21.
[CROSSTALK] [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, it's just.
[CROSSTALK]
>> Yeah.
>> Is anybody willing, that we haven't
heard from yet,
to talk, explain this for us?
>> Stephanie, great.
Thank you.
So, explaining what would be the equation
or the picture.
>> Yeah, well, you could do the picture or
the equation, either one.
We can do both separately if you'd like.
Okay, so first it would, so
it'd be 25 and then, the 29 would be
broken up into 20 plus 4 plus 4 plus 1.
So twenty from oh this is badly out of
whack.
[LAUGH] It'd more like that.
That's four plus one but you're saying
this is oh well.
Is that what you are saying Stephanie?
>> Okay.
So, this whole thing is still 29, but
those are the separate pieces.
Okay, then how would we write
algebraically?
Somebody else?
>> Okay Erin try.
>> I guess it would be 25 times.
>> I feel like I need a different colored
pen somewhere.
Okay I'm going to write it over here then.
>> Okay.
>> So 25 times.
>> Times the quantity of 20 plus 4 plus 4
plus 1.
>> What do you think?
Okay.
Good.
We are done with our number talk.
Thank you
very much.