George Polya, a world leading
mathematician, wrote a short book called
How to Solve It, in which he goes through
a very important problem solving process.
And it has many similarities with my
thinking process.
And his headings are these, now of course
the important details from him,
inside those headings.
And you can easily find his processes by
doing a quick web search.
In mathematics, people have found Polya's
strategies are enormously helpful, but
they've generally being seen as useful for
solving big problems.
Whereas I'm arguing that theirs a thinking
in every mathematical question.
[MUSIC]
So I want to spend the moment now on the
collaboration piece.
Because collaboration gives students
conceptual insight in
an amazingly powerful way.
Have you ever been stuck about something,
anything, not necessarily mathematical,
and told someone about it, and suddenly
you have the insight that you needed?
Or maybe you've asked a student in a
classroom to repeat a question to you, and
as they repeat that question they suddenly
realize what they need to do.
As people have an idea in mathematics or
a solution path and then they hear another
person's idea or solution path.
They are invited in those moments to make
connections and
to think conceptually about mathematical
processes.
These are a critical part of mathematical
thinking.
Mary, one of my students, is talking here
about the conceptual insights she got in
college from hearing other people's
thoughts and
the way that considering others, other
people's methods, helped her.
>> I found in college it's very helpful to
work in groups on problems.
It's easier when you can talk it over with
other people, and
understand their methods of doing it.
In high school, I felt like the problems
we were doing were all very structured in
the sense that there was only one layer to
do it, maybe.
I mean, there were obviously more than
one, but there was.
>> A pretty obvious method to solve it but
in college these problems, there are many
ways that are valid to solve them, so it
was cool to see the different ones, and.
>> So the research study that shows the
power of collaboration, more than any for
me was conducted by Uri Treisman, although
there have been many important studies
showing the importance of collaboration.
At the time Uri was a mathematics
professor at Berkeley.
He's now at the University of Texas,
Austin.
And zuti realized, when he was at
Berkeley,
that large numbers of students were
failing calculus and
dropping out of the university, and mostly
those students were African-American.
Rather than just accepting that, as some
have,
he questioned why there was such a
difference, and he particularly looked.
The differences between African-American
students and
Chinese students, who are much more
successful.
So we set about to study those two groups
of students and we found that there was no
difference in the schools they came in
with, in the background knowledge and
their motivation at college and their
income, but there was one big difference.
The Chinese students did maths together.
They would meet after classes, and they
would have meals together, and
in those social situations they would work
on their maths problems.
So having found that, we instigated a
series of workshops where students work
collaboratively and they particularly
brought in minority students.
So in these workshops white students were
in the minority, and
the results were dramatic.
The black and Latino students in these
workshops started outperforming those
with similar and even those who had higher
SAT scores.
So, black students with SAT scores in the
low 600s started outperforming white and
Asian students who were in the mid 700s.
Soon, 200 students a year took the
workshops.
Uri moved to UT Austin and set up the
workshops again and
at that university minorities now have an
average GPA of 3.53.
Compared to an average of 1.66, and they
now have a 100 Latino, and
Black math majors each year.
In fact most of our minority
mathematicians in the United States now
come from Austin.
So that's a really important study for
equity reasons.
I also shows clearly that when the
students discuss mathematics problems,
Talking about why they chose their
methods, thinking about why they work.
It promotes reasoning, sense making, and
conceptual growth.
There should be considerable time in every
single mathematics class for
students to discuss the mathematical
ideas.
Otherwise they're missing out on
one of the most important learning
experiences they can have.
So I'd like you to write down your top 3
reasons why you think it helps students to
discuss mathematics with others.
[MUSIC]