So now this is Kathy reflecting on that
number talk you just saw.
So now we're going to look at a slightly
different number talk that was given to
third graders, and the teacher has adapted
the method somewhat.
So the teacher is Nick Foot of Barron Park
School, and
he does a lot with number sense, as he
knows how important it is.
And in this clip he's offered two problems
to the class.
Then let them go and work in pairs or
threes.
He gives them the choice, of which problem
to work on.
Usually there's one easier and one harder.
And they record their strategies on an
iPad app called Doodle Class Pro.
And you're going to see some of the
students,
first we'll have a look at some of the
students at work.
So they've been given the two problems,
they've chosen one, and
they get to sit in twos and threes Working
and recording their methods.
So after about 15 minutes of that work,
the students come together and
they share strategies and talk them
through.
So Nick gets all the solutions on the
whiteboard using the reflector app, and
he projects them onto the whiteboard.
And in the clip we're going to see he's
going through one of the harder
problems that he gave with the students.
>> One, I want to say, good.
Teamwork I could, right, work together,
took turns,
shared, tried to solve the problem.
What I want to see is, I want to see if we
can do it together and then we'll take
a look at how, how you guys did it, okay,
to see if we come up with the same answer.
Quentin, so who can help me get started up
here.
Pavel, help me get started.
>> 8 times 3 is 24.
>> Okay.
So you said 8 times 3 is 24.
Okay.
Let's have it, 'cause I want to give
Miranda, it was Miranda's group, so
Miranda, from us
taking a second look here, she might see
something that they didn't see before.
>> So then.
>> Sure.
>> I would do,
I would split the 9 into 3 and 3.
>> okay.
>> And I would split the 24 into.
>> So.
>> 6 and 4.
>> 3 oop.
>> So 3 times 3, right.
>> So you saw this is that, right?
>> Yeah, and then I split the 24 into six
and four.
>> Okay.
So, I've got three and three, and then I
have, whoops.
>> Oh, that's right, I gotta go back here.
>> He used the pen.
>> My fault.
There we go.
Okay, so you said, so
now we've got six, four, three and three.
Okay, alright, we've taken the factors of
these numbers,
made them a little bit something.
Dinello, that has to be closed right now,
please.
Close it.
Okay, so what do we, where do.
>> Maybe you could do 4 times 3 to get 12.
>> Go ahead.
>> You do 4 times 3 to get 12.
>> Jeff has that.
Okay 4 times 3 gets 12.
Okay.
>> [CROSSTALK] You do 6 times 3.
>> And get 18.
18 times 12 [CROSSTALK].
>> So just [LAUGH].
>> So 6 times 3 equals 18.
>> So you're saying, okay, we.
>> Well, then, 18 times 12 equals, 216.
>> How'd you figure that out?
>> So if you go back to eight times, if
you go back to the start.
>> Okay.
>> Eight times
>> Start here
>> Eight times nine is 72.
>> Eight times nine equals 72.
Okay!
>> So time, so 70 times three equals 210.
>> 70 Shhh.
Oh, 70 times three is 210.
>> Then two times three
equals six.
So.
>> Two times three is six.
>> So 210 plus six equals 216.
>> 210 plus six equals.
216.
Okay.
Do we have enough, is there, do we see it
another way?
I'm just wondering.
So 8 times 9 times 3.
Jeremy, let's pass the mic to Jeremy.
Let's go ahead and have Jeremy.
Jeremy?
>> How do you see this one?
I think it's 24.
>> So what did you do?
Tell us what you did?
>> I like, the 8 times 3 equals 24.
>> Okay.
Great.
>> And then 9, and 9 is 33.
>> So you say that 9 is 3 and 3.
>> Okay.
>> And 24 times 3.
>> 24 times 3 equals,
oh, 72.
>> Okay.
>> And 72 times 3 and n equals 216.
>> 216.
Okay.
>> So question for you now, when I asked
the students in this class what they
thought about math, what do you think they
talked about?
So think a little bit about what they
might have told me math was.
[MUSIC]