So I'm going to finish this session with
some thoughts.
Math is a creative subject that can be
seen in different ways,
it can be solved in different ways.
People think of humanities subjects as the
ones that are more open.
And can be solved in different ways.
But math has something really important
and unique really in its contribution.
Often in math there is one answer, not
always, but sometimes there's one answer.
But always people can see methods and
solutions in different ways.
And what we find is when we have students
work together in groups and
they're coming together to find an answer,
but they are sharing their different ways
of thinking, that gives them a really
important opportunity to work together.
And some think it's different in
humanities, they may be more different,
and coming up with different ideas, but
they're actually working to the same
conclusion.
But they're doing that by thinking and
getting contributions from different
students with different types of thinking.
And in my set, what I've found is that
process of getting different ideas and
different perspectives, and
finding one solution led to a particular
form of equity in classrooms that I
called relational equity, that was about
how students viewed each other's thoughts.
And those are, keep that in the references
if you want to read more about that.
So math is a subject that can and
should be represented visually at every
opportunity, and
I'm going to show you some more visual
representations in the next session.
It's a subject that's all about different
connections between ideas and
its those connections that mathematicians
and others regard as beautiful.
And if we want students to understand math
deeply and
to appreciate that beauty in maths and to
develop a strong foundation,
from which your mathematical thinking can
build, then we really need to encourage
a connected approach to the subject, and
it should all start with Number Sense.
So, I'm going to, introduce you to some
more ideas and
ways of thinking about this in the next
session.