So you probably got that the answer is
ninety, but
the answer is probably not the most
interesting part.
The most interesting part of Number Talks
is really thinking about how
you've arrived at the answer.
As of course number problems can be seen
in many different ways, and
it turns out that not only are students
fascinated by the different methods, but
they really learn a lot from thinking
about the methods.
About how and why they work.
So I'm going to, we're going to hear now
from some Stanford students who
were asked to solve this problem, and hear
the different methods they used.
>> That would be 90.
>> Okay and how did you get 90?
>> I well first I doubled 18, getting 36.
Then I doubled that, getting 72.
Then I added 18 again so.
>> Okay.
>> That was fun.
>> 90.
>> And how did you do that.
>> So I take 18 and I half that.
9 times 5, 45.
9 times 5, 40.
Five, add 'em together, ninety.
>> 18 times [LAUGH] five is 80.
>> How'd you get 80?
>> Five times 10 plus five times eight, no
90.
>> 90.
>> huh, and can you describe your method?
How you got to that?
>> I did 9 times 10 instead of 18 times 5,
because it's the same thing.
>> Well I'll do it out loud then.
18 times 5, okay.
Hopefully I don't get this wrong as I'm
doing it.
I do 20 times 5, so 2 times 5 is 10, add a
zero.
2 times 5 is, that'd be 100.
>> And then minus 2 times 5, again, so
that would be minus 10, that'd be 90.
I think, but I might have gotten wrong.
Okay, okay.
>> 18 times 5, okay, that's 90.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Yeah.
>> So how did you reach that?
>> Uh, [COUGH] honestly I tried doing like
you know the whole 18, and
then five under, and like eight times 5,
and then I realized that it's easier to
just do okay, well first of all you are
doing 8 times five which is 40.
And then if you do the one times five
which is actually ten times 5,
that's the 50.
And then you just add them together which
is the 90.
But those are little numbers.
[LAUGH] I wouldn't be able to do big
numbers.
>> That's 90 because 18 over 2 is 8 times
10.
I mean 9.
It's 18 over 2 is 9 times 10.
Which is 90.
>> 90.
>> Mm-hm.
So how did you reach it?
>> Well to do it quickly I separated into
ten and eight.
So five times 10 is easy that's 50.
And then five times eight is 40 and then I
just add them together.
>> I feel like I should be able to answer
18 times 5 pretty quickly, but I can't.
It takes a while [LAUGH].
I do know it's 90 I think.
>> I'd probably do it with the 18 on top,
and then the five on the bottom.
And then 5 times 8 and 5 times 1, and then
add it together.
It's probably a pretty slow way of doing
it.
>> So one thing that's nice about number
talks is the solutions,
the different methods that are used, can
be drawn in these different ways.
So, I'm going to draw out here the
different ways the students that we
just saw solved this problem.
So we can also visually represent the
students methods, and
I'm not going to do all of them but you
may want to visually represent them all.
It's a really good thing to do.
So I might represent Neil's method.
He didn't work out 18 times 5, he worked
out 9 times 5, and 9 times 5 in this way.
Whereas Casey divided her 18 into 9, and
multiplied the 5 by 2 to make it 10.
So she worked out 9 times 10, which I
might represent in this way.
Sammi broke the 18 into 10 and 8, and
multiplied it in that way.
Whereas Jamie made the 18 into a 20 and
then subtracted the extra 2 times 5,
which I would represent in that way.
And there were some other methods, maybe
you can visually represent those.
But providing that visual representation
is really important to
help students with number sense.
And you can also get them to visually
represent their own methods.
Or sometimes what I've done is we've
looked at all the different
representations and then I've said, well
what I like you to do now is you use, for
example, Casey's method to work out.
20 times 14 or whatever the question is,
or
after working on Casey's method see if you
can use Sammi's method.
So the visual representation of the
problems is really great.
So another nice thing to do with number
talks is after we have a representation of
the solutions what I've done with students
is to say.
Okay, now we have another problem which
might be 12 times 8 or something similar.
And to say what I'd like you to do is see
if you can use Zack's method to
use this problem.
We've also done work with giving students
visuals and
having them match the visual to the
method.
So I'm going to give you another problem
to do now.
So we can think about different solutions.
So this time I'd like you, again without
using the traditional algorithm and
without using pen and paper.
See if you can solve the problem 12 times
15 and
again I'd like you to show your method.
[MUSIC]