So how do we develop this inquiry
relationship?
There isn't time left in this session to
talk much about how to do that.
But the last two sessions of the course
will be devoted to that.
Sebastian, one of the most successful math
users of our time, argues strongly.
That he cannot move forward with any
mathematics without fully
understanding it, to the point he feels it
intuitively.
The mathematical thinking process is
really important in that.
And he argues that the students aren't
making sense of a math problem,
they should just stop and refuse to go on.
And that's probably how urgent it is and I
agree with him on that.
So I'm going to end with a British quote.
You'll see the Britishness about the
problems in math classrooms.
Again, coming from mathematicians, saying,
In the case of mathematics,
there is a persistent attempt to erase the
subjective and
affective in favor of mathematics.
That is a dry as dust, as exciting as a
telephone book,
as remote as the laws of infangthief of
15th century Scotland.
So let's start focusing together on this
inquiry relationship that students need.
And in the next session,
we're going to think about how to take
this relationship into algebra,
probably the most important place to take
it.
And in the final session,
I'll spend more time on how to build this
inquiry relationship.