Emily tells us that curiosity is what
separates an okay engineer from
a good engineer.
Sebastian tells us that his intuitive
approach to math has allowed him to
make these great discoveries and
breakthroughs he's made.
And it may be, it may well be whats needed
for
students as well to do well in the new
Common Core Assessments in the US.
But the problem is, the focus and
the policies and the testing in math's
education for
decades, have completely ignored that
relationship as though it doesn't exist.
And focused only on the knowledge that
should be crammed into student's heads.
And that process of cramming too much
knowledge,
has really stopped students developing
that critical relationship.
In some cases, it's killed the
relationship students entered school with
or entered the class with.
So what are the important pieces?
I want to unpack this inquiry relationship
a bit.
Intuition is really important and it's
been studied and
considered by mathematicians and
philosophers and others over centuries.
Leone Burton interviewed 70 research
mathematicians to find out how
they worked, and her main finding was the
huge role played by intuition.
And 83% of her mathematicians embraced
that and
talked about it's essential role in their
work.
But most students in math classrooms don't
think intuition is allowed or
appropriate when they work on math
problems.
It's [INAUDIBLE] intuition, I think,
is a little related to having a feel for
numbers.
And that ability to sort of feel where you
are in a problem is also rare or
absent in a lot of today's math learners.
Reuben Hersh wrote a great book called
what is mathematics really?
And in math, he says,
if we look at mathematical practice, the
intuitive is everywhere.
So intuition is one part of that
productive inquiry relationship we
hope that learners develop.
Sebastian talks about solving a problem
intuitively, then going back to work it
out mathematically and over a period of
two weeks.
But it was his intuitive insight that
allowed the researchers to move forward in
the problem they were having with robots
getting interfering data.
Let's think about something else.
Curiosity.
That's a really big idea.
It's something that's great.
Everybody knows how important it is.
Everyone knows it's valuable.
But how many of you, I wonder, as teachers
and
parents, see mathematical curiosity in
your students.
So I'm going to ask you a bit, a bit like,
a survey question now just to rate that.
So, how often are your children, students,
mathematically curious?
[MUSIC].