So, here's what I learned, from
interviewing the five people.
What became clear to me, from all the
interviews, and
I didn't show you, all the parts where
this came up.
Was the reason these people were highly
successful math users,
comes from two things.
It comes from knowledge and understanding
of maths.
But just as importantly it comes from a
relationship with that
maths knowledge that's different to a
relationship many people have.
And I'm going to call that an inquiry
relationship.
So whats in and inquiry relationship?
Both Michelle and Sebastian talked about
using intuition.
Sebastian was very strong and very
reflective about that which was helpful.
Saying he could never work on math without
intuition.
And he gave specific examples of using
intuition to solve problems in
his robotics work, which obviously led to
the design of this self-driving car.
Which you probably know about.
Sophie talks in these under the clips,
about having a feeling for math and
a connection to it.
That's important to her, in allowing her
to use it.
And Emily talked about curiosity.
Chris outlined the inquiry relationship
very well,
saying that those who have it display
courage.
Courage to think, if I interact with these
people and
I use resources, I can solve any problem.
And Chris talked about his work involving
new problems that no
one has ever solved be, before.
Today, we'll talk about an approach to
maths,
a relationship with mathematical knowledge
that comes into play whenever they
interact with maths in their lives and
jobs.
And what's significant to me is that
they're talking about math's use,
not in terms of knowledge they use.
But about this relationship they have with
the knowledge and understanding.
So we all know or have known people who
have this inquiry relationship with math.
Hopefully you have this relationship.
It's about being curious.
Making conjectures, not worrying about
uncertainty or mistakes.
It's about using intuition.
It's about approaching math as a world of
exciting inquiry.
And being confidently, you can solve any
problem.
That relationship is to do with maths
knowledge, it isn't unrelated but
it is something very different from
knowledge.
Lots of people have a lot of maths
knowledge without that relationship.
Some people, particularly young children,
have that relationship without any or
much maths knowledge.
And I strongly contend that an inquiry
relationship with maths is what is
needed to work successfully in today's
world.
So I'd like you to write down what kind of
relationship with maths would you
like your own students or children to
develop?
What features does it have?
What do they look like when they play out?
So write about that for me to read.
[MUSIC].