So, we're going to listen now,
to three of the boys in Nick's class that
I caught up with after the number talk.
So, the first question that I asked them
that you'll see them respond to,
is what they think of math?
So, if you can get past their cuteness, I
want you to think about and
discuss afterwards, what surprised you or
interested you in what they said?
>> So do you guys like math?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> What about you?
What's your favorite math thing to do?
>> I like the composing and adding.
>> Uh-huh, uh-huh.
What's, what are friendly numbers?
>> A tiny number.
>> [CROSSTALK] Ten to five.
>> A friendly number is like when you add
five.
Like for example, five times five plus
four plus seven.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Ten is a really friendly number.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So, you, and five plus five equals ten.
>> Right.
>> So you know, so you put the ten and
then you just add four plus 11.
>> I see.
>> Which equals 21.
>> Uh-huh, cool.
What do you think about the talking about
math part.
Do you think that helps you understand?
>> It does.
>> [INAUDIBLE] It's like, it does and
doesn't.
>> Uh-huh.
Tell me about why it does at first, or you
tell me.
Anyone.
>> It actually does, because you can see
what other people do, compared to yours.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> See how other people would do it.
[CROSSTALK].
>> And well you can see what other people
think and
then you can tell what you think.
>> Mm-hm.
>> There was also, sometimes we make
mistakes, but
everybody makes mistakes, so [INAUDIBLE].
>> That's right.
>> You'll be able to see where you made a
mistake too, if you made one.
>> And mistakes are great, because you can
learn from mistakes; we all make mistakes.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you feel okay if you're doing in
a math talk and you make a mistake?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, pretty much.
>> because if like they, they just like
help us out and then tell us Mm-hmm.
>> They help us with the answers.
>> That's right.
>> [CROSSTALK] have to do more math work.
[LAUGH].
>> So do you think math is subject where
you're always following rules or
is it a subject where you get to think
about ideas?
>> I think it's like you can think about
different things at one time to
make one thing work.
>> It's like it, it's you're free.
You can do whatever you want like breaking
down.
>> You can pause.
>> You can do what you want to get an
answer.
[CROSSTALK].
>> You can make [UNKNOWN] numbers,
you can, like, breaking down into
multiplications.
>> Uh-huh, so there's math talks, like,
you do all those things then?
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Did you use math in those ways before
with class, or
did you break it down and do all those
different things [CROSSTALK].
>> No.
>> Not at all.
>> So what did you, what did you, how is
it different?
>> Well it's like, Nick teaches us like
how to break it down,
like use multiplication problems.
So it's like easier to like make friendly
numbers.
Like decomposing and all that stuff.
>> Uh-huh.
So does that help you solve math problems
being able to break down the numbers and
make friendly numbers?
>> A lot.
>> Also it's different too at the same
time because you don't normally do
that until third grade, so.
>> Mm-hm, so do you think, now you've
learned to do that.
Do you think you can do that in other math
problems that you get even when you're not
in the math course?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, if Nick didn't teach us this we
would be like, what is this in the fourth
grade?
[MUSIC].