[MUSIC].
So you may think, if you're a high school
math teacher,
why go through that when you can use the
formula a plus b over a times b?
There is a very good reason for going
through that longer method, and
it's about thinking and making sense.
When we provide students with formulas
that they don't understand,
they're not useful to them.
If you're lucky they may use them in a
test but often they don't even do that.
You may have used another method that's
more conceptual or
a whole different approach.
So one thing that's missing from most
students' math lives and
that would help them enormously.
Is knowing about and engaging in what I
call the mathematical thinking process.
So, this is my proposed thinking process
for solving any math question.
So the first thing I do is I read the
question and
think about what it's telling me.
I just sit with it for a while.
I look at it, think about the numbers.
Students often don't do that as they think
they should instantly know a method or
formula to apply.
I make a lot of use of visuals.
They help me in virtually every problem I
solve.
So, my first strategy is usually to draw
the problem.
Other people I helped in this stage by
restating the problem, reading it aloud,
or writing it in another way.
So I''m going to call this stage the stay
think say draw stage.
Then there's a point where it's really
helpful to talk to other people to
discuss problems and possibly consult
resources.
Those actions are some of the most
important things to do in
any math problem.
Estimate is so useful to do at different
stages in a problem.
What sort of answer should we get at this
stage or in, in this part.
Where should I be.
And at some point, we mathematize.
That's the process when I bring out my
mathematical methods or tools.
And convert my thinking into something
more formally mathematical.
And that word comes from Freudenthal.
There's a process whereby you might try
something, realize it doesn't work,
refine it or revise it.
That process is an essential component of
designed thinking as taught by
Stanford's D school.
But it's also an essential part of
mathematical thinking.
And then super-importantly, does the
answer make sense?
You may need to stop and ask that at
various stages of a problem.
So these are the sort of shortened
headings of my mathematical thinking.
So I'm going to show you how those stages
came into play when we worked
through those solutions.
Because they're all short questions, you
don't see the try and refine and
revise stage.
But that's super important, especially
when dealing with bigger problems.
And in these solutions, I didn't consult
others,
even though that's a very important step.
You'll see as I go through these that the
stages are used in a different order.
There isn't one set order as different
problems draw on different parts.
So in solving the turkey problem, the
first thing we did was think about what we
had three slices weigh a third of a pound.
So I'm going to call that thinking stop
think process.
And it was really important to stop and
think about that because that thinking
about it led to what's a really important
realization that often people don't go to.
Which is that if three pieces a third of a
pound, then nine pieces is equals a pound.
And that is a mathematizing move.
From there a really important piece was to
draw it.
And I think at that point once we'd drawn
nine slices.
And then we made another mathematical move
of
another mathematizing move of dividing
them into quarters.
We then stopped right at the end and
thought about that does it make sense.
And I thought about that by thinking,
he was given three slices that weighed a
third but he was only allowed a quarter.
So it's going to be a little bit under
three slices which is where we
get our answer of 9/4 or 2 1/4.
So, those were the stages of the thinking
process that I used in that problem.
I really stopped and thought about it for
quite some time.
I drew, mathematized, mathematized again
and
stopped to think about it making sense.
So, in the Charmaine and
Tesha problem there's immediately a lot of
words in this problem.
Charmaine and Tesha have cards in the
ratio 2:3, Tesha and
Holly in the ratio of 2:1, Tesha has four
more cards.
This is the kind of problem that instantly
confuses people.
Students and
when I was solving this, the very first
thing I did was to draw the problem.
So I'm going to label that as my first
process.
And I drew out what I knew, which was that
if we use these blocks to represent
ratios, then the relationship between
these three people would look like that.
At that point so I knew Charmaine and
Tesha had cards in the ratio 2:3 and
Tesha and Holly in the ratio 2 :1.
At that point, we're given another piece
of information.
Tesha has four more cards than Charmaine.
How many cards to Holly have?
So, I'm going to call that a kind of
mathematizing move although all of this is
very mathematical.
Where we just think about the numbers
here.
So, if we know that Tesha has four more
cards than Charmaine, then Holly,
they may know that each of these blocks
represent two.
And that gives us an answer that Holly has
6.
I then thought about like Holly has 6 just
comes out of the blue.
Does that fit with the problem?
Does it work out?
And the best way to check it, or
to check that it makes sense is to go back
and put the numbers in for the others.
So we did that to find that Charmaine had
8 and Tesha had 12.
We knew they cards in the 2:3 so that
solution seems to make sense.
In this problem we know that Joe takes 3
hours to paint a house and
Sam takes 5 hours.
How long do they take if they paint it
together.
So, again the very first stage is to stop
and
think about the information that we have
there.
And, at this point I found it really
important to estimate.
And so, if Jo takes 3 hours, Sam takes 5
hours and
they go to do it together, it has to take
less than 3 hours.
And that's an important insight that I
gained from that estimation.
At that point, I drew and again I found it
very helpful to create a visual
representation of the houses and the
amount of time they spent on each one.
Then there's definitely some
mathematizing, putting the.
Working out the fraction of each house,
working out what that would be together
and turning that into one house.
And then I stopped at the end and thought
about whether that made sense.
We knew it was going to be less than 3
hours with both of them.
What we got to was 1 7/8 of an hour, so
that seemed to make sense.
So the process in this one was different
again.
Stop, think, estimate, draw, mathematize,
make sense.
But again many of those different
processes were going on in order to
get that solution.
So I didn't think many students are aware
of needing to go through these
mathematical thinking processes.
Especially when they have these short
fraction or algebra problems.
But if I was given any math question,
especially the verbally dense ones such as
the card question.
Then I need to engage in these processes
to be successful.
You may be gathering by now that I think
there should be a much larger part played
by visual representations in maths.
It helps everybody.
You may have kids who've been given the
idea that they're not a visual thinker.
That's a kind of misuse I think of Howard
Gardner's multiple intelligences.
But even if they come in with that idea
then.
They need to work in visual ways more than
anyone else.
Visual thinking and visual solutions, as
we saw with the number problems in
the last session, help us see mathematics
as conceptual and meaningful.
Here's my student KK again, talking about
the importance of visuals to him.
>> I think that I'm a, I'm a very visual
learner, so
when it comes to problem I guess words
problems in math.
I just couldn't comprehend them because
I'd be like,
I don't, I can't visualize this.
>> How easy would it have been to engage
students like KK if
maths were taught differently and more
visually.
One thing that's important making students
aware of these thinking processes is
they learn that working on math is a
process, it's always a process.
It's not about instantly coming up with a
method or a formula.
How many students go through this kind of
thinking process or any process.
Many of them think that they should
instantly be
able to solve a math problem or they're
doing it wrong.
So teaching students to engage in a
thinking process is really important.
So what I'd like you to do now is design a
way that you can think of of
making children, students aware of the
thinking process.
You, you can use my steps of the thinking
process or you can adapt those or
use your own.
But the question is how can you get
students to start using something
like that?
So this is a peer assessment question.
You're going to be given three different
people's answers to comment on and
yours will be sent out to comments on.
[MUSIC]