With all of these problems, there are
procedural ways to solve them,
where you plug in a procedure with little
thought, and
there are more productive, conceptual
ways.
That doesn't mean that using a procedure
is bad, or can't be conceptual.
As I said in the last class, most use of
procedures is conceptual.
And procedures are very important to
mathematics, when they're understood.
It's really all about how you think you
can use them,
as I'll show you in a minute.
So, the turkey problem is one that Ruth
Parker uses and
she's used it with parents a number of
times and,
when she gives it to them, most of them
try to make use of the numbers.
They try a quarter times a third, or a
quarter times three.
Often realizing those answers don't make
sense.
Some try, and usually fail, to remember
how to set up the algebraic formula.
But two fourth graders solved it in this
way.
One of them said, if three slices is a
third, then nine slices is one pound.
And she can have nine quarters of a pound.
Another solved it visually like this.
Another student also found out that there
were nine slices and
drew visually into quadrants to see those
two and a quarter slices.
So the card problem, I hate problems like
this, and I love maths, but
there's something about them that makes me
so linguistically, heavy going and so
removed from the world for me, but anyway,
here's a way to solve it.
See if this is what you did or similar.
So, the first thing we know is that
Charmaine and
Tesha each have a number of cards in the
ratio two to three.
So I'm going to draw up four spaces for
Charmaine and six for Tesha.
So that is in the ratio 2 to 3.
We don't know that they have four and
six cards because that's a ratio that
we're representing, not the numbers.
It could be that they have two and three,
four and six, 10 and 15.
We don't know at the moment.
We also know that Tesha and Holly have a
number of cards in the ratio 2 to 1.
So if my cards for Tesha look like this,
and the ratio is 2 to 1,
we're going to need half as many spaces in
our representation for Holly.
Then it says if Tesha has four more cards
than Charmaine,
how many cards does Holly have?
That sounds very confusing, so
I am going to use some of information I've
got that helps me.
We know that Tesha has four more cards
than Charmaine and
I can see form the diagram that two spaces
show those extra four cards for Tesha.
So I realize now that all the spaces I
drew have two cards in them we need to
know how many cards Holly has.
So Holly has three spaces, so I'm going to
say that Holly has six cards.
At this point, I would check that because
we know some things,
we know that Charmaine and Tesha have a
number of cards in the ratio 2 to 3, so
I can see that Charmaine now would have
two, four, six, eight, and
Tessa would have two, four, six, eight,
twelve.
So 8 to 12, is that in the ratio 2 to 3?
I think it is.
So what about the tough algebraic rate
problem, also a very unworldly problem and
the sort of problem that haunts students
for years.
We can really see the extent of the horror
around such problems,
by the way Hollywood uses them.
And in the movie Little Big League, a pre
teen boy is given the position of
managing the local baseball team when his
grandfather dies.
So he asks the team to solve the problem,
and it's kind of funny or
sad, I think, in the movie.
So first, what happens is there are just
lots of blank stares.
Then the first person comes up and says
it's simple 5 times 3, so it's 15 hours.
The next one says no it's eight hours,
it's 5 past 3.
Then another comes up and says there's two
of them so
it's 8 divided by 2 that's 4 hours.
One says why didn't they get a house
already painted?
Another says maybe it's a trick question
with no answer.
I don't know.
8 sounds good to me.
Then this very confident man strides up
and says fellows, stand aside.
It's a plus b over a times b.
And he draws that and says it's 8 over 15.
This movie, as in so
many others, gives us a very negative
image of mathematics and maths learners.
We see people working very unproductively,
just throwing out,
doing things with the numbers, putting
them together.
We see no mathematical reasoning at all.
So lots of procedural thinking.
And putting them two numbers together to
get anything which is sadly what a lot of
students will do.
Then we see, see somebody else provide a
formula as though by magic,
that others are mesmerized by with no idea
how it works.
So this is another way to solve the rate
problem.
So I'm told that Jo takes three hours to
paint a house and Sam takes five hours.
And the question is how long will it take
if they paint it together?
So I'm going to look and think about that
for a bit.
I don't wannna move straight on.
And the first thing I'm going to probably
think about is,
somebody takes three hours, somebody takes
five.
Together they've got to take less than
three hours.
What I know is Jo, this is Jo's house,
paints that house in three hours, so
we're assuming she paints the constant
rate,
we're going to say she paints a third of
the house in one hour.
Sam takes five hours so Sam takes can
paint a fifth of the house in one hour.
So already we know together in one hour,
they're going to paint that third and
that fifth of the house.
We put that together and that makes eight
fifteenths.
So what we know now, is that in one hour
they paint eight fifteenths of a house.
But I want them to paint a whole house.
So I'm going to multiply both sides by 15
over 8.
And that's going to tell me that one house
with the two of
them takes 15/8 of an hour or one and
seven eighths of an hour.
And does that makes sense?
I have to think about that and yup.
I did think it would take less than three
hours.
So that sounds about right, just under two