So in this first part of the class, we've
explored what it means to think and
problem solve conceptually.
For the second part, I want to work on
something just as important.
And that is,
I want to think about what it means to
build an inquiry relationship with maths.
[MUSIC].
So I'd like now to show you some
interviews with five people who use
mathematics, including some very high
level math users.
And in my view, they're saying something
really important that I
want us to think hard about and focus on
in this session.
Please give them your full attention,
maybe take a break between each one.
They're really interesting.
And after each one, you're going to be
prompted to write down the main ideas that
they're saying just in a few different
words.
You can make it into a concept map, or you
can just list it.
But what were the big ideas that they gave
you or
what were the big ideas that they talked
about and the smaller ideas, too.
>> Given, you know, how you think you use
math in your work, and
how lots of issues math.
I guess, if you were to help teachers
design courses that would be useful for
people when they're going into the
workplace, what,
what do you think would be important to,
what would be the emphasis?
>> I mean I believe that kids need to
master the basics.
But after that I think for me,
project-based or
practical examples are the best way to
learn and
reinforce material because that again,
that's how I learned the math that I use,
is by seeing patients and going through
real life examples.
>> Mm-hm.
>> For me, that's what I remember better
than if I'm sitting down and
trying to memorize something from, from a
page that I'm reading.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So I would be trying to incorporate
that more.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Did you have that much in your math,
teaching?
>> I mean.
It was,
you know it was abysmal [LAUGH] where I
went to school.
There was nothing progressive about it and
it was very traditional and [INAUDIBLE]
and dull.
>> You didn't enjoy it in school.
>> Mm-hm.
I liked calculus was the first time I
enjoyed math.
>> Interesting.
>> Well, calculus is more conceptual.
>> Um-hm.
It was the first time I didn't feel
terrible about my mathematical abilities.
I always felt, I always felt I was bad at
math.
When I was thinking about answering
questions about how I use math,
at first I was having trouble thinking of
examples outside of work.
>> But When I probe deeper I, I realized
the reason I was having trouble using
examples is because I'm using it but, not,
I don't consider it math.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And it's so interesting to me, so
an example is, a couple days ago I ordered
a desk for a, for, the study, and
I realized, you know, I was measuring the
space, you know, the height and
length and width.
And then I went online and I want, I had
to see which of the desk would fit or,
you know even loading the dishwasher,
you're using geometry.
Or, you so, I mean, it was kind of once it
clicked I realized it's everywhere.
And so I was explaining this to my
daughter during dinner and
she, you know she, it, I think she really
understood finally.
She and I said we're using math all the
time without realizing it.
It becomes intuitive.
>> Right.
>> We don't consider it math.
I think the reason we don't consider it
math is we view math as
something that's either hard or very
formal or structured.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Right.
So it's just a problem in our perception.
>> So if it's not hard or formal or
structured we're not saying it's math.
>> Yeah.
>> But the truth is we're using it
all the time.
Even you know estimating, you know like,
make, having my kids share things so
I'm dividing up portions all the time and
seeing, you know is this equal.
All kinds of ways.
You, you know, even things like, driving.
>> Yeah.
>> I think we all do this.
We're estimating how long is it going to
take us to get to the school and
I need to leave at this time.
>> Right.
>> Oh, but I have to stop and
pick this kid up, so my whole carpool
schedule and
all the things I do outside of my job that
are just with my kids or
household, there's so much math you don't
even realize it.
[MUSIC]
>> I'm a software engineer at Udacity.
Udacity's a education startup for online
kind of learning platform.
>> Mm-hm.
And, how about if
you just start by describing what you do
in your current job.
>> Sure.
So, I'm a software engineer.
I work with a team of people.
I mainly focus, at the moment on analytics
so we're analyzing the performance of
our course content and also the
performance of students.
And it's a problem that really never has
been solved before.
And so I work, you know day to day on,
something that I don't know how to solve.
And you know, then it's coming up with
different ideas and
testing things and we got a lot to learn
about, things like data science, and
a lot to learn about handling huge data
sets.
>> so, a lot of innovation that we're
trying to work through.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But you know an IMP,
you know you're presented with a problem
that you didn't know anything about, and
you worked together to find your own
vernacular that you could share with
each other.
And then, and
then that vernacular would be evolved to
be the one that's more commonly accepted.
But that was yours, it's not something
that people gave, you know gave to you.
You developed it.
You own it and call it whatever you want.
That concept exists outside of you.
You found it.
You put your claim on it, and to me that
matches more closely with what we have to
do in the rest of our life once we
graduate.
And you know that's what you'll do, you
know as a little family and
that's what you'll do as a, in, in a team
of, you know, software engineers.
A mechanical way, I guess, of going about
it just never sinks in.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And you know, which, because I never
honed that aspect of my mind, you know,
at least in terms of math, of just you
know, remembering,
you know these steps on how to, I can
always get back to where I need to go, but
sometimes I have to spend a little bit of
time building that.
And I, I wonder, I mean, so the people I
guess in my life around me that have more
traditional math they also don't remember
the mechanics unless they're familiar.
But the difference is that they don't
often have the courage to sit there, or
that, that self-confidence of given enough
time and enough resources, and maybe
a couple other people to help me, I'm
going to be able to solve this problem.
You know, and it's, there's that sense of
self confidence and, you
know you know there's, you know the talk
about fixed versus growth mindsets and
sometimes, you know there's a certain
amount of courage I
think it takes to have a growth mindset,
you know and just self confidence.
And and so it, it doesn't seem like, the,
the traditional math to me seems like it
really doesn't offer students the ability
to develop their own sense of courage and
so they, if they're lucky enough to have
it and
maintain it through that math experience,
awesome, great.
But there's a chance that if, even if they
started to maintain it or
if they didn't come into math with that
already.
There's a really good chance that they'll
either lose it or
never, never gain that aspect of.
Which, then, to me, that's a really
critical part of life.
[MUSIC].
>> Because I saw that, for myself, was
really, that.
Really, what made, made a big difference.
Both when I was younger, and when I was
out of school.
>> Uh-huh.
>> What, what could be the answer to that?
>> Yeah.
>> How could that be?
>> Right.
>> Why?
>> Yeah.
>> And the more that we ask those
questions I think and
let children answer them, the more
interested they'll be in that topic.
And I, I, I think that for me that made a
big difference.
That, there were people who were willing
to help me figure out why.
And that takes a long time.
>> Right.
>> So
to, to figure out why there are two
different kinds of clouds in the sky.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To figure out, you know I don't know,
why one duck is floating faster down the
river than the other one, and
to do a little experiment with it.
>> Takes, takes time.
>> Yeah.
>> Which not a lot of us have myself
included.
And to answer, to not be willing to
answer, answer it with,
good question, let's figure it out
sometime or.
>> Yeah.
>> Let's do that later.
[LAUGH] To be, to be willing to cut
yourself is, is tough and
I think especially for an educator.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Has a classroom of kids.
But if you have I, I see some of my
daughter, my daughter's friends,
there might be very few circumstances
under which some of the kids will ask why.
>> Yeah.
>> And if you have a kid that asks why all
the time,
I think you have a lot of chances.
But if you have a kid who doesn't.
>> The time that he does say, why is that?
>> Yeah.
>> Great.
[LAUGH] Let's answer that for you.
And you see it in the workplace,
you see those people who have a creative
curiosity.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And, and I, and, I have to believe that
it's been cultivated for them.
Some of us are more curious by nature,
sure.
That a, a lot of people have either let
themselves answer questions for
themselves or they've have people when
they were little help them answer.
That curiosity is what, what makes the
difference, I'm an engineer, makes
the difference between someone who's a
perfectly fine engineer and someone who's.
>> He's a great engineer.
[MUSIC]
>> You know, so math was sort of a slogs.
There was nothing fun about it.
There was nothing, you know yehey, math!
You know, this is something I can,
whereas, you know I was reading books,
you know gobbling them up as much as
possible, so
it was part of my school life and my
pleasure life.
But by the time, and I actually started
calculus when we
started to doing sort of pasts like the
algebra calculus.
I was like oh, this is actually kind of
fun.
Like I like the, the,
kind of conceptual, conceptualizing of
math, ideas not numbers.
because the numbers were like, can you do
you do your times tables in your head?
No.
But then we did geometry, and you think,
geometry, of course that's easy, right?
That's squares and circles, you know
spheres, but that, that was so
hard for me.
And I think I'm such a practical person.
I'm sort of a problem solver so
here I was, well I understand the circle
but it's a perfect thing.
And sort of circles aren't perfect.
And suddenly the, the, it took it to this
meta level and
I couldn't, I kind of put it in the real
world at all.
It was just, yeah.
>> So how does that make you feel?
>> Well, you feel terrible, right?
You feel sort of hopeless, and, and
especially when some people are getting it
and some people aren't, so there's no,
there's no parameter to say you know oh,
well that means I'm not so smart because I
don't understand geometry because that
other person seems to be doing fine.
And I think, I think, that, that sort of
breaking up of what you're good at and
what you're not good at suddenly makes the
world into sort of sequestered parts and
I think that plays with your self esteem
and, and you know you
walk down the street, you don't say well
I'm, I'm not good at walking so I'll skip.
Like you know it, it's, it's, you want to,
it the world is holistic.
Everything you do is connected so
when there's some thing, one thing that
you don't do well,
it makes you question whether, you know
you will do well with everything.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Well.
You know what I
think is really interesting in your class
when the, the math students.
They approach.
They were approaching math like we
approach humanities.
As,.
Not as a right or wrong answer.
Not as a.
There.
You know.
If you don't, if you don't follow these
steps,
you will not get to the pot of gold at the
end of the rainbow.
But that it, it's adaptable and changeable
and fluid, and
that your emotions can get involved and
you can feel it.
And I think, you know that, I think
there's something that we're taught about
numbers, that they're cold, you know,
they're, it's either right or it's wrong.
You either get it or you don't, and I
think that the difference of feeling,
you know, and we all have an intuitive
sense of numbers too.
I mean we all have an intuitive sense of
what time it is, or
how long something takes.
And you can develop those muscles to be
really good but to the minute or
to the number.
Or you can let that be loosy, goosy and
time will just disappear.
So I, I really sort of appreciated that
the, in human, we talked about the sort of
the sciences or the hard sciences and the
soft, you know, soft subjects.
And soft subjects are always given such a,
such a bad rap for being,
you know touchy, feely and not being about
accuracy or or true knowledge.
>> Mm-hm.
>> You know seeing,
seeing your class made me think of you
know numbers don't have to be hard and
impenetrable they're a part of they're,
they're one organic part of our lives.
So if you can have that sort of, if you
have feelings about math and
you could actually enjoy it.
[MUSIC]
>> Most of my, my math is extremely
intuitive.
>> I remember writing a paper actually
definitely [INAUDIBLE] for
Coursera on on a robotic formula which was
very complicated, mm hmm and I Intuitively
guess the formula correctly and implement
it and it worked beautifully.
And I spent the next like three or
four weeks trying to derive it
mathematically and
because I knew it was intuitively correct
and I couldn't quite understand why.
And eventually I got the math together, I
had to make certain assumptions that
were implicit in the duration that made
the formula correct.
I always felt math was just about the most
intuitive thing on the planet.
Its just explained very poorly, like well
all know, i don't know, how long one
hours are, two hours are, we don't know
something that takes two hours and
we wait for sixteen hours a day, what
things we can do.
And at that level of math, I think really
easy, and really everything from measure
theory, to integration, to like the most
abstract approximation fee and asymptotes.
I think that's similar nature, they're
very intuitive.
These are observations are key
observations I think.
And everybody is proficient at those.
Everybody knows how to play Sudoku.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And then the, the, the sad part is
when, when, when the abstraction comes
along putting this into formulas, people
often lose intuition.
They think, boy, these are like abstract
little things they have to
manipulate according to fixed rules.
And those fixed rule manipulations are
devoid of an,
of an intuitive interpretation.
And that's when we should just stop, we
should just not do it.
We should refuse to do it.
We should say, okay, I only am willing to
manipulate equations I understand.
I understand intuitively, and if it takes
us longer, that's fine.
I remember in my early scientific career,
I, I,
I stared at papers that from today's
perspective look easy, and I want to
spend two weeks thinking about what math
formula to unders, internalize it.
And after two weeks, I would get it
eventually and understand it, and
then these two weeks made this piece of
complicated math We the intuitive have
never been able to make any progress in
math without really understanding and
having an emotional relationship to what's
happening.
[MUSIC] [MUSIC]. Now, you've watched all
five of the interviews.
I'd like you to choose one of them.
And write about a really cool, either a
lesson idea, perhaps.
Or a discussion topic, if you're a parent.
That the math person's words and ideas
make you think about.
One of them, at least, I'm sure, inspired
you to do something really interesting in
a class or in a conversation.
And I want to give you a space to write
about that now.
So write a paragraph, perhaps, about that.
It's going to be sent to three other
people, and
you'll get others' people's to comment on.
[MUSIC]