So in this first part of the class, we've
explored what it means to think and
problem-solve conceptually.
For the second part, I want to work on
something just as important.
And that is, I want to think about what it
means to
build an inquiry relationship with maths.
[MUSIC]
So I'd like now to show you some
interviews with five people who use
mathematics, including some very high
level math users.
And in my view, they are suing something
really important that I want us to
think hard about and focus on in this
session.
So, I'm going to ask you to listen to five
people.
Each person is a little over four minutes
long, so that's 20 minutes of your time.
Please give them your full attention,
maybe take a break between each one,
they're really interesting.
And after each one you're going to be
prompted to write down the main ideas that
they're saying, just in a few different
words.
You can make it into a concept map or you
can just list it.
>> But what were the big ideas that they
Gave your,
what were the big ideas they talked about,
and the smaller ideas too?
>> Given how you use math in your work and
how lots of us use math, if you were to
help teachers design courses that would be
really useful for people going into
the workplace, what, what do you think
would be important to them?
>> Be the emphasis?
>> I mean I believe that kids need to
master the basics, but
after that, I think, for me, project based
or,
practical examples are the best way to
learn, and reinforce material.
Because that again, that's how I learn the
math that I use, is by seeing patients and
going through
>> Real life examples.
For me, that's what I remember better than
if I'm sitting down and
trying to memorize something from, from a
page that I'm reading.
So I would be trying to incorporate that
more.
>> Did you hear that much in your math
teaching?
>> I mean it was It, you know, it was
abysmal.
[LAUGH] Where I went to school.
There was nothing progressive about it and
it was very traditional [UNKNOWN] and
dull.
>> You didn't enjoy it?
>> Calculus was the first time I enjoyed
math.
>> Interesting.
>> Well calculus is more conceptual.
>> Mhm.
It was the first time I didn't feel
terrible about my mathematical abilities.
I always felt like I was bad at math.
>> When I was thinking about answering
questions about how I use math,
at first I was having trouble thinking of
examples outside of work, but
When I probed deeper, I, I realized the
reason I was having trouble using
examples is because I'm using it, but not,
I don't consider it math.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And it's so interesting to me so
an example is a couple of days ago I
ordered a desk for for the study.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And
I realized you know I was measuring the
space,
you know the height
>> Uh-huh.
>> and length and width and then I went
online and
I want-, I had to see which of the desk
would fit or even loading the dishwasher.
You're using geometry.
Once it clicked, I realized I use it
everywhere.
I was explaining this to my daughter
during dinner and
I think she really understood finally.
I said we're using math all the time
without realizing it.
It becomes intuitive.
We don't consider it math.
I think the reason we don't consider it
math is we view math as
something that's either hard or very
formal or structured.
So it's just a problem in our perception.
If it's not hard or formal or structured,
we're not saying it's math, but
the truth is we're using it all the time.
Even estimating you know like make having
my kids share things,
dividing up portions all the time and
seeing you know is this equal.
All kinds of ways you know even things
like driving.
>> Yeah exactly.
>> I think we all do
this we're estimating how long
>> Yeah.
>> Is it going to take us to get to the
school and I need to leave at this time.
>> Right.
>> Oh but I have to stop and
pick this kid up so.
My whole car pool schedule and
all the things I do outside of my job that
are just with my kids or
household, there's so much Matthew don't
even realize it.
>> I'm a software engineer at Udacity.
Udacity's a education start-up.
>> For online kind of learning platform.
>> Uh-huh, and
how about you just start by describing
what you're doing in your current job.
>> Sure.
So, I'm a software engineer.
I work with a team of people I, I mainly
focus at the moment on analytics.
So, we're analyzing the performance of our
course content and also the performance of
the students, and its a problem that has
never been solved before.
That's why I work, pretty, day to day on
something that I don't know how to solve,
and it's coming up with different ideas
and eating things and we have a lot to
learn about things like data science and a
lot to learn about handling huge data sets
so a lot of innovation that we're trying
to work through.
Actually I don't really know how it
happened and
I think it was kind of an anomaly, but I
managed to spend my seventh, eighth,
ninth and tenth grades of middle school
and first half of high school in
a math program called the Interactive Math
Program,
which was developed by a guy here I think
in the Bay area.
>> That and it was inquiry based math
which I didn't know anything about at
the time.
We talked back then a lot about deep
learning and
shallow learning, and it was pretty
controversial.
And a lot of you know parents,
yanked their kids out of the program
because it was so weird.
I loved it, and it was just based on
problems.
You know, problems of the day and
problems of the week that all, you know,
culminated into a problem of the unit.
And they presented, you know, these
problems, you know, like that we have to,
you know, try and solve and we had no idea
how to solve them and two months later all
of a sudden out of nowhere we had all the
tool we needed to solve them.
And that turns out to be exactly what I do
from day to day.
>> Mm-hm.
>> I would choose learning the skills and
having the courage to just sit down and
figure out how to solve something.
And then, after that, learning the
vernacular, that is incorporated you know,
into that you know.
That as, I was pretty lucky I think to
have that guidance early on and
that certainly set you know built a
framework for
which I pretty much accomplish things in
life.
>> Mm-hm.
>> Oh, a mechanical way I guess of going
about it just never sinks in.
And you know which because I never honed
in that aspect of my mind.
You know at least in terms of math of just
remembering, you know,
these steps on how to, I can always get
back to where I need to go but
sometimes I have to spend a little bit of
time building that, and I wonder,
I mean so the people I guess in my life
around me that have more traditional math.
They also don't remember the mechanics
unless they're familiar.
The difference is that they don't often
have the courage to sit there or
the self confidence of given enough time
and enough resources and maybe
a couple other people to help me, I'm
going to be able to solve this problem.
>> You know.
And, and it's, there's that sense of self
confidence and you know, you know,
there's, you know, the talk about you
know, fixed versus growth mindsets.
And, and sometimes you know, there's a
certain amount of courage I
think it takes to have a growth mindset,
you know, and it's just self confidence.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And so, and
it doesn't seem like, the traditional math
to me, seems like it
really doesn't offer students the ability
to develop their own sense of courage.
And so if they're lucky enough to have it
and
maintain it through that math experience,
awesome, great.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But there's a chance that if even if
they started to maintain it or if they
didn't come into math with it already,
there's a really good chance that they'll
either lose it or never,
never gain that aspect of, which then to
me that's really critical part of life.
>> Because I saw that for myself was
really that really what made,
made a big difference both when I was
younger And when I was out of school.
What, what could be the answer to that?
>> Yeah.
>> How could that be?
Why?
And the more that we ask those questions I
think and let children answer them, the
more interested they'll be in
that topic and I, I think That for me that
made a big difference that s,
there were people who were willing to help
me figure out why.
And that takes a long time.
>> Right.
>> So to, to figure out why there are two
different kinds of clouds in the sky
>> Mm-hm.
>> To figure out you know, I don't know,
why one duck is floating faster down
the river than the other one and to do a
little experiment with it takes time,
which not a lot of us have, myself
included.
And to not be willing to answer it with,
good question, let's figure it out
sometime or let's do that later.
To be willing to catch yourself is tough
and
>> Especially for an educator or
who has a classroom of kids, but if you
have a,
I see some of my, my daughter, my
daughter's friends,
there might be very few circumstances
under which some of the kids will ask why.
>> Yeah.
>> And if you have a kid that asks why all
the time I
think you have a lot of chances, but if
you have a kid who doesn't...
>> The time that he does say.
Why is that?
>> Yeah.
>> Great!
[LAUGH] Let's answer that for you.
And you see it in the work place,
you see those people who have a creative
curiosity.
And, and I, and I have to believe that
it's been cultivated for them.
>> Yeah.
>> Some of us are more curious by nature,
sure but a, a lot of people have either
let themselves answer questions
for themselves.
>> Mm-hm.
Mm-hm.
>> Or they've had people when they were
little help them answer.
>> Yeah.
>> And that, that curiosity is what,
what makes the difference, I'm an
engineer, makes the difference between
someone who's a perfectly fine engineer,
and someone who's is a great engineer.
I wonder how that works.
Could I make that better?
Why did that work that way?
And oh that's strange, I haven't seen that
before.
There are people who just don't ask those
questions, and the more we
can encourage it, they're going to be
better at their jobs later I'm sure.
>> Yeah, wouldn't it be great for
all sorts of people with a thousand
questions over time.
You know, so math was sort of a slog.
There was nothing fun about it.
There was nothing like, yay math.
This is something I can, you know, whereas
I was reading books,
gobbling them up as much as possible, so
it was part of my school life and
my pleasure life But by the time, and I
actually,
I started the calculus when we started to
doing past, like, the algebra, calculus.
And I was like oh, this is actually
kind of fun like, I like the, kind of,
conceptual, conceptualizing of, of math
ideas, not numbers,
because the numbers were like, can you do
the times tables in your head?
No.
But then we did geometry and
you think geometry that's of course that's
easy right that's squares and circles and
you know spheres.
But that, that was so hard for me and I
think I,
I'm such a practical person I'm sort of a
problem solver so.
Here I was where I understand the circle
but's a perfect thing.
Circles are perfect suddenly the it took
it to this meta level and
I couldn't, I couldn't put it in the real
world at all.
It was just
>> So how does that make you feel?
>> Well you feel terrible, right?
You feel sort of hopeless an and
especially when some people are getting it
and some people aren't.
So there's no There's no barometer to say
you know,
oh well that means I'm not so smart.
Cause I don't understand geometry.
Because that other person seems to be
doing fine.
And I think, I think that, that sort of
breaking up of what you're good at and
not good at suddenly makes the world into
sort of sequestered parts.
And I think that plays with your
self-esteem and you know, you
walk down the street and you don't say,
well I'm not good at walking so I'll skip.
You know, the world is holistic.
Everything you do is connected, so when
there's one thing you don't do well,
it makes you question whether, you know
you will do well with everything.
Well you know what I think is really
interesting in your class,
when the math students, they approached,
they were approaching math like we
approach humanities, not as a right or
wrong answer, not as a there, you know,
if you don't, if you don't follow these
steps you won't get to the,
you know, pot of gold at the end of the
rainbow.
But that it, it's adaptable and changeable
and fluid, and
that, that your emotions can get involved,
and you can, you can feel it.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And I think, you know that,
I think there's something that we're
taught about numbers, that they're cold,
you know they're, they're, it's either
right or it's wrong.
You either get it or you don't.
And I think that, the difference of
feeling you know,
we have, we all have an intuitive sense of
numbers too.
I mean we all have an intuitive sense of
what time it is or
how long something takes or you know and,
and you can, you can develop those
muscles to be really good, but to the
minute or you know to the number.
Or you can let that be very loose and
dizzy, and time will just disappear.
So I, I really thought I appreciated the
you know in,
sort, we talk about the sort of sciences
and the hard sciences and the soft.
>> You know, the soft subjects and soft
subjects, they're always given in
such a bad rap for being, you know Touchy
feely and not being about accuracy or or
true knowledge
>> Mm-hm.
>> And seeing, seeing your class made me
think of you know,
numbers don't have to be hard and
impenetrable, they're a part of they're,
they're an organic part of our lives.
>> So if you can have that sort of To have
feelings about math and
you could actually enjoy it.
>> Yeah, but
>> Most of my,
my math is extremely intuitive.
I remember writing a paper actually
[UNKNOWN] from Coursera on
a robotic formula which was very
complicated.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And I intuitively.
Guess the formula correctly, and implement
it, and they work beautifully.
And I spend the next four or five weeks
trying to derive it mathematically because
I knew it was intuitively correct, but I
couldn't understand why.
Eventually I got the math together.
I had to make certain assumptions that
weren't implicit in the derivation to
make the formula correct.
I always felt math is just about the most
intuitive thing on the planet.
Is just explained very poorly, like we all
know, I don't know, how long an hour is,
how long two hours are, we don't know if
you run into something that takes two
hours and we wake for 16 hours a day and
how many of those things we can do.
And at that level of math math is, I
think, really easy, and
almost everything, from really complex
measure theory to integration, to like
the most abstract approximation theory and
asymptote I think are similar in nature.
They are very intuitive.
These little observations are the key
observations, I think, and
everybody is proficient in those.
Everybody knows how to play Sudoku.
The sad part is when, when the abstraction
comes along putting these into formulas,
people often lose intuition.
They think but these are like abstract
little things they have to
manipulate according to fixed rules.
And those fixed rule manipulations are
devoid of an,
of an intuitive interpretation.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And that's when we should say, stop.
We should just not do it.
We should refuse to do it.
>> Mm-hmm.
>> We should just say,
okay I only am willing to manipulate
equations I understand.
I understand intuitively and if it takes
us longer that's fine.
I remember in my early scientific career
I,
I stared at papers that, from today's
perspective, look measly and
I would spend two weeks on one math
formula to internalizde it.
And after two weeks I would get it,
eventually, and understand it.
And then these two weeks made this piece
of complicated math really intuitive.
I've never been able to make any progress
in math without really understanding and
having an emotional relationship to what's
happening.
Now you've watched all five of the
interviews, I'd like you to choose one of
them and write about a really cool either
a lesson idea perhaps, or
a discussion topic if you're a parent,
that the math person's words and
ideas make you think about.
One of them at least, I'm sure inspired
you to do something really interesting in
a class or in a conversation And I want to
give you space to write about that now.
So, write a paragraph, perhaps about that.
Its going to be sent to three other people
and
you'll get other people to comment on.
[MUSIC]