[MUSIC].
Welcome to class six.
I'm excited to be continuing the theme of
the last session of what it means to
think and learn conceptually.
And just as importantly,
what it means to develop a positive
relationship with maths.
So, first of all, I'm going to give you
three problems to solve,
very typical math classroom problems.
This is not any sort of test.
It's, we don't need to know what you can
do on these.
But the reason for doing them is because
we're going to explore what's in
these problems, and how to think
conceptually about them.
And if you haven't tried them, it's hard
to do that.
So, don't feel intimidated if you don't
know how to solve them.
Just have a go,
remembering that mistakes
and struggle makes
your brains grow.
[MUSIC].