[MUSIC].
So you may think, if you're a high-school
math teacher,
why go through that when you can use the
formula A plus B over A times B.
Thee is a very good reason for going
through that longer method, and
it's about thinking and making sense.
When we provide students with formulas
that they don't understand,
they're not useful to them.
If you're lucky, they may use them in a
test, but often, they don't even do that.
You may have used another method that's
more conceptual or
a whole different approach.
So one thing that's missing from most
students' math lives and
that would help them enormously is knowing
about and
engaging in what I call the mathematical
thinking process.
So this is my proposed thinking process
for solving any math question.
So the first thing I do is I read a
question and
think about what it's telling me.
I just sit with it for a while.
I look at it, think about the numbers.
Students often don't do that as they think
they should instantly know a method or
a formula to apply.
I make a lot of use of visuals, they help
me in virtually every problem I solve.
So my first strategy is usually to draw
the problem.
Other people are helped in this stage by
restating the problem, reading it aloud or
writing it in another way.
So I'm going to call this stage the
stay-think-say-draw stage.
Then there's a point that's really helpful
to talk to other people,
to discuss problems and possibly consult
resources.
Those actions are some of the most
important things to do in
any math problem.
Estimate is so useful to do at different
stages in a problem.
What sort of answer should we get at this
stage or at this part?
Where should I be?
And at some point we mathematize.
That's the process when I bring out my
mathematical methods or
tools, and convert my thinking into
something more formally mathematical.
And that word comes from Freud and Tao.
There's a process whereby you might try
something, realize it doesn't work,
refine it, or revise it.
That process is an essential component of
design thinking, as taught by
Stanford's D School, but it's also an
essential part of mathematical thinking.
And then, super-importantly, does the
answer make sense?
You may need to stop and ask that at
various stages in a problem.
So these are the sort of shortened
headings Of my mathematical thinking.
So I'm going to show you how those stages
came into play when we worked
through those solutions.
Because they're all short questions,
you don't see the
try-and-refine-and-revise stage.
But that's super-important, especially
when dealing with bigger problems, and in
these solutions I didn't consult others,
even though that's a very important step.
You'll see as I go through these that the
stages are used in a different order,
there isn't one set order as different
problems draw on different parts.
So I don't think many students are aware
of needing to go through these
mathematical thinking processes,
especially when they have these short
fraction or algebra problems.
But if I was given any math question,
especially the verbally dense ones such as
the card question, then I need to engage
in these processes to be successful.
You may be gathering by now that I think
there should be a much larger part played
by visual representations in maths.
It helps everybody.
You may have kids who've been given the
idea that they're not a visual thinker.
That's a kind of misuse I think, of Howard
Gardner's Multiple Intelligences.
But even if they come in with that idea
then,
they need to work in visual ways more than
anyone else.
Visual thinking and visual solutions, as
we saw with the number problems in
the last session, help us see mathematics
as conceptual and meaningful.
Here's my student K.K again, talking about
the importance of visuals to him.
>> I think that I'm a very visual learner
so when it comes to problem I guess word
problems in math, I just couldn't
comprehend them.
because I'd be like, I don't, I can't
visualize this.
>> How easy would it have been to engage
students like KK,
if maths were taught differently and more
visually.
One thing that's important about making
students aware of
these thinking processes is, they learn
that working on maths is a process.
It's always a process.
It's not about instantly coming up with a
method or a formula.
How many students go through this kind of
thinking process, or any process?
Many of them think that they should
instantly be
out to solve a maths problem or they're
doing it wrong.
So teaching students to engage in a
thinking process is really important.
So what I'd like you to do now is design a
way, that you can think of,
of making children, students aware of the
thinking process.
You, you can you my steps of the thinking
process or you can adapt those, or
use your own, but.
The question is,
how could you get students to start using
something like that?
So this is a peer assessment question,
you're going to be given three different
com, people's answers to comment on, and
yours will be sent out to get comments on.
[MUSIC]