So there are many different ways of
solving that problem and
I'm gong to show you some here.
Maybe you used one of them, maybe you used
a whole different one.
But as you can see form these different
problems, different solutions,
when we show these to students.
And it's very important for
the teacher to do the representing in a
number talk to make.
The Mathematics that's a very, very clear
for students.
But what you can do is use number talks to
help with algebraic thinking.
And you can see how these properties such
as the Associative and
Distributive properties illustrated and we
can help students with those.
So here are five of the different methods.
And the first one that you can see, broken
up into 15 times 10, 15 times two,
makes use of the distributive property,
and I've made a drawing for that one.
And then we have two methods that make use
of a doubling and halving strategy.
Slightly different methods with very
similar visuals.
So it can be important to separate
different methods,
even if they look the same.
Because we want to capture different ways
of thinking.
And then a couple more that, again, use
the distributive property.
I didn't draw this one where we break up
the 15 into ten and five.
And this one, we break up the 12 into, 15
into 12 and 3, sorry.
Again uses the distributive property and
this is where number talks can be
really helpful, in the beginnings stages
of algebra, in having kids.
Break up the numbers, see a visual and
understand both how that's represented
correctly In mathematical notation and to
think about the distributive property.
So I'm going to show you three,
couple more now that use the associative
property.
So these two methods use the associative
And again it's really useful to see the
numbers written out
with the correct representations.
Also really nice to see these officially,
and I was going to draw those for you.
I found it interesting thinking about
those, and
then I thought I would leave them undrawn.
So that you can think about how those
would be drawn as a kind of
interesting problem to work on I promise.
So see if you can think about how those
might be drawn visually.
It can also be nice with these kind of
mathematical thinking to
represent the solutions with multi link
cubes.
But those, another two solutions there are
many more.
But these nicely illustrate the assosiatve
property.
So number talks can be done by teachers in
the whole class, as we're going to see.
Or parents can also do mini number talks
with their children just by
asking them the number problems.
And then challenging them to find a
different solution,
to work with the problem in a different
method.
Having kids solve problems in different
ways, teaches them a very,
very important building block in number
sense and mathematics.
They, it is teaching them a an ability and
willingness to break numbers apart, or
decompose them and regroup them.
This turns out to be a very important
foundational base,
from which all other mathematics builds.
As Sebastian talked about.
They also teach students something, very
important, which is math is a creative and
flexible subject, and this is, so
important.
An English mathematician,
Walter Sawyer ,who wrote the book A
Mathematician's Delight Once wrote, this.
He said, the depressing thing about
arithmetic badly taught,
is that it destroys a child's intellect,
and to some extent, his integrity.
Before they're taught arithmetic,
children will not give their assent to
utter nonsense, afterwards, they will.
And we certainly have a lot of evidence of
that.
We need children to understand numbers not
to blindly remember methods that they use.
But to really understand why they work and
how the methods may be used.
And number talks work really well at
different levels.
I think they're great to use in mixed
groups of students.
I've given that problem, eight times 15,
that exact same problem,
to elementary students, to Stanford
undergrads, to CEOs of companies.
And people have engaged with it with equal
interest and excitement, and
really loved seeing the different methods
and thinking about them.
Luke Bartlett, is the executive director
of Wolfram Alpha,
a site you probably know and love if you
are a math teacher.
And he read my book and wrote to me
saying,
you have no idea how many times I have now
asked people to calculate 18 times 5.
So it turns out people are really
interested in seeing all the different
ways in which people are able to think
about these number problems.
And as I said, I've used them in different
settings and
found people to be super engaged.
And really, you just see their eyes light
up when a problem is solved in lots of
different ways as, as people come to
understand the creativity in numbers and
in maths.
I taught algebra to a group of pretty,
disaffected, seventh and
eight graders in the U.S., a short while
ago.
And I'm going to talk about it more in the
algebra session.
But we started every session with the
Numbers Talk and
they absolutely blew students' minds.
They had never before seen problems,
particularly bare number problems solved
in all of these different ways.
And it really changed their view of maths
and what's possible.
And when we interviewed students at the
end of the program,
it was really the number talks that had
amazed them the most.
And it led to the students saying things
like this.
One of the students we interviewed said,
it's like the way,
the way our schools did it.
It's like very black and white.
And the way people do it here, it's like
very colorful, very bright.
You have very different varieties you're
looking at.
You can look at it one way, turn your
head, and
all of a sudden you see a whole different
picture.
So it really helps give them a much more
authentic view of mathematics.
And they're great to use in heterogeneous
groups which,
of course, all groups of students are
heterogeneous.
Because what we'll find is that some
people are helped just by
seeing the method and how to solve the
problem.
Where students who are at a higher level
are really benefit from
seeing the different solution parts.
Sometimes students are,
who work at a high level, only have one
way of thinking about maths.
Number talks are also the only very quick
pedagocial practice that I
know of,that teaches number fluency, and
ultimaticity.
At the same time as a conceptual
understanding of number.
And you may think that they're not needed
with more advanced classes,
such as high school classes.
clu, students taking geometry and algebra,
but at Stanford, what we've found is
that the high school students who are
given number talks are the worst.
The same exact problems given to younger
children,
they are the least able to use number
sense.
And they really struggle with even the
most basic number problems.
Cathy Humphrey has conducted a study in
the past year with geometry classes in
high school,regular, on track students,
not behind in any way.
When the students were given number
problems, they really struggled.
They could, they tried to use procedures
that they'd learned.
They were saying things like, oh I have to
carry the one or
cross out the three writing with their
fingers in the air.
But they were really unable to use
numbers,
since they were unable at first to use
numbers flexibily.
To break them apart and recombine them to
make them easier.
Gradually, over weeks, they began to make
sense of multipli, multiplication.
They began to use number sense.
But when their teachers gave them percent
problems to work on,
they fell straight back into procedural
thinking and abandoned their sense making.
So when they were asked to work out 25% of
200 They gave a range of answers.
And I want you to think about now,
what answers do you think students would
give to 25% of 200?
That'll help us think about this problem.
[MUSIC].