So, the answers given and see, you
probably found got some of these, but
you may be surprised by others.
Were $200, $50, $75, $125, $150, and $175.
I, so that seems pretty shocking really.
And when they were asked to work out 10%
of $200, the students mainly could find
that answer, but they only knew to move a
decimal point.
They couldn't make sense of it, or explain
it in any other way.
And generally, what Cathy found was that
the students didn't have any sense of
what percent means.
And we had no idea why the procedures that
they were using worked.
And Cathy found that student that were on
track to be successful math students,
they weren't low achievers.
So, what she found in particular,
is that students did not look at the
relationship between quantities.
And they saw every problem that was given
as discrete and separate.
It was very rare for
a student to ever refer back to a previous
problem, when considering a new problem.
Even when it was completely related, and
they could have built from one answer onto
the next.
So, it was really important that those
high school students had
this experience of number talks,
because it really would have helped them
in their high school and beyond.
I wrote about number talks in my book
What's Math Got to Do With It, or
The Elephant in the Classroom.
And even reading about the different ways
numbers can be solved opened the eyes of
people reading about them in the ways they
thought about math.
So, some people like the seventh and
eighth-graders I taught,
had thought it was kind of against the
rules to change the numbers,
to break numbers apart and put them back
differently.
And so here, I'm going to show you a
little bit of Sophie again.
Sophie is the film maker that we met in
the first class.
And this is just a short extract from the
interview with her
talking about what happened when she read
about number, number problems.
>> I had one of those aha moments reading
your book,
where you were talking about, you know,
that, that you can move,
move parts of a number around, like the
numbers aren't fixed.
And I mean, obviously, if you have an
equation, but
you know, this is made up of how many 10s
and this is made up of how many 5s, and
the, that you can, you can share parts of
the numbers.
And I think I've always known that deep in
my subconscious.
But I always thought it was breaking the
rules.
>> Yeah.
>> You're not allowed, to break a number,
you know, like, a numbers a number.
Like you're supposed to do the, you know
it,
a number is the one your supposed to be
multiplying.
>> You can't make it into some other
number Yeah.
>> Even if you're just slipping those
numbers around.
So I always felt like I was cheating.
You know, having that articulated, which
was something that I had known, but I had,
nobody had allowed me the freedom to say,
you are totally allowed.
>> Yeah.
>> To mess with these numbers as much as
you want, until you can, you can do it,
you know, if multiplying by ten is the way
it works for you, do it.
>> So, I'm hopeful that the student
version of this class.
Where students were going to be given
various number problems to do.
Will be a really generative class for
them.
Because in the student version, I'm
going to be able to use more visuals and
animations that I didn't have time to do
for this class.
But I hope to really expand their thinking
about math by giving them lots of
opportunities to engage in number sense.
So, there'll be different problems to
choose for
different grade levels, all the way up to
adults.
And I really hope that this number sense
section of the student class will
present students with the opportunity to
learn to see and use numbers flexibly in
ways that will be enjoyable no matter, you
know, what experience they came in with.
So, your task now is to watch two pretty
different videos,
a number talks and action.
One's taught by a third-grade teacher,
Nick Foote in Barron Park School in Palo
Alto, and
one is taught by Cathy to our elementary
teacher candidates in Stanford.
So, a really nice way to start number
talks is to dot cards.
And these look really simple, they work
great in elementary classrooms.
But again, they can be really interesting
for learners of all levels including
adults, and you're going to see them now
with Stanford graduates.
>> Okay, here
it is.
Okay, so I'm seeing everybody's done.
Would anybody like to say how many they
think there are?
Okay, Stefanie?
>> Ten?
>> Ten.
Does anyone have, sorry, does anyone have
a different idea of what,
how many there are?
>> Okay, so let's share how we saw them.
Who's willing to share how, what they saw?
Okay, Geraldine what'd you see?
>> So, I saw three at the top and
then the two at the, on the bottom of
those preceding 3, as 5.
>> Okay.
>> And then I saw the, the remaining
three, and the other two on the bottom.
>> Okay.
>> The 5 and 5.
>> And did you kind of, you clumped these
as 5 and 5?
>> I clumped the top Okay.
>> Five, and then I clumped the bottom.
>> Okay [CROSSTALK], so this was five for
you?
>> Mm-hmm.
>> And this was five for you?
>> Yeah.
>> So 5 plus 5?
>> Who did it like Geraldine did?
Wow.
Alright, who did it a different way then,
who saw it a different way?
Yeah, okay, so could you pass the
microphone to Joe, please?
>> I saw it like people read left to
right, top to bottom.
So, I saw the top line of three, and then
I added the next line of two to make five,
and then I added the next line three to
make eight, and
then the next line of two to make ten.
>> So, I'm hearing that you went from left
to right on each one,
adding sequentially as you went?
>> Yes, line by line.
>> 3, 2, and so your number sentence would
be 3 plus 2 plus 3 plus 2?
>> Absolutely.
>> Okay, anyone do it exactly like Joe
did?
Wow, okay who would like to share their
method of scene it?
Okay, so let's hear while you're on and
take it close.
All right, so I saw the two lines of
three, going across a line of three, and
then two lines down and another line of
three.
And then I saw a square with the remaining
4.
>> Did you hear those little, you know
[NOISE].
Okay, Elana?
So, what I heard you say is that you first
saw the two rows of three, so
three here and three here, and then you
saw a square.
Where's the square?
>> So the two in the middle, they're like
the second line down and
the two on the bottom.
>> These two?
>> Make a square.
>> And these two make a square, so you saw
a square as something like.
>> Like an overlapping square.
>> An overlapping square.
Alright, and when you did the arithmetic,
what did you do first?
>> So 3 and 3 is 6, and then I can just
see the 4.
Okay, who saw this a different way?
There are so many ways.
>> So I counted by two's I saw them in
vertical lines of two.
So, in sort of a zig zag starting from the
left,
I saw that there were two top and bottom.
>> So you're talking about these two?
>> The very far left two, yup.
>> Okay.
>> And then going immediately to
the right of that.
It went down and there were two more.
>> Okay.
>> And then up to two down and up.
So, two, two, two, two, two.
>> Yup, exactly.
>> Okay, so two, two, two, two, two.
How did you do the, figure out how many
dots there were?
>> I was counting in my head as I looked
at them, so I say 2, 4, 6, 8, 10.
>> So you counted by 2, so 2 plus 2 plus 2
plus 2 plus 2, okay great.
And how about one more method, so.
Okay, Vivian?
>> So, I saw them diagonally going this
way down.
So, from the top up going down.
>> From the top left?
>> Yes.
>> Come again?
Okay.
>> Yeah, and so
I started with the largest diagonal line,
which had a four in it.
It started with the object furthest to the
top.
>> This one?
>> Yeah.
>> You saw this four?
>> It goes straight down, yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So I saw those four,
then I saw the next three up.
>> And then I saw the next two which were
at the bottom.
>> Okay.
>> And then one.
>> And then what?
>> So let’s see so you saw four and then
three and then two and then one?
>> Yep.
>> And how did you?
>> I knew 4 plus 3, I just knew that was
7.
>> Okay, so you started with 7?
>> Yeah, and then from there I just added
on together.
Actually, I, in my mind truly I did it by
ones.
The two and the one.
>> Oh, did you really?
>> Yeah, even though [CROSSTALK].
>> So instead of 2 plus 1 you went 7 plus
1 plus 1 plus 1.
That's how you really saw it?
>> No I, sorry.
>> No how did you see it?
>> I did it.
>> Oh, this is cool.
>> 4 plus 3.
>> Okay, so this way.
>> Plus 1, plus 1, plus 1.
>> 4 plus 3, so
you really did think of the 4 and 3
separately, and then plus 1 plus 1 plus 1.
Is that how you saw it?
>> Yeah.
>> Great.
Okay are there any questions?
We're going to move on to a number, number
talk.
Actually, I want, I don't want to actually
stop.
Does anybody see any similarities between
methods?
I see Joe would you
like to share?
>> Oh, well I noticed that we tend to,
at least most of us tend to clump the
objects linearly.
But in different orientations.
So, Shea would create vertical lines out
of her objects.
Geraldine and I would make horizontal
lines, and Elana as well.
And then, of course Vivian is looking at
them diagonally.
>> Okay, so people saw these in really
different configurations.
What about Geraldine and Joe's method?
What do people notice about that?
Okay, so Erin?
>> It looks like they saw them in the same
rows.
But Geraldine added them two rows at a
time, whereas Joe just went one by one.
So, they're pretty similar.
>> What do you mean one by one?
>> Joe went one row at a time so 3, 2, 3,
2.
Whereas Geraldine just went 5, 5.
>> Okay, so if we covered this set,
we wouldn't have know that they actually
saw those things really differently.
>> So, what I'd like you to do now is
write in the forum.
Just a quick response to that dot card
number talk.
What do you think people can gain from
doing a dot card number talk?
Why do you think that they're important to
do?
[MUSIC]