[MUSIC].
So there are very few research studies,
very, very few that I have read.
And immediately thought the results were
so powerful they needed to be blasted from
the rooftops and everybody should know
about them.
But here's one two British professors,
Eddie Gray and
David Tall, worked with 72 students
between the ages of 7 and 13.
And they had asked teachers to nominate
students they thought of as above average,
average.
Average and below average.
They then gave the students various
addition and subtraction problems to do,
and they categorized their strategies.
For example, they gave them problems such
as 7 plus 18 which is the addition of
a single digit number to a teen digit
number.
As you can see here.
And what they found was that students used
four different strategies when they
worked on number problems.
So the strategies were some students
counted all.
So, with 7 plus 18 they would say 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6, 7.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and count up to 18.
And then to add them, they would count
them all again.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and go on
like that.
The slightly more sophisticated strategy
of counting on is
when students would add up to 7 or to 18
and then continue on.
So, if they'd added 18 they would then say
19, 20, 21.
Known facts was when students just knew
what the the number was.
They just remembered them.
And what they could derived facts, which I
recall number sense which this
whole session is about, was when students
were able to break numbers apart.
And decompose and add them, and use them.
flexibly.
So, for example, they might say with 8
plus 17, I'm going to take 8 plus 2,
and make that into ten.
and, or they may break 17 into 15 plus 2,
and then calculate 15 and 2, and 8.
So, they make the problems into easier
addition problems.
And the results from age the eight year
olds was stunning to me.
So the above average students, 30% of them
knew their numbers.
They used facts, known facts.
61% used number sense.
So they used the numbers flexibly.
And 9% counted on In the below average
group, 6% of them use known facts,
none of them use number sense, 72% of them
counted on, and 22% counted all.
When they worked with the ten year olds,
they found that the below average group
were using the same number of known facts
as the above average eight year olds.
So they're sort of caught up in, in the
number they remember over time.
But still virtually no number sense, and
instead they were continuing to count.
So why's this finding so important?
The researchers who did the study put it
well, they concluded that the low
achievers, so often thought of as slow
learners, were actually not
working more slowly but they were learning
a different form of mathematics.
And what's more, the mathematics that the
low achievers were learning was
the more difficult form of mathematics.
So let's think about this issue of the
more difficult mathematics.
With the case of counting back.
Counting back is a strategy that young
children use when subtracting two numbers.
So when you consider a problem such as, 16
take away 13.
If you start at 16 and count down thirteen
numbers, 16, 15, 14, 13,
12 You'll find that this is actually an
extremely difficult task, and
it has significant cognitive complexity
and enormous room for error.
By contrast, this strategy of the high
achievers, let's subtract him from 10 and
3 from 6, which leaves 3 is much easier to
use.
And those are the cu,
type of strategies that high achieving
students are able to use.
So the fact that high achievers had
learned to act upon numbers flexibly, and
the low achieving students hadn't, is
important, really important.
Because the flexible use of numbers and
shapes It's critical to higher level maths
learning.
In fact it's foundational for everything
that comes above.
All the higher level work.
In algebra, calculus, and beyond.
So the problem for
low achieving children is not that they
cannot work in these ways.
But they haven't learned to engage with
maths in those ways.
And the researchers found that when the
low-achievers failed,
using their counting methods, they didn't
change their method, but
they fell back into counting more and
more.
And the problem for those students comes
about because they may
become efficient with repeated counting of
small numbers.
And that lulls them into a sense of
security.
And they come to believe that math is
about counting very precisely.
Unfortunately as time goes on,
the low achieving students only have these
counting strategies.
And the counting gets ever more complex as
problems become more difficult.
And low achievers also are often
identified as low achieving in school.
And the help that they get then often get
is more procedures more emphasis on
During procedure very carefully rather
than being taught to use numbers flexibly.
And that's probably the very, very last
thing that they need.
So part of the seriousness of the problem
is this.
Mathematics is a conceptual subject.
It's not just a series of procedures and
methods although many people thing it is.
For example, if we think of the hierarchy
of concepts in early number,
we know that students start by learning to
count.
And that helps them to develop the concept
of sum.
Then they work on counting on.
And that helps them to get the concept of
addition.
And when they work with a repeated
edition,
that helps them develop the concept of a
product.
So when we learn mathematics we engage in
a process in our
brain that's called compression.
And this is how it works, when we learn
new material, it takes up a big space in
our brain so If I was to teach you some
new mathematics now,
you would be thinking about how it works,
where it fits,
how it fits with other methods, so it
takes up a very large space.
But if I were, if you were to use some
early mathematics now, such as addition,
you would probably just very quickly be
able to recall and use that.
That addition is not taking a big space in
your brain, it's compressed.
And this is William Thurston he was a, a,
his field medal winner in mathematics.
And this is him talking about compression.
He says, mathematics is amazingly
compressible.
You may struggle a long time, step by
step, to work through the same process or
idea from several approaches.
But once you really understand it, and
have the mental perspective to see it as
a whole, there is often a tremendous
mental compression.
You can file it away, recall it quickly
and completely when you need it, and
use it as just one step in some other
mental process.
And the insight that goes with this
compression is one of
the real joys of mathematics.
But here's the problem,
students who don't engage in conceptual
thinking don't benefit from compression.
So we can represent compression,
the compression that goes on in the brain
as a kind of triangle in this way,
with the space that's taken up with new
mathematics at the top of the triangle.
But for students who don't see mathematics
conceptually, for
them it's less of a triangle and more like
a never ending ladder that stretches up
to the sky with method upon method upon
method.
So they're not thinking in mathematics
conceptually,
instead they are thinking of lots of lots
of different methods to remember.
And so they're not engaging in this
process of compression.
So in mathematics education and policy
documents, people have for
a long time, talked about procedural
methods and conceptual ideas, that,
maths is made up of these two kind of
areas, with a big divide between the two.
So, people talk about, it's either
conceptual, or it's procedural.
But Carolyn Kieran's done some really
interesting work,
which has shown that actually,
we need to use mathematics conceptually
even when we are just learning procedures.
Because every time you need to use a
procedure.
Every time you need to adapt a procedure
you engage in conceptual thinking.
So those distinctions between the two are
probably not even that helpful.
So, we have, what people think of now as
an algebra crisis in the US.
Everybody's worried, that large numbers of
students are failing algebra, and
that Algebra is maybe, just too difficult,
or too hard.
But one of the main reasons students are
failing algebra,
is the lack of foundational mathematics.
Particularly number sense.
So, it's very difficult for students to
learn Algebra if they,
they've missed out on a foundation or
understanding of early number.
And they've missed out on developing
number sense.
So, one of the people I interviewed for
this course was a very interesting person,
Sebastian Thrun.
He's achieved many things.
He's a Stanford professor, a
vice-president of Google, and he
was the one who designed the self driving
car and Google Glass and other things.
And he's now the CEO of Udacity.
And I interviewed him about his use of
mathematics.
And I'm going to show you more of the
interview in the next session, but He,
when, when he reflects on his work and
talks about various things he's done but,
one of the interesting parts was, he
talked about how everything he's done in
his work, including wiring complex
mathematics papers and
using a lot of high-level mathematics.
>> Comes down to an understanding of
numbers.
He talks about addition in particular, and
how everything else falls into place.
So, this is a short extract that I'd like
you to watch and listen to now.
>> I think everyone who works exercises
math everyday, in, in the way we operate.
We, we think about time everyday, we think
about money,
we think about relationships of people How
they interact with each other.
We think about tasks, about things we have
to do, about deadlines.
These are all mathematical examples.
And if you step a step further, there's
more contrived example,
like financing of your house and so on.
They were a little more difficult to
manipulate, but
even there we can get an intuition of, of
what's going on.
And they're mathematical.
I actually believe that somewhat
everything in Math is addition.
Almost everything can be derived back to
very,
very simple operations like putting
numbers together.
It's the core of, of all mathematics.
I'm saying this, I've written a fairly
abstract math book full of formulas and
formulas and formulas I think you would
like your head would smoke seeing all
the formulas and still everything in there
is just basically addition.
So I think the key thing is not to be
afraid of the formulas.
The format is just a language.
The key thing is to grasp the concepts and
understand where they apply.
The key thing is to understand that
certain roles apply regardless of
the context, for example adding apples as
to as adding pears.
And once this abstraction is done between.
An instantiation of a concept that might
involve time or space or people,
to another instantiation, you already have
the basic math skill, which is the idea to
abstract, the idea that there's rules that
transcend beyond a certain domain, and
simple rules are very powerful.
Complicated rules are not very powerful in
my opinion.
There are simple rules.
So rules that say we can add numbers and
we can keep track of them there's some
sort of constancy to certain things like
the way space evolves and so
on, are really powerful.
>> So what I'd like you to do now is think
a bit about what we've seen so
far and what you've heard.
And answer this question.
[MUSIC]