So, we're going to listen now to three of
the boys in Nick's class that I
caught up with after the number talk.
So, the first question they, that I asked
them,
that you'll see them respond to is what
they think of math?
So, if you can get past their cuteness, I
want you to think about and
discuss afterwards, what surprised you or
interested, interested you in what they
said?
So, do you guys like math?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> Mm-hm.
So, you like doing them?
How about you, Dylan?
>> Well, it's, like, it's free.
It's like, you can do whatever you want.
>> huh, you like that?
>> Yeah.
It's, like, it's, like,
multiplication, division, you can, like,
break it down to different,
different parts, and then do the
multiplication and division.
>> Uh-huh.
So,
how many of you thought this about math,
that it's free and
you can do what you want?
>> Probably just now and today.
>> Not like since we're, like, since
second grade.
>> Mm-hmm.
So, it's second grade?
Because sometimes math isn't taught like
that, people don't think that about math.
What has helped you think like that?
>> [NOISE] Well, actually, like all the
ideas help you can do it.
>> Probably the way that Nick taught us to
do it.
>> Yeah, it's like, it's like there's
different ways.
>> Uh-huh.
[CROSSTALK], so
it's like, it's like really cool.
>> It is really cool then.
That's really important thing about math.
You can solve math problems in different
ways, but most people don't think that.
They think there's just one way to do it.
>> Yeah.
>> So it's an important thing.
>> There's like three or four ways to do
it, but nobody even thinks about it.
>> Mm-hm.
What about you?
What's your favorite math thing to do?
>> I like decomposing and adding.
>> Mm-hm.
Mm-hm.
What is, what's a friendly number?
>> It's like ten and five.
>> Friendly numbers is like when you add
five, like for
example five times five plus four plus
seven.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Ten is a really friendly number so.
>> What do you think about the talking
about math part?
Do you think that helps you understand or?
>> It does.
>> It does and doesn't.
>> Uh-huh.
Tell me about why it does first.
Or you tell me, anyone.
>> It actually does, because you can see
what other people did compared to yours.
>> Mm-hm.
>> You see how other people will do it.
>> Well, you can see what other people
think, and
then you can like tell what you think.
>> Mm-hm.
>> And
also sometimes we make mistakes, everybody
makes mistakes.
>> [CROSSTALK], actually, you made a
mistake too, if you made one.
>> Uh-huh, and mistakes are great because
you can learn from mistakes.
We all make mistakes.
Do you feel okay if you're doing kind of
math talk and you make a mistake?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, pretty much.
>> Cause it's like they, and just like
help us out and tell us like, and
help us with the answers.
>> Mm-hm, that's right.
>> They tell us when to do it so we don't
have to more math work.
>> [LAUGH], so,
do you think math is a subject where
you're always following rules, or
is it a subject where you get to think
about ideas?
Which do you think it is?
>> I think it's like,
where you can think about different things
at one time to make one thing work.
>> It's like you're free.
You can do whatever you want.
It's like breaking down, decompose.
>> You can do what you want to get an
answer.
>> You can make friendly numbers.
You can like breaking down to
multiplication.
>> Uh-huh.
So, those math talks let you do all those
things, didn't they.
>> Yeah.
>> Did you use math in
those ways before this class?
Did you break it down and do all those
different things?
>> No.
>> Not at all.
>> So what did you, what did you,
how is it different?
>> Well, it's like Nick teachers us
like kind of, how to break it down, like,
use multiplication problems, so
it's like easier.
>> Mm-hm.
>> To make friendly numbers,
like decomposing and all that stuff.
>> Mm-hm.
So,
does that help you solve math problems,
being able to break down the numbers and
make friendly numbers?
>> A lot.
>> Also it's different to at
the same time because you don't normally
do
that until third grade so.
>> Mm-hm.
So,
do you think now you've learned to do
that, you can do that in
other math problems that you get?
>> Yeah.
>> Even when you're not in
the math course?
>> Yeah, if Nick didn't teach us this,
we would be like.
What is in like fourth grade?
>> Uh-huh.
>> We'd be really bad at fourth grade,
and really in other years of class.