[MUSIC].
So, there are very few research studies,
very, very few that I have read.
And then immediately thought the results
were so powerful, they needed to
be blasted from the rooftops, and
everybody should know about them.
But here's one.
Two British professors, Eddie Grey and
David Tall, worked with 72 students
between the ages of seven and 13.
And they had asked teachers to nominate
students they thought of as above average,
average and below average.
They then gave the students various
addition and subtractions problem to do,
and they categorized their strategies.
For example, they gave them problems such
as 7 plus 18,
which is the addition of a single digit
number to a teen digit number.
As you can see here.
And what they found was that students used
four different strategies when they
worked on number problems.
So their strategies were, some students
counted all.
So with 7 plus 18 they would say one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven, one, two,
three, four, five and count up to 18.
And then to add them, they would count
them all again.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, ten and go on like that.
There's slightly more sophisticated
strategy of counting on is
when the students would add up to 7 or to
18 and then continue on.
So if they added 18, they would then say
19, 20, 21.
Known facts, was when students just knew
what the the number bonds, they they just,
remembered them.
And what they called derived facts,
which I would call number sentencing,
which this whole session was about.
Was when students were able to break
numbers apart and decompose and
add them and use them flexibly.
So for example, they might say with 8 plus
17, I'm going to make 8 plus 2 and
make that into 10.
And or they may break 17 into 15 plus 2,
and then calculate 15 and 2 and 8.
So they make the problems into easier
addition problems.
And the results from age, the eight year
old's was stunning to me.
So the above average students 30% of them
knew their numbers they used facts,
known facts.
61% of them knew, used numbers sense, so
they used the numbers flexibly.
And 9% of them counted on.
In the below average group, 6% of them
used known facts,
none of them used number sense, 72% of
them counted on, and 22% counted all.
And when they worked with the ten year
olds, they found that the below average
group were using the same number of known
facts as the above average eight year old.
So, they're sort of caught up in the, the
number they remember over time.
But still, virtually no number sense.
And instead, they were continuing to
count.
So, why is this finding so important?
The researchers who did this study put it
well.
They concluded that the low achievers, so
often thought of as slow learners.
Were actually not working more slowly but
they were learning a different form of
mathematics.
And what's more, the mathematics that the
low achievers were learning was
the more difficult form of mathematics.
So let's think about this issue of the
more difficult mathematics with
the case of counting back.
Counting back is the strategy that young
children use when subtracting two numbers.
So when you consider our problem such as
16 take away 13,
if you start at 16 and count down 13
numbers 16, 15, 14, 13, 12.
You'll find that this is actually an
extremely difficult task and
it has significant cognitive complexity
and enormous room for error.
By contrast, the strategy of the high
achievers.
Let's subtract 10 from 10 and 3 from 6,
which leaves 3 is much easier to use.
And those are the types of strategies that
high achieving students are able to use.
So the fact that high achievers had
learned to act upon numbers flexibly.
And the low achieving students hadn't is
important, really important.
Because the flexible use of numbers and
shapes It's critical, to higher level
maths learning.
In fact, it's foundational for everything
that comes above.
All the higher level work in algebra,
calculus and beyond.
So the problem for
low achieving children is not that they
cannot work in these ways.
But they haven't learned to engage with
maths in those ways.
And the researchers found that when the
low achievers failed using their
counting methods.
They didn't change their method, but they
fell back into counting more and more.
And the problem for those students comes
about because they may
become efficient with repeated counting of
small numbers.
And that lulls them into a sense of
security, and
they come to believe that maths is about
counting very precisely.
Unfortunately, as time goes on,
the low achieving students only have these
counting strategies.
And the counting gets ever more complex as
problems become more difficult.
And low achievers also, are often
identified as low achieving in school.
And the help that they, then often get is
more procedures.
More emphasis on doing procedures very
carefully rather than being taught to
use numbers flexibly.
And that's probably the very very last
thing that they need.
So, part of the seriousness of the problem
is this.
Mathematics is a conceptual subject.
It's not just a series of procedures and
methods.
Although many people think it is.
For example if we think of the hierarchy
of concepts in early number.
We know that students start by learning to
count and
that helps them to develop the concept of
sum.
Then they work on counting on and that
helps them to get the concept of addition.
And when they work with repeated addition,
that helps them develop the concept of a
product.
So when we learn mathematics,
we engage in a process in our brain that's
called compression.
And this is how it works,
when we learn new material, it takes up a
big space in our brain.
So, if I was to teach you some new
mathematics now,
you would be thinking about how it works.
Where it fits, how it fits with other
methods.
So it takes up a very large space.
But if I were, if you were to use some
early mathematics now such as addition.
You would probably just very quickly be
able to recall and use that.
That addition is not taking up a big space
in your brain, it's compressed.
And, this is William Thurston, he was a,
a, is field medal winner in mathematics.
And this is him talking about compression.
He said mathematics is amazingly
compressible.
You may struggle a long time, step by step
to work through the same process or
idea from several approaches.
But once you really understand it and have
the mental prespective to see it as
a whole, there's often a tremendous mental
compression.
You can file it away.
Recall it quickly and completely when you
need it.
And use it as just one step in some other
mental process.
And the insight that goes with this
compression is one of
the real joys of mathematics.
But here's the problem.
Students who don't engage is conceptual
thinking don't benefit from compression.
So we can represent compression,
the compression that goes on in the brain
as a kind of triangle in this way.
With the space that's taken up with new
mathematics at the top of the triangle.
But for students who don't see mathematics
conceptually, for
them it's less of a triangle.
And more like an never ending ladder that
stretches up to the sky,
with method upon method upon method.
So their not thinking in mathematics
conceptually,
instead their thing there are lots, and
lots of different method s to remember.
And so their not engaging in this process
of compression.
So, in mathematics education and policy
documents, people have, for
a long time, talked about procedural
methods and conceptual ideas.
Maths is made up of these two kind of
areas.
But the big divide between the two, so,
people talk about, it's either conceptual
or it's procedural.
But Caroline Kiran's done some really
interesting work, which has shown that.
Actually we need to use mathematics
conceptually even when we're just
learning procedures.
Because every time you need to use a
procedure, every time you need to adapt in
a, adapt a procedure, you engage in
conceptual thinking.
So those distinctions between the two are
probably not even that helpful.
So we have what people think of now as an
algebra crisis here in the U.S.
Everybody's worried that large numbers of
students are failing algebra and
that maybe algebra is just too difficult
or too hard.
But one of the main reasons students are
failing algebra is
a lack of foundational mathematics.
Particularly number sense.
So it's very difficult for students to
learn algebra if that,
that missed out on a foundational
understanding of early number.
And they've missed out on developing
number sense.
So, one of the people I interviewed from
this course, a very interesting person,
is Sebastian Thrun.
He's achieved many things.
He's a Stanford Professor, a Vice
President of Google, he is
the one who designed the self driving car,
and Google glass, and everything.
So he's now the CEO of Udacity.
And I interviewed him about his use of
mathematics.
And I'm going to show you more of the
interview in the next session.
But he, when, when he reflects on his work
and talks about various things he's done.
But, one of the interesting parts was, he
talked about how everything he's done in
his work including writing complex
mathematics papers.
And using a lot of high-level mathematics
comes down to an understanding of numbers.
He talks about addition in particular, and
how everything else falls into place.
So, this is a short extract that I'd like
you to watch and listen to now.
>> I think everyone writes exercises math
everyday, and and the way we operate.
We we think about time everyday, we think
about money,
we think about relationships of people.
How they interact with each other.
We think about tasks, about things we have
to do, about deadlines.
These are all mathematical examples.
And if we step a step further,
there's more contrived examples like
financing of your house and so one.
We live in more difficult to manipulate.
But even there, we can get an intuition
of, of what's going on and
they're mathematical.
I actually believe that more or everything
in, in math as addition.
Almost everything can be derived to very,
very simple operations by
putting numbers together is the core of,
of all the mathematics.
Things I've written a fairly up-straight
math book full of formulas and
formulas and formulas.
I think you would, like your head would
smoke seeing all the formulas.
And still everything in there is just
basically addition.
So, I think the key thing is not to be
afraid of the formulas.
The formulas are just a language.
The key thing is to grasp the concepts and
understand where they apply.
The key thing is to understand that
certain rules apply regardless of
the context.
For example, adding apples is the same as
adding pears.
And once this abstraction is done between
an Insensation of
a concept that might involve time or space
or people.
To another Insensation, you already have
the basic math skill,
that just [INAUDIBLE] to abstract.
[INAUDIBLE] that there's rules that
transcend beyond a certain domain.
And simple rules are very powerful;
complicated rules are not very powerful.
They are simple rules.
So rules that say,
we can add numbers and we can keep track
with them with them more.
There some sort of coincidency to certain
things like the, the way space evolves and
so on, are really powerful.
>> So, what I'd like you to do now is
think a bit about what we've seen,
so far and what you've heard and answer
this question.
[MUSIC]