So, in this lecture we're going to talk
about convex sets.
And we'll start with some very basic
definitions like what's an affine set and
what's a convex set.
Then we're going to move we'll look at a,
at a catalog of some very important
examples.
Things like balls or half spaces or rays.
Things like that.
Then we'll focus a bit on operations that
preserve convexity,
that's like the intersection of two sets
or a sum, things like that.
And then the basic idea is that will form
a calculus of convex sets,
you can combine the basic ones with these
operations and
create quite a lot of interesting convex
sets.
We'll then move on to generalized
inequalities.
Talk about what that means.
That's in, that's an inequality vector
inequality.
And then we'll talk about some basics
facts from convex analysis.
Separating and supporting hydroplanes, and
the idea of duel cones and
generalized inequalities.
Okay, so we'll start with the idea of an
affine set.
So we have two points, in our n, in a
vector space, x1 and x2.
And we form another point, we take a,
a number theta and we form the vector
theta x1 plus 1 minus theta x2.
That's so it's a linear combination of x1
and x2,
but it's a very specific linear
combination.
The two coefficients add up to 1.
'Kay?
And geometrically, that looks like this.
If I take theta equals 1 This gives you of
course x 1.
If you set theta equals 0 you get x 2.
If you take theta equals a half you're at
the midpoint that would be
like right here.
And as you vary theta you move along this
line.
Now when theta is negative You're out here
on the extension, past x2 on
the way in the direction, in the same
direction that goes from x1 to x2.
And if you take theta bigger than one,
you're on this extension of the line over
here.
If theta is between zero and
one, you're on the segment, line segment
between x1 and x2.
Okay, now we define an affine set to be a
set where if
you have any two distinct points in the
set then the line that passes through it
is contained entirely in the set.
So that's an affine set.
And an example would be very obvious
example is the solution set of a set of
linear equations.
So here, if you have two points, different
points that sol, in,
that solve a set of linear equations.
So I have Ax1 equals b.
S if I have Ax1 equals b, and I have Ax2
equals b,
then The claim is that the line passing
through x one and
x two is also in this set which means
satisfies this equality.
And what that means is we'd have to look
at ax, but
that's a times theta x one plus one minus
theta x two.
And the question is What is that, and in
particular is it B, and it is,
because this is Theta, ax1 plus 1 minus
Theta ax2 and that's Theta b plus
1 minus Theta, b and that is b, alright,
so that's the verification that
the solutions set of a set of linear
equations...
Is an affine set.
Now it, turns out the converse is also
true.
That if you have any affine set,
it can be written as the solutions set of
a set of linear equations.
Okay, this brings us to convex set.
So convex set, it's the same idea.
Except that we talk about the line
segment.
So the line segment between two points,
these are two vectors and a vector space.
That's any linear combination with the
following requirements on
the coefficients.
The coefficients have to add up to one,
that's number one.
And number two, they have to be bigger
than or equal to zero.
Another way to say that is they must have
the form theta plus one minus theta where
theta is between zero and one.
And so this is an honest mixture, both of
these two numbers is between zero and
one and they add up to one.
Kay', so that's the line segment.
And a convex set, it's very simple.
It's any set where it contains a line
segment between any two points that are in
the set.
So if you have two points in the set than
the line segment between them must line
entirely in the set.
Or one other way to say a very simple
would be something like this that if
you have a point X1 and a point X2 in a
set there has to be clear line of
sight path between X1 and X2 within the
set.
So that's idea there's no hidden parts.
Any point in the set can see any other
point in the set.
So an example of a convex set.
Is this this set here and so here I take
any two points,
indeed the line segment between them fits
entirely in the set.
This set, here the [UNKNOWN] table set
here that's non convex, and
to show that is non convex here's a point
in the set, here's a point in the set, and
the line segment between them is drawn
right here, and
you can see that it doesn't lie entirely
in the set, or another way to say it is
that there's not a clear line of sight in
the set, from this point to this point.
This set here it's almost convex but it's
not convex and it's not convex because,
for example, here's a point in the set and
here's a point in the set, and if I
draw the segment between them it crosses
over that area where the boundary was not
contained in the set and so it's not It
doesn't contain the entire segement.
So that's a non convex set.
Okay, now you have the idea of a convex
combination.
So a convex combination,
now generalizes the idea we just looked at
of a line segment.
It's basically this.
It says I have K points now where I use to
have 2.
And if I form a linear combination of the
case in points with coefficients data 1
up to data k.
If they don't want to data, up to data k
or
just any real numbers, that's a linear
combination.
However to make it a convex combination,
these things have to add up to 1 and
they have to be non-negative, so.
In the case when K is two,
it's exactly the same as the previ-, it
defines a line segment, right.
So a convex combination is any element on
a line segment between two points, okay?
So this is the conv-, convex combination.
And you can think of it many ways, I'd
like to think of the thetas as
mixture coefficients and you can think of
x as a mixture.
So it says take 10% of x1, 0% of x2, and
so on and up, you know and 12% of xk and
all of these percentages have to add up to
1, okay, that's the convex combination.
People use the word mixture but that's not
a standard mathematical term, alright, so
people just use they arm convex
combination...
now, the convex hull and the a con of a
set.
That is the set of all convex combiations
of poitns in a set so,
if the original set were this finite set.
These dark points.
That's a finite set.
Then the convex hull of it is this shaded
region.
Gear.
And for example, if you take a point here
you can get that well that that might be
a convex combination of 2 of them right?
If I take a point in there it might be a
convex combination certainly of these 3
but probably of others it's a convex
combation of this one and this one and
this one.
Right?
So there's no reason to believe that that
convex combination is going to be unique.
In general it's not.
It's just a point is in the convex hull if
it is a convex combination of
some points in the set.
Now visually you can think of a convex
hull as simply something like
the smallest convex hull that contains the
original set, so for example our kidney or
[UNKNOWN] table shape here, the convex
hull is this headed region, and so
we have included all of the points in
here...
Which previously were not in the original
set, but they are n the convex hull and
now this shaded region is convex.
So that's the idea of convex hull.
Okay, convex cone, that is simply we start
with the idea of iconic combination and
another name for that is a negative
combination.
So I take a linear combination of two
points.
That is theta 1 plus theta 2.
Now if they're, theta 1 and theta 2 are
general it's just a linear combination.
If the add a,
if they're non-negative and add up to 1
that is called a convex combination.
And here the requirement for a conic
combination is simply that theta 1 and
theta 2 are non-negative.
Alright, so that, that's the definition of
a conic combination.
Some people do say that's an non-negative
combination of x1 and x2, okay?
Now geometrically the picture is this,
here's x1 and here's x2 and here's 0,
then conic combinations is this sort of
pie slice that goes between x1, x2 and 0.
It sits in a plane, even if x1 and x2 are
in a high dimensional space The set of
conic combinations lies in a plane that
passes through zero, x1, x2.
And then for example these points on this
boundary,
these are all the points that are
multiples, nonnegative multiples of x1.
These are all the points that are
nonnegative multiples of x1.
x2, and now all these points for example,
if I take something right smack in
the middle, these are the points that are
non negative multiples of x1 plus x2.
Another way to say that is that's
everything of the form theta x1
plus theta x2, okay?
But general, it sweeps out this whole set
like that.
And a convex cone is this: It's a set that
contains the conic,
all conic combinations of any two points
in the set paired.
So if you have two points in the set, the
entire conic, all conic con,
combinations, are in the set.
So that's a, that's a convex cone.
What we're going to do now is look at some
sets that we
will see throughout the entire course.
Right.
So these are sets like,
you know, solution sets of linear
equalities and other things and
we are going to see these basically
throughout the course.
Right now and in fact for
the rest of this lecture things are
going to be a little bit.
Dry because it's just the mat.
But I can assure you that we will use all
of this later and
it'll make a lot more sense in a practical
context.
But for now everything is just abstract.
And that's just too bad.
That's, that's the way the course starts.
So, okay, so let's look at hyperplanes and
halfspaces.
A hyperplane Is a solution set of a single
linear inequality constrain write
a single linear eq, equation.
Okay, and we will take a0 is equal to 0
right because of a otherwise this thing is
silly if it is 0.
So that's that's a hyper plane and it
would be for example its a line.
Right?
Say solution set of
a single linear equation in two variables
is just a line.
In three variables it's a plane, and
that's, and
in more variables I guess that's why it's
called a hyperplane,
because it's like a plane but it's in
higher dimensions.
So it's a hyperplane.
And a is a normal to that hyperplane.
So Here if this is, of course this is just
a line.
But a is the normal to that.
And these are this set, that's the set of
all points that satisfy a x equals b.
When you vary b what happens is this, this
thing moves up and down like that.
These are, these are parallel planes,
that depends on b.
So, solution set of a single linear
inequalities is a hyperplane.
A halfspace is this.
It's a set, It's the solution set of a
single linear inequality.
So here I say that a transposed x is less
than or
equal to b as opposed to being equal to b.
If it's equal to b it would be this line
right here.
This might be, well, b minus .01 and this
would be b minus 0.2 and so on, so
everything in this half space, these are
all the points where a transpose x
is less than the value of b, and if you
change b you simply move the surface of
this in a parallel way, you move it up and
down...
Okay and now A is an outward normal to
that set.
Okay, so A is a normal vector in this case
it's actual an outward normal.
Now these sets are both affine and convex
and
half spaces are not affine but they are
convex.
I should say hyper planes are affine and
Half spaces are convex and they're not
affline.
Now this has to be shown you can look at
it and you can verify it visually and
by intutition but these are things that
you'd, you'd have to show.
It's not particularly hard to show these
things but you have to.
So let's take a look for example.
A halfspace.
The question that we have to ask is this.
If I take two points in a halfspace, the
question is whether the segment is in it?
And we'll just say well geometrically it's
obvious.
And if you like, we can do this
algebraically.
To show this algebraically, we would say
suppose that a transpose x1,
it less than b, or less or equal to b, and
a transpose x2.
Is less than b.
That means x1 and x2 are in the half
space.
And now let's take a convex combination,
Data x1 plus 1 minus data x2 and
let's call that x.
And, and the question then is whether a
transpose x is less than b and
the hope is yes.
And if that's true then because x1 and x2
are arbitrary and
data was arbitrary between 0 and 1, I
didn't say that actually but I am now.
If we verify this then we'll have verified
a half space is, is a convex set.
Well a transpose x.
Is nothing but A transpose theta X1 plus 1
minus theta X2 and sure enough this
is theta 1 H a transpose X1 plus minus
theta A transpose X2.
Now, that's non negative non negative so
that's less than or
equal to theta 1 B plus 1 minus.
>> One minus theta times b, I'm using the
following fact here,
this number is less than that number,
that's our assumption.
This number is less than that number,
And finally, we get this, and that's of
course equal to b, and we're done.
Okay, so I will never do a derivative this
simple again in this course,
this is just to show you the kind of
argument you'd have to make.
Did you, I mean you draw a picture and
your eyeball says yes that's convex, but
these things actually have to get changed,
okay.
The next thing we're going to look at...
are euclidean balls and ellipsoids.
So, a Euclidean ball, Euclidean refers to
the fact that we're going to
use the two norm here, so the square root
of the sum of the squares.
A two norm, Euclidean ball looks like
this.
It's the set of X for which the distance
to X C,
that's the center of the ball, is less
than r, r is the radius of the ball.
So that's, that's what you mean by a ball.
It looks like this right, it's the cell
thing here there's x c and
the radius is r, that's a ball.
Now this can also be written in a free
parameter or
I should say a constrained parameter
representation.
Right.
This is the style where you say it's the
set of X for
which a certain perdicate evaluates to
true.
The predicate is this inequality.
Here, it's a mixed things.
It says it's the set of all points of the
form the center plus R
times U where U is a vector of norm less
than or equal to 1.
You have to of course show that this is
the case but it's not hard.
And these are, this is convex but again
I'm not going to show it but it's true.
A generalization is an ellipsoid.
So, an ellipsoid is a set.
The set of points to satisfy a quadratic
inequality.
Here c is the center.
And p is a positive definite, symmetric
positive matrix, right?
So, this is an ellipsoid.
And here, for example.
The semiaxes of the ellipsoid are given by
the eigenvectors of p,
and the semiaxis lengths are related.
In fact, the square roots of the
eigenvalues of p,
these are the lengths of the semiaxes.
And there is a corresponding There's
definintly a corressponding representation
just like this.
Op I should mention the following if you
take P to be R squared if I
take P equal R squared I.
Then, in fact, this will give you, that's
an ellipsoid but
it's also a euclidean ball so this is a
generalization.
The generalization of this representation
for
a ball is this one it says it's the set of
Xc plus Au where norm U is less than 1.
So you could even say something like this.
It's the set of all things of the form Xc
plus a matrix A times U where U
is in the unit.
Ball, right.
So it's a linear transformation of the
uni-bulb plus an offset,
which is the center, okay.
So that's the a, that, that is a
representation.
By the way, this representation here, is
unique, in other words,
if this is equal to another set with a
different.
With another p.
Those two matrices have to be equal and
I'm assuming that they're symmetric, here,
right?
If they're not symmetric that's false.
But if they're, if they're symmetric which
you can assume without loss of generality,
then it's true.
Here the A in this representation is not
unique.
A is, A there's multiple A's here that
would give you the same Set
in particular if I take A and I multiply
it on the right by Q,
here where Q is an orthogonal matrix.
So Q trans, Q is square and satisfies
that.
Then for sure AQ can be substituted for A
here and you get the same set.
And the reason is actually quite simple.
The reason is if I take a something whose
norm is less than 1 and
I multiple it by an orthongonal vector I
get something whose norm is less than 1
and in fact it goes vice versa so that's
why it's the same thing.
I'll just mention the following we can
make this representation unique here
by insisting that A B.
A symmetric and positive definite, so that
makes it unique, and I'll let you
figure out how that would be, how, well
how you would make that argument, but
the hint would be to take a singular value
decomposition of a.
Okay the next in our tour of some of these
very basic sets that are convex...
Is, we'll look at a more general norm.
So if we have a, a norm, and a norm is
nothing but a function.
And it's usually written with instead of
as a,
as a normal function notation like this.
It's usually written with it's argument
surrounded By double bars,
that's the standard notation.
The double bar, by the way, is supposed to
make it look like an absolute value
because a norm is something like, it's
supposed to serve the purpose of
an absolute value, but in multiple
dimensions.
That's what a norm is supposed to be.
Here are, here are the requirements that
should be, that for, for
a function to be a norm.
One is it always has to be non negative.
It's supposed to measure the length of a
vector.
So, negative doesn't make any sense and it
should be 0 if and
only if the vector is 0, right?
And that, I think that's called
definiteness.
So, these two together is called positive
It's a function that is 0, only if the
argument is 0.
In other word, it's always non negative.
Okay, it has to be homogeneous of degree
1, that is if you scale.
X by a scale factor t.
Then that's the same as the norm of x
times the absolute value of t,
and that would work with negative.
So for example the norm of x is the norm
of minus x.
And finally, you have the so called
triangle inequality.
And that says that the norm of x plus y is
less than the norm of x plus the norm of
y, right.
So and, it basically it's called the
triangle inequality.
Roughly because well we'll get it to but
it says something like this.
If you have a point x here and you have a
point y over here then x plus y is
over here and it says that this distance
here is less than this distance plus
this distance, which is the same as this
distance plus this distance, so
at least for the euclidean norm...
Where we all of a lot of intuition this
says basically,
that in a triangle the longest side is
certainly not longer than the sum of
the lengths of the two shorter sides,
okay?
Now the notation is when you right just
the norm it's a general unspecific norm.
And usually what that means is the
ascertion you're going to make.
It's true for any norm, right?
Now when we're talking about a particular
norm, usually there'll be a numonic or
a symbol down below that tells you the
particular norm.
I mean we've already seen one,
we've seen the two norm that's the
Eucidian norm, that's the that's this.
So, we've seen that, but there's lots of
others okay?
Now from a norm this is supposed to be
review,
now from a norm there's some very
interesting sets you can come up with.
One is a norm ball, that's the set of all
points which are,
have a distance, as measured by the norm,
less than r, from some center.
And that's a norm ball with radius R.
Here, norm cone, that's something much
more interesting we'll see a lot of
this in the class as we move on.
The norm cone is a, is a set that sits in
the graph space, right, so
the graph space of something.
Is the set of all pairs that, that's a,
that's in say RN.
And T is in R alright, so
if you were to plot graph of a function
that would be the set of all x and f of x.
for example, alright something like that
so
x is in Rn, alright that would be the
graph of a function.
Its a set of all things were x,
you think of x is being down here and then
the height is what gives you f of x.
'Kay?
So, here this is not the graph.
It's actually what's called the epigraph
of the norm.
Which we'll talk about later.
But now it looks like that.
And what it is, is the differences is in
inequality here.
And it says, it's not just.
So in fact, in this picture here, this
should all be filled in.
That's a solid cone.
It's a solid cone.
I, I'm drawing the sort of a boundary.
But in fact, you should think of a solid
cone that goes up like that.
And people would call this a circular
cone,
that's if the norm is the Euclidean norm
That's a circular cone, okay?
And if you take a Euclidean norm cone,
that's drawn here,
that's called a second order cone and
we're going to be seeing a lot of it..
Oh, main assertion, norm balls and cones
are convex.
So by the way, the norm cone, as the name
implies Is a convex cone.
So by the way you can't just say that, I
mean you know technically somebody has to
show these things well that could be you
on your homework or something like that,
but will that's something we'll well you
can either what you can either trust us
read about it or some of these things are
very good exercise yourself.
This is sit down and
show that some of these things hold, by
the way some of these might are.
are trickier than you think.
Showing something like this, the triangle
inequality.
It's not so bad for Euclidean, but for
others it need not be that easy,
ahead of time or if you haven't seen the
proof in awhile.
Okay, this brings us to a polyhedron,
another name for this is polytopes.
I'll say a little bit under that minute.
And that's defined as a solution set of
finitely many linear inequalities and
equalities, right?
So if you have a set of linear equations
and a set of linear inequalities, right?
Oh, and here, this symbol means
componentwise inequality.
Right so, not everyone uses a different
symbol, right?
So a lot of people just write that this
way.
Because there's not that many different
definitions of what it means for
one vector to be less than another, right?
So, but we'll write it with a swiggly
thing.
And that means that every entry of this
vector is less than the corresponding
entry of that vector.
And of course what that means is each row
of Ax is less than or equal to B.
Each row defines a single hyperplane and
so it would look like this here is A1.
Here is the boundary of it.
The first row of this is all points, kind
of over here.
Okay?
It's that halfspace.
That's all points that are over here.
And the second row of this inequality,
that gives you all the points that are
over here.
And of course if you take the
intersection,
what you end up with is this shaded set,
something like that Okay.
So, that's the, that this is defined to be
a, a, a po, a,
a polyhedron and the plural is polyhedra,
right.
And another name for this is polytope, is
that a name.
And, so, and then what gets even more
bizarre, is some people refer.
Distinguish between a polytope and a
polyhedron by,
using one to refer to the bounded version.
So if it's a bounded polyhedron it's
called a polytope and then believe it or
not, you can find another author who
exactly switches these, right?
So, for example, the general is a polytope
and a bounded one is a polyhedron.
So your best bet is just to stick with one
and either put bounded or
not in the front as a qualifier, so okay.
Alright so that's a polyhedron.
Another set that we're going to see a
whole lot is positive semi definite cone.
And the notation is this.
SN...
Is going to be, that's the set of
symmetric end by end matrices, right?
So that is that's a, a vector space,
right?
Because it's closed under linear
combinations and things like that.
Oh by the way, what's its dimension?
It's like n n plus 1 over 2.
because, well, I mean you could just
numerate a basis or whatever, or
you could just build very roughly
speaking, yeah,
it's how many numbers you need to describe
and general element and the answer is,
you describe the diagonal and the upper
triangle and you're done right, and so
that's n and plus one over two elements,
okay?
If you put a plus at the bottom that's the
set of positives positive semi definite n
by n matrices and that's the set of, that
what that means of course is that this is
the following issues quadratic form, its
just a z transpose Xz,
its bigger than equal to 0 for any z you
pick.
Right, so that's what that means.
And that's a convex cone, and what that
means is if you take two positive
semidefinite matrices, if you, if you take
a non negative linear combination,
then you get a non neg, you get another
positive semidefinite matrices.
Where it says, see these are covariances
if, if you like, if you like to
think statistically or something like
that, they're covariance matrices.
If you put plus, plus it, its something
like positive and that's the set of
positive definite ones right, so these are
I guess called co-variances of
random variables that are non-degenerator
I think there is some name for it.
But basically what that means is the
covariance matrix is,
the co- variance matrix is positive
definite.
And here's an example, here is the
positive semidefinite cone that,
in, in here is s plus two.
And it's got a dimension three, right,
described by x, y and z.
>> And here it is plotted, I mean you
can't see it,
actually This should look kind of, I've
had people describe all sorts of
things like the front of a ship or
something like that.
I don't know.
But you know what it really is, it's the
same as that cone.
It's the same as an orange cone it's just
rotating.
That's not hard to show.
I mean just write out what it means for
a 2x2 matrix to be positive, to be
definite that's what it means.
To determine it's positive.
I won't do that but I'm just saying that's
what this is.
Okay, so one of things that you are
going to need to do as practical matter is
this we will talk about convex functions
you know like may be next well,
definitely next week but one of the things
you are going to have to do is
to be able to determine whether a set is
convex or not.
That, that's going to be one of the things
you will absolutely need to know.
and, here's this, not that many ways you
can do this.
But the basic one is this.
And this is sort of you know, when you're
starting off or
something like this and sometimes it's the
right thing to do.
But actually quite, rather rarely, it's
this.
Is basically you just go, you go right
back to the basic definition.
And it says to show that it says convex,
here's what you do,
you say give me one element, give me
another one,
they're arbitrary, give me a number Theta
between 0 and 1 and then verify that
the convex combinations theta x1 plus 1
minus theta x2 is in the set.
That's, that's your, you can always fall
back on that.
But more interesting, and
something that's going to fit with a lot
of other things in the course...
And other stuff that we're going to do is
actually to come up with a an interesting,
is actually to use a calculus of convex
sets.
That's actually a more interesting.
It's constructive.
It's also going to to fit in with a sort
of a more modern computer sciency type
view of all this.
And if you actually wanted to do any of
these things,
this is going to be much more useful.
What I might add is that you will be doing
this and so it will be useful for you so
the idea there is that you have a calculus
yo have a bunch of atoms right?
You have a basic sets that are basic
solutions of linear equality.
By the way somebody.
It has to show at some point these verify
their properties right.
You do that.
And then the key is this.
You use operations that persever
convexity.
And then you build up a,
you generate new convex sets from your
atoms and these operations right.
And in fact if you like to think this way
it's a very good way to think.
It says, that what it means is that we'll
be messing around with
sets that are described generally by
expression trees.
They'll be an expression tree.
They'll be your set, and you'll go down
the expression tree.
The leaves will be atoms.
They'll be things.
Known that can change too right?
I mean, you, but it will basically these
will be things known to be convex.
And then at every note in the tree there
will be some operation that
preserves convexity.
Everybody following this?
So, or if you like to think of it, I mean
it's like a calculus.
Okay, and we're going to look, we'll look
at some of these things.
Some of these are kind of obvious, some
are not, and
we are going to hit some ones that are not
obvious today, so at least then you can
say in a first lecture it is not true that
you didn't hear anything.
It's not true that you didn't learn
anything.
Okay, alright so the first one is
intersection, right, so
intersection of any number, finite number,
infinite number,
uncountable number of convex sets is
convex, right?
By the way these things need to be shown.
That's a two liner or something like that.
I'm not going to do it.
I would recommend that you sit down and
you know show some of these.
So let's look at an example...
Here it is, S is going to be the set of
vectors in Rm for which this polynomial p
of t, which is going to depend on x, we'll
get that in a second.
Now, this polynomial p of t is less than
one for the, for
t absolute value less than or higher than
number 3, the p is this.
It's this it is a trig is so-called
trigonometric polynomial,
partial Fourier series, whatever you
want to call it, okay?
So there it is.
That's that's what this is, right?
Some periodic function with I guess up to
m, you know m, m plus 1,
you know Fourier coefficients or something
like that, right?
There it is.
So.
That's it.
In other words I'm going to identify with
each vector in RM,
well, a trigonometric polynomial, right.
That's it.
I didn't put constants in here but who
cares so okay.
So that, that's it.
And what this says is it is...
The set of all coeffi-, points in
coefficient space,
because that's really what R superscript m
is now.
It's the point of coefficient space where
the corresponding polynomial,
if you plotted it here that between, I
mean, 0 and pi over 3,
it's between negative 1 and 1.
That's the picture.
Everybody got it?
Okay, now you might ask a question like
this.
You might want to actually because of your
training you might want to right,
if you have this 19th century mathematics
training otherwise known as
the training we now give all our students.
But if you are trained in that you'll have
this urge to look at this and
try to write out some secret.
Lets work out what is S, lets write down
some formulas for S.
Right, let's, let's try to figure it out
OK, well and you can do that for
m equals to 1, 2, 3.
By the way, abou-, about m equals 5,
its impossible, there is no formula for it
right.
That, that it I mean, that that comes from
Gauss's theorem about polynomials and
things like that.
So, so this, basically there is no formula
for this for m equals 10,
there is no formula for it.
There is no way to write down this is true
if and
only if x satisfies the following things,
right.
Okay so, that's not quite true, I, I
misspoke there, it doesn't matter.
So it, anyway, its fantastically
complicated okay?
So.
Alright so and so first lets check of its
convex and
the first thing is to just make sure that
on an intuitive level we all agree.
So what we are, what we are saying
inconvexity is something like this,
what we are saying is that if you have two
points lets call it x and
y is correspond to polynomials lets say p
and q.
And so what we're saying and by the way
you don't have to check for
theta, all theta's between 0.
And what it's good enough to show for
theta equals a half.
If you can show it for theta equals a half
you got it right.
So that's with I mean you don't need about
a set to say the following.
So say it's convex if and only if.
It's closed under averaging, averaging two
points nothing more, okay?
You do, you do need a little bit more but
that's getting into weird analyses, okay?
So, but let's see what that's saying.
It's saying that if I have two
polynomials, here's one, right?
And here's another one.
Let's see, here's, here's another one.
And there both in that set because on the
region 0 pi over 3 you're value is
between you know plus and
minus 1 and now we form the average of the
coefficients but when you form the average
of the coeffients you're actually forming
the average of the polynomial.
And the average of the polynomial indeed
is between minus 1 and
1 on that little interval and so it's in
the set.
Everybody got that?
That says this set s, is convex.
And when m equals 10 or
something like that it means we don't have
a very good way to describe s.
We don't, there's not an explicit way to
say this is what it means to be an s.
I mean there is one but we'll see it later
in the class right.
It's really complicated.
Right.
So, so the idea is it can be easy to
verify convexity even if
you don't have a simple discription of the
set.
That's actually a very important thing to
know.
Right because it, in fact that's going to
be fantastically useful.
That, this idea, okay.
So here's, heres a super quick proof of
it.
It's really simple.
It goes like this.
What I do is I'm going to introduce s sub
t.
And that's going to be the set of x n r m.
For which pft is less than one, okay.
So that's, that's St, yeah, notice it,
it's just a single point, that's a,
and I want you to tell me, so that's,
that's for each T, I get this set.
I want you to tell me, what is that set,
what does it look like.
It's an intersection of 2 half spaces
right.
Because this P of T is a linear function
of X's right?
It's just,
it's actually just the inner product of
cosine T cosine 2 T that vector of X.
So it's a linear function.
That says a linear lye's between 1 and
minus 1.
Linear fucntion less than 1 that's a half
space.
A linear function bigger than minus 1
that's a half space actually oriented
the other way and what it says is that is
a slab.
That is the correct term for that.
It's a slab.
It's the intersection of 2 parallel half
spaces with opposite orientation.
Okay, that's a slab.
And what that says is I can write s this
way.
S is the intersection over an uncountable
number, you know?
But you know, you know not to get bent out
of shape over that, it's this.
Right, so it's, it's that, it's the
intersection of those slabs, and
here is the picture, so here is s, and you
can see it, it's got some curvature if you
look in there, and what these lines show
is for each, for sets of some values of t,
maybe 20 values or t or 10 or something
like that...
What we've done is we've actually just
plotted the 2 slides now when the slab.
When T ranges between 0 and pi over 3 that
slab it rotates and it width changes.
Right.
And it says if you take an intersection
over all of
the slabs the inside is what's left.
That's gives you the set S okay.
So that's alright so just that's the idea.
Okay.
We'll look a couple more of these
operations.
Affine function.
So an affine fucntion is linear plus an
offset.
Alright, hmm and by the way some people
call this linear but
I hope only in informal context.
If you are with people you know very well
on stuff like that, you can,
you can do this right in [INAUDIBLE] but
its not linear its affine OK.
So it turns out that affine mappings they
preserve convexity both,
in both directions for mapping and
reverse.
And here again this is a standard
mathematical notation, but
it is something we should go over.
If I have a function then I can overload
that function to take as
argument as set and what it means here is
the following.
Its says its so
here f of S is the set of all things of
the form f of x where x is in S, right.
So that's, that's absolutely universal
standard notation to
overload a function to root.
So I could talk about a function and I
could say what is the, what,
I could ask about what is the function of
say a unit ball or a polyhedron.
And the answer is some set.
It's the, all the values or something.
Right?
Now the inverse image is also is, is also
absolutely standard notation and
it is not maybe what you'd think.
Okay, so there's two ways to parse that,
and I'll, I'll explain what they are,
to interpret it.
So one way is to simply take the inverse
function, F inverse, and, and is, and
say that it's a f, it's something of this
form.
So you take this inverse function and then
it's the same as that.
But, in fact, the inverse image of a set
under a function is
defined even when that function is not one
to one with, by the way,
there is the case, that function does not
have an inverse.
So this is defined, f inverse of c is
defined for a set.
Even in cases when f is not invertible, so
f inverse the function does not even
exist, f inverse the relation does.
Okay, so and it's simply defined this way.
It is the set of points that map into the
set, right?
So if that's your set C then you just
simply apply f and if you land in the set,
in fact let me have them land at the same
point, there you go,
then these two points are in f inverse of
c.
And notice that they both land, they both
have the same value of f and
therefore f is obviously not invertible.
Right but this f this notation does work.
And by the way, when the two contexts
agree they are consistent,
right that's required of notation, right,
that if you have ambiguous notation it
must be the case that when two contexts
overlap, that you get the same,
you assign the same semantics, right and
that, that's correct, okay.
So, so affine functions preserve convexity
Both forward and reverse.
So images and inverse images.
Okay?
And that's and again, you have to show
this.
But let's look at some examples.
Well, some are obvious, right?
If you scale a set.
If I multiply it by 2 or 3 or minus 5.
That, that, that's going to preserve
convexity.
If I translate it, if I move it here,
that's going to do.
I mean, another one of course is if I
rotate it and stuff like that.
If I project it.
If I take a set which is an R10 and
I simply look at the first five components
of it.
Right, so Or, well, let's, let's do an R3.
I take a three dimensional object and I'll
only look at X1,
X2 which is basically the same as waking
it's shadow, on that,
on that plane, then that's going to become
fixed.
That's kind of obvious, right, that the
shadow cast by a convex set in R3.
Is convex.
That's the convex set in R 2.
Okay here's one, this is something we'll
see, you know,
fairly often, it's called a linear matrix
inequality, and so it says this,
I have a bunch of matrices A1 through AM,
I form the sum of xi times ai, right?
And I say that's less than or equal to b,
where b is a matrix, a symmetric matrix.
This is in a matrix sense, right?
And the idea is this is supposed to look
like linear inequality.
Right?
Written out, right?
An ordinary, if the a's were lower case B
was a number and
that squiggly was an ordinary inequality.
Oh, by the way, if the two notations would
match up then it would be the same thing,
then that would be a half space.
But here it's the,
it's defined by matrix inequalities,
that's called a linear matrix inequality.
It's convex and the way you know this is
convex is the following.
I'm going to form a function, which is f
Its going to map rm into s sp.
And its going to be this, it's going to be
b minus sum xi, ai.
Okay, so that's, that's my function.
Its affine, that's an affine function and
its inverse image,
the inverse image of that function of the
positive semi-definite cone.
Is this set, is this linear matrix
inequality.
Right because what I'm saying is the set
of x's for [INAUDIBLE] this
thing here is positive semi definite
that's exactly this set here.
I mean you'd have to put something on the
other side but
its the same thing, right and so that,
that tells you that, that's it.
You'd have things like this.
The hyperbolic cone.
That's the set of points where x transpose
px, that's a quadratic form,
is less than some c transpose x squared
and c transpose x is bigger or equal to 0,
that's actually convex because it's the
inverse image of the standard cone,
the nor cone, two norm cone, under an fi
mapping and I,
I won't go into that but I'll let you look
into that...
Okay.
Now we're going to get to something that's
actually different, cause so far,
everything so far is kind of obvious and,
you know, two lines and stuff like to show
everything, now we're going to go up to
something that takes four, so, here it is.
The perspective function.
Is a function that maps, well let's say rn
plus 1.
I mean it could also map rn into rn minus
1.
But let's say it maps rn plus 1 into rn,
and
it's this: it's the perspective function
is p of x and t.
You simply divide the first n elements of
the vector by its last component,
that's called the perspective function.
But it's also called projective I think
in, in,
in some areas right, called projective
mapping.
Okay, and the domain is the half space
where t is positive.
Okay?
So that's what it is.
And it's the effect of sort of normalizing
by the last component, or
something like that.
By the way, it comes up a whole lot more
than you think.
So, okay, so it turns out inverse images
forward And reverse and
inverse images of convex sets under the
perspective mapping are convex,
and that is not obvious at all, okay.
It's true.
It's not hard to show.
Like I said instead of two lines it's
four, okay, but its not obvious, right, so
it says that if you have a, um...
If, if you have an operation that does
this,
it says that if I have a bunch of points
in the convex set, and
then I simply take the first chunk of the
vector divided by the last element.
That makes, that gives me a new set in in
one smaller dimension.
That's convex, okay?
And, it's, it's not obvious, it I don't
think.
So, and a generalization, it's not even a
generalization of it,
if you precompose the persecutive function
with an [UNKNOWN] function you get
something called a linear fractional
function, and that looks like this.
It's a function that's an [UNKNOWN]
divided by [UNKNOWN] and
the denominator scaler, and the domain is
where the scaler is positive...
Right.
The denominator's positive.
So that, that's called a linear fractional
function.
And probably if you've taken a course on
vision, for
example, you would've seen these and maybe
some other things as well.
It comes up in other areas as well.
It's very basic in probability.
This is called conditioning.
Right.
You work out what you do
when you compute a conditional
distribution.
That's what you are doing, you are taking
an,
an offline function in the numerator, and
then denominator, you are normalizing.
You are normalizing [UNKNOWN] by
the probability that said that that's
exactly this.
So, conditioning is also is like a linear
fractional function Okay.
And these these preserve convexity.
Okay.
So, a quick example, is something like
this,
here's one here's a mapping from R2 to R2,
and
the domain is X1 plus X2 plus one is
positive, that's the domain of F, okay?
And, so the domain is everything over here
this, that dash line says, you know,
that's, that's out of the domain.
Right?
So is the line, it's not in the domain
either.
And the image,
it says that the image of a convex set
under this mapping is is convex.
Right?
So.
But then it's kind of boring for me to
show that for example if I showed a circle
here it would be like ellipsoid over here,
so it's kind of boring to show.
But just to give you a rough idea of what
it does, here's a non-convex set and
here's it's image.
And if you look at it carefully, you'll
realize it,
something about it looks very natural.
And then, then you'll understand and it's
a good, it says that,
it tell you why we are all intimately
familiar with perspective and
linear fractional mappings.
This is actually what this looks like on
your retina.
Here's, here's why.
Let's take this set here, and you fly,
let's fly above it, so
let's get, let's put it in 3D so it's
lying down and
you have that shape, whatever it is, c,
and let's fly above it...
Like this and
lets get may be like right you know here,
actually we would be like right here.
Let, lets be there but lets, lets go
couple of 100 meters in the air and
lets look down at it and what would you
see.
You would actually see exactly that, right
and this for shortening right,
cos the this is, these, these, these
correspond to like these things,
the things that are close to you right and
so they're, they are strecthed out.
And the stuff that's in the distance is
shrunk and that's, that's this, right?
And that would actually be sort of the
horizon.
That's that thing.
That's looking way off that's if you look
parallel,
you look way up to the horizon, okay?
So in fact, and if you've had a class on
vision or something like that
you would You, you would know this, that,
that actually what we
see all the time I mean the damage on your
retina is a linear fractional mapping.
Or for that matter the image on a camera
plane is
a linear fractional mapping of well,
neglecting optical aberrations,
is suppose to be a linear fractional
mapping of the 3D Object space.
Okay?
And so what this says is the following.
And it's kind of cool.
It says this.
It says that if you, if an object is
convex in 3-D, then it says that
the image it casts, it, it puts onto your
camera or your retina is, is convex.
Look at one more topic.
And that's generalized inequalities.
So, this is going to be very useful for
us, that is you generalize inequality,
r, to other contexts, and you have all
undoubtably seen this for
example in the context of matrix
inequality, so here it is...
If you have a convex cone in Rn it's
called proper if it satifies a couple
of things.
First of all it's closed in other words
I'll draw one in R2 it
says it's gotta contain, it has to contain
it's boundary elemets okay so it's closed.
Oh the other things it's solid so it has
to have non empty interior right.
So for example this.
That's a cone.
A rate is a cone, right, so rate is just a
point that goes from 0,
goes off in some direction, that's a rate,
and it's a one.
But it is not solid, right.
I really like these terms, right, because
they are very evocative of what I mean, so
solid means it's not, it's not flat...
Or something like that.
It means there's a ball in it..
Okay.
And it's pointed.
Pointed says you don't, it doesn't contain
a line, right?
So for example, a line is a cone, right?
A line is a cone, but there's something, I
mean, technically, it's a cone, and
that's just fine.
It's a cone.
But it's, there's something about it,
because the whole idea of cone for
us is supposed to mean, or it's supposed
to evoke The idea of
something that's asymmetric that it goes
one way but not the other.
Right, so
I mean well that is a cone, when it is not
a proper cone because it's not pointed.
So pointed means that it doesn't contain
any line.
[INAUDIBLE] it says, it says that in any
ray you can't have a ray and
it's negative both in the cone that's what
it says.
Okay, that's, that, that's what pointed
means.
So Here's some examples.
Nonnegative orthant, right?
That's the, that's the, that's the denoted
R plus to the end.
You know, it's a, the set in R2.
Positive semidefinite cone, that's
pointed.
Sorry, that's proper.
Of course, it's pointed.
Nonnegative polynomials.
So there you go.
The set of coefficients of polynomials
that are nonnegative on some interval.
That's a that's a proper cone.
Okay, it's a bit of an obscure one, but it
is one.
Okay, so these are proper cones.
Now when you have a proper cone, you can
make up an inequality out of it.
And the way you do that is really simple.
You simply say That x lesser than equal to
y with respect to the concave, that's how
you read this in English right and its
denoted x squiggly lesser than equal to y,
sub k as with respect to k and that simply
means y minus x is in the cone, right so
this idea of the cone, the cone is
supposed to define your what you
going to call your non negative elements.
So what we do is, armed with this idea of
a cone.
And the cone is going to be, roughly
speaking, our non-negative element.
Oh by the way, here's a really simple
cone, ready?
The set of non-negative numbers, okay?
And that's a proper cone.
I mean it's kind of silly to take an
elementary idea and make it so
complicated, right?
kind of pedantic.
But anyway, that's, that's, that's what
these are supposed to be.
And so then, then you can define an
inequality.
An inequality is defined in the obvious
way,
it says that one thing is less than
another.
Says that the difference is non negative.
And strict inequality means you're in the
interior of the cone, right?
And so for example, if I take the cone as
r plus to the n,
than This inequality here, means simply
that you have componentwise inequality.
It means that each element, I mean,
technically what it means is that y minus
x is in the nonnegative orthant.
Nonnegative orthant is all vectors with
all entries nonnegative.
So, that means this, right?
So, ok.
Matrix inequality.
You've already seen this presumably
somewhere.
It says this, it says that one matrix is
less than another.
You'd say x is less than or
equal to y with the represent to the
positive semi definite cone.
That would be the formal reading of this.
And that means simply that the difference
is positive semi definitive.
But you've seen this before.
You've seen matrix inequality.
Now these two are so common...
That we simply, we drop the subscript.
So if you see two vectors and somebody
writes that or if you see two matrices and
they write that.
I should emphasize the curvature a little
bit more, like that, right?
The default is that the default subscript
that you will fill in is r plus to the n.
And Sn plus here, okay, meaning so if you
see x squiggly y and their vectors,
that means element y's and if their
matrices, it means with respect, if their
symmetric matrices, it means with respect
to positive semidefinite cone, 'kay?
So these are kind of standard.
>> Now when you introduce some notation
like this, you know obviously the point of
introducing notation like that is it's
supposed to evoke.
It's supposed to be like ordinary
inequality.
But ordinary inequality is defined only
for numbers right so
you know when you generalize notation or
something like that or overload it.
The idea is it's supposed to suggest
things that are true, for
the, the original, the, the non
generalized one.
It's supposed to suggest things that are
true in the generalized setting, 'kay.
By the way not everything it suggests will
be true.
So you, you're going to have to be very
careful.
So for example how about this.
It says that if x is less than or equal to
y with respect to a cone and
u is less than v then You know, x plus u
is lesser or equal to y plus u.
By the, by the way, you have to, you have
to check this.
I mean, I'm not, you know, I'm allowed to
just say this but
then you should take random ones of these
and just check that it's true, all right?
So so And it kind of makes sense, right?
You know, one number is less than another,
another number is less than another,
then the sum of these 2 is less than the
sum of those 2.
I mean, okay.
Fine.
Right?
So, so that, that's, that's true.
Okay.
I'll tell you what is,
there're some things that are not true.
Here's one.
Here's something true for numbers.
For any 2 numbers x and y, either x is
less than or equal to y, or
y is less than or equal to x.
That's a, that's true for numbers.
And by the way that's got a name for a
ordering, a partial ordering.
That's called a total ordering a linear
ordering if, and so
if you've seen this in some class
somewhere, great.
So that, that's what it means.
But, in general you don't have that.
And in fact that's what it means I guess
in general to be a partial ordering.
So we can actually have cases where one
vector is not less than another,
in which case, well I'll say something in
a minute and
the other vector is not less than the
other one, in which case we say that x and
y are incomparable, that's one name for
it, right?
And you don't have that on r with ordinary
inequality.
>> You can't say, you know, 12.6 and minus
2.3 and say No, I'm sorry.
They're, they're incomparable.
They're.
Neither is bigger than the other.
I mean, it's silly.
Right?
But this already happens.
I mean, I, obviously it happens for
vectors immediately.
In fact somebody give me a pair of
incomparable vectors,
with respect to the order, the ordering
generated by say, r plus 2.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Thank you.
So there you go.
2,1.
And 1, 2.
And it is, this is false, right, and this
is false, right, and so
they're just incomparable.
Okay and what happens then is this, and
you're going to have to get use to this,
it's actually going to play a big role in
the course.
And it's, I mean it's a very basic thing,
so you have to think through all this.
It's going to, it actually quite
interesting, it's this.
What happens when you go from a linear
ordering or
total ordering to partial ordering is the
following.
By the way a lot of things you think are,
are still true.
But the one thing that happens that's
really interesting is your idea of
minimum, or smallest or something like
that.
It splits into two different concepts.
That's what happens.
And so, they're called minimum and
minimal, and
it just says it's a much more complicated
idea.
And let's see why.
I mean there's actually other things in
between, but let's look at them, and
by the way, we're not doing this for the
math.
You'll see that,
you'll see later that this has all sorts
of like real implications.
so, a minimum element, you say you have a
set S,
then A minimum element is defined to be
this.
It is a point in the set like this, you
would say that x is the minimum element if
it is comparable to every other element in
this set and it's smaller than or
equal to it.
That, that's what it means to be the
minimum element, and yes it's unique.
But that's easy to show, actually.
Because you know if x, you have x less
than x and the other way around so,
okay, okay that's the idea of a minimum.
A minimal element is going to be this.
It says that a point in a set is a minimal
element...
if the following holds.
It says that if you're in the set and
you're less than or
equal to that point, then you're equal to
the point, right?
Now you can rewrite this.
There's other definitions of minimal.
You can rewrite it and stuff like that,
and right now this utterly context free so
it means nothing.
But later this will You'll actually
realize it's actually quite useful and
quite important, right, that the, this
idea and just to,
just to start getting the idea in your
mind now for what, what the difference is,
geometrically, it's this.
Let's look an example, the cone is with
respect to R plus 2 and so
what that means is, we have points here
and what it says is if that's, for
example, x These are all the points that
are bigger than or equal to x, right.
And these are all the points that are less
than or equal to x in this cone.
And what are these points here?
Incomparable, right?
So these are all the points, these are the
points that are incomparable with x.
Right.
It is,
it is neither true that x is less than or
equal to them or
that they are less than or equal to x.
Okay, so.
Minimum says the following, it says that
if you are in s
than you must be comparable to it and
bigger than or equal to it.
And that says that the set s has to lie
sort of like, like that.
Right.
It says, it's, so it's, it's over here.
And it's in, it's, that's the point.
X.
Right.
So that's this picture.
So here, X1, is, and it's unique.
It is the unique minimum of S1.
Okay.
Now that's, that's, that's kind of the
natural generalization of minimum.
Which makes perfect sense.
Right.
It's going to turn out one
that's actually much more useful is
actually this, is minimal.
Minimal is this.
Here's a set, S.
It has no minimum point.
There is no minimum there.
There's no point in that set that is
comparible to every other point in
the set and less than or equal to it.
There's, there is, it doesn't exist.
But what there are is there are minimal
points, and a minimal point is this.
It says that if you're, if you're here.
It says that if you're in the set and
you're comparable to it, right?
Then you cannot be less than x without
being x.
That came out really long and weird but
you, you got the idea, right?
So, so what that says is the following.
It says if you draw The set of points down
here,
which are the points comparable to x, and
less than or equal to x.
It say that the intersection of this set
and s2, the only possible point is x2.
That's what it says.
Okay?
And so
that says that every point on this face
here.
Is minimal, okay?
How about any other, I mean the other,
there's no other point that's going to,
right?
Because to check of a point is minimal,
you take the point and
you draw this set that goes left and down
and you intersect that with the set.
And if you get anything other than a
singleton, which is the corner,
then it's not minimal.
So the seperating hyperplane theorem,
it's Quite straight forward geometrically
it's extremely intuitive,
it says the following, if you have two
convex sets, say like D and C, and
they're disjoint then it say that you can
actually put a hyperplane in between them.
Okay, so that, that's, that's a statement
and or, another way to say it is Or
if you have taken a course on machine
learning or something like that.
You can say that there is a linear
classifier that will distinguish C and D.
Again, that is if you have taken a machine
learning course.
What it says is there is an affine
function or
linear function like A transpose X.
And that liner function is less than or
equal to B here.
And it is more than or equal to B On d.
So there's a sort of little linear class
of fire.
By then we'll talk about these things
later in the course.
But this is the idea.
And I think last time I,
it's kind of clear how this would fail if
c and d were not convex, right?
That you would have that you would have
disjoint non
convex sets that cannot be seperated.
By hyperplane.
Okay, and there are many variations on
this,
variations that talk about strict
separability.
Strict separability is you replace these
inequalities with a strict inequalities.
And these require additional conditions
and so on.
And this brings us to the supporting
hyperplane here and
this says the following First of all a
supporting hyper plane this is
something we'll see a bunch of times but
the basic idea is you have a set and
then you have a hyper plane that touches
it at a point.
Um,and has that touches it but doesn't go
into it right.
So that, that's called supporting it.
I guess the idea is it's like the contact
point and if you orient it
the right way it could actually be a force
that would hold or something against.
Another force like gravity.
So that's a supporting hyperplane.
This is a picture of what a supporting
hyperplane looks like, right?
So here you would say that this hyperplane
supports C at x0.
So that's the idea.
Another way to say it is there is a linear
inequality or
it's a half space which does not intersect
or many ways to say it.
It's a point on the boundary of C.
And there's a half space that contains C.
See that's one way to say it.
so that's a supportive hyper time.
This is easy to say to say the following.
If a set is convex, then their existence
supporting hyper plane and
you apply it to two things.
If you have a x zero boundary.
Of the set c.
Then you simply apply to, and c is convex
you apply it the separating hyperplane
theorem to the following two sets, x0 and
the interior of c.
Okay, so you'd take these are both convex
sets,
they are disjoint well that's just one
point, x0 is not in here.
Is in the boundary and you apply the
separating hyper plane theorum.
One thing I want to talk about.
This will come up a lot more in the future
right now it probably makes very
little sense but we might as well just get
the definition out there.
And you'll see it's going to play a very
big role later in the course.
And it's the idea of a dual cone.
So if I have a cone K.
And you can imagine a cone as looking
something like that.
Right?
That's a -- that's a cone.
That's, that's the point 0 here.
That's a cone.
And the dual cone, then, is the set of
vectors that make a non-negative inner
product with every element of this cone.
Okay?
So that's the, that's the idea.
And so to evaluate if a point is in the
dual cone, let's just check.
So here If I ask is this point y in the
dual cone.
If this is k, then what we do is we look
at the following.
these, this half space here,
that's the set of points that make a non
negative inner product with y.
Right, its this, its this half space here.
Okay and you can see that in fact every
element of k is in it.
That says that this point y is definitely
in k star.
Okay.
That's in k star.
Now a point like this here lets lets call
that y
[INAUDIBLE] that's not in k star and the
reason is, well.
Well, it's, it's quite emphatically not in
k star, right, because in
fact there are tons of points in k that
make an inner product with y tilde.
Okay, so that's the picture.
So if you wanted to draw for
example the dual cone of something that
looked like this if his is k.
What you'd do is you'd go out, this point
is right on the boundary, right?
Because here if you look at the non
negative, the,
the points that have a non negative inner
product with y.
If this is why, it's this half space and
you can see that's just barely touching k.
If I were to push this just a few degrees
to the left it would be outside k star.
That's the boundary of k star.
That's one, and then the other is this.
I would go out that way, where it, where
it's just about to pull out of there, so
this here, this thing would be k star...
Okay, this example already suggest some
interesting things which is
generally true of like dual relationships.
So here what you can see is kind of
something like this.
If k is kind of thin and sharp.
Then k star is thick and blunt and you can
kind of see that, that's the picture here.
This also suggests, by the way, that k
star is, is k, right?
And in fact, whenever someone says dual or
conjugate or, I mean there's several words
in mathematics that kind of
give you the hint That if you do it twice,
you end up back where you started.
Right transpose, adjoint, dual, conjugate.
All these kinds of things.
Now of course it's not always true right.
There might be conditions but
these are the thigns that are hinted by
just that language.
Alright so, and we'll see a lot more about
this later.
So here's some examples.
Let's take the nonnegative orthant.
There it turns out the dual cone is
exactly the nonnegative orthant, so
what it says that's called self dual.
It means that it's dual as it's self.
Oh, and by the way in terms of angle, and
bluntness, and
sharpness, it basically says that a 90
degree.
Something like a cone that's 90 degrees.
Is actually self dualed.
Right, because actually that 90 degree
cone is right on
the boundary between blunt and sharp.
Right, so this kind of makes sense.
This also turns out, I mean someone has to
show this.
But what this basically says is the
following,
it says that a vector is now negative, if
and only if,
it makes a non negative interproduct with
all non negative vectors.
But you have to parse all that, but when
you do,
you'll realize it's actually correct.
Okay.
Another one is the count of positive semi
definite matrices.
Now there I've to say what the inner
product is and the inner product is
this if X and Y are symmetric matrices
there's lots of ways to say it but
one is trace X Y and that is absolutely
nothing but the following.
Right, its, its, its the sum, its, its
basically.
Vec of X transpose vec of Y.
Right?
Where I simply write out the,
I write out the matrices as vectors.
Okay?
So that's the inner product.
The standard inner product on, on
symmetric matrices.
And this says, now this is less obvious,
this is self-dual.
It says.
It says that a matrix is positive semi
definite if and only if it's trace against
all positive semi definite matrices is non
negative, so that's what this is saying.
It's a non trivial statement.
It's not hard to show, I mean if you know
a little bit about linear algebra you can
show this, so it's not hard to show,
but...
It's actually saying something, so
what I'm saying is that little formulas
like that pack a lot of
meaning into a very small number of ASCII
characters, okay, as, as usual.
Okay.
A couple of others.
Things like norm cones.
Here is the Laurence cone, or the cone
associated with the, um...
With the euclidean norm and that cone is,
is, is also it's own dual, right?
So that's the same thing.
And here's the l1 norm cone.
And that, the dual of that is in fact the
the norm cone
associated with the infinity norm, okay?
And again, that's something you should not
be surprised about.
I mean these, you should expect these
things.
Okay.
Now if you have a duel cone, of that, if
you have, if you have a duel cone of
a proper cone that's going to be proper as
well and then it defines inequality.
So you can talk now about a vector being
non-negative in the duel inequality.
And what it means is this, this is just,
basically, just shorthand, it says the
following.
This, to be nonnegative in the dual
inequality simply says,
you make an inner product which is
nonnegative for any vector in the cone.
So that, that's a, it's basically
[INAUDIBLE] for saying that, okay?
So that's the again, none of these has any
context right now but it, it will.
Well there's a connection between minimum,
minimal elements.
These are, remember these are the two
extreme ideas of minimizing something in,
in with a vector inequality.
And one is this.
If you have a minimum element, that's
characterized the following.
If you have a minimum element it's
characterized this way.
If you take any dual positive vector,
if you minimize lambda transpose z over
the set.
You always get the minimum element.
Remember, minimum elements are unique.
That's it.
That's, that's one way and we'll, we'll
come back to this later.
It will tell you that you can get a
minimum element, well,
if you're solving optimization problems,
you just minimize any,
actually any non-negative com, linear
combination of the element sub z and
that will give you That will give the
minimum element.
Minimal element goes something like this.
If you minimize a the inner produce lamba
transpose Z where lamba is dual positive,
then you're guaranteed the result's
minimum.
And so the picture would be something,
like this.
Lets take, R, plus, 2.
Right?
So that's this cone.
And of course what that means is, that to
be, less than or equal to a point or
something like that is everything down and
to the left.
That, that, that's less, that's what it
means to be less than or
equal to in this cone.
Now minimal is basically this, this edge
here.
These are all minimal because if I take
any of those points and
I put something like this here it only
intersects S at that point.
So those are all minimal points.
This this, this one portion of the
boundary are the minimal points for
this set S.
And what this says is, take any lambda
that's positive and the dual cone of R
plus 1 is R plus 2 so it says take any 2
positive lambda 1 lambda 2 so
you take a take a lambda that points you
know somewhere like that.
And it says minimize lamba transpose Z
that means basically,
to go as far as you can.
That's lamba in this direction and
you'll find the basically a point of
contact here.
That which is minimum okay and that's the
picture okay.
This is the first glimpse at this and no
more.
Okay so lets just look at an application
of this and
if you've taken economics you've maybe
seen this.
So I have something that I
want to build and produce.
And that takes different resources and
here I've drawn in two variables,
it's kind of silly, it's with like fuel
and labor, right.
So I can, I can use more fuel or I can use
more labor.
And then every point here, this is called
the production set P,
gives you a possible method for producing
that product.
Right, so and in fact there could be so
theoretically I mean in
principle every single shaded point here
actually should be tagged or along with it
should be a method for, a full description
for how you should make that product.
And in fact this is how much fuel that
method uses and
this is how much labor that uses.
Okay.
So that's the that's the idea of
production set.
Now the idea is end and we do this in our
end where you would have end resources.
And here we're going to use the assumption
all these resources are valuable.
In other words all of them you don't want
to waste any of them or
anything like that.
So, in that case, it turns out minimal has
the obvious meaning.
A minimal point in the production set is
exactly, and that's with respect to r
plus to the n, a minimal point is one
where It doesn't intersect this thing and
that's good, it means that there is no
other method for
producing that product that uses, or the
only, if there is another method that uses
no more of each resource, then you're back
to that method, right?
So that's what it means or another way to
say it is,
if someones says I'm going to operate my
factory here There would be other.
That means the technical terms it's non
minimal and another technical term for
this would be stupid.
Right would be the other one because it
basically.
Look any of the other points here are
methods for
doing exactly the same thign with less.
For example this point here.
Does exactly the same thing, it uses the
same amount of fuel, but
less labor, right?
And under the assumption that all of these
are valuable, that's worse.
Okay?
So that's the picture.
Now our prescription here tells us that a
way to find a minimal point is to
take some thing that's dual positive.
Minimize that linear function over over
the set, so
what it says is, you should minimize
lambda transpose X.
Here lamda is a set of positive numbers
and
effect to have a perfect interpretation.
These are prices, right, lamda1 is the
price resource 1 and
lamda2 is the price of resource 2.
And it says, set any prices you like.
Man - find the most - now, find the
cheapest production method, right?
So you find the cheapest production method
of those prices, and what's guaranteed is
that, that production point is minimal, or
I guess they call it "efficient".
Pareto Optimal is another name for it.
We're going to come back to all of these,
by the way, later in the course.
So, this is just a glimpse at these ideas.