Here, what this is is the following.
Is we have, I mean, this is a very simple
thing.
We actually have, it's a two dimensional
ellipsoid.
I guess you might even call it an ellipse
or something like that, of A matrices.
You commit to x, and then we find the,
we'll find like the worst integral that
we'll actually plot here, is the histogram
of the residuals.
Right?
Now, here we'll take uniformly distributed
on the unit disk, okay?
And we'll take several values of x.
The first is, suppose you just completely
ignore uncertainty and
you solve the least squares problem,
minimize A0x minus b.
That's the nominal problem.
You minimize that and you get this
distribution of residuals.
Right?
So they're all over the place.
And You know, some, some of the residuals
are 4 and 5.
And, by the way, how do you,
how would you describe what happens in
this situation over here on the left?
Dumlock, that's exactly what it is, right?
You commit it to an x and in fact there
are As
that make the residuals than you thought
it was going to be.
Okay, so that's just dumlock but you pay
for it over here.
Okay.
Now you turn on Taken Off Regularization.
And you can even imagine.
I mean, one could even make a cartoon of
this.
Right?
You can
imagine turning the Taken Off
Regularization knob.
When it's 0, you get this distribution.
Okay, as I turn it up, what happens is
that distribution will,
will end up looking like this.
This is sort of the best looking one, the
Taken Off Regularization one.
And you can see it did exactly what it was
supposed to do.
Right?
Taken off regularization is something like
heuristic for, it's a heuristic for giving
you a robust solution and
you can see, and here robustness, we're
going to make it very vague,
you get a tighter distribution of
residuals, okay?
And in fact, the expected value of this
distribution is smaller than this one.
I mean, I'm not going to work it out
because it's too simple here.
But, you can see its simply, from robust
point of view, a better solution.
Okay?
So,
this shows exactly what people have known
for, I don't know,
50-100 days that you had regularization
and one interpretation for
regularization is to make your solution
more robust variation here.
Okay, now the exact robustly squares.
The one that minimizes the worst case
residual over this, over this ellipsoid of
matrices is the one you have attained by
solving this this stp here.
Right?
So, you solve that stp there and
you get the following distribution of
residuals, its right here and
this is right there, that is, that's the
number.
Right?
That, that is the optimal,
that is the globally optimal number for
the best you can do.
That is kind of the idea, and I think
these distributions explain everything.
Right?
About what you're trying to do here,
and and what robust optimization does.
Right, so this is the kind, this is, this
is the idea.
Notice that when you I mean we can
anthropomorphize this a little bit,
one thing interesting to notice is all of
these, everything over here in either
the Tikhonov regular rise, or the nominal
solution.
All of those are cases,
where by dumb luck, you did better than
the robustly squares.
Right.
so, and what's interesting though is,
when you typically push the worse case
residual down.
Usually an affect is that actually the
best case actually [LAUGH] goes
the other way.
Right?
And I mean, this is sort of natural, but.
And, and again, what I'm saying now is
extremely vague.
These are not the arguments you would be
allowed to make.
In public but its just something to point
out.
So, now we move on to another section.
It's going to be
a world wind tour of some interesting
problems in statistical estimation.
As with these other lectures, there is
actually much more.
We expect you to read all of it.
Skim it all.
Homework will cover other things.
But we'll look at [COUGH] some of the big,
big picture questions here.
And, we'll look at some interesting
examples.
So we'll start with the idea of Parametric
distribution estimation.
Though any, I mean this is at the
[INAUDIBLE] absolute core of statistics.
So wait until so if you have, I mean,
well, there's several.
We won't look at the non-parametric case,
we'll look at the parametric case.
The, the parametric case is this, is that
you have a, you have observed
a variable, an outcome, of a random
variable, but it came, you don't know
which distribution in came from, and you
have a parameterized set of distributions.
So this is kind of the basic starting
point in standard classical
frequentist statistics.
So, so this, this is the idea.
So you have a parameterized family of
distributions and
it's parameterized will you, the parameter
will call x, okay.
So yeah.
This notation does not exactly conform to
standard statistics notation.
I guess it would be theta or something
like this, right?
But, that's fine.
okay.
Now.
An absolutely standard method for
estimating which distribution generated
the actual observed outcome, y, is maximum
likelihood estimation.
And what that says is, you take, you take
your observation.
That's y.
You plug this in to the density.
It doesn't have to, I mean, it could also
be a discrete probability, but,
density, whatever you like, right, here.
And you consider this function as a
function of
the parameter that parameterizes the
family of distributions, right?
And that's called a likelihood function.
And in fact, usually people take the log.
It doesn't matter if you're maximizing.
And so if you choose x by solving this
problem,
that's maximum likelihood estimation.
Right so, and if you take a statistics
course,
you'll hear all about why this is a good
idea, you know,
in some cases asymptotically optimal and
all that kind of stuff.
So this l of x.
That's going to be the log likelihood
function, and
you can add constraints on, on that, and a
lot times they're implicit.
You know, for example.
X, the parameter might include something
like a co-variants metrix,
that's right because your, your, for
example your family might be Gaussian or
something like that.
And, so the mean and co-variants might be
the parameter plus they characterizes it
and they of course, the parameter,
the co-response of the co-variants
obviously has to be positive depth, right?
These could, and there could be then what
you do is, yet
that's the domain of the likelihood
function, and
you would simply make something, one, one
simple way is to simply say that
this is 0 there, because then log of it is
minus infinity, right?
So, and that's infinitely bad if you're
maximizing.
So that's one.
Okay.
Now.
The maximum likelihood estimation problem,
that's convex.
If the log likelihood is concave That, but
this is, by the way,
this is different for a log concave
distribution which we've looked at before.
This is, this is log concave in the
parameters that describe
the family of distributions.
Now, if you know about exponential
families,
then these two coincide, because there's
actually only,
they're both involved in exp of an inner
product, and then a normalizing constant.
So if you know what I'm talking about,
fine.
If you don't, Don't worry about it.
Okay, but, but its a different concept.
The concept here is, is the log likelihood
function
concave in the parameters that describe
the distribution?
Actually something very interesting's
going to happen.
In a lot of cases you'll have the, you'll,
you'll sort of have what you think are the
natural parameters for distribution.
And sure enough it will be log concave in
those parameters.
Well, we're going to see examples very
shortly.
Right?
But actually in other cases something
really cool is going to happen.
You look at the log concave, you'll look
at the log likelihood function as
a function of what you though were the
natural parameters, and
guess what, won't be concave.
It just won't be.
Give us an example.
Let's estimate the mean and covariance of
a Gaussian that generated the sample.
What could be simpler?
Okay?
Well it turns out in
the log likelihood function, in sigma and
mu, is not concave.
But it's going to turn out, you just got
to change your variables and it will be.
Not if you had enough machine learning and
statistics.
You'll understand that the correct, it, it
will not be a shock to you that
the correct branders there are like sigma
inverse and sigma inverse mu, okay.
These, these are actually more natural,
right, than sigma and mu.
So, again, this is a bit more advanced
than I want to be at this point,
but just, just to mention to those people
who know about these things, right.
And it turns out those are precisely the
parameters in an ex,
in an exponential model.
So, okay.
Okay.
So, oh, and I should say all of this
material.
I mean, you know, your, our goal here is
just to
go over something interesting things that
you have never seen the stuff before.
Some of the stuff we are going to about,
that's going to be super simple and
completely accessible.
And if you have, you know some PHD level
courses in statistics or machine learning.
Then they'll be a little bit added stuff
and I'm going to mention some of
that stuff like I just did some of the
more advanced stuff just for fun.
Okay.
So let's start with a very simple set up.
Let's do linear measurement models.
So here, x is a vector of unknown
parameters and
we have linear measurements so we have y,
i.
Is a, it's a scaler, it's a linear
function of x plus a noise, right?
And so and by the way, this is a good
point to stop and
talk about sort of just, I mean it's, it
doesn't make any difference at all,
but sort of the philosophical way you
would regard the setup, right.
So if you're in something like signal
processing or
something like that, you would say This
says, I mean,
your, your view of the world is, you know,
this gives you the ideal measurement.
If your measurements were perfect, they're
not perfect.
And vi is sort of like an added noise,
right.
So this is your corrupted or real or
whatever you like to call it measurement.
Okay, and that would be the view from
someone who does signal processing or
something like that, right?
That, if you had, if you were to, if you
were to do something like get
a perfect sensor and run this experiment
at, like, 0 or 0.01 degree Kelvin,
right, so there's no thermal noise or
whatever else that comes from.
Then, in fact, you'd get y i equals a i
transpose x.
Right?
You don't, since you don't do those
things, the i is a noise.
Right?
So,
a statistician would say the following.
They would look at that and they would
say, x is a, y comes from a distribution.
Right?
It's a distribution,
because that's a random variable right
there, the vi.
Those are random variables.
They would say, so y comes from a
distribution.
And you say, well, what distribution does
it come from?
And the answer is, well, it depends on
what x is.
So, x here is, is a parameter that descri,
that tells you which distribution
generated y, right?
So, I don't know if this is making.
I, at the end of the day, you end up doing
the same things with this.
But it is actually just interesting to sit
for
a minute, and think about the different
views of what y equals ax plus v can mean.
Okay, so, and so there's nothing deep in
this.
I'm just saying these are the two views.
Okay.
Now what you, what you do here is, is
this, is why has, and
I'm going to assume that the vi are IID
here, with some density p of z.
If you, if you, if x has the value x, or
if the parameter has the value x,
then the distribution, the density of y,
is this, right?
It's the product, because they're
independent, and
y i minus a i transpose x is, well, that's
exactly v i.
Right?
So, and then, that, these are the, that's
the value that v i had, and
you simply take the product of the
densities, because it's independent,
to get the density of Of, of y the vector,
right, so that's that's the idea.
By the way, other people would call
something like this the residual.
And the residual here is in fact nothing
but the noise.
So that's another way to, to think of to
think of this.
Okay, so the maximum likelihood solution
says.
Here, if you want to estimate x by maximum
likelihood, what you do,
is we'll form the, we'll max, we'll
maximize the log that this product, but
that's the sum, right, and
it tells, gives you a hint as to why the
log is going to come up off it, right.
So, you maximize the sum of the log of the
density of the residual.
Okay?
Now, by the way, if the residuals are,
have a density that, that is sort of
centered around 0, right?
And, and be kind of, if they don't, by the
way,
that means it's sort of a known offset and
that's a bit silly, right?
But if, if they do, what that says is, you
know, these are functions that are kind of
centered, this function is sort of
centered around 0.
And then it kind of goes off.
Right?
It, it's a concave function that tails off
after that.
That's actually quite interesting because
this is, this is actually a penalty.
This is penalty approximation, right?
Is exactly minimizing a sum of a function
a, a, which,
which we previously called penalties, it's
a penalty approximation method.
But here the penalty is specifically,
the negative log likelihood if you convert
this to a minimization problem.
Everybody got this?
So, so in other words, where you might
just say, that's the penalty, and
then give a story about your penalty
function in terms of how much it
irritates you to have a big residual, a
small residual, you know,
medium sized residual, all this kind of
stuff.
A negative versus a positive residual,
that would be your discussion of why
you're using a certain penalty.
It says that all of that can be transposed
perfectly to a statistics framework, and
there, instead of saying something like,
it irritates me to have,
a positive residual is more irritating
than a negative residual.
What you're really saying is something
about the distribution,
the density, of the noise.
Okay?
So let's look at some examples.
Here's one.
Suppose these noises are Gaussian.
Well then, if I take the negative log
likelihood, I get this, right?
So that, that, that, sorry, that's the log
likelihood.
And, it's this, that's a constant.
And when I'm maximizing over x, it doesn't
matter.
This constant's irrelevant, and I'm
maximizing this thing,
well there's a negative sign here, so I
can just minimize this thing.
That doesn't matter, because it's a
positive constant.
So I can minimize, hey, that's just least
squares.
Okay, so now you know Lee Squares is
nothing but it is exactly maximum
likelihood estimation under the assumption
that the noises are Gaussian.
If you say get the square and say what
does that mean?
You say well it means if the residual is
small,
I mean it's fine with me because its sort
of small squared.
But if it's big, that's not so good.
What this says is that corresponds exactly
to statistical model with
Gaussian noise because you have Gaussian
noise and you say if something is
less than one sigma like say fine okay no,
that's entirely plausible.
Right.
Whereas if something was like six sigma or
eight sigma you'd look at that and
say hm, that's, that's I mean I can't say
it's impossible, but
it seems very strange, that, that my fit
here or my estimation is
telling me that the parameter that what
I've observed is an eight sigma event.
Everybody see what I am saying here?
So okay.
Let's look at Laplacian noise.
That's noise with a density that is a
double-sided exponential like that.
And it's actually a little bit interesting
to look at that distribution.
Compared to a Gaussian, what can you say
about the tails of a Laplacian
distribution compared to Gaussian?
Much heavier, right?
Because this is like e to the minus
[COUGH] you know, z squared.
This is e to the minus z.
Okay, so it's way bigger tails.
What that says is that the likelihood of,
of big outlier is, well,
I mean it's going down, right?
It's e to the minus z.
But it's way bigger than for a Gaussian.
Everybody following this?
And then, this is a bit of a weird thing
here, right?
This, you have that point there.
And it even says that, something like
this.
I mean that, that's going to tell you
that, the probability of having, of being
a little bit off actually is substantially
reduced from being right at zero.
Everybody, and that,
that's comes now just from probability
from that kink right there.
Okay, so this turns into, guess what?
L1, and it makes perfect sense, because
now if you look at l1.
You, you get both of those things about
what happens for large residuals and
small residuals.
For large residuals, a one charges you
linearly, where as get,
where as least squares charges you
quadratically.
So, it's not you like, it's not like you
expect to have large residuals, but
you don't go nuts as you would if it was
quadratic or worse, right?
And at the, then you focus on small things
small residuals and this says it actually
keeps up the it, it keeps up the incentive
to drive residual to zero, right?
And you can see that exactly here, right
so, so its actually a kind of interesting
that both, both of these could be it can
be, you can interpret both but it's just
from an intuitive description of a penalty
function, abstract penalty function.
Or from the probability, the implied
probability distribution of the, of,
of, of the noise in a, in an additive
noise model.
Let's do uniform noise.
Right?
Well, if you have uniform noise,
then the log likelihood function is well,
it's actually just constant.
And it's, basically, it's a constant
doesn't matter what constant it is,
actually, provided you are consistent with
the measurement.
Right?
And so, there you simply solve a
feasibility problem, and
there are multiple maximum likelihood
solutions, and
you simply choose one that satisfies this,
this condition.
And all of those are maximum likelihood
estimates, right?
By the way, their statistical properties
would not be would, would not all be
equally good, so, because the maximum
likelihood's been used for
maybe 100 years, something like that now.
Is, most of that theory assumes things
like that this
log likelihood function has a unique
maximum or something like that, roughly.
Right, so, and that's not the case here.
Okay.
oh, let's, let me mention just one other
thing.
So here, what this says is that you can
actually go backwards.
You can start from a probability
distribution and
find the penalty, because you just take
the negative log of the distribution.
But you can also go backwards, right.
So for example if, if you decided, if you
discussed with someone in some
fitting problem, what they want, and it's
determined that what they want is
something that looks like this, you know
that's quadratic, and this rises deeply.
You know, I don't know how this would come
up, but it would.
You, you talked them, you'd say what do
you feel about under fitting.
And they'd say, oh, that's, that's bad.
That is not good.
Right?
And, you would say,
how about if you under fit just a little
bit?
No, that's bit, that is not good.
And then say, but what about if you under
fit a lot?
And, you'll say, look because the data has
got weared out, wires and stuff like that.
If there has to be, and I have to under
fit in a couple of my points it, so be it.
I don't want to go nuts over it and that
discussion generates that.
And then you'd say, what if you overfit?
And you say, well, the fact is,
if you overfit a little bit, it doesn't
make any difference at all.
And you say, what about overfitting more?
Then they'd say, well, I don't know.
So anyway, it doesn't matter.
You end up with a story like this.
Right.
We all know this now.
You can translate a little of the story
and description into this.
Okay.
What this says is the following.
It says then if a statistician walks into
the room, and you say, what are you doing,
they don't want to hear a story about your
feelings about over-fitting and
under-fitting and things like that.
They don't want to hear that.
So what you say to them is you say, oh,
excuse me,
I'm doing maximum likelihood estimation.
Right.
This implies a distribution, and the
distribution is very simple.
It's e to the minus this.
Course you have to normalize it, but
that's it.
So you'd say to them, you say, I'm doing
maximum likely es, estimation, and for
this problem, we can even say what it is.
How would you describe this distribution?
Somebody describe it to me.
I mean, in words.
So it's some weird Frankenstein
distribution on the left.
It's got some weird exponential, right.
On the right, it's Gaussian, and in the
middle it's got some uniform phase.
Now, they would think you were weird.
But you, then you turn to the statistician
and
say, no, no, no, we, we've been doing this
for years.
And we know this, this, it looks like
this.
Okay, every, everybody got this?
So the, so it's actually very interesting
that you can justify these from
different points of view.
[NOISE] and you get, you'll, you, you, end
up at the same conclusion.
Okay, so Alright.
Now, these things here by the way, are
things that are kind of obvious.
These are things we talked about in
approximation,
little linear approximations.
In some ways, they're penalty problems
with an aphine function, you know?
ax minus b or something like that.
I mean, that's what this is.
But actually, what's interesting is, in
maximum you end,
you end up with all sorts of interesting
things where you do not end up with a,
an affine function, a norm, or a penalty
function of an affine function, and so
these are actually quite interesting.
So we'll look at a couple of these.
So, first is logistic regression.
So the, this is a distribution actually
on, so
the outcomes are zero one, boolean
outcomes, and.
The probability that you get a one is the
logistic function.
So, it's, it's e to the a transpose u plus
b divided by 1 plus a transpose u plus b.
And the probability that y equals o is 1
minus this, right,
which of course is 1 over 1 plus e to the
a transpose u plus b.
Okay?
So that's the idea.
Now here, the idea is that u are here,
these observable explanatory variants,
right?
So I mean, I, can tell all sorts of things
about these would be,
lets say that patient admitted to the
hospital eventually develops Sepsis.
That, that's what we looking at, okay?
And then, you here would be all sorts of
medically relevant variants.
Right?
Could, could be basic, that,
you know, all sorts of basic things.
Various scores given to them, various,
anyway doesn't matter.
That's a whole bunch of things like that.
By the way, some of these could be boolean
too.
That would be very often the case.
Right?
So
it'd be so-called categorical variables.
Right?
And so
a model like this, and this model is
instantiated by fixing a and
b then gives you a model of the
probability of someone developing Sepsis.
Right?
When they're admitted to the hospital.
So that.
Coz you just simply take their u, you
evaluate this function.
And if it is 0.05, that's good, and if
it's 0.87 that's not good.
Okay?
So that's the idea.
Alright.
So the estimation problem is to estimate,
a, these parameters a and
b from observations.
Right, so, that's, that, that would be
your, that's what we're going to do.
So we're going to work out the
log-likelihood function.
And and then, we're going to maximize it,
right?
And it, I guess it wouldn't be in this
class if it didn't turn out to be concave,
so that's, okay.
So, let's take a look at that.
So what we'll do is so you, you've been
given a,
a bunch of observations and basically what
these are is these are previous patients.
Right?
Could be from the last year,
from the region, doesn't matter.
So you just get a whole bunch of data
[COUGH].
'Kay?
And the ys are, are just 01.
Right?
So I guess you, you'd call these maybe
labels in, in machine learning.
Alright, so well just make it simple and
reorder them so
that all the ones that actually develop
sepsis are first, that's k of them.
And the rest did not.
Right?
Just for simplicity.
Then, the log likelihood function, well
it's very simple.
It's simply the, you, you take this, for
the, over the ones where y was 1.
So that's, that, that's these terms,
right?
And then for, for the case where y was 0,
that's 1 minus this,
which is exactly that.
And so that, that's the log likelihood
function.
And it is a function of a and b.
Okay?
Well, if you work out what this is well,
you can see all sorts of bits.
This is log of the probability of x.
But that's just this thing, right?
And then you get minus, and then here
there's this thing on the bottom,
you just, you sum that over, over the, all
of it.
That's log sum x.
But we all know, we all recognize log sum
x is convex.
And so, now we do this in, in discipline
convex programming, or cvx style.
We just walk from the inside of the
expression tree out.
And you say, that's [UNKNOWN].
By the way, you don't then say exp is
convex.
That would be a false move.
You recognize log of 1 plus exp.
As log of e to the 0 plus e to the a
transpose u plus bi.
And you say log sum x is convex, log sum x
of [UNKNOWN] is convex,
sum convex minus concave, done.
Everybody got this?
Okay, so what this says is if you have a
bunch of data,
you simply maximize this function here.
And that will give you a and b.
That'll, that'll give you parameters a and
b, and now, you have a model.
And you have model that will predict
predict probabilities for, for new and
unseen values of u instances, right.
That's, that's, that's the idea, so.
This is of course, extremely widely used,
so.
And depending on your background and I can
speak from my own so
if your background is from, sort of,
traditional EE type things,
with signal processing, you probably won't
have seen this.
Which is sort of a pity, right.
You've seen a lot of stuff involving
linear things and
stuff like that, but you probably won't
have seen this.
So, okay.
So here's an example.
But this is an example where you hardly
need anything fancy, right, but just so
we can draw it.
So the example here has n equals one.
There's one explanatory feature.
It's kind of dumb.
That's u, that's here, and it varies
between 0 and 10, and
what, what are plotted here, are a bunch
of samples, right.
And so, ignore this curve for the moment.
We just take a look at it, and we'd say
things like this.
Look its kind of I mean you don't need any
fancy for u equals 1, you look at this and
you say yeah look I mean if, if u is like
2 or I don't know 2 or
3 below 3, its quite likely but not its
quite likely that the, that
the outcome y will be 0 its but it is not
1 because look at this guy up here, okay?
It sorry, it's not probability,
it's not the probability that your 0 does
not want, right?
Because there are exceptions.
On the other hand, if you say that if u is
bigger then about 6, its, its quite
likely that the outcome is going to be 1
but it is absolutely not, certainly.
Because look at that.
Okay, so what this shows here, is the
logistic fit right, and
so and it, I mean it certainly seems about
right, and
it has all the way to the statistics
behind it.
So it can be justified at great length.
and, and so the use of this would go
something like this.
A new sample will come along and you would
be too.
And you would say, well I think the
probability is about 8%.
That it's 1, right?
U comes along, it's 8 and you'd say it's
about 94% now.
And u will come along in it's, it's 5 and
you'd say I don't know.
Okay, so we'll move to a completely
different thing which is
actually this hypothesis testing.
Actually these are all realated because in
fact.
Maximum likelihood estimation with
parameter that is continuous.
Is something like the hypothesis testing.
Right?
Because you're,
you're sort of testing one value of x
versus another.
And in fact, we're going to see that
maximum likelihood is basically.
It, it, it's the thing that would win in a
binary hypothes,
hypothesis test against any other value.
But, okay.
So here it is.
This is it's absolutely, most basic form,
goes like this.
And it's the most basic form, actually,
of, well, I guess, statistics, it's this.
What you have, is you have two hypotheses,
that you have a variable that was
generated either from one distribution,
this is a finite value, it's got n
possible values.
It's either generated from one
distribution or
another, period, that's it.
So it can't get any more basic than this.
I guess you could have, like, 2, or
something here, but, okay.
So you have two distributions, and you see
a sample, and what you want to say is,
you want to say something intelligent
about whether or
not, which distribution it came from.
That's it, that's the most basic one.
Okay.
And,
you know some things would be obvious
here.
Right?
That if one distribution, you know,
looked like this, you know .9, you know
.100, or something like that.
And, the other looked like, you know, .05,
you know .05.
You know, .8 and .1.
Then, you know, it's, I mean you could
guess, right?
That if the,
if in fact what you observe was say, this
one, then you could say with absolute and
total certainty that it was this
distribution that generated it, right?
If it turned out to be.
If your observation was one capital X
equals one.
You could say with very good confidence
that in fact it
was generated by the distribution.
Does everybody see that?
Right.
So in fact the whole idea here is
as the two distributions get closer
together this gets harder to do.
Okay, and so now we're just going to look
at,
what's a, what's a, what is a good and
principled way to make this choice?
Okay.
So we're going to look at randomized
detectors.
So randomized detector, that's a matrix.
It's going to look like this.
It's 2 by n.
These are the outcomes here, over here.
So we write the outcomes here, and then
this is something like 1 and 2.
And what it is that each column is
going to be,
is going to tell you what you should do
when the outcome is if its
column four if the outcome is capital X
equals 4, right?
So if you look over here you might have
point nine and point
one that's pretty weird because what it
says is something like this it says like
capital x equals four you should say Next
one's going to be a randomized detector.
So you're going to say with probability
.9,
you're going to say that it was generated
from distribution 1 and probability .1,
you're going to say was generated from
distribution 2.
So, we'll talk about why you might do this
in a minute.
Now, much more natural, would be things
like this, okay?
And that says that if capital X equals 7,
you simply say, well it was, it was,
it was outcome 2.
That was distribution 2 that it came from.
Okay, so this is the idea.
Why you would want a randomized detector
we will talk about in a minute.
Actually it's interesting you can think of
it as a relaxation of an estimator.
Okay.
And if all of the elements are 0 or
1 it is called a deterministic detector,
so that's the idea.
Alright.
So, how you choose that detector?
Well, if you simply multiply, you take.
There's a detection matrix.
In the detecting matrix, you simply
multiply T by p.
You multiply T on the left by p and q, and
you get a 2 by 2 matrix, and
the entries can be interpreted in a very
interesting way.
They're basically the probability of.
air, so this gives you,
this gives if, if P is the true
distribution, q is the distribution.
Then this tells you sort of the
probability of selecting the correct one.
Right?
So these entries tell you something about
the probabilities here of, of being right.
Right?
Being right means capital X came from
distribution one and
you announce that it came from
distribution one.
And you can swap 1 with 2, and that's
being right.
Being wrong is the distribution came from,
the sample came from distribution 1,
but you announce that it was distribution
2, right.
And these have name like, you know, false
positive and false negative.
And you know that, that means one of
things you, anyway so
that's the idea, right.
So So this is the, this, this is the idea.
okay, so, Pfp, that's probability of
selecting hypothesis 2 if x
is generated by distribution 1, and that's
a false positive.
So, you're saying it's from distribution
2, but
in fact, it was from distribution 1, and
false.
And of course, what you'd like is, you
want both of these things to be zero.
I mean, that would.
I mean,
you want this matrix to be i, the
identity, right?
Oh,.
There's another name for this.
I think some people call it a confusion
matrix, I think.
alright.
So we basically have a multi-criterion
formulation, right?
Because what you would really like.
Oh, by the way.
How would you make false positive rate 0?
That you can do.
You never want to select hypothesis 2, if
it was generated by, what?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, just clear, this make everything
negative.
Just, then, the great news there is that
your false positive rate is as low as it
can get, zero.
Okay, so that's one.
And so, and so, so, I mean, it's a real
trade-off here.
Right?
Right, so if we make this a bi-criterion
problem, it just looks like this, right.
It's very simple one.
And the natural thing to do is scalarize.
So if you use scalarize, right, this'll
give you the Perito curve.
actually, it won't in this case.
You'll see exactly what it does get you,
it, because, the piece,
the Perito curve in this case is piecewise
linear and it gives you vertices on it.
So we'll, we'll see that in a minute.
So you minimize this, but in fact that,
this is, this is completely trivial to
solve.
For one thing, the whole problem splits
across the columns of t,
right, because the constraints only
involved, tell you that the columns are.
Have sum up to 1, right?
And the objective is linear, so its
completely separable, so
this things splits, you can decide each
one and then as [INAUDIBLE]
completely trivial to work out what the
answer is and the answer is simply this.
It's very interesting, it says, here
lambda remembered is, is actually, and
lambda is a beautiful interpretation.
Lambda is our,
is remembered something as translates, I
think its the false positive.
I think it's the false positive rate,
the irritation at false positive versus
irritation for false negative.
Right so it's the exchange rate between
the two things that you want small.
That's the interpretation from duality
your multi criteria.
So the answer turns out to be really
simple.
It's this.
You get a deterministic detector.
And you should choose one, if p is bigger
than the lambda q, and
this is sometimes written this way, like
that, right.
And the other one is written, of course,
this way.
And then, this is called a likelihood
threshold test, or
likelihood ratio test, right.
So you simple have a threshold, and so
all you do now is you simple take one
distribution and the other one.
You take the ratio.
And then, all you're doing is just setting
a threshold.
And then, for any given threshold.
You choose whichever, whichever one has
the higher, value, or
something like that, right?
So, or you sort these, and then choose
those.
anyway.
And then, as you vary Lambda here, the
ratio, than what you're
getting are a tradeoff, you're trading off
false positive and false negative.
Okay?
So, another one you could do is minimax
detector.
That's very interesting.
So, minimax detector says, no, no, I care
about false positive and
false negative equally, please minimize.
In fact, this says, please minimize
probability there.
I want to minimize probability of error.
Then you get this thing, and actually,
that's a real, that's an honest LP, and
the solution is generally not
deterministic.
Right?
It's generally something
where the detector has entries that are
not 0 1 1 0.
Okay?
So let's look at an example.
obviously, you don't need this kind of
heavy stuff for this thing, right?
Here's an example.
So, here's two distributions I guess
that's P, and that's Q.
And, you know?
Some things are obvious, right?
If the outcome is one, it looks rather.
It looks like a pretty good guess that
distribution P generated it.
If the outcome is 3.
It looks like [COUGH] a quite good bet,
rather good bet that distribution,
the second distribution q, generated the
data, right.
Just, just, just looking at it.
And let's see.
eh, if the outcome is 2 or 4, it's maybe
less obvious, right,
as to which one generated it.
Right, so
here is the tradeof curve, [COUGH] so this
trade off curve is piece-wise linear.
And this is showing you these various, so
the, this is the actual trade off curve.
These actually are the points you get from
the likelyhood ration tests.
Right, these, well I guess you get these
too.
Those, those are the two we talked about
before.
Which is how, how can you get zero false
positives or something like that.
So, you get something like this.
So you see the idea.
Oh, by the way, this picture when inver, I
think it's, you turn it.
I think you just flip it top to bottom.
It's, it's got a name called ROC, which is
Receiver Operating Characteristic.
Now the minimax one is 4.
Right?
This line here is the line of equal error.
A false, false positive and false
negative, and it's right here, right.
So that's the, that's the idea, so.
So, it's a bit strange.
By the way, this is one of those cases
where well, as, as, as a big picture,
we will and we have talked about these and
we will talk about it more,
where you want to solve a problem and you
end up doing something like a relaxation.
Right.
So, if someone comes up to you and
says find, these are the two
distributions.
I want you to estimate repeated, what's
going to happen repeatedly is,
you're going to see samples, outcomes, and
I want you to guess which distribution it
came from, and I want you to absolutely
minimize being wrong.
Right, simple.
You have to use the minimax detector.
What's weird about it, is you're not
consistent.
Right because you'd say things like x
equals 3, and
you go that came [INAUDIBLE] come one.
And then later they say x equals three,
you go, sorry that, that came from
distribution Q.
I'm sorry the first one came from
distribution P, then Q.
So you're not consistent, it's a, it's a,
it is a.
It's a non-deterministic detector, right.
But, that is the, that is actually the
only way that you
can actually minimize the probability of
being wrong.
Right, so, okay, so thats, that.
By the way.
It's not very interesting with
two distributions, right.
This actually is already very interesting
when I have lets say ten distributions.
There bigger and things like that.
It's already way interesting.
And I should add something there.
You can, you can actually get really
interesting problems.
If I show you ten distributions on let's
say, 1,000 outcomes, or 10,000 outcomes.
it, it's actually there your confusion
matrix or
I think we called it the detector matrix.
What'd we call it?
Find the detection probability matrix or
the confusion matrix, it's got a lot
entries in it, right.
Like, for example, it's got 100, okay.
And you can think of all sorts of
interesting convex problems you could do.
You could say things like, you'd say, you
know what, I, I absolutely do not,
the probability that you think that you
say,
that you estimated came from distribution
7 when it really came from distribution 6.
That absolutely cant exceed 10%, okay.
Anyone understand what I just said?
That's just simply a linear inequality on
one entry in that matrix.
You see what I'm saying, right?
And you can go on and add all sorts of
panel convex, constrains and
things like that.
You'd say, the probability of being wrong,
when the distribution come,
is actually generated from distribution
three.
I want the probability of being wrong to
be no more than 10%.
What would that be?
What I just said, what kind of constraint
on D would that be?
That's it.
That's nothing more, right?
Either the diagonal element.
Is bigger than 0.9.
That's just fine.
Or actually the sum of the off diagonals,
is less than the number.
But that's the same, because they all add
up to, you know, okay.
Everybody, everybody got this?
So, by the way a lot of these problems are
not, I don't think
taught in standard statistics type things
or machine learning.
I mean, I think there is.
They have a lost function for all of these
things.
So on.
But you can now do interesting things,
just because you know about linear
programming, for example.
Okay.
So.
We're going to go to our last sample here
of topics.
It's actually a very interesting one.
It's experiment design.
Right, so, and it's in a very specific
setting, it's in the setting where you get
a simple problem, but It's actually quite
interesting useful, search this.
We're going to have M linear measurements,
so I have a bunch of measurements.
Yi is ai transpose x plus wi.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to normalize
things to have all these noises in 0,1.
Right, so, I mean so for example if the
noise actually had a smaller variance or
something like that.
I would scale it up and that would
actually just make upscale a and
y would just scaling all that kind of
stuff, right?
So that's yes.
So
all noises are normalized to have variance
one, standard deviation one, okay.
And so if you want to, I mean we can talk
about various things here.
X is, x is a parameter we want to
estimate,
y is a measurement and you should
interpret the size of
a now as something like a signal to noise
ratio, right.
Because if a is big, if a3 is big that
means that's a,
that's a clean sensor measurement.
If a3 is small, that's a crappy sensor
measurement.
Everybody got this?
Right?
So, because, you know,
the bigger a3 is the bigger.
This chunk is compared to the noise, which
is on the order of one.
Okay?
So, norm of a being big is, is good.
That, something like a signal to noise
ratio.
Now, if I estimate this, well the least
squares estimate is just that.
Right, it's just whatever it is.
A-transposed A vs B-transposed B.
And that's this, and we write it this way.
And, what you see here.
Is its a sum, the other products of the a
Is and then inverse times this sum.
Okay?
So, that, that's simple enough.
Okay, now, the air that's x hat minus x is
0 mean.
And has a co-variants metrix which is
actually just thing here.
So, that, that's the co-variants metrix.
Okay?
And,
and notice that this kind of makes sense.
Right?
Because look at this.
If, that's, now that's a co-variance
matrix,
so it's a positive semi-definite matrix.
Well it's actually a positive definite
matrix.
What's interesting about it is this.
If a at i is bigger, this thing gets
smaller.
I mean if they're all bigger, right?
Because, we'll just look at it.
This, this matrix is monotone, in the
matrix sense, in ai.
I mean that sounds weird, but you know
what I mean.
It means that if, if you were to double a,
you know,
a7 that dyad contribution would be bigger
in the matrix sense.
This matrix would be bigger,
and then when you take the inverse, that
would switch and it would be smaller.
So you'd do, you'd get better estimation.
Okay, so it'd all make sense.
Okay.
And so for example, if you wanted to get a
confidence ellipsoid.
That would be related this way.
It would be something like this.
You'd have x hat, that's your, that's your
estimate from here.
And you'd select data depending on the
confidence level of what you want.
You know, depending on some chi squared
distribution or something like that.
That would give you the confidence level.
And.
So experiment design says the following.
So all of this is basic.
Experiment design is the following
problem.
You can choose from a palette of
measurements that are possible.
In other words, you have something like p
possible measurements here.
They're going to be denoted v1 through vp.
And you are allowed to choose a bun like
from e,
for each m, you choose one of those,
right.
So, for example, you might say something
like this.
I want all my measurements to be v1.
That's why.
Why?
Because it's the best sensor, okay?
Something like that.
Or you might say, I want to do this, I
want to, I want, I want to start with v1,
and then v2, then I'll do a v7, then I'll
come back with another v1,
everybody following this?
This is what you have to choose.
Some things are kind of obvious here.
For example, this just, it's a sum of
dyads, right?
So it actually doesn't matter what order
you do them in, right.
And in fact, the only thing you really
have to say here to specify an experiment
design is to say, I want to do 22 of
experiment one, 12 of experiment 2,
0 of experiment 3, and so on, and those
integers have to add up to m,
which is the total number of experiments
you're going to do.
Everybody got that?
So, and you can imagine.
All sorts of variations where you add
costs for
the experiments, and time, or money or
something like that.
You can imagine all sorts of things,
but we're going to stick with the simple
one at first.
Okay, so we ended up with a problem that
looks like this, and, and
this'll, this is a good time for
me to say something, it's a general thing
that we can talk about and this is fun.
Okay.
So,
you end up with a problem that looks like
this.
Choose a bunch of integers, m1 through mp,
they add up to m.
In fact what you're really doing is you're
allocating a set of m experiments accross
p possible experiments.
So you just, that's an, it's an allocation
problem, but
notice that it's an integer allocation
problem okay.
And you want to do that to minimize this
covariance matrix.
Now, of course that's a vector
optimiszation problem, because it has,
it makes absolutely no sense of say
minimize echo variance matrix, right.
So, it's pretty optimal and.
Many ways of that, you could scalarize,
you could do all sorts of things, right.
There's many ways to talk about a
minimizing a covariance matrix, right.
So, or if you like, this,
you like things geometrically, find me the
smallest confidence ellipsoid, right.
By the way, there is no such thing, so you
want to say something like this.
Find me a small confidence ellipsoid, and
that's translated to mean.
Find the pareto optimal one.
So pareto optimal in that sense means find
me a confidence, a choice of these ms so
that the confidence ellipsoid you get,
there's no smaller confidence
ellipsoid that you could get by another
allocation of experiments.
Right that, so what that means.
Okay, so, but
we all know that because that's what
multi-criterion optimization is.
Okay.
Now the variables are a bunch of integers.
That should be lighting up a big warning
sign.
So the amber light in your convex
optimization conceptual center
should be blinking.
When you hear, integers.
And, in fact, this problem is difficult,
in general, right?
I mean, that's the right thing to say
whenever you see integers.
Actually, in some cases, it's false, of
course.
There are plenty of integer problems which
actually are solveable.
But, in in general they're not.
So, instead what we're going to do is
relaxed experiment design.
So, relaxed experiment design says this,
hmm.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to
rewrite it this way.
I'm going to work with the fractions of
the experiments of each type I do.
And so I'm going to get, I'm going to work
with a lambda.
And, I'll have one transposed lambda is 0.
and, if I added one more constraint.
If I added simply this, m lambda is in z,
then, this problem would be identical to
that problem.
Right?
This says
that the lambdas are integer multiples of
one over m.
So if I added this constraint, this is
identical to that one and
now, want to see what, want to see how
convex relaxation is done?
Everybody knows this now?
You know what convex relaxation is, right?
Watch very carefully.
Convex relaxation is this.
You write down an optimization problem.
There are a few constraints that you don't
know how to handle.
Comment them out.
That's what is is, okay.
What are some common scalarizations?
Well you can minimize the log of the
determinant.
That's a convex well sorry.
Concave increasing function, and
therefore [COUGH] will produce a pareto
optimal point.
[COUGH] You can take the trace, the
maximum igon value,
all sorts of crazy stuff.
You can add all sorts of you know, you can
add all sorts of constraints now to it.
[COUGH] Sorry fo, for this thing.
Okay, so it needs to have names, right.
So, [COUGH] when you minimize the log
determine of the inverse.
It's beautiful interpretation.
That's exactly, you are minimizing the
volume of the confidence ellipsoid.
Right, and you end up with this problem
which is convex.
Right, so you solve that.
And then, you know depending on what, if
you were successful in convincing someone
that it was more sophisticated to solve
the relaxed problem, your done.
If you haven't then you round and
you hold up the optimal value of the
relaxed problem as a lower band.
Okay.
Let's take a look at that.
I mean, I'm, I'm not going to go into the
details here.
I'm not going to argue everything about
the dual, but
it's actually quite interesting.
So the dual problem of this can be
massaged.
I, I should say a dual problem.
And that means you have to allow me to do
a few little manipulations before and
a few after.
But you get it into a real form that looks
like this.
Maximizes log det w plus a constant which
is totally irrelevant.
Subject to [COUGH] vk transpose wvk less
than or equal to 1.
And this has a beautiful interpretation
geometrically.
It turns out this says, find me the
minimum volume ellipsoid,
center at the origin, that includes all
the test vectors.
[COUGH] And it turns out that the LaGrange
multipliers on these constraints
are precisely the fractions the optimal
fractions that you should use, right?
So, it's beautiful.
So you get this connection between an
experiment design problem, and
a geometric problem, which is going to be
our next topic.
Right.
And so the picture is something like this
well, this is the picture, right.
The picture is, is this.
We have 20 test vectors.
That's the origin, and here's a bunch of
things, tests you can do,
potential tests, and here's a bunch.
Okay?
And now I'm going to, before we even look
at what the optimal design is, I'm
going to ask you some questions about it.
Okay.
So let me ask you.
Please explain intuitively, why you would
never chose, choose that experiment.
Let's suppose that's experiment #11.
Why would you not choose experiment 11?
[COUGH] You can say,
and don't say anything about convex
optimization or log data or anything else.
Just you tell me why would you not choose
that experiment.
What is this experiment here?
It basically it gives the negative of that
experiment but it's about twice as big.
So in other words it's a completely
equivalent measurement with
one-half the noise.
Twice the signal to noise ratio.
Right?
So if I give you a set of, a palette of 20
experiments you can carry out, one is
basically a copy of another, but twice as
bad, then why would you ever use it?
You would not.
Okay?
So I'm just,
I'm just saying, all of this is kind of
intuitive, right.
You want to use experiments that are
spread apart.
Now, roughly speaking, you don't choose
any of these because these, well not quite
because they don't go up here, but these
measurements here are kind of like those.
I mean, they're, got a minus sign, but who
cares?
Actually, it goes away immediately when
you form that dyad, the vkvk transpose.
It goes away instantly.
So what happens is you're, you're not
going to choose any of these
because these sort of stand in for them
and have higher signal to noise ratio.
And sure enough, look what it does.
It picks the two [COUGH] which have kind
of highest angle.
The two measurements which are most
independent if you want to say that, or
something like that, have the highest
angle And, it concentrates 50-50 on them.
Okay?
So.
By the way,
this is stupid in r2, you don't need this,
right?
But, if you are making, if you are
estimating 10 or
a hundred parameters, these things are not
obvious at all.
Right?
Not at all, right?
You have a thousand possible experiments
to do and so on.