So, we'll look now at something that's
like the dual
of the approximation problems, or norm
approximation problems.
And that's a least norm problem, and the
basic idea is, is this.
here, you have a equality constraint, so
in this case, A is not generically tall,
it's generically wide.
So, A is a wide matrix.
And this says that I have, something like
M equality constraints on x,
presumably not enough to completely,
constrain x, I mean,
and it's a silly problem, it has one
feasible point.
And then, among the x's that satisfy ax
equals b,
we're going to choose the one, that has
minimum norm.
And you've probably seen this in some
class, if you took 263,
this was a least norm problem, it was the
two norm there.
So, what, what's the interpretation of
this, and
of course, I should say something here,
when I say equals argmin.
If this norm is strictly convex, and
that would be the case for example, for a
two norm then it's unique, of course.
But in, it can easily be not unique,
right?
So, we should say something like, well,
one notation would be,
x star is in argmin, because one,
one, one notational convention is, that
argmin returns the set of minimizers.
So by x star equals argmin, we just mean,
it's a minimizer.
So, the geometric interpretation is this.
We have an affine set, that's generically
given by the set of x,
such that ax equals b.
So we have this affine set, and what we
want to do,
is find the point closest to zero, in that
set, right?
And, a simple completely elementary
variation on this, is where we project
a point in, a non, a non-zero point on,
onto that set, so, that's the idea.
It's a, it's a projection of zero, onto
the affine set.
estimation, is this, the idea in,
the estimation interpretation is something
like this.
We interpret, b equals ax to mean that, we
have M perfect linear measurements.
So there are, there's, there's no noise,
nothing, they're perfect.
And then, but we have n parameters to
estimate, and
we have more parameters, than we have
measurements, right?
So, I have 150 parameters to estimate.
I have 50 measurements, or 100
measurements, something like that.
And that leaves me basically, 50 unknown
dimensions or something like that.
So ax equals b, in that case, we interpret
as the set of parameter values,
are consistent with the perfect
measurements, right?
So this, if you were to put a comment
here, you would say something like,
consistent with measurements, like, like
this, right?
And, and the assumption is, the
measurements are perfect, right?
So, so that would be that.
And then, the interpretation of minimizing
the norm is,
you then choose the most plausible, right?
Choose the most plausible point, right?
And here, implicit is the following idea,
that the larger x is, the less plausible
it is, right?
So that's, that's the idea.
In other words, you're in some situation,
where there are many parameter values,
consistent with the measurements.
So, nobody, any, anybody who chooses it, x
with ax equals b, cannot say to
another person, who chooses another x that
satisfies ax equals b, that they're wrong.
What, what one can do then, is just talk
about, which is more plausible or
something like that.
And so the idea is that, the norm is here,
used as a surrogate for, I should say,
implausibility, because the larger the
norm, the less plausible it is.
And, by the way, we'll connect this
possibly, even later today.
We'll connect this to a statistical
interpretation.
Another one is design.
So here, you think of x, as a bunch of
design variables,
these are inputs, for example.
This could be forces that you apply to a
vehicle, or something like that, right?
It could be voltages or current drives,
that you're going to send to a motor, or,
or current drives that you're going to
send to an antenna, right?
Something like that.
Then ax gives you something like the
result, right?
So, this, this gives you the result.
So, and it might be something like this,
that you choose 150 forces to apply,
maybe at different times, different
actuators, but actually,
all you care about are maybe, six or eight
things at the end.
For example, the position and momentum, at
some final target time.
Something like that, right?
In which case ax gives you the result, of
the action x.
Then, b is actually your desired action,
and so,
any x that satisfies ax equals b, is
valid.
It says basically, find me a set of forces
that will take my spacecraft,
move it over to here, 12 seconds later and
arrive here, you know, with this position
in momentum, right?
So that would be lot's of x's do that, and
here what you're doing is you're saying,
please find me a, an efficient one, one
that minimizes a norm.
Could two norm it could be one norm, one
norm would be closer to feel usage in,
in, in a lot of cases, something like
that.
It could be infinity norm, it could be
anything, in fact, okay.
So this, this is just interpretations of
the problem of
minimizing the norm of a, of x, subject to
ax equals b, equality constraints, right.
Oh, I should say that, one nice thing
about our approach to these, which is
simply to look at that and to simply say,
that's a convex problem, period, right?
One nice thing is, eh, you can mix and
match, if all of a sudden comes,
somebody comes back, and says, oh dear,
you know, I need to add some constraints
here, like, for example, the x's have to
be between plus and minus 1.
It's not a big deal for us, we just add
these constraints, right?
So, okay.
I'm not showing them here, just for
simplicity.
Okay, let's look at some specific
examples, of least norm problems.
Here's one.
The most famous one, is you take the two
norm, and in fact, what you
really minimize, is not the norm, but the
two norm squared, not the two norm, but
the two norm squared, and this is the
same, because minimizing the two
norm squared and two norm is the same, it
has the same solution.
And this, the optimality conditions,
you work them out, the KKT conditions are
linear, they're a set of linear equations.
So you can solve them exactly, and there's
a formula for it, if a is full rank and
all that kind of stuff, I mean, and you've
seen that in 263 or
some other linear algebra course, right?
So, and that's why this is, this is, of
course, extremely widely-used,
right, because it fits up, fits the, it
fits everything, right?
Looks like it's simple, fits the 19th
century, you know, formula model and
all that kind of stuff, okay.
now, you can do other things, which is
actually quite interesting.
You can do things like this.
You can actually take the l1 norm, and
this is a very interesting problem.
This says, minimize the norm of x1,
subject to ax equals b, okay?
And this is, this is something actually,
that's that,
that's quite in vogue right now, and has
been, maybe for five, maybe ten years now.
It has no analytical solution, in general.
well, I mean, it's, except for very silly
cases, has no analytical solution.
So it's got, and it's got various names,
this one's basis pursuit.
And let me ask you, in view of the
discussion we had last time.
Now, last time we talked about a penalty
function, and how the shape of the fenal,
penalty function, has an influence, on the
distribution of residuals.
That discussion transposes perfectly, to
this situation, right?
So here the idea is that, if you have a
penalty function, here,
the penalty is embarrassingly simple, it's
the absolute value.
But what it does is, that's going to shape
the distribution of x's.
And what I would like to know from you is,
what do you imagine the solutions of the
basis pursuit problem, look like?
What you would expect, and turns out, in
fact, to be true,
is that when you solve this problem, most
of the x's are zero, okay?
And, I mean, there's various ways, you
will observe this as a, as a,
as an empirical observation, and in fact,
you can prove various things about that,
and so on, and so forth.
So in fact, this is a heuristic, for
getting a sparse solution of ax equals b,
right?
So, okay, and this is going to be a theme.
It's going to kind of, follow us through
the rest of the course, and so
on, so, okay.
And we will see a lot about this.
okay, so, well, I've already been talking
about this, but
the least-penalty problem says that you,
you choose a penalty function phi here,
and then you, minimize the sum of the
penalties, subject to ax equals b, and
then you would, you would choose phi, to
shape to get an x that you like, right?
And by the way, this is, there's something
quite interesting about it because it
has something to do with, how, people
don't talk about it a lot, but
this, the question of, sort of, the entire
design flow.
How do you use, like convex optimization,
this kind of thing?
And in fact, there's this big trend across
many fields,
to move away from something to direct
solution, it says oh,
you know, I want a sparse solution or
here's what you should do, with the data.
Towards one, where you put one level of in
direction in between, and what you do is,
you form an optimization problem.
And what the user does, is mess with the
optimization problem, and then,
you let some numerical method work out the
actual solution, right?
So, I mean, this is a big trend across
many, many fields, right, that for
example, in areas like control, signal
processing, even statistics, you,
you move away from this idea of, here's
how you, here's what you do to the data.
And instead, what the designer of a method
is really doing is actually,
designing an optimization problem, he
changed parameters here and there.
Something's too smooth or some, if
something's not smooth enough,
you add a little regularization and you
crank that up.
But you're not, you as the user, are not
actually figuring out exactly,
how to transform your data into your
estimate or something.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So this is, I mean this is a very big,
it's a big picture observation, but
it's it, it's happening, it's prob, okay.
Well, the parent of these two problems,
least norm and
then appro, norm approximation, is, is
just regularized approximation.
And in fact, there's even a more general
parent.
And the, the basic idea, so
regularization, is it's kind of
ubiquitous, across lots of fields.
and, it, it's basic, the correct way, I
think, to think of it,
is it's a bi-criterion problem.
And it basically says, I care about two
norms, each of which,
I would like small, right?
So the norms are, this is the most
traditional setting.
The first one is something like ax minus
b, that can have lots of interpretations,
depending on, if you're doing a
statistical model, or
data fitting, this is your misfit.
x is your model, ax minus being norm, is a
measure of,
how well your model agrees with the data
you have observed, that's,
that's, that's something like misfit, or
fit.
Norm x is basically, how big are your, how
big are your model parameters.
And we'll talk in a minute about, why
would it be,
that you would want small parameters?
actually, there's some very good reasons,
why you would want small parameters.
Well, like many good ideas, it can be
justified from, like, five different,
completely different, points of view, so
let's look at some of them.
So the idea here essentially is,
you're saying, you know what, what I want
is, I want a good fit,
I want ax to be about b, but I want to do
it efficiently, I want x to be small.
So this is, this is the essential idea,
right.
Oh, and again, these ideas are all very
simple, so
if you're not following don't over
interpret what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is so simple, that there's
there are no subtleties here, none, right?
So okay, so when would this come up?
Well in estimation it might be something
like this.
You'd say, well I, I happen to know, I
mean, what I'm observing is, y equals ax.
So, ax minus y or ax minus v, or
something like, ax minus b, if b is what I
measured, is, is v.
And so, this is something like the norm of
that this thing, and
you know that, that's small, but I had
prior knowledge, that x is small, right?
So, and that's, that's what this term does
for me, right?
So that, that's what that says.
You could have optimal design.
You could say, actually, I don't insist
that Ax equals b,
I will give up on Ax equals b, I will
simply get close enough, close enough?
Well, this is a bi-criterion problem.
So, you have a whole pareto optimal curve,
and
you would determine, where to operate on
that curve, once you see the curve.
Then you'll look at it and say, okay fine,
I,
I don't need to do, I mean, if I'm, if I'm
within 3 millimeters,
that's actually fine, especially if that
allows me to use, you know,
one quarter the fuel, I might have used
otherwise, right, something like that.
okay, so there, the idea is, you're
willing you don't even, you know,
you're willing to not have Ax equals b.
You'll, you'll get up a little bit on
that.
And hopefully you'll take as a benefit,
for
not doing that exactly, a small and
efficient small x.
Right, so that's the idea.
Another interpretation, is this, is robust
approximation.
And this is something we're going to talk
about later, this, and
this is quite a modern interpretation, and
it's extremely important, and the idea is
something like this.
You really, just want to fit a model.
So, you really want norm Ax minus b, to be
small, that's really what you want.
Problem is, you don't quite know A, right?
This is extremely, typical, right, that
the As are measured or
something like that, you don't quite know,
what they are.
And by the way, it's, it, this can happen
in a design settings,
it can happen in an estimation setting,
right?
In a design setting, someone you say, you
know what, I, I do know,
I, I know the moment of inert, you know, I
know the moment of inertia,
I know the mass of the vehicle, the cg, I
know all these things pretty well.
But actually, only about 1%, no better
than that.
And what that says is if I, if I apply a
bunch of control surface,
deviations to an aircraft, and I ask,
where will it be in 22 seconds?
The answer is actually, technically, you
don't know, right?
Because, I don't know, there's plenty of
error, [INAUDIBLE] I mean hopefully,
you have a pretty good idea of, where it's
going to be, right?
Because otherwise you, you're in deep
trouble.
But the point is that,
there's really like a, a cloud of, where
it might be, depending on what you do.
Everybody see, what I'm saying?
Hey, it should be a tight cloud, one
hopes, right?
But the fact of the matter is,
you don't, you don't know exactly what's
going to happen, right?
So this is, that's the, that's the idea.
Okay, so then you say, well, what's
interesting about this is
how much does your, is your x affected, by
changes in A?
And that we can even work out, I mean,
this is going to be an intuitive one.
We'll look at this more carefully, later.
But, so what you do is, you think of A, as
being sort of the nominal one, and
delta is a, is a matrix, presumably small,
which is basically your error in A, right?
So this is, this is what you have, right?
So for an aircraft, this is, this is the
nominal model,
that assumes that your estimate of the
mass, moment of inertia, you know,
blah, blah, blah, all these things, are
perfect, right?
They're, they're double precision perfect,
right?
This, is basically a var, these are
variations, due to the fact that,
you know, these things are manufactured,
things vary by 1%, you know,
all sorts of things happen, right, that's
what the delta is here.
And if you look at this equation, we're
going to work this up and
it is very, very simple.
What you get, is Ax minus b, and then,
plus delta x.
And what you see very clearly, is the
following, is that these,
the errors in A multiply x.
And so for example, suppose I chose x to
be 0.
How much would that be affected by model
errors, by the delta?
Not at all, right.
And you can see immediately, I mean this
is very intuitive, but
the, the basic idea is, oh, by the way,
these are sometimes called
multiplicative errors, that's a, that's a
name you will hear.
And it makes perfect sense because it's an
error in A,
which then multiplies your choice x.
So it's a multiplicative error, and for a
multiplicative error, it's, it's,
it is in your, if, you want to be least,
less sensitive to multiplicative error,
then here's what you want.
You want x to be small, the thing,
everybody see this?
And so, this is why a small x would be
preferable, right?
That, it would, it would be that, it would
be less sensitive to errors in A.
Now, that was a long description, I, it's
not,
it's not supposed to be fancier than what
I just said, but that's the idea.
And I can give you, yet another
interpretation of it.
I mean, in some sense,
all these interpretations come around at
the same thing.
Another one is this.
You have y equals you have a model like
this estimation,
you have y equals Ax plus v.
But the truth is, you really have
something like this, right?
You really have a non-linear model.
However, near, you do, near where you're
looking right now,
y equals Ax plus v works, that's provided,
x is small, okay?
So, the idea there is this,
this sort of tells you your nominal error,
based on your say, linearized model.
This says, please have x small, because
the smaller x is, the more accurate,
the more I trust my lenearized model,
right?
And in fact, in that, in that case, this
the, the term that constrains x, either
via regularization or as an additive term
in regularization, or as a constraint.
If a constraint, it's called the trust
region constraint,
which is a beautiful term, because it
basically says, please estimate x.
I want norm Ax minus b small, but I want
norm x small.
And someone says, why do you want norm x
small, do you care?
And you go, actually, no, I don't care at
all, how big the parameter is.
The problem is, I have to add that there
because if x gets bigger, my model Ax,
is no longer accurate.
Everybody [INAUDIBLE] this?
[UNKNOWN] That the idea it's very, it's
pretty straight forward, okay, alright.
Let's look at some simple cases.
I mean so, how do you, how do you solve a
bi-criterion problem?
You scale a rise, right?
This is the simplest method.
And so, you take the norm of Ax minus b
plus gamma norm x, it, and for
us, that's a convex problem, no big deal
we solve it, okay?
So that's fine.
And, and gamma is a positive parameter,
you sweep it from zero to infinity.
And at the two extremes, you would get you
could get the extreme points,
by solving a constraint problem, or
something like that, okay.
And, so this traces out the, the tradeoff
curve.
a, a very, a very traditional method, is
to square the two.
You get the same tradeoff curve.
And by the way, that's something you would
want to check, right?
That, in fact, the, the curve of solutions
here, parameterized by delta,
is identical to the curve of solutions
parameterized by gamma here, right?
So, in fact, you could even work out, how
delta and gamma are related, right?
And it's not totally straightforward and
then,
it has to do with the particular problem,
but these are two parameterizations, okay.
So if these are two norms, and the reason
generally, one square's a norm, I mean,
there's several reasons, but the most
traditional one is,
when you square two norm, you get a
quadratic function, which is nice and
smooth and, you know, the derivative is
linear and you know, and
then, then all your, you have a formula
for the answer, right?
Okay, so most famous there is, is Tikhonov
Regularization.
Oh, and I should say, in statistics, it's
called Ridge Regression, is the name in,
in statistics, there's, maybe another one,
but it's called Ridge Regression.
And this just turns into a single least
square,
I mean you can solve this analytically, of
course, it's two norms, right?
so, and the solution, you can either make
it, stack it, and make a big least
squares problem, or you just get sort of,
an analytical‎ solution like that, okay?
And, and that's the thing.
Now, the horrible reason to use this, the,
the, the one that, that I don't like at
all, and is in fact, probably the most
common use of regularization is, someone
says, what are you doing?
And you say, I'm doing, I'm, I'm adding
regularization.
Why?
And you'd say, because without it,
I was getting numerical, my solver was
sending complaints to me, right, so,
everybody see that?
That, if you add delta here, this just,
this is just now works per-,
it has to work perfectly.
You can never get a complaint that says,
you know, inverse condition number big, or
you know, numerical, something like that,
it's not going to happen.
You can't get something singular working
position.
So, let's look at an example, and
this example actually it's, it it's very
simple.
But it's, it's going to be an example
actually of, it's meant to illustrate,
exactly what I talked about earlier, this
idea of a design flow, right?
How, how do you use these things, right?
And this'll be one from, you know, control
if you like.
This could just as well be statistics, it
could just as well be, you know,
anything else.
It could be image processing, video
proce-, it could be anything.
And you could construct a similar story,
right?
Could be finance, right?
So, let's, let's look at this.
Here's the idea, I have a, a convolution
system.
So, I have, I apply an input u, scalar
input over, at, at various time intervals.
It could be a force, I apply to something.
It doesn't matter what it is, right?
And something I call the output is a
convolution of the input,
with some convolution kernel or in EE
dialect,
that's called an impulse response, okay,
but that's dialect.
Okay, standard term is convolution kernel,
okay?
So and, and in mix company, you should
always say convolution current, okay.
So the input design problem is,
choose this input u, so that y does
something you want.
And you know, this is just going to be a
very simple example to show,
what a typical design flow looks like.
So, here it is.
What I want to do is, I'm given a desired
trajectory and
I want to track it, that's it.
So, and, and I, I want to make, I, I have
to give a measure for
mis-tracking, and so, I'm going to call
that Jtrack.
And if, if you can't think of anything, if
nothing immediately comes to mind,
then you should just use the squares, just
as through historical to follow
in a historical tradition and what, I
mean, it's not a bad thing, right?
I mean, by the way, if I were to make
this,
the sum of the absolute values, it's, it
would change the result and
you could even kind of guess, what would
happen when you, when you do that, right?
If I were to make this the infinity norm,
right.
That you would call it something like mini
max tracking error, you might give a,
a name like that, and you would get
different results as well, right?
So but here, we just take squares, to make
it simple.
Okay, now at the same time, I want u, not
so big, right?
So I'm going to introduce an objective
called the, the magnitude, Jmag.
And these are by the way, if you look at
these, they're quadratic forms, right?
So, so far, right,
because that they're, they're squares,
they're squares, their sums of squares.
And I'll take an input very, this is,
tells you how, well, you shouldn't say,
see how wiggly the signal is or something
like that.
And it's going to be the sum of the
difference,
of the first differences here, right?
and, and now I can ask some questions,
like, when would Jtrack be zero?
Which is, its minimum possible value.
It means, you have, your y is equal to y
desired.
And you, yes and a good name for that, is
you might, you might say,
that you interpolate the desired thing, or
you might say,
you achieved perfect tracking, meaning
that,
the output absolutely tracks, what it is,
that you required, okay?
So, that would be that.
When would the input magnitude objective
term be zero?
When u equals 0, okay?
So, in which case, by the way, you're
tracking error would simply be,
sum y desired squared, right, because your
output would be zero, at that point.
Okay, and how about input variation, when
would that be zero?
>> Constant.
>> Constant, exactly.
So, if you were to crank up the
coefficient on input variation,
very high, you would expect to see inputs
that were constant, right?
And at the same time, they're attempting
to track and things like that, okay?
And you could go on and on.
For example, you could have a second
finite difference,
which would be something like a smoothness
measure, and
that would be something like ut plus 1,
minus 2 ut, plus ut, minus 1.
That's, I don't know if you recognize
that, but it's the all,
it's the famous, you know, minus 1, 2, 1,
in a tri-diagonal matrix or something.
It's a second difference, right?
And then, and that would give you
something smooth.
And when would that be zero, by the way?
Linear, exactly.
So, if u, u looks like that or that, that
would be zero.
Right?
So, okay great.
So what we'll, do is we'll just make this
a regularized least-squares problem.
We'll take the tracking error, plus delta,
times the derivative error,
plus eta times the magnitude error.
And, I mean this is a least-squares
problem right, so
I mean, we just solve it, right?
This is the idea, we get least-squares
probably.
And then the idea now is that, delta and
eta are knobs,
that you will fiddle with, to get
something that you like, right?
And you could, you could do this in a
formal way.
And actually, do ten values of each, I
mean, it's a trivial problem,
you could do ten values of each, and then,
just make a, a big 10 by 10 matrix and
actually, plot all these things, look at
them, whatever you like.
You could have two big knobs in front of
you, that labeled, you know, delta and
eta are two sliders or whatever on some
user interface, and, and
you can fiddle with them, and see what you
like, right?
So that's the idea.
Okay, so, quick example, here, here's
some,
here are three Pareto optimal solutions,
right?
So, the first one has delta equals 0, and
that means we have, we,
we're putting zero penalty on the
variation in u, right?
So, fine, we're, and we're putting a small
weight on the size of u, that's eta small.
And here's the input and the output, and
two things are plotted in the output.
You can't see, there's a dashed curve
here, which shows you the desired one.
The desired one is just this kind of,
square wave thing,
that was dialect, it goes like, it jumps
up and then jumps down, right, like that.
So that's, that's the desired one.
And you can see, if you look at this, that
we're tracking quite well.
well, you can see, there's little errors
right at the transitions, and so on.
And this is the input that does the trick,
over here, right?
So, that's the input.
And you can see, the input gets as high
as, you know, almost 5 positive and,
it jerks down to, like, minus, oh, I don't
know, 7.5 or eight there, okay?
So that's, that's, and you can also see,
that the input is quite wiggly, right?
So, fine, that, that's just one point down
the the tradeoff curve, right?
Then you'd say, well, in the second, in
the middle, what we're going to do is,
we're still going to have no derivative
here, but we're going to crank up eta.
And we expect, so that means, we're
going to add more penalty to the size, and
so, what we expect, is the size of u to
come down.
And by the way, we're going to pay for
that in tracking error, right?
So, and indeed if you look on the right,
you can see here, you know,
the tracking error probably is mostly
accumulated around these end points, and
it's pretty small.
Here you can see, there's some pretty,
you can actually see some pretty
substantial tracking error, here.
everybody, got this?
The difference is, look at this,
instead we've, we've basically halved the
input, right?
So, with half the input, you know, and so,
if this is good enough for you, great.
I mean, this is kind of the idea, right?
And finally, in the, in the last one, what
we're going to do is, we are going
to add we're going to now turn on a, a
bunch of smoothing regularization.
And again, you pay for it, in terms of
tracking.
Well maybe, this is good enough for you,
maybe not.
And now, but you can see immediately, what
happens.
Things like these, which rack up a big
bill in the derivative
cost function, now are smoothed out, and
you get something like this, okay?
So and, this is, so this is not supposed
to be called,
it is not complicated, it's simple but the
idea is, this is what you would do.
And you would typically sit there and turn
knobs, and see what you like, right?
And this could be any application area,
right?
This could be image processing, where you
tun a knob and you go, no, no,
no, it got too smoothed.
And then you crank it down the other way,
and now, some of the noise comes back, and
then you turn another knob, and this is
how this goes.
So, let's look at another area, it's also
very simple bi-criterion problem.
It's signal reconstruction, it's quite
straightforward, it's this.
What I have is, I have,
I'm given a corrupted signal, that's x,
you know, corrupted, okay?
And what I would like to do, is to come up
with x hat,
which is supposed to be an estimate of
this corrupt,
of well, it's an estimate of the signal,
before it was corrupted, okay?
And that's what I'm going to do.
And so I want x to be, close to x
corrupted, but
I don't want it to be equal to it because
it's been corrupted.
And what I'm going to do is, I'm going to
have a second function here,
which is known as, it's got lots of names,
it's a regularize, it's a regularization
function, or sometimes people call it a
smoothing regularizer, okay?
And so, that's this function phi of x, x
hat.
And the idea is, by looking at a tradeoff
between these, I'm going to do some,
it's a, if this is, this is a principled
way to do smoothing, or
something like that, to smooth a signal,
right?
And the model is something like this.
You have have some unknown signal, you
observe a corrupted version,
and then, you're going to solve this
problem.
And examples would be something like this,
you know, so simple quadratic smoothing
would be,
you simply take the differences squared,
like we did in the previous example.
the, sum of the absolute values,
that's called a total variation
regularizer, right?
So that's, that's completely standard, so
that, that's actually a standard term.
Let's look at an example.
is, simple example, right?
So here's some signal, it's 4000, you
know, time samples or whatever you like.
Here, this is the original signal, and
this is the corrupted one, and I mean this
one's kind of goofy because, you know,
taking the signal, you've added some, and
you can see that, that, the difference
between the signal and, and
the, the corruption, you can see that the
corruption is very like,
high frequency or something like that,
again.
So that's, so it's kind of obvious, right?
So here what you do now, is we simply use
a quadratic smoother.
And what you would get would be things
like this.
So this is with a little bit of smoothing,
this is what you'd reconstruct.
This would be, substantially more and even
more still, right?
So, that's the idea.
And you know, you might say,
that's a little bit too much, and then
that's just about right, right?
Now, now unfortunately for smoothing
problems like this,
there really aren't any particularity good
ways, to choose,
the level of smoothing you do, except
maybe aesthetically.
I mean you have to have some, side
information, right?
Or you can have some cases,
where you actually knew what the exact
signal was, right?
So that, then, then you could actually do
reasonable things, like cross-validation.
Here's one, and this is, this is much more
modern.
By the way, total variation reconstruction
this is great.
This introduced, maybe only in the 1990s,
so, this is pretty relatively recent.
And it's, it's actually quite interesting
and
quite stunning, in fact, I've tried to get
some audio recordings of this.
I mean, I haven't' tried that hard, I
should because they're amazing and
I'd put' em on, the course website or
something like that.
If, anyway, I'll explain that in a minute.
So here's a picture.
What I have is, here's the original
signal.
Alright, it's got a smooth component but
these, these kind of jumps, every so
often.
I mean, this is all just made up, right?
So, this is just to illustrate what
happens, right?
So, here we have this signal, and
so, and then we add this high frequency
noise to it, like that.
So, that's the corrupted signal, right?
Now, one of the problems here, is that you
don't have this frequency scale
separation, right, because the original
signal has these jumps.
And a jump, again, if you know about 4EA
analysis and
all kind of stuff roughly, is going to
contain a lot of high frequencies.
So, you don't have the spectral separation
of the underlying signal and
the noise, here.
And the result is, if you do quadratic
smoothing, which in fact,
is a linear operation, it's just a low
pass filter frankly, is what it is and
what you get is this.
If you do some low pass filtering, well
sure, this gets, this gets smoothed out,
that gets attenuated.
But you can see as you crank it up,
to smooth out more, you can see exactly
what's happening here,
that a transition, that in fact, was a
single value, has now widened, and
now it's taking place over, oh that's a
lot, you know, 50 or something, right?
So, a transition that was,
that, that went in like one time sample,
is now happening over 50, right?
So, by the way,
if this were audio this would bait, make
something sound very muffled.
If that was a, if this was the attack
caused by a drum, right,
someone hits a snare drum, you will get
something that looks like that.
And if you smooth it, like this, and
instead of the attack you know,
rising in ten samples, you know, 48
kilohertz or something like that,
instead of ten samples, it goes at 1,000,
it just, it sounds like a thud.
And it doesn't, it doesn't sound like a
drum anymore, okay?
So, alright.
But let's do total variation de-noising,
right?
So total variation denoising does this,
and
actually, we can see a lot of things here,
that you would predict.
So the first is this.
This is where you have put a lot of total
variation denoising in, and
you're beginning to see something pretty
cool.
When you crank up, something which is
basically,
the l1 norm of the difference of, x hat t
plus 1 and x hat t.
again, you should start now, and
by the end of the course, it should be
completely engrained in second nature.
But you, you want to make connections,
between things like l1 and sparsity,
right?
And that's the very simplified model, but
it should really be Kinks and Sparsity,
right?
So, let's look at l1 and sparsity.
When someone says, please minimize, you
know, well, it's part of it,
right, if they say, please minimize this,
right?
What you would expect is that, if the
coefficient in front of this is
high enough, right, that a whole lot of
these numbers will be zero.
And that says, that if you do total
variation de-noising,
you should expect a piece-wise constant
signal,
because a piece-wise constant signal is,
that's what it means.
This is like a derivative, this first
difference.
And if you have sparse derivative, it
means you're piece-wise, constant.
Everybody got that?
By the way, if this were the second
difference, and I put an l1 norm and
I minimized.
What would you expect to see?
Piecewise linear, exactly, right?
And if I took the third difference, what
would you get?
Piece-wise quadratic.
And by the way, those would be splines,
just for
the record, you get splines, okay?
So, this is sort of, the idea.
Now here what's happened is, you are
tracking this, right?
But what's happened is, your
regularization is so
high, that things like that, just got
constant, right?
You've, you've lost the fact that this is
varying here, right?
Oh, I should add also kind of, a cool
thing.
If you do this on images say, grayscale or
color stuff, you get very cool stuff
that I think, start looking cartoonish,
right, because you have a whole bunch of,
you have a, you have whole regions, where
it was one color or
one shade, or there was some gradient, and
it's just like, now replaced flat.
So I think, you even imagine what this
looks like, right?
So, right, this is, so, if you do total
variation regularization on an image,
what happens is, as you, at, at first, you
have a million pixels.
You're probably going to have a million
gray scale values, right?
I mean, there would be no reason for any
of them to repeat, right?
If they do, it's an accident.
You turn up total variation regularization
on an image, and
that'll jump down dramatically, and after
a while, you'll have a only 1000.
And then you keep turning it, and
at some point, you'll have, like, ten gray
gray levels, right?
And by the way, it'll still be completely
recognizable as the,
as the image you wanted, right, but,
anyway.
So, I'm just saying, these things apply to
everything, right?
You'll, you'll see these all over the
place.
So here, you can see, this is where we
might have maybe, not quite enough,
total variation regularization because you
can there's some swigglies there and
this is kind of the proverbial just
enough, right?
Something like that.
Finally, there's a big thing, we,
we looked at the, this idea of robust
approximation.
So here, and we've already seen a little
bit of this, there is hints added, right?
So, the idea is, you want to minimize,
let's say, norm Ax minus b, but
the problem is, you don't know a.
Now, I should add, this issue is universal
in actually, in all optimization problems,
right, that, that you have data in an
optimization problem.
And, you know, we can talk a little bit,
some generic things to say about data.
You know, when data, when values that are
0, 1, minus 1, sometimes 2, minus 2,
1.5, things like that, those are probably,
really those numbers right, because it
maybe some coefficient, that makes sense,
like you're basically saying, you know,
this thing's equal to that and that would
reveal itself, as a 1 in a minus 1.
And it's really, really, probably are,
[INAUDIBLE] 1 and minus 1.
Any other constant, other than the ones I
just named and maybe a handful of others,
generically speaking, they have a
provenance, and you can trace it back.
And they trace back to models of things,
or measurements, or experts, or a kind of
metric models, or mechanics or physics
models, or something like that, right?
And in fact, if you trace them all the way
back, you'd say, oh, you know,
that came from finite, finite element
calculation and blah, blah, blah.
And, by the way, that means they, those
numbers are suspect, right?
I mean, they could be accurate, two three
significant figures, maybe five,
right, maybe one, right?
Or, in economics, the sign is suspect,
right, or something like that.
>> [LAUGH]
>> I mean, you just don't, you know, so,
there's places where it's dominated,
right, I mean, so, you know, there's
extremes here, right?
so, alright.
So the point is, though, that in all these
cases you have, there,
there is error in the data, I mean, that's
just period, right?
And there are ways to handle it simply
simple methods, and
I've, we've seen one already.
Regularization is essentially, a method to
choose x's
that are not extremely vulnerable to
changes in a.
For example, that's a very simple example,
of a robust optimization problem.
But there are plenty of others, right?
By the way, how is parameter variation
handled in real life?
So what do you think is, by far, the most
prevalent method, for
handling the fact that, your parameters
are not known?
In that, in, in, in real life, I'm talking
about, when people actually solve things.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> What?
>> Ignore it.
>> Ignore it, thank you.
That is absolutely correct.
That is, by far, the prevalent method.
Now, that's okay in my opinion, provided
you do one thing, which is,
which, which then [INAUDIBLE] makes this
okay.
What would that one thing be to, to do?
It's the least you could do.
So you've just solved a problem.
You assumed that all your data was
accurate,
they're double precision numbers.
You got them from, you know, Bob or
whatever, some other intern, doesn't
matter.
You got the model and you did it.
What should you do now?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Generate a new A, with the entries
changed by a plausible amount.
Everybody got this?
Right?
And you just simply, test the, the x you
found before, with the new A.
And if things are way off now,
then you know that you cannot ignore
safely, robustness.
Has everybody got this?
I mean, this is incredibly simple, but
it's unbelievably important, and
it's actually shocking to me, how many
people don't do this, right?
So, but it's, this is just completely
standard.
If you come up and say, oh, wow, I've got
a fantastic, a fantastic force
sequence to land an airplane, you gotta
see this, it's just, it's unbelievable.
Yeah, it's like no, people don't even
notice it, when they're, I mean, you say,
okay fine, here it is.
You absolutely have to go back and change
the model,
change the total mass, move the center of
gravity, and re-simulate the same thing,
with these changed parameters, and you
have to do ten, 100 of these.
Now, after which by the way,
you know absolutely nothing, I might add,
technically.
But I mean,
from a strict point of view, right, but at
least you've done the common sense check.
Everybody got this, right?
If you, if you come and say, I've got a
trading strategy, it's unbelievable, and
they go, really?
And they go oh my god, you should see what
it did last year, unbelievable.
And then you'd say, well, did you try it
on the year before?
Yeah, no.
The main method, traditional method used
for handling uncertainty in data,
is to ignore it, and I would say, that's
actually a perfectly respectable option,
provided you do a posterior analysis of
the effect of the variations.
Then it's, then it's totally legit.
I mean, assuming the posterior analysis
reveals that it's, it works fine, okay.
Now, the next step, is to have a heuristic
that kind of, kind of is a heuristic for
kind of making sure things don't get too
wacky, when the parameters change.
That'd be like regularization, absolutely
fine.
Again, you do a posterior analysis, to
understand if it works.
And the new thing, this is been coming up,
maybe in the last, could be 20 years,
but, then it was done by a handful of
esoteric, you know work by academics.
It's now coming on mainline, main, main,
mainstream is this, you
simply take into account, the uncertainty,
directly in the problem statement, okay?
And so, that, these are called rob, that's
robust optimization, and
this is a special case.
Okay.
Now, we're jumping back to the specific,
that was the background.
We're jumping back to the specific
problem, we're looking at.
So you have to have a model for how A
varies, right?
And in one it's sto, it's stochastic.
You would say, A is random and
you'd describe its distribution, and the
distribution could even be finite.
Like you'd just say, it's got 25 values
with these probabilities, right?
By the way, that's an extremely reasonable
thing to do.
Because what you'd do is, if you tracked
the provenance of A, and it came from
other measurements and data, then what
you'd do, is you go back to someone there.
It's like cross validation or something,
if you know what that is.
But you'd go back and you'd say, here's a
model for my chemical process, and
you go great.
How'd you get it?
And you go, from data, I fitted from data.
Then you go, you know what, fit me a
separate model, for every day of the week.
I'd like to see, I'd like you to fit a
model for your chemical process for
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday, Saturday, Sunday, right?
So, you get seven models now, right?
Now, by the way, if you look at these A,
so now you have A Monday, A Tuesday, A.
Now, by the way,
if they're all completely different, you
should just turn around and go away.
Because basically, your host is nothing
you can do that, not,
it's nothing intelligent, this is not a
place for, us to be doing anything, right?
because it basically means, there's no
consistency and it doesn't make any sense.
Okay, fine.
So hopefully, all the entries of a Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday, they are closed.
In a worst case in a, in a worst case
robust fitting,
or approximation problem, you would do
this.
You would say, I'm not going to use a
stochastic model.
Instead, what I'm going to do is,
I'm simply going to, I'm going to have a
set of values of a and
I'm going to, I'm going to judge my fit,
by the worst case, right?
And by the way, there's everything in
between these two, right,
so these are just two.
And there's incredible, you know, complete
nonsense silly religious wars between
people who, you know, I mean, and it makes
no sense out of a context, right?
And in any particular context, it makes
tons of sense, as to discuss,
what would be a reasonable robustness
model.
But outside of a, context free, it makes
no sense whatsoever, right?
Mostly what you do, oh and
this is oh, this is sometimes called
minimax, minimax fitting.
This that doesn't have a name.
Yeah, it does, it's called stochastic
optimization.
Okay, so, that's the idea.
now, to sol, solving these problems is
tractable only in special cases.
I mean, in, in a lot of cases, it's not
tractable at all, but some are.
Here's, here's a super duper simple
example.
We have a matrix, which has,
a one parameter variation, it has the form
a0 plus ua1.
And u varies you know, between let's say,
1 and minus 1, something like this, right?
So, basically in matrix space, you have a
little line segment, right?
You know, I mean, hopefully it's not a
giant one, right?
But you know, its a little line segment?
And of course, in a more realistic one,
it's varying in a ball, I don't know, but
this has a line segment.
That's it, right?
So, okay, and you could actually easily
imagine, where the dominant
variation is one line, right, because it
could be some process that you run, and
in fact to first order, it's mostly
affected by, say, ambient temperature.
And so, the ambient temperature goes from,
you know,
10C to 35, and that changes the model,
right?
I mean, things like this happen all the
time, alright.
So, what you do here is, in this case, you
can solve all these problems, all of them.
And so, here are, this shows you a couple
of the solutions.
So, x nom simply ignores it entirely,
minimizes this.
And then what you do is, you take this x,
and
I calculate the norm here, as a function
of u, and that's plotted here.
So this is x nom, and the nominal point is
right here, and look at that, of course,
by definition, it has to get the lowest
value at, this is the nominal value,
sure enough, it does, it gets the lowest
value, it's right there.
But then you see, as u changes, you start
paying for it,
right, by rising, rising cost, okay?
So here's stoc,
the x stochastic, that minimizes the
average, over the interval, minus 1 1.
So, over here to here, that gives you this
one, here.
Sorry, this one here, this, this one here,
this is x stochastic, right?
And you can see that it, you pay for it,
in nominal performance, right?
because, at the very, you get a, at the
very, the stochastic one dips,
not as well, so the nominal performance is
a little bit worse.
But now, as u varies out to be 0.7 minus
0.8 you're actually doing much
better, okay?
So everybody, I mean, this is kind of
clear, but that's, that's the idea.
And the final one, shows worst case.
And that's this last one, is very flat,
you've paid for the cost, a nominal cost.
You do much worse than, if it's nominal.
But if you look at the minimax over minus
1, 1, you'd do very well, right?
So, this is just to illustrate, very
simple thing.
Okay, so, we can also handle, I mean,
some,
[INAUDIBLE], as an example of another
thing, as an analytical solution,
would be stochastic robust least squares,
so let's work that.
This is, this is an absolutely traditional
one.
It's kind of cool actually, and
it relates to something, we were talking
about, earlier.
It's this, suppose your matrix a, has the
form A bar, a nominal 1 plus u,
where u is random, 0 mean, and has
expected value transposed to u as p, okay?
So we want to minimize the expected value,
of the square,
of the two norm of this thing, [INAUDIBLE]
and
of course, the expectation's over the
distribution of u here, right?
So, they just work that out, I mean, you
expand this thing, the term,
the cross terms, like here, there's,
there's when you expand this quadratic,
there's a cost term which is, x transpose,
u transpose, a bar x minus b.
You take the expected value over u, u has
0 mean, those go away.
So the cross terms drop out, in the
expectation here, right?
Leaving you with the nominal cost, plus
this thing, and
you get that, and it's super cool.
You recognize that immediately, that's
regularization,
it's quadratic regularization.
And in fact, it's even cooler.
It basically says, if you do ticking off
regularization like this, which you
can claim to be doing, is you're actually
minimizing this, which is super cool.
And you say, you're minimizing this thing,
where, instead of thinking of the matrix
a as fixed, you're actually taking into
account, that every entry varies.
They're all independent and have a
variance which is,
I don't know, something like delta over n.
I mean, you can figure out what it is,
right?
Everybody got this?
So, it's actually super cool.
So, if you do, tickin off regularization
or, or, or ridge regression.
I guess, if you're in statistics and
you do ridge regression, you don't have to
justify it to anybody.
But if, if you're in a field where,
they don't have a special name for tickin
off regularization and
they ask, what are you doing, you could
say, oh, I'm doing robust least squares.
I'm taking into account, minor variations
in the As.
Everybody got it?
Now, we can do some worst case ones.
I'm not going to go into the details here,
because they're kind of of hairy.
This, this is quite new, this is something
that's like 15-20 years old.
So lets do the case where, the matrix A,
actually is at,
lies in an ellipsoid of matrices, again
completely reasonable.
And what we really want to minimize, is
the worst case.
So, it's going to be a weird thing if you
like, it's a game or
something like that or it, it slight
again, you know,
basically you choose, you commit to x
first and then,
your opponent will then choose the worst
possible a, that's what this is, right?
So this is so it's something like that.
and, there turns out, something like this,
you can solve exactly, right?
So if you work it out, and again, I'm not
going to go through any of the details
because they're quite hairy, and in some
sense, it doesn't really matter.
I mean, you should go back over and check
it.
Now it turns out that here, when,
one, when the opponent is calculating,
what's the worst thing I should do,
they've committed to x, and I'm going to
find the [INAUDIBLE].
You end up solving this problem, and
that is a non-convex problem, if I ever
saw one, right, because the objective,
is you're maximizing a quadratic, right,
convex quadratic, right?
Now you haven't seen this yet.
Maybe you did or something, but
it's maybe, time for you to know this, so
I'm going to say it.
I'm going to use this as an excuse, to let
you know.
There are some generic, non-convex
problems that can be solved, okay?
And the simplest one, has a very simple
and short description length.
Any optimization problem, involving two
quadratics, can be solved globally, okay?
Everybody got that?
That's in an appendix of the book,
you should read it or remember what I just
said, okay?
Because it actually comes up, in a whole
bunch of different applications, right?
So, and, and that's convexity, not
convexity.
And, you know, lot, by the way,
you know this already, if I walked up to
you and I said oh, you know,
please help me solve, you know, this
problem, a is symmetric, you know, right?
Something like that.
I said, please maximize this thing, right?
How do you maximize that, subject to that?
Well, that, that sure is, no convex
optimization problem, right?
Because this thing was not concave, unless
A is an, an,
unless A is, is negative definite.
Okay, negative semi-definite, right?
There's no way, that's never a convex
constraint, right?
That, that's a sphere, right?
So, that's a hideously,
non-convex problem, but everyone here
knows the answer,
knows, this can be solved, and it's
basically, an eigenvalue problem, right?
The answer is, the largest eigen, the
eigenvector corresponding to the,
it's the largest eigenvalue, and blah,
blah, blah.
Everybody got that?
Right, so, alright.
This fits the thing, I'm saying here.
That is an optimization problem, and it
involves, exactly two quadratic functions.
And the general statement is this.
Any optimization problem with exactly two
quadratic functions,
can be solved exactly.
And so, what that says is, you know, if
someone says, what are you doing?
I'm taking a class on convex optimization.
Oh, is it interesting?
I don't know.
And then they, then you say, well, are all
problems convex?
You go, oh, no, no, no.
And then someone says, name a widely used,
useful problem, that's not convex.
The first thing you should mention, I
would hope,
would be things like, singular value
decomposition, PCA eigenvalues, okay?
Well, you know, what this says?
This says those are convex.
Sorry.
So I mean, it's kind of weird and obscure,
right?
But, and the reason by the way,
is that the duals of these problems, have
zero duality gap.
So, anyway, alright.
So this, I was just my weird little aside,
but this is an advanced thing.
This is not a simple thing, but it's an
extremely good thing to know, right?
So, and if you include these, you'd be
very hard pressed to find problems,
any problem you can solve, that is not
convex, if you include these.
So, that, and that is an open challenge.
So, so, okay.
So, this one actually, can be solved, by
solving it's dual, which is this SDP.
Doesn't matter, the, the fact is, it's
zero duality gap, right?
so, okay, now it's fine, because you want
to minimize over choice of x, this thing,
but this thing has just been expressed, as
a minimization function, right?
And therefore, you minimize both at the
same time.
You solve this SDP, and you solve,
you actually solve exactly, this robust
least squares problem, right?