Today we're going to look at applications
of well, geometric problems.
And again, some of these are very, very
simple, and so, we actually skip them.
Things like computing projections of, of a
point onto a convex set.
Doing things like, calculating distance
between two convex sets,
these are just too simple, to even
mention.
So we're going to skip those,
although they're [NOISE] they're kind of
obvious, by now.
know, an example of that would be,
how do you compute the distance between
two polyhedra, right?
So, without even writing it down, you
should know by now, that's just a QP.
You know, you minimize norm x minus y, to
norm subject to,
you know, ax less than b, and fz less than
g.
Okay, so we don't cover that kind of
stuff, because it's too simple.
Instead, we're going to focus on stuff
that's less obvious.
And really I mean quite interesting and
very useful.
So the first topic is going to be the
Lowner-John ellipsoid.
And this, this is not obvious, although
these things have been known for
about a 100 years, although not, nothing
was about it, computationally.
Right, this was not an algorithmic thing,
this was just theory, until maybe, 20
years ago.
So, basic idea is, you want to compute the
minimum volume ellipsoid that
covers a set, and it's completely general.
So, I have a set c, and what I'm going to
do,
is compute the minimum volume ellipsoid
that covers it, so that, that's the idea.
By the way, there's tons of applications
of this, right?
One would be, to give a, c could be very
large, very complex and
instead, all you want, is sort of a
summary of c, that is, is smaller, right?
And so, to describe, an ellipsoid takes on
the order of n squared,
in fact n squared over 2, parameters to
describe an ellipsoid, in Rn.
So that's sort of, a compact, way to do
this.
And this approximation, covering a bunch
of,
when you're covering a bunch of points,
it's a conservative one.
I guess, so you'd say, that you're
going to cover more, than just the points.
Alright.
Now, generically, you can solve this
problem.
I should be more careful about it.
We can generically write this, as a convex
optimization problem.
So, computing the minimum volume
ellipsoid.
But there's going to be an expression that
comes up in the constraints,
that may be handle, depends on that being
tractable,
before this becomes a tractable convex
program, right?
Oh, and I guess, we've we're far enough
along in the class, that it's time for
you to do, we, we can actually be more
honest here and admit things like,
they're non-tractable convex optimization
problems, this is kind of obvious right?
Because of [INAUDIBLE] convex optimization
problem, but for
example, to evaluate the objective or a
constrain function,
is itself intractable, then you're in
trouble, right?
So, okay.
So what we'll do, is we'll, this is very
carefully chosen parameterization of
the ellipsoid, and we're going to write it
as this.
It's the inverse image of the unit ball,
under an affine mapping, right?
So, so, we're going to take the ellipsoid
e,
to be the set of points, for which the two
norm of av plus b, is less than 1, right?
So, that's the inverse image of the unit
ball,
under the affine mapping, av plus b, okay?
Now here, a here of course, a could be
anything.
I mean, well it has to be square, but it
wouldn't even have to be square.
But we can, without loss of generality,
we're going to take,
we're going to take a, to be symmetric
positive definite, okay?
Now the argument there, I'm just going to
go over it very briefly here,
so this is going to be a little bit
obscure, but hope you can follow up.
The argument is this.
here, I can multiply a and b,
on the left, by any orthogonal matrix, and
it will define the same ellipsoid.
Everyone agree with that,
because it doesn't change, it doesn't
change the norm.
But if that's the case, I can take an
arbitrary non-singular matrix,
multiply on the left, by an appropriate
orthogonal matrix, and
make it symmetrically positive definite,
right?
And the way you do that, again, I'll just
talk through it because it's,
I don't know, we're far enough along, that
we can do this, we can, go faster.
You just take this singular value
decomposition of a.
So, you have u sigma v transpose, and you
multiply on the left, by like you know,
v u transpose, and that's an orthogonal
matrix, and
it converts into symmetric positive
definite, okay?
So that's the idea.
Now the volume of this ellipsoid,
is proportional to the determinant of a
inverse.
In fact the, the pro, the constant
inproportionality,
is exactly the volume of the unit ball, in
rn, right?
Which, which actually doesn't,
if we're minimizing, it hardly matters
what that is.
It's something, it's got some pi's in it,
and some gamma functions, or
factorials and things like that, but it
doesn't really matter.
It's, so, it's proportional to the
determinant of A inverse, right?
Because when you, when things map under
affine mappings, or
linear mapping, affine mappings, volumes
transforms like determinants, okay?
So, alright, so now our problem looks like
this.
It says, minimize over variables, a and b.
Log det A inverse, right?
So that's the log of the volume, well, up
to a constant, right,
because it's an additive thing.
Subject to the condition, that every point
c, is in this set, and one way to say that
is that, for every point in c, the norm of
ab plus b, is less than 1, right so.
And you could write this, this way or
you could write it as, I could remove the
soup and say, for all vnc, okay?
And that would be the, the condition,
right?
So, that's the, that's the condition.
You might ask, why does it say in
parentheses here, over here ab?
Because these, well,
this kind of problem generically, ends up
with maximally confusing notation.
And then of course, norm, norm of linear
is convex, and this is true for any v.
So supremum, that's point y supremum,
that's convex.
So, okay, so here, that's a convex
optimization problem and
it computes the minimum volume ellipsoid,
that covers this at c.
Now, the question's whether it's tractable
or not, and
it's tractable precisely when this
constraint is handleable, right?
so, here's a simple case where it is,
there's actually a whole bunch,
where it is, I mean, not a whole bunch,
but there's, there's, there's a bunch of
cases where it tractable but here's one
where it is, lets look at this.
Let, let's take c to be a finite set.
So, I have a cloud of points, and
I want to compute the minimum volume
ellipsoid that covers it, right?
So that's the, that's the idea.
So here, well that's very simple because
it's the supreme, sup, v and
c is nothing but
a, that requires that each, each of these
points is in the set and so, you get this.
And of course, that's the Lowner-John
ellipsoid for
a polyhedron, described by its, its
verticies, right?
So what that says is, if I give you a
bunch of points, like this, and
then you calculate, then, then you take
the convex hull, right?
Then computing the minimum volume
ellipsoid that covers that
is an entirely tractable convex problem,
okay?
So by the way these things are, are not
obvious here.
So for example if I, I could give you an
ellipsoid, described as, sorry,
a polyhedron described as the convex hull
of a set of points.
And so, that can give you vertices, and
I could ask, find me the maximum volume
ellipsoid, that lies inside it.
That's, that's another natural problem,
that we'll look at shortly, that's
actually NP-hard, okay?
So, so these things are, I mean,
you really have to be very careful with
these things, right?
It depends on the description and it
depends you know,
whether it's extremely easy or extremely
hard, depends on the description.
Okay, so that's the Lowner–John ellipsoid.
well, the dual, roughly, of that, is the
maximum volume inscribed ellipsoid.
So, here, we have, this time, the set has
to be convex.
I mean, it doesn't have to be convex, but
then, it's actually quite intractable,
right?
So we take, a convex set, and then the
idea is,
we want to find the maximum volume
ellipsoid, that sits inside it, okay?
And, we do that this way.
This time, we're going to parameterize the
ellipsoid, as the forward image,
as opposed to the inverse image of the
unit vol, under an affine mapping.
So here, it's the set of points bu plus d,
where u is in a unit vol, right?
So, by the way, there are lots of
different parameterizations of ellipsoids,
as general linear algebra,
that would go between the different
canonical representations, right?
It'd be elementary linear algebra like you
know,
square roots of matrices, things like
that.
What's interesting, is they all have
different convexity properties, right?
So, a problem would be convex in one, but
not the other.
So whenever you have problems in,
when you optimize over ellipsoids, they're
actually kind of fun.
Because it's not, it's not like a problem,
where something's just just given to you
on a platter.
You have to figure out the appropriate
representation, to make it convex, if,
if, if it's even, if that even exists,
right?
So, okay, so here's the forward image, and
in this case,
the volume is proportional to the
determinant.
We want to maximize it, so we maximize log
log determinant, right,
which you recognize as tractable, because
log determinant is concave.
And here, the condition is this this
condition right here,
is simply this, right?
So that's the, that, this condition here,
says that if you take the unit ball and
you multiply b by it, add d, that this set
lies entirely in c.
So that looks like this, right?
I mean, this is just a long and
complicated way to say that, for
all u of norm less than 1, bu plus d, is
in c, right?
I guess this is, it's written this way, so
that we can verify instantly, that this is
convex, right?
And the way to do that, is very simple.
This thing, that expression, is linear in
the variables, which are b and d.
ic, that's the indicator function, that's,
of course, convex, so that's convex.
So for each u, this is convex, that's a
supremum of convex functions, so
that means that the left-hand side is
convex, so you have a convex inequality.
Okay, so, once again, the issue is the
following.
Is this, is evaluating that function,
tractable, right?
And there's very simple cases, where it's
not.
Here's one, if I simply give you a finite
number of points, and
I ask you, does that hold there, that's
actually, that, that,
that one is actually going to be np hard,
right?
Not, not a finite number point, sorry.
The convex hull, of a finite number of
points, that's actually np hard.
Right?
So so it's sometimes tractable,
sometimes it's not.
But here and there's a kind of, a
pre-duality here.
What's interesting is, it turns out,
remember that computing the minimum volume
ellipsoid [COUGH] is tractable.
The canonical case is, when you give the
vertices.
So, computing the maximum volume ellipsoid
is tractable and again,
almost, aesthetics almost requires this
right,
because just to make it pretty it's the
dual representation of ellipse,
of a polyhedron, which is in fact, given
by its linear inequalities, right?
So, so what happens is here, if I give you
polyhedron defined by linear inequalities,
then, this is really simple because
basically you're asking, when is it true,
that ai transpose times bu plus d,
is less than bi for all u, less than one,
right?
That's the question.
What are the conditions on b and d, under
which this holds, right?
And this is actually, relatively easy to
work out, right?
So you have, ai transpose d, that comes
out fine, and then here,
you need to calculate, you know, what's
the largest possible value of that?
Well, that's easy, that's the converse
Cauchy-Schwartz inequality, right?
Because it says, you have a, you have
something, which is b a i, and then
you take an inner product of b a i with a
vector u, whose norm is less than one.
And you want to know the maximum value of
that, and
the answer is, the norm of b a i, alright?
That's Cauchy- Schwartz or the converse of
Cauchy-Schwartz, okay?
So, this problem translates to this, that
is again,
you have to be on your toes here, because
of the variables are b and
d, which, which parameterize the ellipsoid
here.
And that, otherwise these are just
completely legitimate constraints,
that's a clearly a concave function, that
you're maximizing.
And the inequality here, again, with band
d,
that's a linear term, here, that's linear
in b, right?
And so that norm term, so these are
second-order constraints.
So, there's actually some very interesting
things you can show,
about these ellipsoidal approximations.
So let's take a convex, you know, bounded
non-empty interior set and,
it's the following, that there's actually
this basic efficiency.
It says that, if you take a set, so
here's one, here's a polyhedron, given by
its vertices.
This is the Lowner-John ellipsoid the
minimum volume ellipsoid that covers it.
It, it says that if you take that
Lowner-John Ellipsoid and
you shrink it by a factor of n, that's the
space dimension, right about its center.
That's guaranteed to be inside the set,
okay?
Everybody, got that?
And so, actually what that says is that,
you can, I'm going to say it something
like this, it says that, any convex set in
rn, can be approximated, within a factor.
In fact, here, I'll even try it this way.
Within a, it can be approximated within a
factor of square root n, by an ellipsoid.
Everybody got that?
Now, I mean, you might not like the factor
square root n, but
the point is, that's what says.
Everybody, and by the way, that statement
is completely false.
I mean, you can talk about things like,
with other, with other classes of
geometric objects, right you could talk
about things, like a bounding box, right?
And it's just completely false, right?
All sorts of things you might imagine,
things, data structures to
describe regions in rn, and it's just not,
not the case.
I mean, there are others, right?
One would be like, a simplex, right so
that's another one.
Now, by the way, in this example, you can
see that that factor of two,
I mean this is in space dimension two,
right?
In here, you can see, the factor of two
was not needed.
It's quite likely, I mean in this case,
take a look at it.
Here, I mean, we can eyeball it, okay?
Probably, you didn't have to divide by
factor of two, but
by, you just divide it by 20-30%, and
you're inside, okay?
And by the way, that factor is an
interesting number, you might call that,
you know, how ellipsoidally approximable,
this set is or something, I don't know.
So, everybody see what I'm saying here?
So here, it just guarantees, by the way,
what's the worst possible set to
approximate, by an ellipsoid?
What is the convex set, that is the worst
possible one?
Simplex, there we go.
Okay, so let's do triangle, like this.
You know, there's your minimum volume
ellipsoid's, a circle.
There's, there it is, and in this case,
guess what?
You have to shrink it exactly by a factor
of n, before it fits inside, and
that tells you, that this factor of n
cannot be improved, okay?
So the least ellipsoidally approximable
convex set, is a simplex.
I've drawn it this way, but in fact, all
of these ellipsoid approximation methods,
they're actually invariant under affine
transformations, right?
Because if I take a set if I multiply it,
you know,
if I apply an affine transformation,
what'll happen is, volume transforms under
affine transformation, just by a
determinant, by a constant.
So, you get a commutative diagram.
In other words, if you take the original
set affine transformation,
optimal ellipsoid, then apply an affine
transformation of the optimal ellipsoid,
you get the optimal ellipsoid for the
second case.
You get a commutative diagram, okay?
So it's, in other words, you might say
something like this.
Extremal volume ellipsoidal approximation,
is affinely invariant.
Everybody got that?
That's actually quite important actually
it's quite important in practice, right,
because it says that, if the Xs represent
things and,
you actually don't have any idea how this
scale should go together.
I mean if, if it means nothing to you,
then there are plenty of cases like that,
then it says you'd, I mean you should
probably whatever your method is,
should be affinely variant.
So, oh I should say something like this,
if the, if the polyhedron is, is
symmetric.
Symmetric means, if x is in the set, so is
minus x, right?
So an example would be, a norm ball.
Then it says, you can, this factor is not
n, but square root n, okay?
And I said something obscure at first.
I said, any convex set can be approximated
by an ellipsoid,
within a factor square root n, right?
And so, let me explain what I was saying.
That's kind of I, I, I, I take the minimum
volume one and
I divide by square root n, right?
So, I put the one that's geometrically in
the middle.
And what that means is, for any convex
set,
I can produce a convex set which has the
property that if I expand it,
square root n, I cover, and if I shrink
it, square root n, I'm inside, okay?
So, actually, philosophically, it's quite
interesting.
It's that, you could, you can argue
something like this.
Ellipsoids are universal approximators of
convex sets, yeah?
I mean, square root n, is not a fantastic.
By the way, it's the fourth root of m, for
sym-, symmetric, right?
You know, you might not like that.
But the point is, it's a constant, right?
And, and that, that's it.
I mean, its even a constant that doesn't
grow that badly, and
all that kind of stuff.
And so, so this is kind of interesting,
and it kind of explains a lot about,
how, why things like quadratic methods,
would be so prevalent.
By the way, one, one interesting think you
can say here, is the following.
Any norm on rn, can be approximated by a
quadratic norm,
within a factor of N to the 1 4th, okay?
And that's interesting right, because it
says that, anything, any,
any norm and there are some very
sophisticated norms, right?
It's as if, every single one is
approximately with,
within, into the 1 4th, by a quadratic
one, right?
So that tells you actually, I think it, to
me, this is sort of a philosophical,
this explains why least square, why using
least squares for
the last two centuries, people have gotten
pretty far, right?
This this at least explains it, right?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Next topic is Centering.
So I mean, and here is tons and tons of
applications of centering.
I'll just address that first you've seen a
couple already,
even in the first couple of weeks.
We saw yield maximization, so yield
maximization says,
that you're running a manufacturing
process, you want to tell your machine,
to target a certain set of like, critical
dimensions, let's say an IC manufacturer.
But since you're pushing it, right, you're
pushing it absolutely to the limited
technology, when you say, please make this
critical dimension one nanometer.
it's act-, it's going to be off, a little
bit and things like that, so
there's variations.
And so, there you have a, a polyhedron
that describes the acceptable,
acceptable critical pairs you know,
combinations are critical dimensions.
Now, what you want is, you want to tell
them, you want to,
the target you want to shoot for, is
something deep in, deep in that set.
So, that when you have variations away
from it you're still in it,
your yield is high, okay?
So, we, we looked at all that.
So, so, that comes up and we've even seen
some of these problems.
So, here's one, find the center of the
largest inscribed ball.
That's the Chebyshev center, and that's
this problem.
I give you a polyhedron described by
inequalities, and I say,
please find me the ball of maximum radius
that fits inside, and
the center of that, we're going to call
the Chebyshev center.
And it's the point deepest in the deepest
in the polyhedron, right?
And and that means, well it's clearly
defined, right?
It' it's the one which have highest depth,
highest distance to the exterior right,
that's this.
And that's an LP, that was actually one of
our first examples, when we looked at LP.
And it was a fun example,
because it doesn't look like it should be
an LP, right?
because, well it looks like an LP, while
you're drawing the polyhedron outside, but
the minute you draw a ball, that should,
you know,
that, that should not evoke LP, right?
But it's an LP.
Okay, a more sophisticated one,
is the center of the maximum volume
ellipsoid.
Actually that's quite interesting because
this one is actually,
invariant under affine coordinate
transformations, right?
Now, that may not be relevant to you,
right?
If, if, your coordinates are things you
know about,
you're intimately familiar with them, and
you really do know the range of
each one and they all have separate
meanings, good for you.
And affine invariance doesn't mean
anything, right?
But in a lot of, in a lot of cases, that's
just not true, right?
That these are, these are sort of
arbitrary coordinates,
these might features or
something like that, and you don't know
the scale or anything, right?
You pick a reasonable scale and that's
about all you can do.
Okay, so, so this is one, this is the
center of the maximum volume ellipsoid.
There's one,
that we are going to be looking at very
much in the next couple of weeks.
We'll see this, it'll take a while, but
maybe in three weeks, two and
a half weeks, and that's the analytic
center.
So, this is a good time to look at it.
So, the analytic sensor is actually not,
it's not a function of the set,
it's actually a function of the
description of the set.
So, technically, I don't know,
it's not the same as the minimum volume
ellipsoid and all that kind of stuff.
So, here's what it is.
Suppose, I have a set of convex
inequalities and equalities.
Then, I simply form the following problem.
I minimize the sum of the logs of the
minus fi's,
the fi's of course, minus fi, well it has
a perfect interpretation,
it's the margin in the affine inequality,
right?
because the, the third inequality says, f3
has to be negative, less than or
equal to zero, right?
So, if f3 is minus 2.1 you have a margin
of 2.1.
So these are the margins here, right?
Positive means you're in the interior of
the set,
well relative interior because of this,
okay?
So here, this is log its, its the sum of
the logs of the margins,
well it's the product of the margins,
right?
So this says, maximum the product of the
margins, that's what this is, okay?
And, this comes up in a lot of things.
That's a convex optimization problem of
course, right,
because minus log minus, [INAUDIBLE] is a
convex increasing function, right?
I mean, you know to trace through the two
minuses, to see what happens, right?
The first minus changes the sign,
the monotonicity and it changes concave to
convex.
And the second one chain flips the
uh,monotonicity, okay?
So or, makes it go back to be increasing,
right?
So, so the by the composition rule, this
is a convex function, here.
That, that, and that's called the this
function is called the log barrier, right?
So, it's a barrier function, right?
And the meaning of that is that, on this
set of points,
where this is strictly less than zero,
this thing's finite,
as you move that point towards any point,
where one of these goes to zero,
one of these margins goes to zero, and the
product goes to infinity, right?
Well, certain, the sum of the negative log
minus, negative log margins,
goes to infinity, right?
So this actually is, extremely easy to
solve.
I mean, it depends on the definition, it
depends how f is given, but
we'll see that later.
But it's not a property of the feasible
set, it's actually, it's,
it's a function of the description of the
problem, and that'll be clear in a minute.
But, for fun, let's just look at the
analytic center,
of a set of linear inequalities.
So, here's a set of linear inequalities
like this, and what's plotted here,
are various things.
These dash curves show the level sets of
the log, this is the log barrier.
And what's, what are showing here, are the
level sets of the log barrier, right?
So, actually if you say, what's the level
sets?
Wh, where are they equal?
Whe, where's it equal to 1000?
You get, a kind of a cool little, you know
curve, a smooth curve here,
which hugs the boundary of this thing,
very closely, right?
And then, as I decrease that number, this
number is one, by the way.
When I decrease that number to one, it's
looking more ellipsoidal, it's not.
And as I keep going lower and lower, and
actually the Hessian, the hessian of this
thing, at the analytic center
is actually a good ellipse quadratic
summary, of the shape of this set, right?
So that, that, that's a good, a good way
to do that, right?
So, so actually, in a lot of cases where,
you know, you know how to do something,
if you had a quadratic representation or
something like that.
We'll see optimization methods, where this
is the case or
statistical methods, where this is the
case.
But you don't have anything like that.
What you have, is a complicated convex
set.
One option, is to do something like this.
I mean, another option, of course,
is calculate maximum volume ellipsoid
inside it, and so on, okay.
Now, it turns out here, there are
guaranteed approximations, right?
So, one is this.
It turns out, that if you form the
following.
So, the inner ellipsoid is, you go to the
center and
you take the ellipsoid given, defined by
the hessian of the analytic center,
that actually, with a one here, that
always lies inside the set, and
this one, always lies outside the set,
covers the set.
This is a worse approximation ratio, than
the maximum volume one, right?
And the reason is this, this number here
is m, let's call it m squared.
You take the square root and that gives
you the expansion size, right?
So it says, that if you, I mean it says
this, it says,
that if you take this thing, here, that's
shown in dark, in shaded here.
That ellipsoid is inside this set and
if I expand it by a factor m, which is by
the way, not the ambiance base dimension.
It's actually the number of inequalities,
but
the inequalities is at least, n plus 1,
because it takes n plus 1,
in equalities, in our n, to get a bounded
region.
And if you have n plus 1, you have a
simplex, right?
So, that's the so, this is a worse
approximation ratio.
So, I mean, it's not clear that matters,
right?
Oh one question here.
Here, I have let's see, 1, 2, 3, I have
six inequalities,
but analytic center is not a function of
set, it's a function of the inequalities.
What if I added a new inequality, that
looked like that, so it says, it says,
please stay on this side of that
inequality, shift select?
Exactly, right?
And in fact, the following is true.
Given a polyhedron or actually, just, just
given a set,
I can take any point in the interior and
pile up a bunch of, this is a,
you could call that a redundant, or
irrelevant, inequality, right?
It doesn't do, it doesn't change the set.
So I can pile up redundant inequalities
and I can, I can get you,
I can get any point in the interior, to be
the analytic center, right?
So the, all that says is, analytic center
is a,
is an attribute of the description of the
set, not the set itself, 'kay?
So, so technically it's not, it's not a
question of geometry,
right, it has to do with the description,
okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Another topic is Linear Discrimination.
So, and if you've had a course on sort of,
machine learning or
something like that, or modern statistics,
you'll, you've seen things like this.
So, here's the problem.
This is actually also, quite an old
problem.
I think it goes back, at least to the 40s,
something like that.
I don't know how old the perceptron
algorithm is, but.
So you have a set of points, x1 through
xn, y1 through ym, and in some, rn.
And the idea is to determine, whether
they, you can separate them by hyperplane,
and if so, find such a hyperplane, right?
And there's actually a few tricks here,
you want to watch very carefully in
the next few minutes, because you will be
doing these things yourself.
And the arguments are, well they're not
totally subtle,
but, I mean, you have to, all I'm saying
is, you better listen, okay?
That, that, that's the right way to do it.
So, here and I'll, I'll, I'll go over it a
bit slowly.
So, what it is, is, you really want to
know, whether or
not, this set of inequalities is feasible?
Now, the first thing you notice about
those inequalities, is they're strict.
And you might say, hey, wait a minute,
we've been doing this class for
a long time, we haven't seen strict
inequalities before, right?
And then you might say something like
this.
You might think about it for a minute, and
this would generally,
it would generally be true, the following
would be true.
If your problem, if the difference between
a strict inequality and
a non-strict inequality, like changes your
problem.
That's kind of a, mathematical pathology,
right?
You know what i'm saying, right?
If you say, hey, I just built a you know,
I, I, I just built a, a, a machine that
gives, you know, the correct dose on a, on
a tumor or something like that.
And I can satisfy these inequalities, and
someone says, oh, you know,
what are they which inequalities can you?
You say, I can do the non-strict one.
You go, no, no, it has to be strict.
I mean, it just makes absolutely no sense.
No sense whatsoever, right?
Because the difference between the two, I
mean it can hardly matter that,
that if it turns out, the difference
between putting 49.999 grays on
some on some tumor voxel, and 50.
If that really makes a difference, then
give up and
go home, because this doesn't make any
sense, this is not the real world, right?
Or that would be something like in
finance, a hedge fund.
You come back and you go, oh, great news,
I can, I can, I can get this return, with
this risk level.
And they go, equal, equal to the risk
level, or less than?
I mean, the answer is, your risk model is
so ridiculous, it's just totally made up,
so the point is, if somebody is telling
you, there's a difference between strict
inequality and non strict inequality, it
just makes no sense.
Everybody follow me on this?
Okay, right.
So, let's apply that common sense
principle here.
Let's take this and go like this, like
that, okay?
There you go.
Now you tell me.
Now, now the, the I mean the good news is,
the problem has become actually,
substantially easier.
So the answer is, a equals b equals 0, is
feasible, okay?
Everybody, everybody got that?
Okay, alright.
So, so
that didn't, so, the, the, the standard
method, right, didn't work here.
Okay, so that means that, the common
method doesn't work.
Okay, so let's do something.
Here, you have to be a bit more subtle.
What you do, is you observe, that these
inequalities are homogeneous, in a and
b, okay?
So that's, in other words, if, if there's
a and b for which [COUGH] ai transpose x
plus b is positive, then I guarantee you,
there's a and b for which, a transpose x
plus b, is bigger and equal to sorry is,
is, is bigger and equal to 1 okay?
Why?
I mean, you just scale them all up, until
it's true, right?
So what it says is, we replace this with
this, and
I would strongly recommend that you, you
know, go to a quiet place and make
sure you understand exactly, the semantics
of, what went down there, right, right?
It is not the same as saying,
that a strict inequality is always the
same as replacing with 1, right?
So you have to make the observation,
that these are homogeneous, that I can
scale them.
And there, then this is, then, then they
become equivalent, okay?
So, that's the, that's the idea.
This is a bona fide set of linear
inequalities.
And in fact, that's a linear program, in a
and b, right?
So, interestingly, questions about linear
discrimination, it took a,
unfortunately a shock, a much longer time
than it should have, for
somebody to look up one day and say, oh
hey, that's a linear program, right?
So, so sadly, historically, but, but it
really did.
In fact, whole algorithms were worked out,
to solve these kinds of things,
before it was understood, that other
people had worked out,
other whole algorithms to solve these
kinds of things, and so on and so forth.
I mean, now I think, that is even a legacy
of that, in current machine learning.
I mean, there's some weird,
anywyay, maybe I won't go, I won't go any
farther, but, okay, alright.
So what does this say?
This says, that if I give you a bunch of
points, pairs of points and you know,
these might be like labels or say
something like that.
Then, it says, I can now, by solving an
lp, I can determine if they are,
you would know, linearly separable or
linearly discriminable, right?
So, you could test, and, if you can,
if they are, you can exhibit or deduce a
the separating hyperplane.
Now, you can optimize over that
hyperplane,
we're going to see that next, right?
Like, you could, you know, find the
smallest one, or,
we'll see all sorts of things you could
work, you could optimize now, right?
And what would be the idea behind this?
Well, it might be something like this.
This is a giant pile of data.
Here, in fact you'd call this you, you'd
say labels, right?
So you'd, these would be feature vectors,
right?
So this is, I look at, let's say, 1
billion emails, right?
Each one is labeled, as either spam and
not spam, right?
So that's, I don't know, that's spam,
that's not spam, okay?
And how do I know that?
Because I watched, when someone junked
something or something like that, so
I got a pretty good idea of the labels.
And let's say, each of these is a, I have
a feature that's, let's say, I'll be
safe here, let's make it just like, five,
10,000 features, right, for each email.
And make it, a lot of these features,
these features are kind of obvious,
they're, what you think they would be.
They'd be things like word counts and
things like that.
Alright, so you'd take a billion of these
points, some Xs, some Ys, right?
And then you'd want to know, in R1000 or
10,000, whatever we, however many features
we decided there were, you'd like to know,
if there was a hyperplane in between them.
And, but if there were a hyperplane, then
you, then it'd be easy because now,
you'd take that hyperplane.
A new email comes in, you compute its
feature vector, find out,
which side of the hyperplane you're on,
and either announce it's spam, or not.
And in fact, even the distance of the
hyperplane would tell you something,
like if it was way off, in, on one side,
you might say,
with high confidence, that it is spam or
not.
Everybody got this?
Okay.
Now actually, you would be quite nervous,
if, in fact, it separated.
[LAUGH] Right?
There'd be something deeply wrong, in, in
this case, but
at least, that's abstractly the idea, of
the use of these types of things, right?
So, okay, we will get to that.
So it turns out, actually, a very simple
varia, very simple variation on this,
produces something that's actually
extremely effective, right, so.
Okay, so the first thing we're going to
look at, is this.
If you, you have a set of linear
inequalities, right?
That just detects a hyperplane, but the
point is, there's lots of hyperplanes that
separate two clouds of points, if they're
separable.
If they're linearly discriminable, there's
lots of hyperplanes.
So the, by the way,
there's lots of ways you could choose a
hyperplane that separates them, right?
They're lots of reasonable ways to do it.
One way would be to do some kind of
robustness thing, and
one would do that, you would do something
like this.
You can imagine the, the hyperplane is, a
transpose z, plus b is 0, right?
But instead, what we could do is, we could
take the point where that's one and
minus one, and everything in between those
two parallel hyperplanes,
that's a slab, right?
And then, we could very reasonably ask to
find,
to compute the maximum width slab, that
separates the two points, right?
And by the way, what's nice about that, I
mean,
some people will call this thing the
maximum margin classifier, right?
And the reason it's maximum margin is
that,
you can puff up each of these points, by a
ball.
Still classfiied correctly, and the amount
you can puff 'em up by,
is the largest possible, and still
maintain correctness.
Everybody got that?
So, it's maximum margin classifier
[INAUDIBLE].
Okay, completely reasonable, right?
But, the width of the slab is exactly, 2
over the norm of a, right?
So, that's the right?
I mean, if the norm of a were 1, then,
well, a trans plus x plus b,
literally is the signed distance to the
hyperplane, if the norm of a is 1.
If norm of a is big, then in fact the slab
is small, right?
So, okay.
So, then it says, please let's maximize
[COUGH] 2 over the norm of a2.
That's the same as minimizing norm, a2,
and so you'd say, minimize the norm of a2,
subject to these inequalities, and now we
get a qp, and that, that's the maximum
margin classifier, if I'm saying that
correctly, in whatever dialect that is.
Oh, and I guess they would do this,
because it's not,
yeah, you'd have to square the objective,
you'd do something like that, right?
It'd be the same thing, okay.
Okay so now, now if two sets are
separable, linearly separable,
we at least, have a very nice, a, and
utterly reasonable way to to find
a hyperplane that separates them.
It's kind of like it clearly has some good
properties, okay.
A very interesting thing,
is to look at the dual of this, and we'll
do that quickly.
So, I, I just mechanically worked out the
dual of, of the separation problem.
So, the dual of this problem right, this
maximum margin
problem is exactly this, it's maximize
this function, subject to.
And here, what you see, is something very
interesting.
I get two sets of, of I get two sets of
lagrange multipliers, lambda and mu,
they are associated exactly, with the two
sets of linear inequalities, right?
The, the for the Xs and for
the Ys, I have these kind of, inequalities
go the wrong way.
And you get some very interesting
constraints, I get a norm constraint here,
these are, well, those are inequalities,
so, these things are non-negative.
And I get this equality constraint here.
So, again, everything is homogeneous here.
So, what we're going to do is the
following, is,
I'm going to normalize these things here
to be, I'll take both of these to be one,
whereupon, lambda and mu become well,
they're probability distributions or
they are, I don't know, they're convex
mixtures, right?
They're, they're numbers that are
non-negative, and add up to one.
But, if these are numbers that add up non
negative, and
add up to one, these two things are really
simple.
They are elem, they are arbitrary elements
in the convex hull,
of the x-point cloud and the y-point
cloud, right?
And so,
that says, I can rewrite the problem to
look like this, and it's really beautiful.
It says, it basically says, take the
convex hull of the x-point cloud,
convex hull of the y-point cloud, and
actually calculate,
that's an arbitrary point in one,
arbitrary point in the other.
And it says, this is the epigraph, I mean,
minimizing t subject is the same as just,
you just minimize this thing here.
It, it's actually says, find the minimum
distance between two
ellipse two polyhedra, described by their
vertices.
Everybody got that?
So that was it, it makes perfect sense.
So now you know, when are two point,
when are two point clouds separable,
linearly separable.
The answer is, if and only if, and
straight from duality is this, it's if and
only if, the convex hulls don't intersect,
that's it, 'kay?
So the, and that's duality, right?
That's, that's exactly what duality is.
[COUGH] Everybody, everybody, this doesn't
say anything, but
it's just fun to look at, right?
So, okay.
Now, we're going to get to the, to a real
case.
And in fact, it's one of those things,
where you just add one more, one more
feature to this one, to the problem.
And then it goes from being, hm, maybe not
so
useful, to off-scale unbelievably useful,
okay?
So, those who've taken a modern statistics
or
machine learning course, know what's
going to happen now, so.
But anyway, so if you just sit tight,
everything will be fine.
alright, so what you do is this, and in
fact, I want to,
before we even get into this I want to
talk about.
Let's start the story this way, I give you
some x's and
I give you some y's, these are feature
vectors for spam and for, not spam.
You calculate, whether there's a
separating hyperplane and
there isn't, right?
And that's probably good, right?
Oh, by the way, if the two point clouds
are like totally, you know, if, if,
if they're totally on top of each other,
so there's no difference, that's not good.
That means, you've picked some pretty poor
features, okay, right?
But there's some point is that, two point
clouds are there, they do,
the two, the two convex hulls intersect,
period.
In other words, there are spam feature
vectors, that penetrate into,
whatever the non-spam territory, every, I
mean this is just, just a picture.
Okay, and so the question is,
how would you let's skip what I have on
the slide here.
What would you imagine, you might want to
do?
So, you have a, a million linear
inequalities, you want to satisfy, and
they're not mutually satisfiable.
Yeah, so I have a whole bunch of
inequalities, I want to satisfy.
I solve an lp, and I announce with total
confidence, th, there is no hyperplane.
I ca, cannot satisfy all these
inequalities, it's impossible.
So the nat, I think the most natural
things you might want to do next,
would be to say, okay fine, find me a
hyperplane,
that minimizes the number of, of
inequalities you violate.
Now if, if you want to think about a,
a classification problem, that's the
number of missed classifications, right?
And by the way, if that number were like
0.5%, you'd be very happy.
You wouldn't, but okay.
At, at, at some point in time, in the
past, for spam detection, you would be,
you would've been very happy, right?
For a lot of problems, you'd be delighted,
right?
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So you, so you, so then the problem is to
figure out,
which ones can you not, how do you
minimize the number?
Okay, well, and by the way,
then you might ask yourself, what kind of
an optimization problem is that?
And you would find out pretty quickly,
that, that is np hard.
So, I give you a set of inequalities, and
I ask you to satisfy as many as you can,
it's np hard, okay?
Fine, okay.
So then, you'd say, well maybe there's a
heuristic for this.
And what does this mean?
This means, that the violations are
sparse.
You, you know, if there's going to be
violations, and, by the way, the l1 norm
should be the right thing here, because it
says, you know, it's got a v.
I mean, you see, it's not quite an l1
norm, but it's exactly the same.
Actually, it is an l1 norm, for something
that's positive.
You know, and it's something, it means,
what you want is, something that keeps up
the pressure to drive you to zero.
But if you have to violate, it shouldn't
go nuts, it should not be a function,
a penalty that grows, it just should grow
linearly, okay?
Okay.
So, that's the idea.
So, in fact, that leads you immediately,
to the following.
Let me do it, this, I'll write it another
way.
I'll write, ai transpose x plus b, I want
that to be bigger than one, okay?
So, I want this thing to be bigger than
zero, that's what I want.
Now, I know that I can't, I actually can't
chose an A and a B.
Well, that one and the other ones, so that
all these inequalities hold.
Everybody following this?
So, I want that, I if that's positive, I'm
totally happy, right?
So, you might do something like this, you
might form,
ai transpose x plus b minus 1, the minus
part, okay?
If you satisfy that inequality, that
gives, there's no bill here,
you don't pay anything, right?
But if this thing becomes negative, then
you start paying, and
you pay linearly, ever.
So, what, what function is that?
That's a function that looks like this,
right?
Looks like that, right?
And this is called the margin, in the
inequality, and what this says,
if your margin's positive, no charge
whatsoever, if it's negative,
you charge linearly for, negative margins,
right?
Ever, everybody's sort of, following this,
okay?
Now, when you look at that, and by the
way, it helps to turn your head about
40 degrees then l1, your l1 part of your
brain will light up, okay?
I mean, it's the same thing, right?
Okay?
So, and, by the way, this is called hinge
loss, is, is the name for
this, in several, in several fields.
I think that, in both, in modern
statistics and in machine learning.
Anyway, so, that's hinge loss.
And so it suggests, that actually, doing
something like this,
adding that in, would be a great idea
because you know,
it doesn't look like l1, but by the time
you see this, I mean it should,
l1 is not to be taken literally, although
a lot of people do.
This is l1, right?
Actually, it's linear plus l1, so it
actually, kind of is.
But you look at that, and, and, sparsity,
the sparsity part of your brain,
should be lighting up, okay?
Right?
And, what does it mean, if this is sparse?
It's super cool.
If that's sparse, it says the following.
It says that, you satisfy most, it means
that, that mis-classifications, these
are not by the way, mis-classifications,
there's even a little extra there,
because the one, without the one, it's
mis-classification, right?
This says that, mis-classifications are
sparse, that's exactly what you want.
Everybody following this?
I mean, that was a very long story, but
the idea is, and I just wanted to give,
I just wanted to give the whole, like,
everything, about what you're doing here.
Okay, so that's what this is.
u, is a slack variable here.
I mean, this is the way, this is the
traditional description of it.
actually, this is a more modern
description, you don't even introduce use,
because you just look at it, you say, it's
convex, done, right?
That's the correct way to do it, in my
opinion.
But we'll do it the traditional way.
The traditional way, is you say, I would
like to satisfy this inequality and
this one it's determined that you cannot,
and then you go,
oh, okay fine, then you add in slacks.
Now the slacks are, by the way, nothing,
but these things, right?
So, a slack is something that says, fine,
I'll subtract something from the one,
to make it easier to satisfy this, and
I'll do the same here.
I'll make the inequality easier, easier to
use in Vs, those are [INAUDIBLE], and
then, I'll minimize those.
And by the way, you'll find out, this
problem is absolutely identical to
the problem of this, plus of course the,
the opposite ones, the, for the Ys, right?
So, you get exactly the same problem,
okay?
Everybody, following this?
Okay, so that, and, and, and
you should even think of this, it's a
beautiful thing.
You should think of this thing, as the l1
type heuristic,
for solving the following hard [INAUDIBLE]
problem.
Find me a hyperplane, that satisfies as
many, you know,
that mis-classifies as few as possible,
right?
So, that's the correct interpretation of
this, okay?
And you get something like that, you know,
here's a case.
Okay.
Now the only thing you have to do now,
is you put the two together and you have
something kind of famous, right?
So and I guess the traditional one, I
think the traditional one,
would look something like that, right?
So, but at the, you get the same trade-off
curve.
So what you do now is this is, you put
slacks in, to minimize, to,
for the for, for actually,
mis-classifying, right?
And then you, at the same time,
and you could also think of this as
regularization, by the way, so here,
traditional l2 regularization, turns out
to have a beautiful
geometric interpretation, because when
you're minimizing the norm of A,
I guess you call it the weight vector or
something like that.
If you're minimizing over the weight
vector, it turns out,
that's equivalent to, geometrically, to
saying, don't look for a hyperplane,
look for a slab, and, in fact, maximize
the width of the slab, which means,
that you've separated them well.
Everybody, kind of seeing all these things
go together?
So, I mean, for people who've seen this
before, that's fine,
you may not have seen the geometric
interpretation,
the full geometric interpretations, but
now you have.
So, it's actually kind of, kind of cool.
So, this, this is given the name, support
vector machine.
Here, you have a parameter, and the
parameter is very simple.
It trades off, the parameter, now describe
it geometrically, and
there are statistical interpretations of
all of these, going to go into them.
But there are so the geometric
interpretation is quite beautiful.
lambda, or gamma here, sorry, trades off
the width [COUGH] of the slab.
and, and this this is going to be very
rough the viol,
the number of inequality violations, okay?
And that's what it does.
Right, and so you can imagine what, what,
what turning that parameter will do, here.
This is unbelievably, widely used.
I mean that is much as [INAUDIBLE] squared
or
something like that, but it's catching up,
let me put it that way.
So, it's used tons of places, everywhere
all the time, right?
So, you couldn't possibly get through a
day, here, except if you're like,
hiking in Yosemite or something, and
maybe, even then you couldn't.
when, when something you did, didn't run
through, a support vector classifier.
I mean, I'm not, it would be, you'd have
to touch no electronics, and I don't know,
what else you, you'd have to do.
So, but, be very hard to, very hard to do,
and you don't, certainly don't pick up
your phone or anything like, don't, don't
read email, because then it's all over.
so, anyway, so.
These are good things to know.
Okay, let's look at the idea of non-linear
discrimination.
So, here, I, we've been looking at linear
We can just as well look at, non-linear
discrimination because in fact, it turns
out that, the fact that the classifier was
linear, was totally irrelevant.
All that mattered, was that it was linear
in the parameters, right?
So, non-linear classification says, find
me a function f,
that is you know, positive on, on the x's,
negative on the y's, okay?
So, so, here's one approach to it.
Actually, there's multiple approaches
here.
I mean, one which doesn't fit in this
theme but, we could talk about but,
don't have time to, would be, sort of
kernel methods, but, we're not.
Instead, we're going to look at
somethings, that's much simpler and
that fits with the theme of, context
optimization.
What you do, is you simply take a set of
basis functions here.
And what you're going to do, is you're
going to look a,
at a finite dimensional, set of candidate
functions, that's all.
And, you know, these are basis functions,
right, f1 through fk, right?
They could be anything you'd like.
So, it could be polynomials.
They could be weird exponentials, they
could be things that,
that pertain to your particular problem,
right?
I don't know, I, I don't know why, but
I mean that, you know, could be, these
could be prolade spheroids, or
something like that, or bessel functions
of some order, I, I don't know.
We, they could, you just, they could be
anything, right?
These could be the eigenfunctions of some,
of some partial differential operator,
right?
Doesn't matter, right, it's just supposed
to be
functions you're going to linearly
combine, to do separation, okay.
So here, it's the same thing.
You just end up with, I mean,
absolutely nothing whatsoever, is
different, I mean nothing.
Right, so that's, that's what you get.
And so, this tells you, can do fun things
like this,
you could say, [COUGH] please separate my
points quadratically, okay?
And that says, find me a quadratic
function,
that's a general quadratic function.
And what's being asked, is that you should
find P, Q, and
R, those are the variables, that separates
your points.
Okay, so here's an example of,
quadratically separable points, right?
And this, by the way,
goes back to our question of, what would
you do with those ellipsoids?
This would be, if you had two types of
data.
You had places where, let's say, a pilot
flown and came back.
Let's suppose, that's the things inside,
now, and these are the ones,
where there was no recovery, that's a
little bit gruesome, sorry.
So, something else, but that's the idea,
okay?
And, so this would be the case, and it's a
linear program, to compute, and
to compute, actually, just quadratically
separation.
Now quadratic separation by itself,
does not require, there's no curvature
constraint, right?
So, in fact, in this case, it could, you
could, you might as well, you,
you could, if you just do a straight
quadratic classification,
you could actually be looking for a
hyperbola, that, that separates them.
Everybody following this?
Right, and if you know, depending on what
your data is,
that can be completely reasonable and
interest, interesting.
Everybody got this?
If you want to insist, that for example,
if you say, find me an ellipsoid that
covers these points, but not those, then
you simply add a constraint that says,
that the p, is less than or equal to,
actually, you would add p negative
definite, for example, to get ellipsoid or
the ex, exterior of an ellipsoid b, would
be p positive definite.
That's homogenous, and that translates to
this, okay?
And now ,you have sdp.
Everybody following this?
So, this is the idea.
I mean, here's a quasi convex problem.
It says, here's two sets of points, and
this says, please separate them by the
minimum degree polynomial, nr2.
Everybody got that?
And without even saying anything, you
should understand that,
that is quasi convex.
[COUGH] Why?
In fact, how is that done?
How is that figure done?
You take the two sets of points, and
what's the first thing you try to do?
You first try to separate them.
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> By linear, and you can't, okay?
because we're looking at the data, you
cannot, okay?
And that doesn't work.
So now you try quadratic, and you cannot,
okay?
Then you try cubic, and you can't.
And then you try quadratic, and you can.
Everybody, so that's, that's the idea.
I mean, I don't know, why you'd want to,
and
by the way, I mean, one of the nice things
about these sort of,
convex formulations is, here, we're
showing you the simple ones, but
in fact, you can just, you know, you can,
yeah it's like cooking.
You can add stuff in and things like that.
I mean for example here, suppose instead,
you want to say yeah, this is,
oh yeah, this is what I want to do, I
really want to do that.
But you know what, it doesn't work
exactly, and
I don't mind, if a few end up
mis-classified.
Everybody following this?
So, what do you, what would you do?
Yeah, yeah you had the u and the v the
slacks, or
whatever you like, and then, you know, and
then, and then, you have a parameter, that
would trade off various things, right?
I mean so that, that's, that's exactly
what you do.
You add in u and v, and, then you'd end
up, computing an ellipsoid and
there would be hope, if you're lucky,
couple of points outside, couple of,
couple of points on, eh, on either side of
their boundary, that went the wrong way.
Everybody got this?
So, it's, it's okay.
So that's, I mean, you get it.