What we're to do now is look at equality
constrained minimization, and you know,
we're stepping slowly towards solving
general context [COUGH]
optimization problems.
Right?
[COUGH] So, so,
we're going to add constraints.
But, the easiest constraints they handle
are equality constraints which are linear.
Okay, so, and it's going to turn
out actually there's a few interesting
things here, but some of it is actually.
It turns out to be quite simple.
We just reduce it to the other one.
Okay so we want to minimize f at the
smooth.
Subject Ax equals b.
And we-, we're going to assume that A s
full rank.
It's wide and full rank.
And we'll assume the optimum is attained.
Right?
And so basically it says you simply want,
these are the necessary insufficient
optimality conditions right.
The, it's the kk key conditions.
Nu star is an optimal dual variable here.
That's the, you know, or Lagrange
multiplier.
And so you want to solve these two
equations, and
let's stare at the two equations for a
minute.
interestingly, these equations are affine
in nu star.
Right?
They do not,
they're not nonlinear in nu star, they're
affine.
Now what are they in x?
Well, that's linear, right?
That depends on that.
Oh, except for one case.
When is the gradient of a function an
affine function?
When it's quadratic, right?
So if the function is quadratic these are
a set of linear equations, okay, and
that's, so that says that solving linearly
constrained quadratic
Optimization problems, is pure linear
algebra.
Right?
That's it.
You just set up a linear algebra and you
do it.
OK?
So, but in general, this thing, if f is
non-quadratic, this is non-affine, and
that's a set of nonlinear equations.
People have names for the residuals,
right?
The name for the residual in this equation
is called the primal residual.
>> And sometimes denoted RP.
and, and the condition, of course, the
optimality conditions are P equals 0.
This one, that expression on the left is
called the Dual Residual and
it denoted RD.
And, of course, the optimality condition
is that RD equals 0.
So, you're looking to find X and Nu that
make RP and RD 0.
Okay?
And by the way,
the number of equations is about right.
You have m plus p-, you have m plus p
variables, right?
N plus p variables.
And you have n plus p equations.
So, but they're possibly non linear.
Okay.
So,.
Well, we already talked about this, right?
If, if you, if you want to do equality
constrained quadratic minimization,
it's linear algebra, until you get
something like this.
Right.
The right, the optimality conditions this
way, and
you're actually computing both x star,
and, nu star,
which is an optimal Lagrange multiplier,
you compute both of them.
By the way, there's some structure here,
there's a block of zeros, and
your eyes should be looking at it or
something, already, without my saying.
I mean that's not a lot,
you know, you could have more structure
but that, that, that's that.
And it turns out, I mean you can work out
a lot about this KKT matrix, for
example It's non singular if and only if
if you're in the null space of A,
P is positive definite or something like
that.
So another way to say that roughly is P is
positive definite on the null space of
A, right.
So P has to have positive curvature kind
of on the feasible set,
that's the right way to say it, okay.
That wasn't quite right, but that's the
spirit.
Okay, just set up linear equations.
There's a very general method for
handling equality constraints if you just
eliminate them.
Right?
So, you would do the following.
I would, this is my constrained
representation of an affine set, but
I will write it instead as a free
parameter representation.
And so what I'll do is, you compute an x
hat that satisfies Ax equals b.
That's this one.
Lot's of names for this.
By the way, a traditional name for this is
x sub p for a particular solution.
That's the 19th-century name is, you have
a particular solution.
I think the other one's, like, a
homogeneous, I don't know, anyway.
So, that's a partic-, a par-, part-, a
particular solution, sorry.
And then, f is a matrix whose range is
exactly the null space of a.
Right?
Lots of ways to compute that, that's just
linear algebra.
So, tons of ways to use, a QR
factorization,
all sorts of things, all sorts of ways to
do this.
Okay.
so, what you do now is, we'll change
variables in our optimization problem.
Instead of x, we'll go with z, and you end
up with this.
And now it's totally unconstrained.
Still a convex problem, because, you know,
f is simply applied to a applied to an
affine transformation.
Here by the way if the original f was self
concordant it still is right?
So that's it and we know how to do that.
I mean we can apply Newton's method
gradients, deepest ascent,
whatever you like.
Okay so that's, that's the idea.
Okay, and if you want, after solving this
problem, you can reconstruct x.
I mean that's x but you can also
reconstruct the optimal Lagrange
multiplier, and it's got just a particular
formula like that.
That's if you wanted it, in the original
one.
Okay?
So, oh, I should mention something about
the interpretation, sometimes it's useful,
sometime you want to know this.
Because the interpretation of nu star is
actually something like I'll be very,
it's something like the prices for, if
these,
if every row of this is interpreted as
some kind of clearing constraint, right?
That, sort of the amount produced balances
the amount consumed, or
something like that.
So it, that would be the economic
interpretation.
Then in fact, nu is a vector of the
optimal prices of each of
those commodities.
It said, basically as you know,
the interpretation of nu star is, you know
what?
What if you allowed me to change b a
little bit?
What would happen?
Nu Start tells you how the optimal value
would change, okay?
So, I mean I just mentioned this.
Okay, so, so that's that.
So, what this kind of sends at this point
you don't need to know anymore.
From some point of view,
you don't need to know any theory about
the quality constraint problems.
Because you just reduce it to an
unconstrained problem, it's done.
Okay.
So quick example of that.
Let's solve here's an optimal allocation
with a resource constraint.
So I minimize a bunch of individual costs
subject to all these things add up to b.
Right?
And so, so
this is an allocation problem, right?
I have, I have b as sort of an amount of
resource I have,
and I'm, I'm dividing it up among a bunch
of agents, right?
And agents.
And I want to do that,
sometimes this is called the social cost
in that context, right?
And here, by the way, The optimal Lagrange
multiply, which is scalar,
it actually tells you the optimal price
for the commodity that we are, allocated.
Okay?
So just, I mean, it's kind of obvious but,
okay.
So, that's a constrained problem.
How would you solve it?
Well what we could do is just is.
We'll do the following obvious
elimination.
I could take X hat to be BEN, here's
another X hat.
Right?
It's B over N times the vector of ones.
That's a uniform allocation.
But, doesn't matter.
So, I'll take it to be BEN.
That means I give everything to agent N.
Okay, and here's a matrix whose whose
range is exactly the null space of A.
A is the, is the vector.
It is the row vector one, one, one, one,
one,
one and the null space of that is all
things which sum to zero.
Right?
So, that's this.
And you know, look.
It just says that this transforms to that,
and that's unconstrained.
By the way, so that says.
Whatever you can say about this problem,
you can solve it super fast, okay.
Actually we'll get to that, because we're
going to see that there's a way to,
to get the structure to exploit the
structure directly.
Newton's step for a equality constrained
problem and it looks like this.
It says, you formed this 2 by 2 matrix,
right, 2 by 2 block matrix, here.
You have v and w.
And you solve, and on the right-hand side
you have the gradient and 0.
Right?
And, look,
if you read the first one that says Av
equals 0,
that means v's in the null space.
If you're in a null space, by the way,
that says that you can freely add it to a
feasible point x.
Because if a x equals b, and a v equals 0,
can add any multiple of v to x,
and it still satisfies a x plus, you know,
h v equals b, right.
So, that's the second.
And the top one, basically tells you
something, it,
it actually has to do with that dual.
Residual which we'll talk about in a
minute.
So couple of interpretations of this.
Oh notice that it reverts to the Newton
step when there are no
equality constraints because when there
are no equality constraints that's just
a one by one and it's,
it's Hessian times v equals minus gradient
that gives you the Newton step.
So where does this come from, lots of
interpretations.
Here's one.
Form, the quadratic approximation of f at
x.
That's this thing here.
And notice v is like a step or a
perturbation, okay?
Then, this, the equality are, they're
equality constraints,
you don't need to approximate anything.
You don't need to linearize.
Or, you could, even, right?
You could implement the method.
Which is the, the linearize method, and
you would call it on an affine function,
and it would simply return itself.
Right?
So this would be just fine.
And so, how do you linearize the quality
constraints?
They're just the same.
'Kay?
Now, this we know how to do.
Right?
Because this is
minimizing a convex quadratic in v.
Subject to equality constraints.
We know how to do that.
And guess what?
All you do is, you solve this equation
here.
And, that gives you v and w.
So that's, that's another way to say.
And notice that that preserves the spirit
of Newton's method for,
without equality constraints.
I mean, so.
Instead of being explicit, you should say
Newton's method,
really the idea behind it is this, is you
implement a method that says,
you know, get quadratic, get quadratic
approximation or something like that.
And, so, then you call it on, you do
f.quadapprox...
At x, and it returns a quadratic model
valid near that point.
And then you minimize it.
That's Newton's method, right?
This is the same thing.
It says, you call the same method on f,
and now you minimize it,
but subject to the equality constraints.
But you know we know how to minimize
quadratics subject to
equality constraints, because that's
linear algebra.
OK?
So, so that, I think it's natural.
>> Another way to say it is this.
Here's what you really want.
What you really want, when you take a step
here you want,
you would like this thing to be 0.
That's what you'd like.
Right?
that, that's what you really want.
That, that's driving our, our d, the dual
residual to zero and
so what we do is we simply take an
approximation of this.
That's a that's in general non affine.
If f is quadratic its affine but if f is
non quadratic that's affine and
an approximation of the gradient at x plus
v is very simple.
Its the gradient at x plus the [UNKNOWN]
which is after all the Derivative of
the gradient multiplied by the step, and
if you solve these two equations?
That's this.
Okay?
So, so you can either call the linearize
method on the optimality conditions and
solve linear equations.
You can solve the quad, you can, or
you can call the quadratic method on the
original problem and then solve that.
Right?
Either way, and they're the same thing.
Okay, so the Newton decrement is it can be
written several ways.
This is one of them and it's that.
By the way there are some other formulas
for
the Newton decrement which are completely
false in the quality constraint case.
One is I think, Delta x Newton transpose
times the inverse of this times that.
Right?
There's a, there's, there's one of the
formulas looks like that and its wrong.
OK but so you have to be careful.
A couple of the formulas you know for
Newton decrement are correct others are
are are wrong.
OK and its the same thing.
It simply gives you an estimate.
Its the difference between It says that if
you form the quadratic model,
solve the constraint problem, how much
would the objective go down.
And that's, that's lambda squared over 2.
Is, is what that is, so, makes perfect,
perfect sense.
It's also the directional derivative in
the Newton direction, so
that also is preserved.
But it is not equal to that.
For, that's an example of one of the
formulas that's just wrong.
For equality constraint.
Okay.
Now here's Newton's method with equality
constraints.
So here's the algorithm.
You know you compute the Newton step and
the decrement.
You quit if, if the decrement squared over
two,
which is your expected decrease, is less
than epsilon.
The you align search and you update.
So guess what?
That algorithm is identical to Newton's
method for unconstrained.
It's, it's exactly the same.
The difference is we have now kind of
overloaded a few things here.
Newton's step is been overloaded to handle
equality constraints.
It doesn't mean Hessian inverse minus
Hessian inverse gradient.
It means solve this big k k key system.
Right?
And we also overloaded,
the, Newton decrement to mean something
appropriate in that case.
Okay, otherwise, it's identical, the
algorithm.
And it's a feasible descent method,
meaning, every step x is feasible,
and your objective goes down, unless
you're at the optimum point.
And it's affine invariant.
If you change coordinates, it's doesn't
matter.
Okay, I mean you get the commutative
diagram.
You get exactly the same caliber.
Okay, by the way,
what that means is that scaling is sort of
a second-order issue for Newton methods,
right, meaning, yeah if you scale things
by 10 to the 38 and 10 to the -38,
you can have underflow and overflow and
numerical issues and things like that.
Sure.
Okay?
But,
you can scale things very happily by
thousand, ten thousand, and
it will work fine.
And the reason for that is to a numerical
analyst a condition number of a system of
linear equations of 10 to the 3 or 10 to
the 4.
It's not that big a deal.
Right?
Whereas for any first order method,
condition number is a first order effect.
If the first, if the condition number is
like ten, it's going to work super well.
If it's a hundred thousand, just forget it
for
all practical purposes it doesn't work.
If it's a thousand it may not work.
Another way to say it is.
If your method is working with a gradient
method, I can break it by scaling.
Scaling even modest, by modest scaling.
Newton's method I won't break.
It'll worth perfectly.
OK?
So.
OK.
Now it turns out there's a, we don't have
to do any analysis of this and
the reason is the following.
There's a communative you get a perfect
communative diagram here.
If you take a problem.
You take an original problem with equality
constraints,
then you eliminate the variables.
You do variable elimination, then you
apply Newton's method.
You get a commutative diagram with
applying Newton's method with
equality constraints, it's identical.
And that means we don't have to do any
analysis at
all because we already know it all.
We know everything.
Including for self importance I might add,
we know everything.
Nothing to do.
So you don't need any convergence
analysis.
That's good.
Now we're talking about something
different.
And honestly, this is maybe the more
useful one.
And this is actually the more modern one.
And it's actually probably more useful,
and so here it is.
If the idea of a Newton step at an
infeasible point.
And so the basic idea is that you really
say that what you want to do is you,
you, you write down the residual, right,
and that's in n plus rn plus p.
And it's the following.
It's, it's the dual residual and then the
primal residual.
And what you want to solve is a set of
nonlinear equations in n plus p variables.
Right?
Of which, of wh, and the number of
equations you have is n plus p.
Okay, so that's, that's what you want to
do.
So, that's one view of it.
Now, by the way, equa, solving non linear
equations in rn plus b,
with n plus b equations It's super
complicated,
like you don't even know that there exists
a solution.
Right, I mean here you know that there's a
solution,
because well it's a convex problem and so,
and so on and so forth.
So that's the nice part, is that there's
some regularity to this.
But Newton's method simply says,
I want to solve that equation here's what
we're going to do.
I'm going to, y is going to be, actually,
a primal dual variable.
It's going to be a pair consisting of a
primal variable and a dual variable.
And what we're going to do is this, I want
r of y as zero, so
I'll imagine that I'm going to go y plus
delta y, that's going to be my step.
And what I would like, is I want that to
be zero!
But
>> That's equal to R.
I mean, the, the linear approximation of R
is, half fine, but people call it linear,
is R of Y plus DR, that's the derivative,
or Jacobian, multiplied by Delta 1.
DR is exactly that.
Now, you get a similar set of equations,
here's what you get.
You get this.
Actually the right hand side is is, is,
is a little bit different here.
actually, it turns out these are
completely the same, right?
If, if, here, we're actually calculating
the, that's the full Newton thing.
sorry, the full dual variable.
And here we're calculating an update to
the, the, a dual variable, okay?
So, this is a, a, very nice form of
Newton's method.
And it is to be interpreted this way.
It says, and you should think of it as a
primal dual method.
Because every step, you're updating a
primal and a dual variable, right?
And the idea is to drive both the primal
and
dual residuals to zero and, so, you solve
this.
This is the same KKT system, and
on the right hand side are the residuals
of both, right?
So, by the way, it generalizes the Newton
step for a feasible point,
because if x is feasible, that's 0.
And guess what?
You get the Newton step, that we had
before, for feasible points.
So it's a generalization.
But you have to be kind of careful.
Let me tell you why you have to kind of be
careful.
What's kind of cool about this is, this
defines a Newton step,
even when you're infeasible.
In other words, you don't satisfy a x
equals b.
It says, as a direction to go in.
Now you have to be very careful.
Because that direction to go in is a
combination of two things.
There's one is you want to make f small so
you're kind of be going in the direction
minus gradiant f.
I mean that is after all what we're trying
to do.
But if you don't satisfy ax equals b
you're also going to
be going in a direction towards which ax
equals b.
Right, so you going to have kind of these
two directions and you also have to be
very careful because in a problem like
this you could end up,its,
its not a dissent method, I mean for
obvious reasons right, if that's my
equality restraints, right and here's my,
my function I'm minimizing.
Right?
You know, I don't know.
Maybe the, it's the solution would be
right there.
It's, it's whenever the tangent touches
this line
>> [COUGH]
>> That's the solution right?
But, suppose I started right here.
That, that's my initial point.
Okay?
So, at that point,
what's the gradient of F?
It's 0.
Right?
So.
The only minor problem is you're not
feesible.
Right?
So, the Newton step, in this case,
is going to point you to somewhere on the
line here.
Right?
because, if you take one,
if you take a full Newton step, the
equality constraint becomes feasible.
Okay?
So that's, that's, that's the idea.
And by the way what will happen to f from
your first iteration?
It will go up.
Has to go up because you started at the
minimum of F right?
So, it's clearly not a descend method.
Now when you see F go up someone says, hey
that's a crappy job you
did on the optimization I gave you an
initial point and the first thing you
do is your function values goes up and
what do you say to that?
What would be your, what's your comeback?
Yeah, it's like, well dude, your point
wasn't feasible.
So, it had excellent objective, but, it
didn't, satisfy the constraints.
So, that's all.
Okay.
I just mention this because, things like
this come up,
and, you'd be surprised, actually.
So, okay, so, it says the line search is
different.
So you don't, you don't measure progress
by the function value obviously although,
you should measure values, you should
measure two things.
The primal and
dual residual norms or some people lump in
together into one and either, either way.
By the way this will tell you something if
you look at things like Sedumi or
STPT3 output.
I don't know if you do, but
when you run CVX a few of the columns are
now going to be demystified.
Now they'll be fully demystified by next
week.
But, you will see things that say RP and
RD.
Or, it'll be obscure.
It'll say d norm and p norm.
And these, well these literally mean the
primal residual and
the dual residual norm.
So, OK.
OK.
So here it is.
What you do is you compute these Newton,
the, the Newt-, the primal dual Newton
steps, and then you do a backtracking line
search, on the, on the norm of R, okay?
So, on the total residual, that's easy
enough.
And it turns out the directional
derivative is simply minus the residual.
That's a, a quick calculation.
And so you get a very simple code that
looks like this, then you update x and
you keep going.
It's not a descent method, but
I'll tell you what does go down is the
norm of the residual.
So whenever you have an algorithm and
people analyze it,
there's the basis of a proof or something
is of some function that goes down, right?
In the Newton method the gradient descent
of things we focus on the function value
going down I mean what could be more
natural you want to minimize that.
So its kind of cool that the thing you
want to happen happens actually locally at
every step.
Greedily it happens right?
Here it turns out that the by the way its
got all sorts of names.
I think one name, one method is a
[UNKNOWN] function and
there's another one.
I forget there's all sorts of names and
optimization too for that I forgot the
name.
And in computer science you got another
name,
which I also can't remember right now but
anyway.
But the concept is very simple.
There's a, you have an internet method and
you have a function that goes down every
step.
And that's base, the basis of your proof
that it works.
Right?
So, by the way,
there's a huge practical, advantage of
having such a function, if it's explicit.
Because if it basically says you can do
anything you want in that algorithm.
Any modification that you want at all,
as long as you make sure that function
does go down.
Right, so for example, you can insert
weird steps in your algorithm that does
some kind of local optimization.
But, you better make sure that local
optimization better ensure the Lyapunov
function goes down.
I just remembered one of the names, merit
function.
But there's like five of them, you'll,
the, the concept is clear.
So here it turns out that the merit
function is the norm of the residual.
So, let's talk about solving KKT systems.
How do you solve something like that?
Well, there's lots of ways.
so, one is,
you just use LDL transpose, because that's
a symmetric indefinite system, right?
It's indefinite because you look at the 0s
down there.
And in fact, it has exactly n.
Well, if H is positive definite, has
exactly N.
actually, if it's solvable, it has N
positive item values and exactly M.
Or P?
I think its P is the size of
the equality constraints.
P negative was.
Okay?
so, that's very simple.
You just plug in this stuff and, and, and
use LDL transpose factorization.
You can also do elimination.
What you do is, you know,
in many applications, H will be diagonal,
block diagonal, something simple.
There we go.
And so, H will be, and
then, and then H would then be a natural
target for elimination.
I mean, for sure, if you saw that system,
and H was diagonal.
I'm hoping every single one of you would
have
an overwhelming urge to eliminate the one
one block.
You should and, and we're going to train
you until that's the case.
Okay?
So that, if,
if, but doesn't, I mean the math doesn't
matter either way.
So if you eliminate the, the v.
Here you end up with a system that looks
like this.
By the way that is the negative sure
compliment of that matrix.
Right, because the sure complement is zero
minus a h inverse transpose,
that's the sure complement.
Well, with a minus sign.
Okay?
so, that's a sure complement.
And, by the way,
I think this is called, people refer to
this system as the reduced system.
That's standard notation.
So people would say, you, you'd say, oh
what are you doing, Newton,
blah blah blah, and say oh yeah, how are
you solving it?
And they'd say reduce system.
By the way, they then call this the
augmented system.
Don't ask me why, the KKT system, that's
augmented and reduced.
Okay, so you could do this.
Now if H is singular, there's lots of
interesting things you can do.
One is that in fact any solution of this
is identical to a solution to that.
You can just check, but the point is that
what this allows you to
do is to make sure that this 1 1 block is
non-singular.
Right?
Then you can apply elimination.
So, okay.
Now we're going to, we're going to finish
with an example.
And it's going to tie a whole bunch of
stuff together.
And actually, it's going to, you're
going to see something really interesting.
Which is to say, that all these, there's
lots of methods to solve a single problem.
They relate, they go through duality and
stuff like that.
And what, you'll, you'll see, but I'll get
to the punchline right now.
That you, you're going to look at a
problem, and you can solve it many ways.
You can solve the problem, you could solve
the dual, you could do this and that, and
in each case, if you use Newton's method,
this is going to be the critical part.
If you use Newton's method, The systems of
equations you're going to
come down to solving in each step of each
of those is not exactly the same but
has exactly the same structure and that
structure will be such that if you
know what you're doing you can solve it
efficiently.
Right?
And so, what's what's kind of interesting
about that is a lot of
times you will actually hear people who
don't know any better.
>> Say things like, Well, I'm solving the
dual.
Right?
And they might say that because it sounds
cool.
Right?
To solve them.
Doesn't it?
I mean, you kind of,
people don't know, you say, Well, I'm, I'm
solving the dual [UNKNOWN] .
Anyway, sounds sophisticated.
And you say, why is that?
You go, Well, I get efficiency or
something.
I mean, there are good reason to solve
duals.
Like, you can distribute stuff in parallel
thing.
That's another story.
But, if you're doing like a Newton method,
there's absolutely no reason to do it if
you know linear algebra.
If you know numerical linear algebra.
There's absolutely no reason to do that.
We'll see that.
What is different, actually the
initializations.
So, all right.
Let's, let's jump into it.
We want to calculate the analytic center
of AX equals B and X nonnegative.
And that's the feasible set for a classic
linear program.
Right?
Minimizing transpose X.
Subject AX is BX, X bigger than or equal
to 0.
That's a feasible set.
It's the intersection if you like of an
affine set with a non-negative orphan.
That's what it is.
And we want to write down, I mean so the
analytics center is this, right,
that we want to minimize some of the logs
that 's
the barrier associated with that subject
to Ax equals b.
Okay.
So, now the dual of that problem, you can
work it out, is this!
You maximize this.
And, here, it turns out, this thing is
strictly,
the original function is strictly convex,
and that says that if we know the,
if we solve the dual, we can recover the
primal solution.
And there's a silly, simple formula (but
it's a really dumb formula) it's like,
it doesn't even matter what it is, let's
just It's there.
Right?
And you can,
by solving the dual, you get the primal.
Okay.
And they're kind of interesting.
Let's take a look at them.
The dual is unconstrained.
Well, not quite.
There's an implicit constraint that A
transpose new is positive.
Okay?
So,
the domain of the dual is a bit
complicated.
It's a set of vectors new for which A
transpose is positive.
That's actually a open polyhedron, right?
So, the domain of the primal is simple.
It's r plus to the end.
R plus plus to the end, right?
It's all positive vectors, right?
Sorry.
Intersects with a x equals b, my mistake,
so, okay.
So, whatever.
So, let's look at some things.
Here's what we can do.
Let's just take Newton method with the
quality constraints.
So we have a problem with 500 variables,
100 equality constraints, and
if you run Newton's method, you get
something like this.
And what we're doing,
here, is these four traces show you just
four different starting points.
Right?
And, you know, that looks very Newton-ish.
This what you should, this is what you
should see, and you will see, presumably.
Later.
This week?
And then, they're doing it this week.
Okay, so you'll see things that look like
this.
We, this is what you're shooting for,
right?
And the idea is, look that's a ridiculous,
that's a 10 to the 15 range there.
So, this, this may be actually quite
perfectly good,
respectable conversions, but on a plot.
Whose range goes covers 10 to the 15.
You're not seeing it, okay?
But the key thing you should see is
something like that, right?
That's, that, that's your basic Newton
behavior, right?
By the way, that should also correspond to
the place where you do undamped steps.
So the step size should be one in that
region.
Fine.
And this is what you expect.
Okay.
Oh, the initialization was interesting.
We needed to know a positive vector with A
x equals b.
Right?
I mean if this is just a general problem,
you don't know such a thing, so
that would be kind of a pain.
Let's apply Newton Method to the dual
problem.
Okay?
So here, if you applied that means what we
do is we
need a vector new zero that starts in the
domain.
And we apply Newton's method, and then
here it is for four different things.
And by the way, you might be tempted to
say, in fact I will give you the entire
fallacious argument because I promise you
will hear this from someone you know.
In which case you can correct their
misunderstanding.
They would say, I have a fantastic method
for
solving this problem, I'm going to solve
the dual.
And someone says, well why would you do
that?
And they would say the following.
Number one, that original problem has 500
variables, the dual has a hundred.
Last time I checked, 100 is smaller than
500.
Person says, I'm solving, you're solving a
problem with five hundred variables,
I'm solving one with a, with a, with a
hundred, 'Kay, that,
that's fewer, that means it's a 125 times
faster, number one, number two,
to add sort of, just a bonus, you're
taking 15, 20, steps.
Look at this.
This thing typically converges in eight or
nine steps.
I'm half the number of steps.
My advantage over you is 250x, plus you
get the added bonus of it sounds
cool if you say, I'm solving the dual,
because it sounds more sophisticated.
You know what I'm saying?
Right?
Everyone following this argument?
Okay.
We will see that it is totally and
completely wrong.
Okay.
But
that's the argument you will hear it from
people.
Okay.
Now let's look at another one.
Let's look at Infeasible Start Newton
Method.
Now, this is its huge advantage.
And this is probably why this is more
useful than, than a lot of the others.
Although it depends on the situation.
The initialization is very modest.
The only thing you need, it does not have
to satisfy x equals b,
it only has to be in the domain.
The domain is the sum of the logs.
Right?
So, does someone want to suggest a
starting point?
All 1s.
Thank you.
That's an excellent starting point, and
you start from there.
And then, it's actually kind of cool,
right?
Because the first couple of, you know,
first couple of steps, you'll see two
things happening, right?
The function may or may not be going down.
But, you'll be moving towards a x equals
b.
All right, so, okay.
And if you do that, you know, here, here
you go, you get between 10 and
20 steps or something.
That's the infeasible start method.
That's the first one that actually puts.
Approximately 0 actual burden on you.
You know, you could write this code right
now, right?
because it doesn't need some weird things.
Okay.
But now let's go back and look at these 3
methods.
And if you look at them here's what's
going to come up.
It's really quite cool.
If you look at the original one you end up
solving This system
of equations to determine to get a Newton
step and look what it is.
Its diagonal a, a transpose.
Right?
That should induce in you an immediate
urge to eliminate,
to eliminate the first top delta x block
and you will get the following.
You will get a times you'll get this
reduced system times a transpose w
equals b.
Right?
So that's what you'll get and
you'll solve that.
Right?
okay.
Now, if you solve the Newton system for
the dual, well,
you end up solving something that looks
like this, okay?
But if you look at that carefully, you'll
realize, I mean,
it's a totally different system from this,
right, but the structure is the same.
It's A diagonal, A transpose.
It's a system of that form.
That's the coefficient equation.
That's what you have to solve.
Right?
In the third one you, the Newton system
looks like that.
I mean the only thing different here is
instead of the dual variable, you now have
a delta dual variable, and instead of a
zero you have a residual here.
And you get this.
So, it's the same, actually, as the first
one and you get the same thing.
The right hand side is different but that
doesn't matter.
So, in each case, you end up solving A, D,
A transpose, W equals H.
What that says is, the cost of the three
methods is identical despite
this one appearing to have 100 variables,
whereas, this one has Well,
this one has 500 variables, and this one,
down here, has 600.
Because your, you would say, well I'm
updating the primal the dual, right?
So, so all of this says don't be fooled
by, when someone just walks up to you and
tells you about what's in Newton's method
Ask a few questions to
prob if they know numerical linear algebra
and
if they don't, ignore everything they have
to say about what is hard and
what is easy because they are probably
completely wrong.
So that's the idea.
By the way I want to finish with just one
comment, if a has sparsity ADA transpose,
that comes up all the time.
And in fact, you can get the sparcity
patterns of ADA transpose.
Right, which is what you'd have to solve,
directly.
In this case, it's going to depend exactly
on this.
This will have a non-zero in the I J
position, if and
only if A, if you write, if you make a
like a, if you make a graph out of a or
actually if you take the matrix a, only if
there is a, I guess it's a row,
if, if i and j share a non zero in that
row, that, that's the condition.
So, in a lot of practical applications,
this would make it very clear what the
sparsity pattern is.
Okay, so, anyway, so the bottom line is
for
a lot of these problems smart that things
that would appear to be quite different
in complexity right numbers of variables
things like that actually aren't, but
that's assuming you are applying smart
linear algebra.
Right.
If you just, if you just made these and
then backslash on each one and they
weren't sparse You'd get you it would,
it would come up with the same conclusion
you'd want.
This would be way better because it's 100
variables way better than that and
that's better than that.
All right then next, the next example is
network flow optimization.
So the idea is this we have a network we
have flows so
Xi is the flow along arc Or edge i here.
Fi i is a cost function for flow along
that arc.
And ax equals b.
A is the node-incidence matrix.
So the node incidence matrix is the
following.
It tells you whether there is, looks like
this.
Right?
So you, you start with this.
And you put a plus one and a minus one, in
each.
So, each of these, these are the nodes.
Here, and these are the arcs.
And you put a plus 1 and minus 1 in each
column to tell you
which way the, that arc, where it goes
from and where it goes to.
Where it, it's head and tail is his
incident.
And then this matrix here, is ranked
efficient.
Well for example if you have one transpose
on the left times his mate, you get 0.
That would actually be perfectly okay to
leave it here.
But instead it's conventional to simply
remove one, row, and
that gives you a reduced, node incidence
matrix at tilde.
And if the graph is otherwise connected,
then that matrix is not ranked efficient.
That's standard.
We could say lots of things about that,
but this is the same,
this is done in electrical engineering,
this means you choose one node as the
ground, reference, or data node.
Okay, so that's, that's all that matters
there.
And Ax equals b is flow conservation.
So that says that if I, at every point,
every node here, might,
if I have some arcs flowing in, and some
arcs going out like this, it say, for
example that's x3 that's x5, that's x,
x10, and that's x12.
That says the following.
That x3 plus x5, that's flowing in, that
has to equal.
X10 plus x12, that's the outflow.
So basically Ax equals b is flow
conservation, and I should say what b is.
B most, if b on the right hand side, over
here,
the right hand side of this equation, that
is an external source or sync.
So that looks like that, right, so if,
if there is nothing else connected to that
node, then that the associated
B sub of i is zero otherwise that's a
source or sink, right, so okay.
So, this says among all flows please find
the one that minimizes the cause,
that's the cause.
Okay, so we are going to take a look at
that,
and we're going to figure out how to, how
to solve this problem.
More interestingly, we'll see how
structure comes in.
Well the KKT matrix looks like this.
We minimize a sum of functions of the
individual variables.
But I know what the Hessian of such thing
looks like.
The Hessian is the diagonal of the second
derivatives.
Right?
So, the Hessian, is here.
It's diagonal.
Just like that, and that's up here.
Then, I put A, over here.
Because I have AX equals B as the
constraint.
I have, this is my Newton.
My KKT system is, has involves A and A
transpose here, like that.
And I have to solve that equation and, you
know, you're staring at it,
you see a a you see a, a diagonal matrix
here and
by now, you should have a very strong urge
to eliminate that block, right?
And if you do eliminate that block,
you're going to get this thing that is the
negative sure complement of this matrix
with respect to H.
So you get this thing.
Now, by the way,
H inverse shouldn't scare you, even though
if H is big, because H is diagonal.
So, that was the whole point after all,
it's easy to invert.
So you end up solving a system that looks
like that, okay?
But we can actually say more, because this
is A times H inverse,
that's diagonal times A transpose.
And the sparsity pattern,
well it's the same as the sparsity pattern
of AA transpose.
Now A is here, a FAT matrix like this, so
AA transpose is the small one.
A diagonal one doesn't affect this
sparsity pattern.
Okay, and this is nodes here, right?
So, this is a nodes by nodes matrix, and
we can say exactly what its sparsity
pattern is.
Okay, this sparsity pattern is the
following.
An entry is non-zero here if and only if
nodes I and J are connected by an arc.
Okay?
So, that suggests, well, depends on the
network, of course, right?
So that suggests something like this.
Well I can, I don't know, I can ask you a
question about it.
This says, that, if the degree, right, if,
if each node has a maximum degree d, say.
That's the number of connected edges.
Then that tells you that every row of this
matrix and column,
by the way, has a maximum number of 3,
entries.
Non-zeros entries in it, right?
And then it tells you that this matrix is
probably sparse too, and
that suggests you can do a sparse cholesky
on this matrix, right?
And, in fact, if the graph is sparse
enough, and
if the gods who control the heuristics use
to order,
gelesky factorizations for sparse matrices
are smiling on you,
then there will be very little, if you're
lucky there will be not much fill in.
And that says basically that you can
solve, you can solve this system and
do one Newton Step in something that's not
much more time than the number of flows or
solve n, solve n.
And you could, if you're lucky you could
solve a pretty big flow system pretty
quickly in Newton steps, would only cost
you something that's really kind of on.
I mean, it's going to have a not totally
small multiplier in front, but
it's going to be something that would have
not many,
it wouldn't be much more then just walking
over the graph one.
So, and this would allow you to solve
this.
Very, very fast.
Again, that requires the sparsity, here.