What we're going to do now is look at a
quality constraint minimization and
you know, we are stepping slowly towards
solving general context
optimization problem.
Right, [COUGH] So, so we're going to add
constraints but
the easiest to handle are equality
constraints which are linear.
Okay, so, it's going to turn out actually,
there is few interesting things here but
some of it is actually, it turns out to be
quite simple.
We just reduce it to the other one.
Okay.
So, we want to minimize f.
F is smooth, subject to ax equals b.
And we're, we're going to assume that a is
full rank.
It's wide in full rank.
And we'll assume the optimum is attained,
right?
And so b-, basically, it says you simply
want,
these are the necessary insufficient
optimality conditions, right?
It, the, it's the kk key conditions New
star is an optimal dual variable here.
That's the, you know, or Lagrange
multiplier.
And so you want to solve these two
equations, and
let's stare at the two equations for a
minute.
interestingly, these equations are affine
in new star, right?
It, they do not, they're not non-linear in
new star, they're affine.
Now what are they in x?
Well, that's linear, right?
It depends on that.
Oh, except for one case.
When is the gradient of a function an
affine function?
When it's quadratic, right?
So if the function is quadratic, these are
a set of linear equations, okay.
And that, so that says that solving
linearly constrained quadratic
optimization problems is, is pure linear
algebra, right?
That's it.
You just set up a linear algebra and you,
and you do it, and you solve it.
Okay?
So, but in general, this thing,
if f is non-quadratic, this is non-affine,
and that's a set of non-linear equations.
By the way, people have names for the
residuals, right?
The name for the residual in this equation
is called the primal residual.
And sometimes denoted RP.
And the condition of course, the
optimality condition is RP equals zero.
This one, that expression on the left is
called the dual residual, and
it's denoted RD.
And of course, the optimality condition is
that RD equals zero.
So, you're looking to find x and nu that
make RP and RD zero.
Okay?
And by the way,
the number of equations is about right.
You have m plus p, you have m plus p
variables, right?
N plus p variables and you have n plus p
equations.
So, but they're possibly non-linear.
Okay.
So well, we already talked about this,
right?
If, if you, if you want to do equality
constrained quadratic minimization,
it's linear algebra, and so you get
something like this.
Right?
You write the optimality conditions this
way and you are actually
computing both x star and nu star which is
not the optimal Lagrange multiplier.
You compute both of them,.
By the way there's some structure here.
There's a block of zeros and your eyes
should be looking at it or
something already.
Without my saying.
I mean there's not a lot.
You could have more structure but, but
that's that.
And it turns out, I mean you can work out
a lot about this KKT matrix.
For example.
It's nonsingular if and only if if you're
in the null space of a,
p is positive definite, or something like
that.
So, another way to say that roughly,
is p is positive definite on the null
space of a, right?
So p has to have positive curvature, kind
of on the feasible set.
That's the right way to say it, okay?
That wasn't quite right, but, that's the
spirit.
Okay.
That's the set of linear equations.
There's a very general method for handling
equality constraints.
It's used to eliminate them.
Right?
So, you would do the following.
I would, this is my constrained
representation of an affine set, but
I will write it instead as a
free-parameter representation.
And so what I'll do is, you compute nx hat
that satisfies ax equals b.
That's this one.
Lots of names for this.
Tradi-, by the way, a traditional name for
this is x sub p for a particular solution.
That's the 19th century name, is you have
a particular solution.
I think the other one's like a homoge-, I
don't know.
Anyway.
So, that's a partic-, a partuc-, a
particular solution,
sorry, and then f is a matrix whose range
is exactly the null space of a, right?
Lots of ways to compute that.
That's just linear algebra, right?
So, lo, tons of ways to do this.
You could use a qr factorization,
all sorts of things, all sorts of ways to
do this.
Okay.
So what you do now is we'll change
variables in
our optimzation problem instead of X we'll
go with Z and you end up with this.
And now its totally unconstrained, still a
convex problem because you know F is
simply applied to a, applied to a affine
transformation here.
By the way, if the original f was
self-concordant, it still is, right?
so, that's it, and we know how to do that.
I mean we can blend Newton's method,
gradients, steepest descent, whatever you
like.
Okay?
So, that's, that's the idea.
Okay.
And, if you want,
after solving this problem, you can
reconstruct x.
I mean that's x, but
you can also reconstruct the optimal,
Legrange multiplier.
And it's got, just a particular formula
like that.
That's if you wanted it in the original
one.
Mm-kay?
So, oh, I should something mention about
the interpretation.
Sometimes it's useful.
Sometimes you want to know this.
Because the interpretation of new star, is
actually something like, eh, I'll be very,
it's something like the prices, for, if
these,
if every row of this is interpreted at
some sort of clearing constraint.
Right?
That, sort of,
the amount produced balances the amount
consumed, or something like that.
So it, that would be the economic
interpretation.
Then, in fact, nu is a vector of the
optimal prices of each of
those commodities.
It said, basically, as you know, the
interpretation of nu star is,
you know what, what if you allowed me to
change b a little bit?
What would happen?
Nu star tells you, how the optimal value
would change.
Okay, so.
I, I mean I just mentioned this.
Okay.
So, so that's that.
So what this kind of says is at this
point, you don't need to know any more,
and, and from some point of view,
you don't need to know any theory, about,
equality constraint problems,
because you just reduce it to an
unconstrained problem and it's done.
Okay, so quick example of that.
Let's solve here's an optimal allocation
with a resource constraint.
So, I minimize a bunch of individual costs
subject to all these things add up to b.
Right?
And so, so
this is an allocation problem, right?
I have, I have b is sort of an amount of
resource I have and, I'm, I'm,
I'm dividing it up among a bunch of
agents, right?
N agents.
And I want to do that.
Sometimes this is called the social cost
in that context, right?
And here, by the way, the optimal Lagrange
multiplier, which is scalar,
is actually tells you the optimal price
for the commodity, that we are allocating.
Okay?
So just, I mean,
it's kind of obvious, but.
Okay.
So that's a constraint problem.
How would you solve it?
Well what we can do is just this.
We'll do the following obvious
elimination, I could take X hat to be BEN.
Here's another X hat, right?
It's B over N times the vector of ones.
Right?
That's a uniform allocation.
But it doesn't matter.
So I'll take it to be BEN.
That means I give everything to agent N.
Okay?
And here's a matrix who's,.
Whose range is exactly the null space of
A.
A is the, is the vector, it is the row
vector 1,1,1,1, or 1 in the null space of
that is all things which sum to zero,
right, so, that's this and you know, look,
it just says, that this transforms to that
and that's on constraint, by the way, so
that says Whatever you can say about this
problem, you can solve it, super-fast.
Okay?
Actually we'll get to that, because, we're
going to see, that there's a way to,
to get the structure to exploit the
structure directly.
Newton's step, for a, equality-constrained
problem.
And it looks like this.
It says, you formed this 2 by 2 matrix.
Right?
2 by 2 block matrix here.
You have V and
W and you solve, and on the right-hand
side you have the gradient and zero.
Right?
And look, if you read the first one,
this says AV equals zero.
That means V's in the null space.
If you're in the null space, by the way,
that says that you can freely add it to a
feasible point x,
because if ax equals b and av equals zero,
I can add any multiple of v to x and
it still satisfies ax plus you know, hv
equals b, right?
So, that's the second, and the top one
basically tells you something it, it's
actually has to do with that dual residual
which we'll talk about in a minute.
So, couple of interpretations of this.
oh, and notice that it reverts to the
Newton step when there
are no equality constraints.
'Cause then there's no equality
constraints, that's just a one by one and
it's, it's hessian times v equals minus
gradient that gives you the Newton step.
So, where does this come from, lots of
interpretations.
Here's one.
Form the quadratic approximation of f, at
x.
That's this thing here.
And notice, v is like a stepper of
perturbation.
Okay?
Then there's, you, there's the equality
constraints or, they're equality
constraints, you don't need to approximate
any, you don't need to linearize.
Or, you could, even, right?
You could implement a method, which is
the, the linearized method.
And you would call it on an affine
function, and
that would simply return itself.
Right?
So this would be just fine.
And so, how do you linearize the equality
constraints?
They're just the same.
'Kay?
Now, this we know how to do.
Right?
Because this is
minimizing a convex quadratic in v.
Subject to quality constraints.
We know how to do that.
And guess what?
All you do is you solve this equation
here.
And that gives you v and w.
So that's, that's another way to say it.
And notice that that preserves the spirit
of Newton's method for,
without equality constraints.
I mean, so instead of being explicit you
should say Newton's method really,
the idea behind it, is this.
Is you implement a method that says, you
know, get quadratic appro-, you know,
get quadratic approximation or something
like that, and so then you call it on.
You do F dot quad, approx at X and
it returns a quadratic model valid near
that point.
And then you minimize it.
That's Newton's Method, right?
This is the same thing.
It says you call the same method on F.
And now you minimize it, but subject to
the equality constraints.
But you know we know how to minimize
quadratics subject to
equality constraints, 'cause that's linear
algebra.
Okay?
So, so I think it's, it's natural.
Another way to say it is this.
Here's what you really want.
What you really want, is you want when you
take a step here, ,you want,
you would like this thing to be zero
[COUGH].
That's what you'd like, right?
that, that's which you really want,
that, that's driving R, RD, the dual
residual to zero.
And so, what we do is we simply take an
approximation of this that's,
that's in general non-affine, in fact is a
quadratic it's affine, but if
the f is non-quadratic its affine, but if
the f is non-quadratic that's affine and
then the approximation of the gradient at
x plus v is very simple.
If the gradient at x plus the hessian,
which is after all the derivative of the
gradient multiplied by the step.
And if you solve these two equations,
that's this.
Okay?
So, so you can either call the linearized
method on the optimality conditions and
solve the linear equations.
Or you can call the quadratic method on
the original problem and then solve that.
Right?
Either way.
And they're the same thing.
Okay.
So the Newton decrement is, can be written
several ways, this is one of them.
And it, it's that.
By the way, there are some other formulas
for
the Newton decrement which are completely
false, in the equality constraint case.
One, is I think, Delta x Newton transpose,
times the inverse of this, times that.
Right, there's, one of the formulas looks
like that, and it's wrong.
Okay?
But so, you have to be careful.
Couple of the formulas you know for
Newton decrement are correct, others are,
are, are wrong.
Okay.
And it's the same thing.
It simply gives you an estimate.
It's the difference between it says that,
if you form the quadratic model,
solve the constraint problem, how much
would the objective go down?
And that's, that's Lambda squared over 2,
is, is what that is,
so, makes perfect, perfect sense.
It's also the directional derivative in
the Newton direction so
that also was preserved.
But it is not equal to that.
That's an example of one of the formulas
that's just wrong for equality constraint.
Okay.
Now here's Newton's method with equality
constraints.
So, here's the algorithm.
You know, you compute the Newton step and
the decrement.
You quit if the decrement is squared over
2 which is your expected decrease is
less than epsilon.
Then you do a line search and you update.
So guess what?
That algorithm is identical to Newton's
method for unconstrained.
It's exactly the same.
The difference is, we have now kind of
overloaded a few things here.
Newton's step has been overloaded to
handle equality constraints.
It, doesn't mean hessian inverse, minus
hessian inverse radiant,
it means solve this big KKT system.
Right?
And, we also overloaded the Newton
decrement.
To mean something appropriate in that
case, okay?
Otherwise, it's identical, the algorithm.
And it's a feasible descent method,
meaning every step x is feasible and
your objective goes down unless you're at
the optimum point.
And it's affine invariant.
You change coordinates, it's, it's,
doesn't matter.
Okay?
I mean, you, you get, a commutative
diagram.
You get exactly the same algorithm.
Okay.
By the way, what that, means, is that
scaling is sort of a second-order issue,
for Newton, methods.
Right?
meaning, yeah, if you scale things by 10
to the 38,
and 10 to the minus 38 You're going to
have underflow, and overflow, and
numerical issues, and things like that,
sure, okay?
But you can scale things very happily by a
thousand, ten thousand, and
it will work fine.
And the reason for that is, to a numerical
analyst, a condition number of a system of
linear equations of 10^3 or 10^4 is not
that big a deal.
Right?
Whereas, for any first order method
Condition number is a first-order effect.
If the first, if the condition number is
like ten, it's going to work super well.
If it's 100,000, just forget it.
It, for all practical purposes, it doesn't
work.
If it's 1,000, it may not work, okay?
So, that's the idea.
Another way to say it is,
If your method is working with a gradient
method I can break it by scaling.
Scaling even modest,
by modest scaling, Newton's method, I
won't break, it will work perfectly.
Okay?
So, okay.
Now it turns out, there's a, we don't have
to do any analysis of this, and
the reason is the following.
There's a commutative, you get a perfect
commutative diagram here.
If you take a problem.
You take an original problem with equality
constraints.
Then you eliminate the variables.
You do variable elimination.
Then you apply Newton's method.
You get a commutative diagram with
applying Newton's method with
equality constraints.
It's identical.
And that means we don't have to do any
analysis at all.
Because we already know it all.
We know everything.
Including for self-concordance, I might
add.
We know everything.
Nothing to do.
So you don't need any convergence
analysis.
That's good.
Now we're going to talk about something
that's different.
And, honestly, this is maybe the more
useful one.
And this is actually the more modern one.
And it's actually Probably more useful so
here it is.
It's the idea of a Newton step at an
infeasible point.
And so the basic idea is that you really
say that what you want to do is you,
you, you write down the residual, right?
And that's in n plus, rn plus p, and it's
the following.
It's, it's the dual residual and then the
primal residual.
And what you want to solve,
is a set of non-linear equations in n plus
p variables, right?
Of which, one of which and the number of
equations you have is n plus p, okay?
So that's, that's what you want to do so
that's one view of it.
Now, by the way,
equate solving non-linear equations in r n
plus b with n plus b equations,
is super complicated like, you don't even
know that there exists a solution.
Right, I mean, here you know there is a
solution because well it's
a convex problem and so on and so forth.
So that's the nice part is that there is
some regularity up to this.
But Newton's method simply says I want to
solve that equation.
Here is what we going to do.
I'm going to, y is going to be actually a
primal-dual variable.
It's going to be a pair consisting of a
primal variable and a dual variable, and
what we're going to do is this.
I want r of y is zero, so
I'll imagine that I'm going to to go y
plus delta y, that's going to be my step.
And what I would like is I want that to be
zero, but that's equal to r,
I mean the, the linear approximation of r
is affline, but people call it linear,
is r of y plus dr, that's the derivative
or Jacobian, multiplied by delta 1.
Dr is exactly that.
You get a similar set of equations, here's
what you get you get this.
Actually the right-hand side is is, is, is
is a little bit different here.
Actually it turns out, these are
completely the same.
Right?
If, if here we're actually
calculating the, that's the full Newton
thing, sorry, the full dual variable.
And here we're calculating an update to a
dual variable.
Okay?
So, this is a, a,
a very nice form of Newton's method, and
it is to be interpreted this way.
It says, and you should think of it as a
primal-dual method, because every step,
you're updating a primal and a dual
variable.
Right?
And the idea is to drive both the primal
and dual residuals to zero.
And, so you solve this.
This is the same KKT system.
And on the right hand side are the
residuals of both.
Right, so.
By the way, it generalizes the Newton step
for a feasible point.
Because if, if x is feasible, that's zero,
and guess what?
You get the Newton step that we had before
for feasible points, so
it's a generalization, but you have to be
kind of careful.
Let me tell you why you have to kind of be
careful.
What's kind of cool about this is,
this defines a Newton step even when
you're infeasible.
Notice you don't satisfy ax equals b.
It says there's a direction to go in.
Now, you have to be very careful.
Because that direction to go in is a
combination of two things.
There's one is you want to make f small.
So you're going to kind of be going in the
direction minus gradient f.
I mean that is after all what we're trying
to do.
But if you don't satisfy ax equals b,
you're also going to be going in a
direction towards which ax equals b.
Right?
So you're going to have, kind of,
these two directions.
And you also have to be very careful.
Because in a problem like this, you could
end up.
I mean, it's, it's not a dissent method,
for obvious reasons.
Right?
If that's my equality constraint, right?
And here's my, my function I'm minimizing,
right?
You know, I don't know, maybe the, it's
the solution would be right there.
It's, it's whenever the tangent touches
this down.
That's the solution, right?
Now, suppose I started right here.
That, that's my initial point, okay?
So at that point, what's the gradient of
f?
It's zero, right?
So.
The only minor problem is you're not
feasible, right?
So, the Newton step, in this case,
is going to point you to somewhere on the
line here, right?
because if you take one, if you take a
full Newton step,
the equality constraint becomes feasible,
okay?
So that, that's, that's the idea.
And by the way, what will happen to f from
your first iteration?
It will go up?
Has to go up, because, you started at the
minimum of f, right?
So, clearly not a descend method.
Now, when you see f go up,
someone says, hey, that's a, crappy job
you did on that optimization.
I gave you an initial point, and
the first thing you do, is your function
value goes up.
And, what, what do you say to that?
What, what would be your, what's your
comeback?
[INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, it's like, well dude, your point
wasn't feasible.
So, it had excellent objective, but it
didn't satisfy the constraints.
So, that's all.
Okay.
I just mention this because things like
this come up and,
you'd be surprised, actually.
So.
Okay.
So, it says the line search is different.
So you don't, you don't measure progress
by the function value, obviously, although
you should measure val-, you should
measure two things the primal and dual
residual norms, or some people lump them
together into one and either, either way.
By the way, this will tell you something
if you look at things like SeDuMi or
STPT3 output, I don't know if you do, but
when you run CVX a few of the columns are
now going to be demystified.
They'll be fully demystified by next week,
but you will see things that say rp and
rd, or it'll be obscure.
It'll say dnorm and pnorm, and these will,
these literally mean the primal residual
and the dual residual norm.
So, okay.
Okay, so here it is.
What you do is, you compute these ,Newton,
the Newton, the primal and
dual Newton steps.
And then you do a backtracking line search
on the, on the norm of r.
So, on the total residual.
That's easy enough.
And it turns out the directional
derivative is simply minus the residual.
That's a, a quick calculation.
And so you get a very simple code that
looks like this.
And then you update x and you keep going.
It's not a dissent method.
But I'll tell you what does go down is,
the norm of the residual.
So whenever you have an algorithm and
people analyse it, there is,
the basis of a proof or something, is that
some function that goes down.
Right, in the Newton method, the gradient
descend,
the things we focused on the function
value going down.
I mean, what can be more natural?
You want to minimize f.
So it's kind of cool,
that, the thing you want to happen,
happens, actually locally at every step.
Greedily, it happens, right?
here, it turns out that, that, by the way,
it's got all sorts of names, I think one
name, one method is the Lyapunov function.
And there's another one, I forget,
there's all sorts of names in optimization
too for that.
I forgot the name.
And
in computer science they have yet another
name.
Which I also can't remember right now.
But anyway.
So, but the concept is very simple.
There's a, you have an iterative method
and
you have a function that goes down every
step.
And that's the base, the basis of your
proof, that it works, right?
So.
By the way, there's a huge practical,
advantage of having such a function if
it's, if it's explicit.
Because it basically says, you can do
anything you want on that algorithm, any
modification you want, at all, as long as
you make sure that function, does go down.
Right?
So for example,
you can insert weird steps in your
algorithm that does some kind of
weird local optimization, okay?
But, you better make sure,
that local optimization better ensure that
that Lyapunov function goes down.
I just remembered one of the names, merit
function.
That's one of them.
But there's like five of them, and anyway,
you'll, you, the concept is clear.
Okay.
So here,
it turns out the merit function is the
norm of the residual.
So, let's talk about solving KKT systems.
How do you solve something like that?
Well there's lots of ways,.
So, one is you just use LDL transpose,
because that's a symmetric indefinite
system, right?
It's indefinite because you look at the
zeros down there, and in fact it
has exactly n, well, if h is positive,
definite, it has exactly n actually,
if it's solvable, it has n positive
[INAUDIBLE] values, and exactly m, or p,
I think it's p, is, the size of equality
constraints, p negative ones.
Okay?
So, that's, very simple.
You just plug in this stuff, and, and,
and, use LDL transverse factorization.
You can also do elimination.
What you do is, you know,
in many applications H will be diagonal,
block diagonal, something simple.
There we go.
And so, H'll be, and
then, and then H would then be a natural
target for elimination.
I mean, for sure if you saw that system
and
H was diagonal, I'm hoping every single
one of
you would have an overwhelming urge to
eliminate the one one block.
You should.
It'll, and we're going to train you until
that's the case, okay?
So that if, if h, but, doesn't, I mean,
the math doesn't matter either way.
So if you eliminate the, the v, here.
You end up with a system that looks like
this.
By the way, that is the negative Schur
complement of that matrix, right?
Because the Schur complement is 0 minus a,
h inverse a transpose,
that's the Schur complement.
Well with a minus sign, okay?
so, that's a sure compliment.
And by the way I think this called people
refer to this system as
the reduced system.
That's standard notation.
So people would say oh, you'd say, oh,
Newton, and blah, blah, blah.
And say oh how are you solving it?
And they'd say, reduced system.
By the way, they would then call this the
augmented system.
Don't ask me why.
It's the KKT system.
That's augmented and reduced.
Okay?
So you could do this.
Now, if H is singular, there's lots of
interesting things you can do.
One is that, in fact, any solution of this
is identical to a solution to that.
You can just check, but the point is that,
what this allows you to
do is to make sure that this 1, 1 block is
non-singular, right?
Then you can apply elmination.
So, okay.
Now we're going to, we're going to finish
with an example and
it's going to tie a whole bunch of stuff
together.
And actually, it's going to, y-, you're
going to see something really interesting,
which is to say that all these, there's
lots of methods to solve a single problem.
If they relate, they go through duality
and stuff like that.
And what I'll you'll, you'll the but I'll,
I'll,
I'll get to the punch line right now.
That you're, we're going to look at a
problem and you can solve it many ways.
You could solve the problem, you could
solve the dual, you could do this and
that and in each case if you use Newton's
method,
this is going to be the critical part.
If you use Newton's method, the system of
equations you're going to come down to
solving, and each step of each of those,
is not exactly the same.
But it has exactly the same structure.
And that structure will be such that if
you know what you're doing you can
solve it efficiently.
Right?
And so,
what's kind of interesting about that is
that a lot of times
you will actually hear people who don't
know any better say things like, oh,
I'm solving the dual, right?
And they might say that because it sounds
cool, right?
To solve the dual.
Doesn't it?
I mean, people don't know, you say I'm
solving the dual.
Anyway, it sounds sophisticated.
And you say, why is that.
You go, well, I get efficiency or
something.
I mean, there are reasons to solve duals
like you can distribute stuff, and
parallel things.
That's another story.
But if you're doing, like,
a Newton method, there's absolutely no
reason to do it.
If you know linear algebra, if you know
numerical algebra,
there's absolutely no reason to do that.
We'll see that.
What is different actually is the
initilizations.
So alright let's, let's jump into it.
We want to calculate the analytic center
of
Ax equals b and x non negative.
And that's the feasible set for a classic
linear program.
Right?
Minimize transpose x,
subject Ax equals b, x bigger than or
equal to zero.
Of the feasible set.
It's the intersection if you like, of an
affine set,
with a nonnegative orthant, is what it is.
And we want to write down, I mean, so the
analytic center is this, right?
That we want to minimize some of the logs,
that's the barrier associated with that,
subject to x equals b.
Okay?
So.
Now the dual of that problem, you can work
it out.
Is this.
You maximize this.
And here it turns out, this thing is
strictly the original function is
strictly convex, and that says, that, if
we know the,
if we solve the dual, we can recover, the
primal solution.
And there's a silly, simple formula,
right, it's really dumb formula for it,
it's like it doesn't even matter what it
is, let's.
If it's there.
Right?
And you can,
by solving the dual, you get the primal.
Okay.
And they're kind of interesting, let's
take a look at them.
The dual is unconstrained.
Well, not quite.
There's an implicit constraint, that A
transpose new is positive.
Okay?
So
the domain of the dual is a bit
complicated.
It's the set of vectors nu for which a
transpose nu is positive.
That's actually a open polyhedron, right?
So the domain of the primal is simple.
It's r plus to the n.
R plus plus to the n, right?
It's all positive vectors, right?
Sorry, intersect with ax equals b.
My, my mistake, so okay.
So, they're different.
Okay, so let's look at some things.
Here's what we can do.
Let's just take Newton method with
equality constraint.
So we have a problem with 500 variables,
100 equality constraints.
And if you run Newton's method, you get
something like this.
And, what we're doing,
here, is, these four traces show you just
four different starting points, right?
And, you know that looks very Newtonish.
This is what you should, this is what you
should see and you will see.
Presumably.
Later.
This week?
Are they.
They're doing it this week.
Okay.
So you'll see things that look like this.
We, this is what you're shooting for,
right?
And the idea is, look,
that's a ridiculous, that's a 10 to the 15
range there.
So, this, this may be actually, quite,
perfectly good, respectable convergence,
but on a plot, whose range goes covers ten
to the 15, you're not seeing it, okay?
But the key thing you should see is
something like that, right?
That's, that, that's your basic Newton
behavior, right?
By the way, that should also correspond to
the place where you do undamped steps, so
the step size should be one in that
region.
Fine.
And this is what you expect.
Okay.
Oh, the initialization was interesting.
We needed to know a positive vector with a
x equals b, right?
I mean if this is just a general problem
you don't know such a thing so
that would be kind of a pain.
Let's apply Newton method to the dual
problem, okay?
So here, if you applied,
that means what we do is we need a vector
nu zero that starts in the domain and
we apply Newton's method, and then here it
is for four different things.
And by the way, you might be tempted to
say, in fact, I will give you the entire
fallacious argument, because I promise you
will hear this from someone you know.
In which case you can correct their
misunderstanding.
They would say, I have a fantastic method
for solving this problem.
I'm going to solve the dual.
Someone says, why would you do that?
And they would say the following.
Number one, that original problem has 500
variables.
The dual has a 100.
Last time I checked 100 is smaller than
500.
A person says, I' m solving, you're
solving a problem with 500 variables,
I'm solving one with 100.
That's fewer.
That means it's 125 times faster, number
one.
Number two, to add sort of, just a bonus,
you're taking fifteen, twenty steps.
Look at this.
This thing typically converges in eight or
nine steps.
I'm half the number of steps.
My advantage over you is 250x.
Plus you get the added bonus that it
sounds cool if you say,
I'm solving the dual.
Because it sounds more sophisticated, you
know what I'm saying?
RIght?
Everyone getting this argument?
We will see that it is totally and
completely wrong.
Okay?
But that's the argument.
You will hear it from people.
Okay.
Now let's look at another one.
Let's look at infeasible start Newton
Method.
Now, this is its huge advantage and
this is probably why this is more useful
than, than, than a lot of others.
Although, it depends on the situation.
The initialization is very modest.
The only thing you need, it does not have
to satisfy ax equals b,
it only has been in the domain.
The domain is the sum of the logs, right?
So, could some one, want to suggest a
starting point.
All ones, thank you,
all ones, that is an excellent starting
point and you start from there.
And then, it's actually kind of cool
right?
Because the first couple of, you know,
the first couple of steps you'll see two
things happening, right?
The function may or
may not be going down but, you'll be
moving towards ax equals b, right?
So, okay.
And if you do that, you know here, here
you go you get between 10 and
20 steps or something.
That's the infeasable start method.
But the first one that actually puts
Approximately zero actual burden on you.
You know, you could write this code right
now, right?
Because it doesn't need some weird thing.
Okay, but now let's, let's go back and
look at these three methods.
And if you look at them, here's what's
going to come up.
It's really quite cool.
If you look at the original one, you end
up solving
this system of equations to determine to
get a Newton step, okay?
And look what it is.
It's diagonal a, a transpose, right?
That should induce in you an immediate
urge to eliminate eh,
to eliminate the first top ec-, delta x
block, and
you will get the following: You will get a
times, you,
you'll get this reduced system times a
transpose w equals b, right?
So that's what you'll get, and you'll
solve that.
Right?
okay.
Now if you solve the Newton system for
the dual, well you end up solving
something that looks like this, okay?
But if you look at that carefully you
realize,
I mean, it's a totally different system
from this, right?
But the structure is the same, it's a
diagonal a transpose.
It's a system of that form, that's the
coefficient equation.
That's what you have to solve, right?
In the third one, you, the Newton system
looks like that.
I mean the only thing different here is,
instead of the dual variable you
now have a, a delta dual variable, and
instead of a 0, you have a residual here.
And you get this,
so it's the same, actually, as the first
one and you get the same, same thing.
The right-hand side is different, but that
doesn't matter.
So in each case, you end up solving a, d,
a transpose w equals h.
What that says is, the cost of the three
methods is identical despite
this one appearing to have 100 variables,
whereas this one has, well,
this one has 500 variables, and this one,
down here, has 600,
because you're up, you would say, well I'm
updating the primal and the dual, right?
So, so all of this says, don't be fooled
by when somebody walks up to you and
tells you about the complexity of Newton's
method.
Ask a few questions to probe if they know
numerical linear algebra, and
if they don't, ignore everything they have
to say about what's hard and
what's easy 'cause they're probably
completely wrong.
Okay?
So that's, that, that's the idea.
By the way, I want to finish with just one
comment.
If a has sparsity, ADA transpose, that
comes up all the time.
And in fact, you can get the sparsity
pattern of ADA transpose, right,
which is what you'd have to solve,
directly.
And in this case it's going to depend,
exactly on this.
This will have a non-zero, in the I, J,
position.
If and only if, a if you write, if you
make a like a,
if you make a graph out of a, or actually
if you take the matrix a.
Only if there is a, I guess it's a row if,
if i and
j share a non-zero in that row that,
that's the condition.
So, in a lot of practical applications
this would make it
very clear what the sparsity pattern is.
Okay, so anyway.
So the bottom line is that for a lot of
these problems it's,
it's smart that things that would appear
to be quite different in,
in complexity right, numbers of variables
things like that, actually aren't.
But that's assuming you are applying smart
linear algebra right?
If you just, if you just made these and
did back slash on each one and
they weren't sparse, you'd get, you, it
would,
it would come up with the same conclusion
you'd want.
This would be way better.
Because it's 100 variables, way better
than that.
And that's better than that.
Alright, the next example, is network flow
optimization.
So, the idea is this; we have a network.
We have flows.
So xi is the flow along arc.
Or edge i, here.
Phi i is a cost function for flow along
that arc.
And ax equals b, I'll say what a is, a is
the node incidence matrix.
so, the node incidence matrix is the
following.
It tells you whether there is, looks like
this, right?
So, you start with this.
And you put a plus 1 and a minus 1.
In each so, each of these, these are the
nodes, here and these are the arcs and
you put a plus 1 and minus 1 in each
column to tell you which way the,
that arc where it goes from and where it
goes to.
Where it's head and tail is is incident.
And and then this matrix here is rank
deficient of well for
example if you have one transpose on the
left times this matrix you get zero.
That would actually be perfectly okay to
leave it here.
But instead, it's conventional to simply
remove one row and
that gives you a reduced node incidence
matrix at tilde.
And if the graph is otherwise connected,
then that matrix is not ranked efficient,
that's standard.
We could say lots of things about that but
this is the same this is done in
electrical engineering.
This means you choose one node as the
ground reference or datum node, okay?
So that's, that's all that matters there.
And Ax equals b is flow conservation, so
that says that if I at every point, every
node here,
I might, if I have some arcs flowing in
and some arcs going out like this.
It says, for example, if that's x3, that's
x5, that's x, x10, and that's x12.
That says the following that x3 plus x5
that's flowing in that has to
equal x10 plus x12, that's the outflow.
So, basically, ax equals b is flow
conservation.
And I should say what b is.
b, most, if b on the right hand side over
here,
the right hand side of this equation, that
is an external sourcer sync.
So, it looks like that, right?
So, if, if there is nothing else connected
to that node.
Then, that the associated b sub i is zero.
otherwise, that's a source or sink.
Right.
So.
Okay.
So, this says,
among all flows, please find the one that
minimizes the cost.
These are, that's, that's the cost.
Okay.
So we're going to take a look at that.
And we're going to figure out, how to, how
to solve this problem.
More interestingly we'll see how structure
comes in.
Well the KKT matrix looks like this.
We, minimize a sum of functions, of the
individual variables.
But I know at the hession, what such a
thing looks like.
The hession is the diagonal of the second
derivatives, right?
So, the hessian, is here, it's diagonal.
It's like that.
And that's up here.
Then I put A, over here, because I have ax
equals b, as the constraint.
I have, this is my Newton, my KKT system
is, has, involves A and
A transpose, here, like that.
And I have to solve that equation.
And you know, you're staring a at it and
you see a, a, a diagonal matrix here.
And by now you should have a very strong
urge to eliminate that block.
And if you do eliminate that block you're
going to get this thing that is
the negative Schur complement of this
matrix with respect to H.
So you get this thing.
Now by the way H inverse shouldn't scare
you,
even though if H is big because H is
diagonal.
So, that was the whole point after all;
it's easy to invert.
So you end up solving a system that looks
like that, okay?
But we can actually say more, because this
is A times, h inverse,
that's diagonal, times A transpose.
And the sparcity pattern, what, it's the
same as the sparsity pattern of a,
a transposed.
Now a is here.
Of that matrix like this.
So a a transposed, is the small one.
Diagonal one doesn't affect the sparsity
pattern.
Okay?
And this is nodes, here.
Right?
So this is a nodes-by-nodes matrix.
And we can say exactly what its sparsity
pattern, is.
Okay?
This sparsity pattern is the following.
An entry is nonzero here if and only if
nodes i and j are connected by an arc.
Okay?
So that suggests Well it depends on the
network of course, right?
So, that suggests something like this.
Well I can, I don't know, I can ask you a,
a, a question about it.
This says that if the degree, right?
If, if each node has a maximum degree d,
say, that's the number of connected edges.
Then that tells you that every row of this
matrix, and column by the way,
has a maximum number of three, entries.
Non-zero entries in it, right?
And that tells you that this matrix is
probably sparse,
too, and that suggests that you could do a
sparse Cholesky on this matrix, right?
And in fact, it, if the graph is sparse
enough and
if the gods who control the heuristics
used to order
Cholesky factorizations for sparse
matrices are smiling on you,
Then there will be very little, if you're
lucky, there'll be not much fill-in, and
that says basically that you can solve,
you can com, you can solve this system and
do one Newton step in something that's not
much more time than the number of flows.
Yeah, we're, so, n.
So, of n.
And if you're lucky you can solve a pretty
big flow system pretty quickly.
And Newton's steps would only cost you
something that's really kind of only,
well it's going to have a not totally
small multiplier in front.
But it's going to be something that would
have not many,
it wouldn't be much more than just walking
over the graph once.
So, and this would allow you to solve this
very, very fast.
Again that requires the sparsity here.