Today we're going to look at Unconstrained
Minimization.
So that's, how do you minimize a smooth
convex function?
So that, that's what we're going to look
at.
And we'll start with just some basic ideas
and
definitions about what it means to
minimize it.
By the way, most of these problems don't
have exact solutions,
they don't have analytical solutions.
So we're going to come up with algorithms
that only in the limit actually achieve
what you want.
But that's good enough for any practical
purpose.
We'll talk about what is basically the
most obvious and
the most famous algorithm.
That's the gradient descent method,
where you just evaluate the gradient and,
roughly speaking, go downhill.
Steepest descent is a variation on that.
And then we'll get to something quite
interesting.
Newton's method.
well, the very name suggests that this is
not new.
but, we'll see the important thing about
Newton's method is we'll understand how
you get an algorithm that exploits not
just a first-order, a gradient, but
also a Hessian, as well.
These methods, probably you've seen it.
I hope you've seen it in some other
context, and you might know,
you might know about Newton's method is
that yet, when, once it gets close to
the solution, it converges to extremely
high accuracy and very quickly.
And we're going to analyze that very much.
then, what will do is we'll switch gears.
You know, this is obviously not new.
I mean, it is, after all, Isaac Newton's
Method.
So then, we'll switch gears and
we'll talk about something which is
actually quite modern.
It's a theory only 10, 15 years old.
And that's the theory of self-concordant
functions.
This is pioneered by Nesterov and
Nemirovski.
And so we'll talk about that and it's a
new,
it's a new way to analyze Newton's method.
And it's, it's the method that will be
successful later in the course in showing
that the methods we're going to look at
into your point methods actually have
polynomial time complexity on convex
optimization problems.
Finally at the end, we'll say a little bit
about the implementation.
We'll tie the ideas of this section.
We'll tie all of this together with the
ideas of numerical methods that we
discussed in the last lecture.
And in particular particularly interesting
will be topics like this.
How do you exploit structure in solving
the linear equations that you'll have to
solve when you implement Newton's method?
And that'll be a very interesting topic.
So we're going to look at smooth
unconstrained minimization.
So we're going to minimize an objective
function, f.
And we're going to assume it's it's convex
and
twice continuously differentiable, right?
So its domain is open.
And we're going to assume that the optimal
value is attained, right?
The only other option, of course, it'd, is
that it's minus infinity.
It's unboundable up.
Actually, all the methods we're looking at
will do the right thing when its
unbounded below.
We'll see how that works but we're just
going to assume its, we're in,
we're in the case where we assume its
bounded below and attained.
And so the idea the goal is to produce a
sequence of
points where f of xk goes to p star,
alright?
So that's, that's the, that's the idea.
And by the way,
even when it's unconstrained, it's the
same statement, right?
So, you've produced and unbounded
sequence.
I mean, that's a bit silly because when
you run an algorithm, it terminates at
some point, finite, you know, term, it'll
run out some maximum number of iterations.
And produce a, a, a, a function value
that's very, very low.
okay, and you can, you can interpret a
method, you know,
a method that produces a minimizing
sequence.
That's sometimes what people call a
sequence that does this.
You can interpret that actually as these
are iterative methods for
solving this set of equations,
which are the optimality conditions such
as gradient equal to 0, right?
So that's the other way to interpret it.
And in fact, for several of the algorithm,
we'll see both interpretations are quite
illuminating, right?
So okay, oh, and I should mention one
thing.
We're going to look exclusively at
iterative methods.
There are a handful of problems where
there's some sort of like,
silly analytical solution.
I mean, some they are important, what is
least squares, alright?
So you don't need an iterative method to
solve least squares.
So that, I mean, that is an important
building block.
Of course, minimizing a least, least
squares problem or
something like that, that's Linear
Algebra, right,
because the optimality condition is the
gradient equal to 0.
And that's a set of linear equations and
so
you know all of that already, there's
nothing to say.
so, but we're mostly interested in case
where that's not true.
And so you'll need iterative method to
solve it.
Okay.
Now, there are a couple of assumptions,
I'm not going to go into it
in huge detail, but they're actually
important to understand.
So the first thing is you have to have a
point that's in the domain.
So you have, have to start with a point in
the domain.
Often that's easy.
The domain is all of Rn.
It's nothing.
You pick your favorite point.
If the domain is, you know, R plus to the
n, that's so, again, very easy.
You might start from the vector of R1s.
But actually, in some cases, it may not be
easy to find a point in the domain.
We will later see methods that would work
even if you don't know a point in the
domain.
So, we'll, we'll see that later.
Another very important thing is we're,
we're going to have assumed that the
sublevel set,
the initial sublevel set is closed.
Alright.
And that's, and this is basically
going to, you know prevent us from,
prevent the algorithm from having x, you
know go towards a point which is
not on the closure of, of this and that
would, you know, okay, that's a pathology.
Now it turns out this is generally quite
hard to satisf.
But one simple sufficient condition for
that is that all sublevel sets are closed.
And that, by the way some people simply
say,
f is a closed function, that means epi f
is a closed set.
So, by the way, if you have a background
in analysis that's fine and if you
don't then at least you should understand
what this means intuitively, right?
And you can work, figure out what, what
these things mean.
So, now if your differentiable and closed,
it means your domain is open and the
epigraph is closed.
And that means you can't do something like
simply have a boundary in the domain and
then go straight up to infinity, right?
That would be closed, that's a closed
function but
it's not closed differentiable.
Closed, if you have a closed
differentiable function,
it basically says the function kind of has
to go to plus infinite,
there's no other way to do it, right?
You can't have something like entropy or
square root, where you get a, a,
a pathology like this and then it stops at
a finite value.
You can't, that's you can't do.
And some conditions here that are
sufficient, you know,
obviously if the domain is everything,
that's fine.
Another one is if the function goes to
infinity as you go to
the boundary that's good enough.
That's, that's called a barrier function
for the domain and
that's good enough to imply this.
Okay.
So here's some examples.
Here's a log sum x function.
this, it's obvious because the domain is
everything.
The domain is Rn.
So, of course, that has closed sublevel
sets.
Then here's another one, this one does not
here, that's the log barrier for
a set of linear inequalities, right?
Which is ai transpose x less than bi.
That's the log barrier.
And by the way, this is the perfect
example of a function where it is not,
it need not be easy to find a point in the
domain.
To find a point in the domain of this,
means find a point that satisfies a set of
strict linear inequalities, and
you may have to solve a linear program to
find such a point, right?
So, this is an example of that.
But it's also an example of a point where
the domain is obviously not all of Rn.
The domain is an open, is an open
polyhedron here.
So, it's the interior of a polyhedron,
right, that's the domain.
And in fact, this has, this has the
property that epi f is closed and
what happens here is that it's a barrier.
As you move towards the boundary, if any
if ai transposed x gets close to bi,
then one of these terms gets super
negative with the minus sign here,
the whole function goes to plus infinity.
So, okay.
So we will be using, at several times,
we're going to be using basically a
sledgehammer t, well, show convergence.
Let me explain why.
In some sense, these convergent,
convergence analysis of algorithms and
things like that in this case, they're,
they're important.
What they really are is they're sort of
like feel good things, right?
They, because, you know, you implement
something in a real language and
it works, and stuff like that.
And, and there's always something in there
that has a maxIter like 30 or
50 or something like that.
And, you know,
if you hit the maxIter, you're, you're not
going to go forever, right?
So the, the kind of algorithms you have, I
mean these results that you have that say
something like, you know, as m, as k goes
to infinity, you converge to a solution.
And technically speaking you're not per,
you're not actually really relevant in
practice.
If, if you see what I mean, right?
They're just not, right?
Because you don't run algorithms for
infinity, right?
You're not interested if the limit is, you
know, has, has optimal value.
I mean, these are not interesting, right?
So, these are more like sort of feel good
things that basically say,
well, in my running, in my production
code, I have this maxIter thing there,
but if, but if you don't hit that, right,
then in principle,
this would produce a solution, or
something like that.
And so these are not bad things to say.
My feeling is, given the, that, by the
way,
we will see some exceptions to this later
that are very impressive.
so, we'll see some exceptions to things,
they're not feel-good things things.
They're actually quite explicit.
But most of this stuff is just feel-good
stuff.
we'll, you'll see why.
I'll, I'll stop and make various points
about this earlier.
But what it means is,
I'm going to feel free to take extremely
strong assumptions, right?
Because it just shortens the proof, and
because there's no point, you know,
proving this under the most general
conditions, or something like that.
So, here's one of them.
Ready?
Is strong convexity.
So strong convexity, basically says,
there's a minimum curvature.
It says, the Hessian has min, minimum
curvature, little m.
And, you know, this could hold, this has
to hold only on
that initial sublevel set or something
like that but that's all you need, right?
And by the way, if the sublevel is
bounded, this is automatic, right?
Because if the, actually all you really
have to say is that the Hess,
is that the Hessian is positive definite
everywhere.
Then, I mean, if the sublevel sets are
bounded, right,
then the minimum of a continuous function
all comes back to the positive, right?
That, that, that of a positive function.
So, that's again, if you know analysis.
because if you don't, don't worry about
it.
Okay.
So that's a very,
that's a very strong assumption.
Alright, now what this does is actually
something very interesting.
And we'll see variations on this later.
This inequality right here, that's the
classic inequality that holds, right, so
that's, that's without this term.
This inequality holds, of course, for any
convex function.
I mean that's what it says.
It says, that the first-order of Taylor
expansion is a global lower bound on f.
If you add the assumption of minimum
curvature here,
then you can actually tighten it, alright?
So, you can actually say,
plus m over 2 times x minus y normal
squared here, right?
So, you actually get a, and, in fact,
that's really cool because what
was before, this used to be an affine
lower bound.
You now have a quadratic lower bound,
okay?
Not, not as quadratic but one with a
curvature m, alright?
All sorts of implications here, right?
So, for example, if I minimize over y, the
right-hand side,
it's a quadratic function in y.
It has a lower I mean, has a number,
right?
And in fact, if you do that you
immediately get the following found,
which says this.
It says that f of x minus p star is less
than or
equal to 1 over 2m times the norm of the
gradient squared I mean,
that's actually very useful as a crop as a
stopping criterion.
again, in a feel-good way.
And the reason is you don't really know m
in practice, right?
So, the actual code says, you know, if, if
the norm of the gradient
is less than 1e minus 7, right, or
something like that, it says break.
That's, that's what actually in the code.
And someone looks at that and says, what's
that all about?
And you would point to this at the
justification.
You might even put this in the comment in
the code, right?
Only minor problem is you don't know m,
right?
So that's the, so that's why I would call
this a feel-good thing, okay?
So that's the idea.
So biggest class of methods.
Not, not, not all methods but
a very big class of methods that are
called descent methods.
And we'll look at them completely
generically.
It looks like this.
It says that your new point is going to be
your current point plus a scaler
which is going to be positive, right,
times some direction vector.
And it's typically written something like
delta x.
I mean, there's, people write it other
ways, but
this, this is, it's, it's a, anyone would
understand this, right?
And it's a descent method because when you
run this method,
you all, the function value goes down,
right?
So, it says that at every step, your
function value goes down.
Now, whenever you have an iterative method
and
especially if you have one that actually
works the analysis of it
usually hinges on some quantity which is
decreasing, right?
And so, well, if you want to minimize f,
this is the most natural quantity.
It says, so you say what do you do, what
is your algorithm doing?
It's minimizing f and it has the property
that every step it takes, f gets lower.
Oh, by the way, unless you're at the
optimum point.
If you're at the optimum point, the
gradient is zero and
you break because you're done, right?
Otherwise, it produces a point that's
better.
So basically the, the stopping, the, the
algorithm has a little,
the control flow looks like if not
optimal, then produce a better point.
Better means lower function value, okay?
Okay, by the way, you might think that it
has to be this way but that's not true.
The names, there's many names for the
function that goes down, for
a function that decreases during an
algorithm.
And in fact,they have lots in you know,
actually for all algorithms usually
there's something like this.
And it doesn't have to be f.
Another function that could go down that's
used all the time is
something like the norm of the gradient
and that would do the trick, too, right?
It says that because what your trying to
do is find a quote with zero
gradient you'd say, well, this algorithm
does the following.
If the gradient is not already zero,
it produces a new point with smaller
gradients that's it, right?
That's, that's kind of the idea.
So, it doesn't have to be f.
And we'll later see algorithms for which
something like this or something more
complicated, but in the spirit, closer to
this actually goes down rather than f.
Okay.
Now oh, and this is written lots of other
notations you know,
something like this, that's, that's some
kind of like pseudo-code assignment or
something, read, you know, or something
like that.
And, or it might be written this way to
make lighter notation.
If you don't want to have ks and k plus 1s
floating around,
all over the place, x is sort of the
current point, x plus is,
you know, reasonably standard notation for
the next iterate, right?
And you just get cleaner notation.
Okay, now if, if in fact, f of x plus is
less than f, so it's a descent direction,
that says that the inner product of the
direction you stepped in,
that's delta, x and the gradient has to be
negative, okay?
So, and such a, such a direction is called
the descent direction, right?
So, here's a generic scheme.
It's a, a, a gradient descent method, it
looks like this.
You're given a starting point in the, in
the domain and
in each step, you determine a descent
direction.
Now that, we have to make,
we have to instantiate that to make this a
real algorithm.
So, this is like a prototype, right?
So it says, you find a descent direction,
we're going to see tons of ways to do
that, okay?
Then you'll line search, again, tons of
ways.
But you'll have to choose t so
that this holds up here and possibly some
more, right?
And then, you update.
And then you do this until a, a stopping
criterion is satisfied.
And, in fact, a real control flow in a
real algorithm doesn't quite look
like this, because the stopping criterion
usually involves something.
Actually, when you calculate this you
would do something like look at its norm,
and you'd, and if the norm is less than
some tolerance, you'd break.
So the control flow doesn't look exactly
like this, but
it looks close enough to this, okay?
This is, this is the idea.
Okay, so, to make, to instantiate, to make
a real algorithm out of this prototype, we
have to say, how do you compete this, how
do you compute the search direction and
then how do you compute the step size,
right?
And there's actually a couple of surprises
on each of these.
S, I will we'll get, today, there's
going to be maybe one or two surprises.
I think these are not just intuitive, that
you might not know and there, I,
there are just things that you would not
know unless you actually tried a bunch of
these things.
Okay.
This is,
there's going to be punch line here which
is one of them.
So so here's some line search types.
One is an exact line search, so it says,
hey, you know what,
you're trying to minimize f you've
specified a direction that x plus t
delta x is well, t is positive so that's a
red.
And so, what you simply do is you say,
well, along that ray, I'll choose the
minimum value of f, okay?
I mean that, that's, what you're trying to
do,
you're trying to minimize f so why would
you not do that, right?
now, by the way, that that means that you
restricted that convex function to a line,
oh, and we should probably deal with that
right away.
How do you minimize the convex function of
a single variable?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Yeah, binary search.
Yeah, that's it.
So just do bisection, that's all.
So, so, there's no issue there.
You don't have to do, you don't have to
know anything,
you just do binary search so this would be
done with binary search, for
example, okay?
Oh, I guess we call it bisection.
Okay, here's something at the other end,
it's extremely simple.
It's called backtracking line search and
it's got other names, depending on your
cultural background, right?
So it's also called an Armijo search a
Goldstein search, and, and
Armijo-Goldstein search and probably many
other things.
You'll, you'll see this line searches like
this in spirit all over the place.
And it says, it says something like this.
You take two parameters, an alpha and a
beta and, and
what you do is that the line search starts
like this, you start with,
with a step of one by the way, all of this
can be changed.
You start with the step one.
And here's what you're going to do.
This is the convex function which is
restricted to this ray.
And so, if you did an exact line search,
you would pick that t,
something like that, that would be the
exact one, okay.
And instead, what you do is this If I,
if I look at the function f of x plus t
and then, the inner product
of gradient with delta x take alpha equals
1 in this expression, that is actually,
that's, that's the affine lower bound on
the restriction function, right?
That's plotted here.
So, this is where you are.
That, that's t equals 0 right here.
So you're at t equals 0.
And then this function here, is this
thing, right?
It's that thing with alpha equals 0.
Now, that's a lower bound on your
function.
So, whatever your function is, it's above
that, okay?
By the way, that means there is no t that
would ever get you a,
a decrease as big a this, right, so that,
because it's a lower bound.
So, here's what you do, you degrade that
lower bound by a factor and
the factor is alpha.
So, if alpha is 0.5,
it says you take half that slope, and you
get something that looks like this.
Okay.
This might be for, yeah,
it could be alpha equals 0.4 or something.
I don't know what it is, right?
So, you take alpha equals 0.4, and that's
this thing, okay?
Now, this one has the following property.
That there are plenty of ts where you will
get a decrease at least
as much as this, okay?
And then that's, the algorithm says, you
start at t zero, t, t, whatever one.
It could be anything you like.
And then, you simply multiply by beta
until this inequality holds.
And I think that's called maybe the Armijo
condition or I guess if,
if you're in Moscow, it's the Goldstein
condition or something like that, right?
So, that, that, that's the idea.
That's, now, when you look at this so
here's going to be the first surprise.
Here it is.
When you look at this you would say,
whoa, the exact line search has got to be
way better, right?
I mean it just, because a typical
parameter value for beta is a half, right?
So, the only step lengths you ever take
are half, one, half, quarter, eighth.
I mean this looks very crude.
By the way, alpha can be all sorts of
weird things.
Here's a very common value of alpha,
unbelievable 0.01.
So, that basically says, if I get, if the
minute I get 1%
of the decrease predicted by the linear
extrapolation, I'll take it, okay?
I mean this sounds you're not coming close
to doing a, an exact line search, and
the exact one, I mean the picture, all
your intuitions suggests and
exact line search would work way better.
Guess what?
That's false.
It, it doesn't work actually any better.
I mean, it does for silly little problems
in like three dimensions or five or
15 or something, right?
But for any real problem, it turns out it,
in fact, quite often
the backtracking search works not just
just as well, but actually often better.
Now that's bizarre and there's no way, I
actually don't even
really have any particular intuition to
explain that but it's true.
Okay, so here's gradient descent method,
there's a fully inst,
here's our first fully instantiated
method, method.
oh, and I might add it's due to Newton
without the backtracking.
But anyway, so, here it is.
It says what you do, where, so
the search direction will simply be
negative gradient, right?
And by the way, what could be more
natural.
By the way, we're going to find out it's
not natural at all.
But then this, this is just to set it up,
right?
So, what could be more natural?
You're at x and you say I would now like
to
choose a direction where the function gets
smaller, right?
So you take the gradient, that's the local
information.
And the negative gradient direction is
actually the direction where
the function is going down the fastest.
So you, I mean, why would you not do this?
It would be hard to imagine not doing
this, okay?
So, let's just start with doing this
because it's,
it's kind of the most basic algorithm and
so on.
So, here it is.
We choose the gradient, negative gradient
direction, and here it is.
So we evaluate the negative gradient
direction.
the, the real algorithm might have it
would test the gradient here and
it's a gradient where less than the
[UNKNOWN] should break, okay?
Then, do a line search.
You could do exact line search,
backtracking is fine.
And then, you update.
And so, this works.
I mean that's, that's the idea.
I mean it's not hard.
It is actually quite easy to show it
works.
And you could read to the book.
And you can show various things.
Like here, you could show that, for
example, the objective value converges,
you know, exponentially or,
you know, towards the to, to to p star,
something like that.
Now, now, to that c is like basically
0.9999999 or something like that.
But, that's another story, okay?
alright.
now, here comes the first surprise.
I mean, actually this is used because it's
extremely simple, right?
And, you know, for some problems, you will
soon know why it works on some problems.
But on others, it's completely useless.
It doesn't work at all.
Well, of course, in theory, it works.
But since in practice, you're not
interested in doing ten to the nine
iterations it, it doesn't, it work in
practice, okay?
I mean, in theory, it always works, okay?
You will soon know exactly why it doesn't
work but
this is the first, I mean, I think this is
the first thing that's not obvious, right?
because the gradient is, if you just,
if you didn't know monotomization, someone
said what [UNKNOWN] streets and
please make up an algorithm for it, you'd
make this up.
This is the I hope you would make this up,
right?
because it's the most obvious thing to do,
You said, please make me an algorithm, you
can use local information, you know,
wherever you are.
I'lI, I'll tell you things like gradient
and whatever.
You, this is the, I hope this is the
algorithm you'd come up with.
And the weird part is, it doesn't work
that well in, in a lot of cases.
You'll soon see why, okay?
Okay.
So, let's examine it Let's take a, a
quadratic problem, looks like this.
This is just an R2 just to understand.
So here we have parameter here, a gamma
and
we can make as we make gamma big, what
happens is
we're changing the condition number of
the, of the quadratic form here, right?
This is x tranpose px, I can change the
condition number to gamma, right?
because this is diag, the matrix diag 1
gamma.
And if I make gamma huge or small, the
condition number gets really big, right?
And so, what does that mean geometrically?
It means that the sublevel sets, if gamma
is 1, the sublevel sets are round.
Oh, yeah.
Please, let's discuss that.
How does the gradient method work if the,
if gamma is 1?
I mean, you can work out the exact
formulas but who cares.
Just tell me what, what happens then?
Here, here are the sublevel sets, right,
like that.
Here are you, which way is the gradient
pointing?
It's pointing straight uphill.
And then negative gradient is pointing
straight towards the solution, okay?
So, you know, gradient method works
superbly when gamma is 1, right?
Because, in fact, the gradient points you
directly to the solution, okay?
And then, you know, so what if you're
doing a backtracking line search, right?
You, you make up, if you, you'll cover a
distance of factor two each time, and
you're going to get very fast convergence.
Everybody see this?
Now, if you'll look at what happens here,
this is a,
this is condition, this is condition
number 10, actually,
which is really square root of 10 in terms
of the, the, the semi axis ratios.
But, so here, look what happens These are,
they, they are now ellipsoids, right.
And what happens is the gradient, of
course,
is the normal to the level curve pointing
uphill.
So a negative gradient is the normal to
the level curve pointing downhill.
And so, you can see what happened is that
is the direction of
the negative gradient, okay?
Now, is it pointing directly?
I mean, is that pointing generally in the
right direction?
Yes it is, right?
It's point, it's pointed more towards zero
than away from zero, okay?
But it's not pointed the right direction,
right?
And so what happens is you go over here,
then here, and this is because for
exact line search, you get exactly the
same thing for backtracking lines.
For exact line search, you can just work
out what the iterates are, right?
And so, you get this kind of thing.
And this actually has a name and I forgot
what it was but it doesn't matter.
So somebody's name is attached to this
zigzagging, okay?
Now this picture makes it completely
clear.
If I made gamma, that, that was 10, what
if I made it 10,000, what would happen?
I mean, you can see exactly what would
happen, right?
The iterates would just go like this,
right?
And they'd make very slow progress towards
zero but that's what would happen.
By the way, what happens if I make gamma
really small?
Yeah, and this thing just rotates 90
degrees and this, and
so actually, this is your first hint.
Your first hint of what's going on, is
that the condition number,
right of the sublevel sets is going to
play a role if you look at something like
a gradient method, right?
That's, that's, that's the, that's the
hint, right?
So, a gradient method works beautifully
when, and condition number of sublevel
sets is basically how anisotropic, the
function is, right?
Isotropic means it's going the same in all
directions, you know, it means that these,
the level sets are kind of a roundish,
right?
Anisotropic means they're weird and have a
big condition number, right?
They, they, it's very different going in
one direction from another, right?
So, if the sublevel sets, if the function
is kind of a well-conditioned, right,
then what happens is gradient method works
really well.
because for one thing,
the negative gradient points you towards a
solution, right?
If, if it's not if, if, if you have a big
condition number, the gradient
method points you some, somewhere that's
vaguely in the right direction but
you made, you might be making an angle of
like you know,
89.9 degrees or something like that
towards the right direction.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
Okay, so, that's, and this is why it
doesn't work.
By the way, if you're really lucky and
the function you want to minimize has
reasonable condition number,
then gradient methods going to work great
for you.
And that's great, your code will be 4
lines or
whatever, and something like that, and
everything will be fine, okay?
Okay.
So
let's look at a nonquadratic example and
see how this works.
So here's one where in, sublevels levels
that are not sphere, I mean they're
certainly not ellipsoidal, right, they're
not spherical or anything like that.
But, you know, roughly you still have the
same idea.
Here, the sublevel sets are, they're not
round, right?
I mean, they're a bit wider than they are
tall.
I mean, not even by much, right?
I mean, that's the hilarious part.
And you can see you get kind of the same
phenomenon.
This actually looks like it works pretty
well.
By the way, this is an example of an exact
line search beating a backtracking line
search but this is an R2.
R2 is really not even, it doesn't even
count as a legitimate problem.
So, okay, so this is the idea.
Now, that brings us so here would be like
a, a measure of what f looks like.
There's a problem in R100, right?
And here, I mean, you can see all the
various things here.
Oh, by the way, this is a funny one,
right?
So here you are minimizing this, that's a
real problem, okay, that's a problem in
R100 and you're minimizing a log barrier
plus a linear function.
And, by the way, what's kind of clueless
here,
look, look at all of this, I mean, it
hardly matters but
it basically says, doing the cruder line
search, you're doing better for a while.
I mean, it's, this doesn't matter but it,
this is just not obvious, right?
You might imagine that this run two
different paths and things like this.
By the way, this is called a sort of
linear convergence
that's standard notation.
And it means that, it actually means
exponential convergence, right?
Because these iterations on a linear scale
and
that's some kind of error, in this case,
sub-optimality on a log scale, right?
So, linear means, and the slope, of
course, gives you the, the factor, right?
It says, so, it says something like this,
each iteration, you reduce your error by a
factor of 0.9, you know, or
we could work out what it is here, I'm not
going to do it but that's the idea, okay?
So, that's linear convergence.
Now, so let's now talk about this idea of
gradient because you think,
now you think and you realize, wow,
the gradient had to do with, I don't the,
what's wrong with the gradient method?
And the answer is something like if the
function is has, has if,
if, if it's, if it is anisotropic or if
the, if the sublevel
sets are not well-conditioned is when
gradient works badly.
And this kind of hints that you can come
up with something that's the spirit of
gradient method but then actually adapts
for the geometry or, you know,
the work, that has a different geometry,
right?
And it turns out that's correct.
So, here's what you do, it turns out when
you ask,
if you ask the very simple question, if
you're sitting at the point x and
you say what's the fastest way down hill,
you ask someone for directions, right?
And they point.
You would think, there's really only one
way they can [INAUDIBLE] and
they can get the gradient.
That's reasonable, right?
It's actually wrong.
because it turns out there's actually a,
a cultural bias when you ask which is the
fast, the fast way, and the re,
it's not a cultural bias, what it is, is
this kind of bias.
It depends on the metric you're using.
If you change the metric and ask someone
what's the fastest way downhill,
you get a different answer, okay?
It's weird but it's true.
You'd think, what's wrong with minus
partial f, partial xi.
I mean, that, how can that not be.
That is the, that will be,
in fact, the fastest way downhill if
you're using a Euclidian norm.
If you're using [UNKNOWN] norm or weighted
norm or
some other weird norm, that's not the
fastest way downhill.
So that's the topic we're going to look
at.
It's actually interesting.
And it's important to understand that the
gradient, well,
I guess if you know about physics and
things like that.
The gradient, it, it changes when you
change coordinates, right?
So, okay.
So, let's see how that works.
So, let's take any norm.
Not necessarily that Euclidian norm.
And then, what we are going to do is we
are going to say that the steepest descent
direction is this.
You say, find me a direction of norm 1,
and that's where the norm comes in
because that's how you are normalizing
that minimizes this thing that is,
that is your linear approximated decreased
in f, okay?
Now, if this were the two norm, why the
answer would be the gradient scale, right?
Because it's scaled to have norm 1.
It would be the gradient divided by the
norm of the gradient.
That's what it would be.
And that, but what's weird then, is if you
walk up to someone using a different
metric, and you say, please tell me what
the fastest way downhill, if they're
using a different metric, they'll point in
the different direction, right?
And the reason is that it has to do with
efficiency, right?
If if a narrow metric distance is this way
are, are,
are long I don't know, they might point
you there.
Because according to their, by their idea
of efficiency or you know, or how
steep the descent is, that's better than
simply following the negative gradient.
Okay.
So this is,
this is the normalized steepest descent
because the thing has norm 1.
And then often it is unnormalized.
And it's unnormalized by multiplying this
which has norm
1 by the duel norm of the gradient itself.
And what that does is it makes sure that
the inner product of the gradient and
the normalized steep the, the norm the
unnormalized steepest descent direction
is minus the norm of the gradient squared
with the dual norm, right?
And that makes, that, that actually makes
everything work with things like the two
norm, and this would agree with the two
norm and things like that.
So, steepest descent method is basically
general descent method.
You choose the steepest descent.
And it, the, it's, it's just like gradient
descent.
It, basically for the summaries, it works.
Okay.
But what's very interesting now, is this
really a family of methods because for
every norm, you get a different method.
And you get some interesting ones.
So let's look at a couple.
If you get the Euclidean norm, it's, it's
identical to the gradient descent method.
But supposed you use a quadratic norm and
it's going to be extremely important so
we're going to get to this.
If you use a quadratic norm, so x
transposed Px to the 1 half, right?
Then it turns out that what you use is the
negative gradient but
then multiplied by P inverse.
Okay, now that's positive definite matrix.
It doesn't rotate things more than 90
degrees so it's a descent direction but
it's, it's different, right?
It, it's minus P inverse so we're
going to, we're going to get to that.
I'll come back to that in a minute.
But actually I'll, I'll say another very
cool thing about it.
If you're going to use the steepest
descent with a quadratic norm,
with norm P, it's completely equivalent to
doing the following.
Take the original problem and change
coordinates by P minus 1 half.
If you change coordinates by P minus 1
half, then this P norm actually becomes in
the new coordinates, the norm, and it's
steepest descent.
So what that says is, sorry, it's gradient
descent.
It says that steepest descent with a
quadratic norm associated with
P is identical to the following.
It's, it's exactly the same as doing the
following.
Take your original problem, change
coordinates to make
this metric i and then applying gradient
descent.
So it, so in other words, it's,
it's not much different, it just says
change coordinates, okay?
We'll come back to that in a minute
because that tells you exactly how you
want to choose the change of coordinates,
right?
So okay and okay, let's look at another
one just for fun.
We will take the l1 norm, you'd say,
what's the steepest descent direction.
And it turns out,
you can always choose the steepest descent
direction to be a single, an ei.
So it's something like that, and in fact,
so it's a, it's a var, it's an algorithm
also invented in every field periodically
every 10, 15 years or something.
It has a name in every field.
You know, sometimes like, I don't know if
they do it in blocks,
it's like I don't know, scaler, something
descent.
I don't know, but block descent.
So it does this, it says, you,
you will only update one variable, xi, one
coordinate at a time.
And so, what you do is you, you get the
gradient.
You look at the components of the
gradient, you find out which is largest.
And then, you go in the appropriate
direction.
Either you increase or decrease depending
on
whether the sign of the partial derivative
is positive or negative.
Everybody got it?
And so, and that work, that's just
steepest descent in the l1 norm, okay?
And the picture would look something like
this.
So here's, that would be the negative
gradient.
But here, if, if I have, if, if I use
steepest descent with a P norm, and that's
the ellipsoid, it gets, it says you're not
actually going in this direction.
What you're really doing is you're solving
sort of a linear program.
You're saying, please go as far as you can
in that direction staying in here.
And the solution is here.
And you can see that in fact you're going
in a different direction, right?
Now, the direction is never more than 90
degrees away.
It, it's not even 90 degrees away, right?
It's a positive definite matrix so it's,
but, so the idea is that if
you do steepest descent with a quadratic
norm, P, it says that actually, you,
you have distorted space and it bends the
gradient descent method.
It will bend it to another direction,
okay?
So, I'm saying all these things you don't
have to,
I mean, these don't even have like perfect
meanings, right?
So I'm just talking about this at the idea
level because we're going to get to
something and it's going to be kind a,
kind of obvious.
So let me ask you the following.
You can change, you can choose P for
our problem, how roughly do you think you
should choose it?
I mean, two ways to think of it, right?
One way to think of it is you should
choose P so
the ellipsoid P kind of matches the shape
and dimension of the sublevel sets.
Now the sublevel sets are not ellipsoids
unless the problem is quadratic,
in which case, you can minimize it by
solving linear equations.
And then, I'm so, but just roughly, you
would choose it so
the ellipsoid defined by P kind of has the
same shape and stuff like that.
Alternatively, you would choose P so that
the P to the minus 1 half multiply,
if you transform by the P to the minus 1
half,
the sublevel sets of the function become
round to the extent possible, right?
Now, they're not going to be lipsodes, so
they're not going to become spheres,
right?
But, you kind of, and in fact some people
even refer to that as rounding.
So this tells you about how this,
now you have the intuition about how you
should choose P.
So let's look at an example.
it's, it's a silly example in R2.
But it actually shows what happens.
okay, so here it is.
Here's, here's this nonlinear function.
You know, these sublevels as a
non-ellipsoids, but
roughly speaking, you know, this sublevel
sets here are wider than they are tall.
By the, by the way, not even by a big
factor, okay?
And here, if you choose the,
this, this would be a good choice of P,
right?
P here, a good choice of P would be to
have these ellipsoids kind of
aligned with the sublevel sets of the
function.
In which case, I mean,
you could just sort of visually see that
it's doing well, right?
Here's a case.
That's a bad choice.
That was worse than P equals i, right,
because it doesn't get the right way.
Now another way to think of it is the
following.
When you're choosing p to have the
ellipsoid like that,
that's the same as scrunching space this
way, right?
because that, that's what it means.
It says that, if you're, if you believe
that if this, if you believe sort of
like that distance is the same as that
distance, if that's your view of things,
then the correct way to think of that is
to take this image and scrunch it.
That's, by the way, transform by P minus 1
half, okay, that's rounding it, right?
And if you round these things, you will
see they get more spherical, right?
Less condition number.
Less condition number means gradient is
going to work well, okay?
So here, basically it says if, if this is
your opinion,
if that's the metric you are using, then
what this says is if that is the metric
you're using it says that basically what
you should do is take those images and
crush them like this by a factor of two.
And what's, they're going to get more
elongated.
And gradients going to work much worse.
Everybody following this?
So, I mean this all, okay, fine.
Okay.
So, what this says is,
choice of metric has a very strong effect
on the speed of convergence, right?
So if you're doing some prob, if you're
have some problem and
the condition number is, you know, fine,
go ahead and use gradient.
But, otherwise, the choice of the metric,
actually what says is,
if you do an affine change of coordinates
of your problem,
then it has a first-order effect on
gradient.
In other words,
it can make it go from working well to
terrible, that usually, it does that.
Of course, if you're really good about
your choice,
it can go from terrible to good.
But if it's, if you're not good,
it goes usually from good or okay to
terrible, okay?
And this brings us to your suggestion,
which was let's adapt.
Let's do steepest descent but let's
actually change the metric every time.
And it'll always be based on our best
guess of actually the curve,
kind of the curvature of the function.
By the way, there's lots of ways to do
curvature, this is only one of them.
Other ways are much more sophisticated
this, but this is one.
So here it is.
It's just this.
What we're going to do is, we're going to
have, the Newton step is going to be
negative gradient, then multiply by the
inverse of the Hessian, right?
And you can see this makes total sense.
This says, if, if you're minimizing a
function, you're at a point x, and
someone says, what do the sublevel sets
look like?
The answer is, you know, I don't know what
the sublevel set is,
of course, I don't know.
Because all I, in fact, all I have is
gradient and Hessian oracle.
The only thing I'm allowed to do is call
two methods,
three, maybe one because there are three
things.
I quarry the function at a cost and I get
the function value to gradient and
Hessian, that's it I don't know anything
else, right?
I mean, I may have some other information
but that's not that [UNKNOWN].
So, if I do that you don't know but
it's actually a very good guess if you
knew the solution is the Hessian.
Hessian tells everything because near the
solution, all convex,
smooth convex functions, near the minimum,
they all look quadratic.
And the sublevel sets are exactly given by
the Hessian.
So, that seems like a good choice and
that's exactly what the Newton step does.
Okay.
So, a lot of other ways to interpret it.
Here's one.
One says, well, let's take,
let's take the function, let's form f hat
at the current point.
And f hat is going to be the second-order
approximation.
So that's the first-order approximation
and that's the,
that's the second term of the Taylor
series.
And then, it says I'll take this
second-order approximation and
it's a convex quadratic.
I'll minimize it.
And you know what you get?
The Hessian, the Newton step, that's the
Newton step.
Another way, is to say, I would like, I
would like to find a v so
that the gradient of f of x plus v, v is
the step, I want that to be 0.
But I don't know what the grade, I don't
how the gradient changes, right?
Oh, if the gradient were affine, I would
know exactly how to calculate v, but
that's the case if the function being
quadratic,
which means I can solve it in one, just by
solving linear equations.
So I don't know.
So what I'm going to do is this, I'll say
well what,
what is a good approximation of what the
gradient is when you step v?
The answer, it's very simple.
It's the current gradient plus the
derivative of the gradient,
that's the second derivative which is the
Hessian, multiplied by the step you take.
And so, this,
that is the first-order of approximation
of what the gradient will be at x plus v.
And so, you don't know what the gradient
is at x plus v but you want it to be zero.
So, but what you have is this
approximation.
So, you set the approximation equal to
zero.
Here, solve, you get the Newton step,
okay?
So, so here are, here are the two
pictures.
They're different but they both suggest
some very interesting things.
Here's a function f, just in one
dimension, I'm minimizing, so here I am.
And Newton's method does the following.
It fits f hat, which is the quadratic
approximation.
By the way, f hat does not have to be
above f.
It could go below it as well, or, I mean,
it can, it doesn't have to be above.
In this example it is, but okay.
So, and then, you take the minimizer there
and then that's your,
that's the Newton step, okay?
here, this is the derivative of that
function and what it says is you're here
and what you want is you want to find the
crossing of f prime with 0,
because that's what, f prime is the
gradient you want,
f you want the gradient to be equal to 0,
so you want the crossing.
You're here, and it says, please find me a
point.
Fig, get me a point where you have the
zero crossing.
And the answer is you take, you do a
linear extrapolation.
This slope is exactly the second
derivative, right?
So, so that would give you this point,
okay?
And now I'm going to ask you.
This is just geometrically, I don't
want to hear anything else,
just geometric intuition.
[SOUND] If you repeat,
what is going to happen on the next step
of Newton's method?
We can talk about it on the left or on the
right.
Let's start with the left.
What happens on the next Newton's step?
You start from here.
You have moved closer to the minimum and
the next step is going,
you're going to form a new quadratic model
but now around here.
When I form a quadratic model around
there,
it's going to be way better than this one,
right?
And so, the next step is going to be very
good.
By the way, when you get near the bottom,
how good is the quadratic approximation?
Very, very good.
>> [LAUGH]
>> Right?
Because that's, that's,
that's informal speech for it, it, it's at
least quadratic good, right?
Okay, right?
So, and
what happens here, what happens on the
next step here?
On the next step here, when you want to,
you're,
you're next estimate of the zero crossing
is going to be excellent.
Why?
Because, when you have a smooth function
that's going to cross zero, right, and
you're near, you're near where it crosses
0, the linear approximation is excellent.
And therefore, your next estimate will be
good and
then the one after that is going to be
like stunningly good, okay?
All, but all of this is just sort of,
it's very important to have the geometric
intuition, right?
So what this suggests is this, if we are,
if we do this thing where we update the
metric or however you want to call it,
if you do something like a Newton step,
this is going to work.
you're, we're going to see something very
shocking happening at the end.
We're going to get to that.
Oh, by the way, here's a very, here's a
perfectly interesting method.
It goes like this.
You evaluate the grade, the Hessian at the
first point, just once, right?
You calculate well, you calculate, you
know, now, you calculate, you do
a Cholesky factorization of, of the grade,
of the Hessian, of f at x zero, period.
And then, you simply change coordinates
once, and
do gradient descent in that new thing.
That'll work.
That actually, if your initial point is
okay, that'll work incredibly well.
But this is adapting it every step.
Oh, and there's all sorts of other cool
things like you
can adapt at every ten steps.
You can update it.
You can update it every 30.
There's all sorts of things.
Another interpretation is this,
the the Newton step is simply steepest
decent in the local Hessian norm, right?
So, what you do is you have a a norm
induced by the Hessian and
you take, you take the steepest descent in
that metric, right?
So, and that's what, that's what you get,
okay?
So, alright.
So one of the things you get is that, I
will explain where this is all headed,
and some very interesting attributes of it
but, so this, this is lambda of x, right?
That's called a Newton decrement.
And here's what it is.
It, it is, I mean, it has lots of
interpretations.
But it's a measure of the proximity of x
to x star, right, to the optimal point.
And, what it says, it's a, it's a,
it's a very good estimate of, of f of x
minus b star, right?
Assuming you're close.
If you're close, this is basically, it
says, you've formed the quadratic thing,
and you ask yourself, how much is the
quadratic going to go down?
The answer is exactly lambda squared over
2, okay?
So that's what, so lambda squared over 2
is, is very small.
I mean, that may or may not predict the
actual function going down, but
to the extent that it does, it's,
it's a very good estimate of how far off
you are, right?
So, in fact, stopping criterion based on
lambda are actually,
way better than stop, than based on the
gradient, right?
If you remember the gradient, the relation
between the norm of the gradient, and
how sub-optimally you were, involved that
1 over m, which you don't know, right?
So this one actually gives you a number
that you can trust, right?
And it's not a feel-good thing, right?
Well, this one is because it depends on
third derivative,
we're going to get to talk about that,
too, okay?
So, but it's way better than just the norm
of the gradient is small.
Okay, now it's got all sorts of
interpretations It is the norm of
the Newton's step in the quadratic Hessian
norm.
So that's another way to say it.
And it's the directional derivative so if
you remember,
in the Armijo line search to Goldstein
line search there's that slope.
Which says, how fast are you going down?
And the answer is, it's minus lambda
squared, right?
Which once again tells you if lambda
squared over two is tiny, it says in your
line search, you're not going to, it's not
going to go down much, right?
So that, that tells you that.
Okay, now, this is very important, is the
following.
This measure of proximity of x to x star
is affine invariant, okay?
Affine invariant means if I take my
problem and
if I change coordinates with an affine
transformation and
the simplest one that does the trick is
you scale the variables.
That's all, you just scale the variables.
Instead of x2, you use 50x2, instead of
x7, you use 1e minus 6 times x7.
Okay, that's scaling the variables, right?
Okay, now that, that's an affine
transformation.
The steepest des, the gradient descent
method
does not commute with affine changes
agreed, it's not affine invariant.
Affine invariant means that some operation
or
algorithm is invariant, under, you get a
commutative diagram.
You change coordinates, run, you change
coordinates, run the algorithm or
you run the algorithm and change
coordinates, you get the same thing.
That's false for gradient descent, okay?
And we already knew that.
because in gradient descent, if I change
the coordinates, it's going to,
it's, it's going to absolutely, completely
change the geometry of your set.
And if I change them in a benevolent way,
I can make the convergence faster.
If I change them in a not benevolent way,
I will bring your gradient descent method
to a halt.
Not a halt.
But I'll make it so slow that, for
practical purposes, it's useless.
Everybody got this?
By the way, among changes of coordinates,
there's a lot more bad ones than good
ones.
Just so you know.
So, right?
Everybody got this?
Okay, so this measure is actually affine
invariant and that's very simple to see.
By the way, the Newton step is affine
invariant.
The Newton algorithm is entirely affine
Why?
Because if you change coordinates by t,
the gradient transforms like
t times the gradient or something like
that or t transposed.
And then, then the Hessian undoes that,
because that transform just
like t Hessian t transpose, when the smoke
clears the ts are gone.
There's one t left and you get a
commutative diagram.
Okay, so Newton method is actually
invariant under scaling, right?
Gradient method is very much not invariant
under gradient under,
under, under affine transformation, okay?
And this stopping criterion here if you
base it on lambda,
invariant under changes of coordinates,
which is actually very cool, right?
because the other one will ruin, I can, I
can break any algorithm that has, or any,
if I grep through the code and find, if
norm of something is less than this,
I can break that code so easy it's not
funny.
All I have to do is take, I, all I do is I
take your problems for
it to worthing, working.
I scale the variables in some way.
And you'll either stop on the first step
or you'll never stop or
something like that.
And I can break it super fast.
You cannot do that with a Newton method,
alright?
So, okay, here's Newton's method.
It works like this.
You compute the Newton step and the
decrement.
So, you compute this and that.
And, the real stopping criterion would be
right here.
If lambda squared of 2 is less than the
tolerance, break,
that would be the real the real control
flow would look like that.
okay, sorry, our algorithm here says that
[UNKNOWN].
then, either line search and you could
just use it by backtracking, that's fine.
And then, you do an update.
And so, this algorithm is ab, is affine
invariant, right?
So another way to say this is that this
scaling doesn't matter.
Well, it matters, but it's a second-order
issue and
it matters only to the extent that your
Linear Algebra will be stressed.
But certainly you can handle things like
condition numbers of, you know,
10 to the 5 with no problem, right?
Whereas, a condition number of a 100 will
bring a gradient method to a halt for
practical purposes, right?
So, so, and then there's just a huge gap
in, in how much scaling you can do.
So, okay, it means something like the
difference between fixed-point numbers and
floating-point numbers, right?
I mean, that's, that's the, the,
qualitatively, I mean,
I don't want to push that too far but it's
something like that, right?
That, you know, if you're writing a
fixed-point algorithm, boy, you have to
be careful not to overflow and underflow
and all that kind of stuff, right?
If you're writing something with, with,
with floats, yeah, you know,
I mean it can actually tolerate some
pretty big ranges.
Now you can still overflow and underflow
and
have to write a terrible algorithm but
it's a whole lot harder than for,
if you're doing something with floats than
with some fixed-point numbers.
It's way easier to be in trouble.
Fixed-point, a fixed-point algorithm can
work perfectly provided you've
had incredibly care to set everything up
and scale everything correctly.
But you're using floats, yeah, you've got
much more leeway.
So, I mean, this is just very rough and
I don't want to push it too much, but it's
something like that.
Okay, what we're going to look at now is
the classical convergence analysis,
this is due to Kanterovich and, that's of
Newton's method.
And, so we'll, we'll look at this and
actually before we start, here's what I'd
like to ask you.
So, some questions.
How well, my first question is this,
how well does Newton's method work for
quadratic functions?
Perfectly.
It's one step, right, because, and here's
an abstraction of Newton's method.
You call the method,
get quadratic approximation at a point,
you, you get the quadratic approximation.
It's actually the function.
You don't know it, right?
And then it says, okay, I'm going to
minimize the quadratic approximation, and
here's my next x.
It's actually the minimizer.
So the answer is quadratic, one step,
okay?
So, now if a function now what if the
Hessian is changing slowly?
Or suppose, suppose in fact,
the Hessian doesn't change very much as
you move x around.
It's now a quadratic function but it's
changing very slowly.
That suggests Newton's method is going to
work unbelievable, that's the kind of
function Newton's method will just work
unbelievably well on.
By the way, it comes back to your
suggestion which is
the Hessian is actually a heuristic for
ex, for,
for saying I'd like to change coordinates
to get the sublevels set,
you don't have the sublevels set and use
the Hessian as an appoximation, right?
So, the current local Hessian.
And so if the Hessian doesn't change much,
right, as you move around in space,
that's where Newton's method is going to
nail it.
And the extreme, is the Hessian doesn't
change at all,
that's called a quadratic function one
step, okay?
So, this is just intuition that suggests
the following, how fast the Hessian
changes is what's going to determine
whether Newton's method works well or not.
And so sure enough, guess what comes up?
What comes up is exactly the Lipschitz
constants on,
a Lipschitz constants on the second
derivative.
By the way, if you like, we can talk,
you can talk about the third derivative,
right?
Because L is something like the maximum of
the third derivative, okay?
And there are people who work this out in
terms of f d cubed f, okay?
Now, we're not going to do that but
just to understand what L means, L is a
bound on the third derivative.
Now, the reason, I'll tell you why we're
not going to do it,
because the third derivative of a function
of [UNKNOWN]
function in Rn is actually a third-order
tensor, right?
And, so, unless you're trained in this,
maybe in mechanical engineering or
something like that, or physics it can
cause severe headaches to consider.
so, I don't recommend, it's a trilinear
form.
And, so, you know, the fact is, that you
know, Linear Algebra, you know,
you take all these classes on statistics,
probability, mechanical engineering.
I don't know.
And a lot of matrices come up so
we all have very well developed ideas
about matrices and things like that.
And third-order tensors are only a very
small number of us are cool with, right?
And the rest of us just get a headache.
So I'm just, I'm just saying, that's why
were going to use Lipschitz condition.
But you should understand what l is.
It's the third derivative, that's what it
is.
By the way, that model goes back to why
Newton works well.
If the third derivative is small, that
tells you Newton works well, why?
Here's one explanation, Newton method says
this, call the following method,
get quadratic approximation.
If I get a quadratic approximation, what's
the next term I'm missing?
The cubic, the third derivative.
So, if the third derivative, derivative is
small, I mean as though I'm
waving my hands, but the third derivative
is small, you know what it means?
It means that second derivative
approximation was pretty good, okay?
So, again, so all of this is me, I mean,
this is totally obvious,
there's nothing hidden here, there's
nothing deep here, it just says,
we expect Newton's method to work well,
when, the third derivative is small.
That's one way to say it.
There's another way.
The second derivative has a small
Lipschitz constant, okay?
That's all.
There's nothing, that's obvious.
Okay, so back to the analysis which is due
to Kanterovich.
Okay.
So,
it says, this has a it has a Lipschitz
constant L and
then, it basically, the analysis [UNKNOWN]
basically breaks into two portions, right?
So I'll, I'll say what [UNKNOWN] sometimes
it's called a damped and undamped phase.
And I'll explain what it is.
So I'll, I'll say what uuu, sometimes it's
called a damped and undamped phase.
And I'll explain what it is.
It says the following.
There's, there's a constant eta.
And if the gradient exceeds eta, then
here's what you can guarantee.
The Newton step with backtracking, right,
will go down by a fixed number, gamma.
At least maybe more, okay?
So that's, that's, that's what that's
called some people call that the undamped
phase of Newton's method.
Then there's this.
Once the gradient gets smaller than a
number,
which it must because you can't execute
this step too many times, right?
In fact, if it goes down by gamma each
step,
then it can't, you really can't execute
that more than whatever it is.
You know, f of x0 minus f star divided by
gamma steps.
You can't do any more than that, right?
So after finding the number of steps, the
gradient norm will be less than eta.
And at that point, the following occurs.
The norm of the gradient at the next step,
actually another thing happens.
In backtracking line search, you will take
a step of one, okay?
You'll take a step of one in Newton
method.
You will not backtrack, number one.
And number two, the gradient at the next
step will be less than,
ignore the constant in front.
But, will be less than the norm of the
gradient at the previous step,
at the current step squared, okay?
Now when this is less than one, that's a
very good, that basically says, it,
I mean, so, now very roughly, it says that
when you get into, so
this is called this is lots of names.
One is it's the undamped face, it's the
region of quadratic convergence.
We'll see why in a minute.
But what it says is very interesting It
says, I mean, and roughly speaking,
it says, when you get into that second
phase, every time you do Newton's step,
the number of significant figures is very
rough doubles, okay?
You do a Newton step, it's now 1e minus 4.
Then it's 1e minus 8 then it's all over on
the next step, okay?
Everybody got this?
By the way, this fits our intuition
perfectly about, you know,
you just go back and look at these
pictures, right?
I mean, over here, that fits this stuff
really well, right?
Once you're down near the minimum here,
the quadratic approximation is superb,
right?
When you are near the crossing point,
if you zoom in on it, all you see is a
straight line, like this, right?
I mean, it got a small curvature.
But this method, this method of following
the tangent, is going to get you from
a good point to a superb point to like a
really superb point, that,
so it's all kind of make sense that's how
this works, right?
I mean, I think this, this kind of the
intuition is, is, is clear.
Okay.
So in a damped Newton phase
most iterations are going to require
backtracking, right?
The idea is, I already said this,
the function value decreases by at least
this value of gamma.
And this can only go that number of
iterations, right?
So in the quadratically convergent phase,
that's once,
once the gradient gets small enough no
damping whatsoever, and
what'll happen is, this will converge at
the zero quadratically.
Quadratically means on a log plot,
on a semi-log plot you'll actually get a
quadratic.
So the idea is that the number of
iterations is less than
something dependent on how sub-optimal the
first one is, right?
And then the second term is log log
epsilon 0 over epsilon, right?
So, so why?
Because, if you are doing quadratic
convergence and
you invert what that mean, it's log-log,
right?
So okay, so now this second term, it's
small, you know, it's on the order of six.
And in fact, for a long time, I used to go
around and
give talks, and I would write five for log
log epsilon zero over epsilon.
And I did it just to bait people who were
complexity theorists.
Anyway, so this analysis, this is the
classical analysis of the Newton method.
And, but now, I'm going to, I want to say
something bad things about,
the good news is, it's a feel-good thing.
It says, it always works and it says,
eventually the, the convergence is like
super fast and all that kind of stuff.
And, you know, this is what exam, this,
this is correct.
I mean, it work something like this.
And you get a lot of insight, like they
did to these two phases and
all that kind of stuff.
It's good.
Now, I do want to make fun of it though.
Because this is your classical, I was
going to say your classical western
analysis but unfortunately, this came from
Moscow, so I can't say that.
But it is kind of like your classical
western analysis of
an algorithm goes like this.
It says, if and if you have a whole lot of
hypothesis, halt, then,
and then you have a conclusion.
Now, if you look at the whole lot of
hypothesis,
not one of them is actually verifiable in
practice.
Not one, you'd be like the, you have a
Lipschitz constant.
You have a strong convexity constant.
You have all sorts of crap there.
Not one of, there would be almost no
circumstances where you know them, right?
Except if the function is quadratic but
then it's stupid because how do you
minimize a quadratic if you solve linear
equations.
Everybody see what I'm saying here?
Okay.
Then you look at the conclusions and the
conclusions would be kind of goofy.
They would say things like if, if the the
conclusion would be something like,
you know, a limit point of this algorithm
is optimal.
But yet that's not how you know, you
don't, that's, you know,
Java doesn't have limit points,
accumulation points, right?
I mean, you have a maximum number of
iterers, and that's it, okay?
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So, that's the classic one.
And then you point out that in fact that
theorem, which someone then spends like
two lectures proving, you know, when
everyone's sleeping.
Then you point out, it's actually totally
useless.
And they say, no, no, you don't
understand.
You don't get it.
This is kind of to make you feel good,
kind of,
so that this is, then we run the code,
and, you know, and
then, and then this is the conceptual
framework and base.
But anyway.
Okay.Every got this?
And let me point out here, something here.
Suppose you want to run Newton's method to
find out,
I give you a function like one of these
logs, some [UNKNOWN] or
a barrier and I want to find out, how many
steps is it going to take?
Give me an upper bound on the number of
steps Newton's method's going to take?
And they go, hey, no problem.
We've got this theory.
Look.
Now look, now they look down here and
they say, right there.
There's your number.
Now, number one, epsilon zero,
you don't know it because it depends on
all sorts of crap you don't know.
You don't know m.
You don't l.
Okay?
So, you don't know epsilon zero.
Fine.
Fortunately, log log epsilon zero over
epsilon is basically six.
For all reasonable values of epsilon 0, so
it doesn't matter, okay?
Great.
Now, look at the first term.
Again, you don't know, well, you could,
let's, let's pretend you know gamma, okay?
The first term says, there you go, that's
the number of steps.
It depends on how sub-optimal you are.
And you say, excuse me?
I haven't, how would you find p star, and
they'd say, run Newton's method.
But if you run Newton's method to find p
star,
now you know exactly how many steps and
you don't need an upper bound on it.
Is everyone following this, like how
ridiculous this is, right?
Okay, so, all I'm doing is I'm just making
fun of the way this is
normally discussed and taught and all that
kind of stuff.
Because we're going to fix it next time.
In fact, we're going to get a little bit
I,
these are just the hints of what's
going to happen.
Here's our little example like this, and
you can see exactly what's happening.
What's being plotted at least for the
first two is the actual,
it's the ellipsoid determined by the
Hessian, right?
And you can see, by the way, in this first
one it's maybe not quite right, right?
because, you know, may, maybe the correct
Hessian change accordance will be this.
Well, it's a little bit like that, right?
So, and you can see by the time you get
down here,
by the time you get down to the, this,
this point, you,
you're actually applying the correct local
change of coordinates.
And, and the thing you want to focus down
here is the axis.
This is 10 to the minus 15, right?
So what happens here,
now unfortunately, this thing goes into
quadratic conversions almost immediately.
But we'll see a bigger example, maybe on
the next slide.
Now we'll go, yeah, here we go, here's an
example in our 100's.
This is very typical.
Okay.
So, here's the exact line search
backtracking and what you can see,
the scale here is ten, covers 10 to the
20, right?
So you have to understand how to read the
scale.
So what happens is,
you know, this is sort of the region of
linear that's the damped convergence.
And when this thing, when you get the
undamped phase here's what happens,
you can see that this thing is going down
quadratically, right?
And, I mean, it's all over at 10 to minus
12, right?
That's your, at that point,
your double precision is stationary and
there's nothing more to do, right?
Actually if you run it some more,
you would get things that look like this,
right?
I mention this because you will be doing
it and you might get that.
What would that be when you see that?
What's happening is, what you're looking
at, these numbers would be so small.
You're looking at just the round off error
from floating point numbers.
That's what you're looking at, okay?
So if you see that, then back off and
don't plot and clip your graph higher,
okay?
Because it's unattractive, okay?
And it's, I mean you study this in another
class.
I mean, look, it's all over.
There's no, there's no optimization
problem where you actually have to worry.
If you're solving optimization problem and
you actually have to worry about the
eighth digit that's impossible.
Let's just leave it that way, okay?
It's not good, right?
If, if whatever you're real application
depends on the eighth significant digit,
just go home because it's all over.
Okay.
So here's a big one.
Just for fun.
Just to show you that this persists in
higher dimensions.
So here, we're minimizing, I don't know,
some [UNKNOWN] log barrier type thing.
And this is in R10000, okay?
here, and this is a good point because I'm
going to get to quiz you on
some things momentarily but let's see.
So here, you're minimizing this, this
thing.
That's a log barrier, by the way, for the
unit cube, right?
And this is the log barrier for some
polyhedron.
It's a polyhedron in R10000 with 100,000
faces, okay?
How many vertices does a polydron have by
the way?
Basically, probably more than the number
of subatomic particles in the known
universe, okay?
Maybe with our without the dark matter.
I don't know, it's, it's vague, okay?
It's the point.
So alright, so and here it is, this is on
a huge scale, right?
So for our practical purposes, I mean you,
you've probably done like right there but
and here it is and it, you see exactly,
it persists, you see this is sort of the,
that sort of linear convergence.
When that thing rolls over like that,
that, that's when you,
you you declare success.
and, and you've achieved quadratic
convergence, okay?
And what you'll see at the same time, if
you plot the damping factor,
the tk, the step size, it should be one
from then on, right?
If you see anything else, it means you
messed up or something like that, right?
So, that's it.
So, this works.
By the way, this requires solving a system
of the form of this, right?
We had to calculate the Newton step each
time.
We had to calculate that.
That metric is 10,000 by 10,000.
Maybe this is jumping a little bit ahead
but why this,
this runs really fast, guess why.
You can kind of guess.
I don't know if you can do this.
In your head, you can say what the Hessian
of this first term is.
It's diagonal, right?
Because they don't, its a sum of functions
of xi alone, so its diagonal.
This one, these are sparse, right?
So, we indeed computed this thing, but
we're,
we're relying on this thing being sparse,
right?
Without sparse, we could do it.
It would be way, way slower.
I'd pointed out something very awkward and
that was this.
That the, we were in a weird situation
where
the code was more sophisticated than the
mathematical analysis, right?
Because the, the code is, was actually
affine invariant for Newton's method.
In other words, if you'd scaled things
except for second order effects which
would be just like numerical errors you
would generate the same sequence.
But the mathematical analysis was not
affine invariant.
If you changed, if you changed the
coordinates
in in the mathematical analysis,
everything changed.
There were numbers like little m, big M,
the Lipschitz constant changed.
That was a critical thing that told you
how big the third derivative was, right?
So, this is awkward, right?
The, because it should be the other way
around.
It should be that the math is clean, and
beautiful, as beautiful aesthetics.
And then the code, it's got all sorts of
hacks in it and
the you shouldn't look inside it, because
you didn't want to see it.
Okay?
That's the way it should be.
So this was fixed.
This was fixed about, I don't know, 20,
15, 20 years ago, something like that.
By Nesterov and Nemirovski.
So, and, once with all the background, you
could almost guess what the solution is.
So, here's the background.
This is before we get into anything.
I just, what it is.
So what we're going to do,
so what we're doing is an analysis, what
we want is an analysis of Newton's method.
That, like Newton's method is affinely
invariant that's what we need.
That, because, I mean aesthetics demands
it, right?
So now, let's think about what that means.
Newton's method works well, when the third
derivative is small.
That's the point.
If the third derivative is 0,
your problem is quadratic, and Newton's
method works in one step.
If it's small, you know, then it means
that the quadratic approximation is
a good approximation, do this method
[UNKNOWN].
Okay, everybody remembers this.
And in fact, you should remember that
Newton's method in, in the classical
analysis of Newton's method by Kanterovich
then the third derivative
being small was expressed through the
Lipshitz constant L on the Hessian, right?
That's essentially up bound on third
derivative..
Okay.
So, the question comes down to this
abstractly and
the answer will almost like pop out by
itself.
If you just saw the answer, the answer is
on the next slide.
You just saw the answer by your, yourself.
You' say, oh my god, like who would ever
think of such a thing I mean,
the answer being Nestorov and Nemirovski
but so the question is this.
How would you, how can you express the
third derivative being small
in a way that is affinely invariant?
So that is, that what it comes down to
because if you can do that,
you can analyze Newton's method now in a
way that it's affine invariant.
Did everybody got this?
So, here's the thing you cannot do you
cannot say something like this.
You cannot say, you know,
f prime prime prime, I'll just take the
scaler because it, it doesn't matter.
You cannot say the following, right?
That this, you know, is less than some
numbers I mean, like one or two or any.
You can't say that, why?
Because if I change coordinates here for
example,
if instead of f, I look at f of ax,
right, the third derivative will change by
a cubed or something like that, right?
The third derivative of this would be a
cubed.
And that says that by, by doing a change
of coordinates here,
I can make the third derivative any number
I want.
And I can make it as small as I like or as
big as I want.
Everybody got this?
So this kind of ruins everything, right?
Because it says that the third derivative
is not affine invariant,
the magnitude of it.
Well, okay, duh, right?
So this would be something like L.
Okay.
So then the question is how can you say
that their derivative is small
in a way where whatever that definition of
small is,
it will hold not just for f of x, but f of
ax.
And, you know, this is the, a is, well,
okay, that's the change of coordinates,
the change of coordinates in R is very
simple just says scaling, right?
So, you have to have a scale invariant way
to say that their derivative is small.
And if you think about it for a long time,
only one thing could possibly come up.
And the, we'll get to that on the next
page but
we can almost sort of invent it right now.
This thing will scale like a cubed.
[COUGH] This one, that's the second
derivative.
Here, this thing is going to scale like a
squared, that is always nonnegative.
And so, one completely reasonable thing in
fact, there really is
no other choice is to do something like
take the third derivative or
the second derivative and take it to the
like 3 halves power.
I mean, that's how you convert an a
squared to an a cubed.
And you could do another way You could
take the, the 2 3rds power of the,
the third derivative.
Everybody following this?
I mean.
So, right.
So all of that just came from aesthetics.
It said, let's, let's figure out a way to
say the third derivative is small
which however is absolute, is invariant
under scaling of the argument, okay?
So that's, everybody got that?
So that's it.
Okay.
So, that's the background, so the next
slide is not going to be a shock.
But let me say a little bit about it.
So self-concordance is the name given for
a condition.
You're going to see it on the next page,
but it's basically this.
And what's going to, it, it, it, what's
going to happen is,
it's going to remove all the short comings
of the classical analysis, right?
So, if something is self-concordant, it's
not going to depend on any constants that,
that are unknown.
It's not going to depend on any constants
which change when you change coordinates.
So it's made completely independent of it.
So in other words, we're going to make
our mathematical analysis affine invariant
the way the actual algorithm is.
Okay.
Now, what's going to happen is we're going
to get a special class of convex
functions, these are going to be called,
be called self-concordant functions.
They're going to satisfy this property.
So it's not going to be all convex
functions.
And for these special functions,
self-concordant, what's going to happen is
we're going to have a very streamlined
analysis of Newton's method.
And it's not going to be like one of these
classical Western Western convergence
theorems that says if,
and then a long string of things not one
of which you could ever check, holds.
Then a long string of things,
not one of which you could actually care
about if you're actually solving problems.
Here it is.
A function on R is self-concordant if the
absolute value of the third derivative is
less than two times the 3 halves power of
the second derivative.
[SOUND] Okay?
So that's it.
Now, without the discussion we had
earlier, you would've looked at that and
said, I mean, I remember I did and it
wasn't written that way, by the way,
it's written in a much more complicated
notation.
And you would look at that and go, what
where did that come from.
so, but it's kind of clear.
This is the idea Then if
you like, this could be a Lipschitz
constant.
And you would look at that and go, what
where did that come from.
so, but it's kind of clear.
This is the idea.
Then if you like, this could be a
Lipschitz constant.
By the way, why is the two there?
You can replace two with any other number.
The analysis, all the analysis would work
fine.
Two happens to be a number that works well
with a lot of common functions, right?
So we're going to see that.
okay.
So, the two is there again for
aesthetic reasons.
It's more or
less the same reason why in front of a
quadratic, you often put a 1 half, right?
Just aesthetics, because you take
gradients and
it goes away and I don't know.
Okay.
Now we say a function on our Rn to R is
self-concordant if the following is true.
You restrict the function to an arbitrary
line, right, that, so
f is a function on Rn and g is a function
in R.
If that function is self-concordant,
right, so if it satisfies this,
if g satisfies that, then, you define the
function to be self-concordant.
Okay.
So that, that's the idea.
And it's a way to say.
I mean, the correct way to think of this
is this is
a method to say that the third derivative
is small but
it's a method that will is invariant under
scaling, very important.
Okay.
So, let's look at some examples.
Well, look linear and quadratic functions
f prime prime is 0.
So, I mean, of course, right?
Of course, the theory of Newton's method
applied to linear and quadratic functions
is a pretty short theory, so and we don't
need a theory of it, right?
So, anyway.
But the following is true, if a function
itself can,
well we'll get to that in a minute.
Okay.
So negative logarithm, there's, there's a
function that comes up all the time.
And, you know, how do you verify these
things?
You just check.
You, you take the derivatives, minus 1
over x.
The second derivative is something, and
then you get a q,
in fact you get something like x to the
minus 3 with some number in front.
You take the 3 halves power, whatever the
second derivative is, and
you just verify, okay?
That, that it holds, okay?
That's the negative logarithm is.
Here's one.
It turns out negative entropy, that's x
log x.
That's not self-concordant.
But, x log x minus log x is.
Okay, so that's self-concordant.
And there's a reason for that,
because self-concordant functions will
actually automatically be barriers, right?
So if they're not zero, they'll be
barriers, okay?
So and that adds a barrier.
You'll remember that x log x is not a
barrier because it goes to zero.
At x equal 0, which is boundary of the
domain.
It's not the barrier because although the
slope gets infinite,
it goes up like this, it stops at 0, it's
not a barrier.
And that means, by the way, it violates
one of these rules that we have for
whether one of these unconstrained method
works, right,
which is in sublevel sets are closed.
Okay.
Here's the most important part, is this,
and this is kind of obvious.
It says, let's, let's scale the argument.
The translation, of course, is totally
irrelevant.
But let's scale it by a.
Then it says, that we call that f tilde
and
we'll calculates f tilde prime prime, you
get this, of course, and this is that.
And, of course, if I take the absolute
value of this and
compare it to 3 halves power of this
thing, then the a just go away.
And so, the point is it's self-concordant.
It's just want we want.
It's a way to say that if a function has a
small third derivative,
which is invariant under scaling, okay?
So, by the way, it is not at all invariant
under scaling the function on the outside.
So, 2f, if f self-concordant, 2f need not
be, okay?
So, and, but actually that's not the real
issue,
it's whether you can scale a function like
that.
In fact, you wouldn't want to, because the
complexity analysis based on,
based on scaling the function outside
would be nonsense, right?
Because, one of the things you're
interested in is whether you have
an epsilon of the solution but [UNKNOWN]
of scale function itself, I,
I can make any thing and have any error,
right?
So, okay.
So, there's a whole calculative
self-concordant functions.
And here's this one.
You can scale a function but only by
something more than one, okay?
The sum of self-concordant function is
self-concordant.
By the way, that's not obvious.
I mean you actually have to kind of show
those things.
It's, it's not, you know, it's kind of
classic, classical analysis, right?
You sit down and you work out some stuff
and then some, you know, polynomials and
some various inequalities, couple a of
[UNKNOWN] later or
however you do these things.
And the next thing you know, you have it,
right?
So, but it's you know, it's kind of like
pencil and paper kind of stuff, right?
okay.
It's preserved under composition with an
affine function.
That's clear.
In fact, that's completely clear.
So if f is self-concordant so is f of ax
plus b.
That's pre-composition.
One way to generate a lot of them is, it
turns out that a lot of functions end up
looking something like this, it's the log
of something is self-concordant, right?
And so, a general theorem for that says
that if the third derivative of
a function is less than, you know, three
times the second derivative divided by x.
I mean, these are just obscure weird
conditions, right,
then this function is self-concordant.
And that allows you to show a lot of
things are self concordant, right?
So so let's look at a couple of examples.
Here's one the log barrier.
That's self-concordant.
why?
Well because you know, this, the, the
minus log is, right, and
the minus log of affine is, sum is done.
Here's one.
This is not obvious at all, but it's true.
Negative log det X, that's one of our,
that's actually the barrier for
the positive definite cone, right?
It's also related to all sorts of things.
It's like entropy of a Gaussian
distribution,
it has a function of the covariance.
It's it has to do with volume of
ellipsoids if we're doing
a geometrical problem So, this comes up in
tons of things, right?
And not only is minus log det X, convex,
it is in fact, self-condordant, right?
By the way, this would not have been so
much fun, right?
So, for example, the third derivative of
minus log det X is a pretty,
it's something that could easily give you
a little bit of a headache, right?
Because it's a trilinear form on symmetric
matrices.
So it's a trilinear symmetric form that
takes three arguments, right?
You know a, b and c and it's tri, I mean
so anyway.
I, let's just put it this way.
That's six indices, okay?
So, if you're good at that or whatever,
great.
But six indices, like several passed my
own limit, I can tell you that.
Here's one.
That's a convex function of both x and y.
That is actually the log barrier for the
second order cone, this thing.
By the way, bits and pieces of it do not
look convex, right?
here, right?
So, for example, the y squared looks
deeply suspicious, right?
because how could this be convex in both x
and
y, because, the, this is kind of weird,
right?
Look at that.
That's quadratic in x, but there's a minus
sign.
That's quadratic in y but there's a plus
sign so, but it is.
This is this is convex and actually you've
seen it before.
But it's not just convex.
It's actually self-concordant.
So, okay.
Now, let's look at Newton's method.
All the details are in the book so but
we'll just see how this works.
Remember how Newton's method worked in the
classical analysis but
which by the way also came from Moscow.
So here's the, here's the, the difference
is this.
This says you look at the Newton
decrement, that's lambda of x, right?
And it says the following.
If it's bigger than some number and, you
know, you can get them super duper
explicit about the number, it depends only
on the backtracking parameters, right?
So you get, you get things like if you
tell me whatever alpha and beta in your
backtracking thing, I can tell you what 8
is and it would be like 0.16, right?
And see, I even see cool papers like that
where there'd be
things where this is less than 0.16 and
you're like, where did that come from?
Anyway, so the point is if this,
if this Newton decrement is bigger than
some number then, the following holds.
The function value goes down by at least
gamma, right?
And gamma is an absolute constant.
I mean, they only depend on, you can work
it out and be, you can evaluate it.
And it's just a number.
It depends on absolutely nothing you don't
know.
Well, I guess the prior knowledge here is
that the function is self-concordant so
I guess that's something you know.
But you already know a whole bunch that
are.
Okay, the second is this.
If on the other hand, once this Newton
decrement gets less than this,
this critical value of eta, then the
following is true.
Two times it is less than two times it
squared, right?
By the way, this kind of hints this one
may be that we would have
improve the aesthetics if instead of we
defined the decrement as lambda, maybe
lambda over two, right, because then this
would have been real super duper pretty.
It would have been something is less than
something squared.
But remember in the other one,
in the classical analysis, you had things
that looked like this.
I mean, this thing basically says that the
error at
the next step is less than the square of
the current error.
But in the classical analysis,
there's all sorts of other crap in here
involving little m, big L.
All sorts of stuff you don't know.
Now, that doesn't matter if your idea of a
convergence proof
is that it's a feel-good thing, right?
That kind of, you know,
it vaguely justifies, you know, your
method or something, right?
Then that's fine.
because you don't know those constants in
any way.
So here though, it's not, it's just, there
it is.
It's just, there's nothing there.
And so the complexity bound you get is
shocking.
It's says this.
It says, if f of x0 minus p star,
that's how sub-optimal you start, divided
by gamma plus log log 1 over epsilon.
That's it.
That's the, there's absolutely no constant
in there you do not know.
It's just, that's,that's just the number
the number of bounds, okay?
Now if you take the simple analysis, the
one we have in the book or
whatever, and plug in various things, this
bound will come out to be 375 times f
minus sub-optimality plus 6, okay?
Oh, by the way I would usually write that
as five or six just for fun but mostly
to irritate people who were, do complexity
analysis but and it works, by the way.
I can recommend that.
Well, wait a minute.
You'll look at this thing and you go, that
is so cool.
There's nothing there you don't know.
Oh, wait.
There is something you don't know.
Wait a minute.
You don't know that.
[LAUGH] And you'd say, oh, well.
Okay, that puts a little bit of a hole in
it there, right?
It's 375 times [UNKNOWN] and then you say
well how do you get p star?
Well, you might run Newton's method.
Okay, but once you run Newton's method,
you do not need an upper bound on
the [UNKNOWN] Newton method because you
just figure out you just record how many
steps it took.
Am I capturing the, okay, good.
So, alright, so what I'm going to say,
this is going to be super vague now and
it will not be vague on Thursday.
So here it is.
Have you ever heard of any method by which
a person can get a lower bound on p star?
Let's just admit freely that,
yes, there's a number in here we don't
know, it's P star.
And then well we're going to say somehow,
when, when we actually use this for
something, the way it's going to go down,
it's duality is going to come on.
And, and it will have a, somehow, we're
going to get a lower bound on p star.
By the way this is a, kind of a sloppy
bound.
If you do a very careful, kind of
Russian-style bound, right?
You, this number comes down to something
like 10.5 or
11 times f minus this, plus the log log
thing, right?
That's, so instead of like, half a page,
that's like 6, 8,
pages of some pretty, pretty crazy stuff,
right?
But, that's not bad.
Okay.
So, something very interesting happens.
And, and this is worth looking at.
Here it is.
Here's a log barrier that's a
self-concordant function.
Oh, of course, two or three times this is
also self-concordant.
So, I, I think probably the right thing we
should say about this problem is
this function is it is minimally self,
self-concordant.
Meaning if you not, if you, if you divide
it by any number, if,
if you scale it down, it won't be
self-concordant, right?
So that's that's kind of the idea because
I could also,
I could multiply this by a 100 and
everything will be off, right?
So alright, because actually what happens
is what scales is f minus p star,
f of x0 minus p star which scaled by 100
and
we get it totally, well, it would scale
the wrong way.
Okay.
So
that's a minimally self-concordant
function.
Now [COUGH] what's here is this.
We generated a kind of random instances of
this and then with random number for
n, m, and then we just used Newton's
method to solve it
whereupon we recorded the number of steps
it took.
Okay?
and what this shows oh,
whereupon we recorded two things,
of course, the actual sub-optimality
because once you run Newton's method,
you know what f of x minus p star is, and
you also know the number of steps.
And you just make a scatter plot.
And you get something like this, okay?
So now, what the self-concordance analysis
tells you is this.
It says that's an upper bound.
And the good news, now that would be a
function that looks like this.
It starts here and
then basically goes up with infinite, you
know, it looks like that.
You know, that didn't come out right, but
you know what I mean.
It, it starts at six and goes up with a
slope of 375, okay?
So, and, good news is, all of these are
below that, okay?
Mm.
The better Russian bound.
The Nesterov-Nemirovski bound.
You put a 10 in there or an 11, or
something like that.
And now your slope is, you know, it's not
so bad.
It looks more like, I don't know,
something like this, right?
I don't know.
Like, like that.
Okay.
But what you see hence is the following It
suggests that it
kind of works with c1, right?
That's an empirical estimates, right?
Oh, and by the way, what, how do you
explain that and that and that?
What are these points?
Dumb luck, okay?
So this is the case where you were quite
far from optimality, and
your Newton step, well it only took 10
steps.
So what happened was, it kind of went
there, it went there, there and
just accidentally found itself, you know,
after like two steps in
the region of quadratic convergence and it
was all over four steps later, okay?
So, so these are dumb luck.
And, of course, that's going to happen,
right?
By the way, the way you know it's going to
happen is you
can do things like run Newton backward and
stuff like that.
And, and so you'll quickly get far away
and so that means that in,
in all of space there'll be, there will be
points where dumb luck will prevail, okay?
So, but what's kind of cool about this is
what's wonderful about it is this.
It says that we can actually have two
discussions about the complexity of
Newton's method.
And both discussions work like this.
It says, I can have an actual mathematical
discussion.
I plug in c equals 11 and, of course, I
would expand,
I would explain that six is a macro for
log log 1 over epsilon, right?
So if I replace six with log log 1 over
epsilon, I put 11 for c.
And [COUGH] then it's actually a true
statement.
That is the, is an upper bound on the
number, maximum number of Newton steps it
can take and that, you, you could say that
in the Math department, no problem, okay?
So that [UNKNOWN].
But the other cool thing is if you, you
can also talk, you can divide the audience
in two, people who just care about look,
how many steps does it going to take.
You know, on average or typical what can I
expect, right?
Then all I do is change c and I'll change
it to one.
And it's kind of an empirical upper bound,
I mean change it to a half and
it's probably a good estimate of what it
is, or three-quarters.
Everybody see what I'm saying, right?
So, it's actually, it suggests that
things,
things based on this, you can have a dual
discussion.
You can be talking to the people who want
to do math.
There's nothing wrong with that.
The people doing complex analysis.
And you can also at this exact same time
be talking to people who just
say how should I choose alpha and beta in
my thing?
Or something like that, right?
In which case, you could minimize this
with c equals 1, and
this would kind of give you a reasonable
way to do it.
okay.
So let's
talk about implementing Newton's method.
now, you're going to use Linear Algebra.
Now here, this is it.
And this is where actually knowing Linear
Algebra numerical Linear Algebra is
actually very important, right?
Because, yeah.
In fact, I should give you some of the
history.
So, Newton's method well,
[COUGH] the name suggest it was not
invented 20 years ago, okay?
It goes, I mean, you know, and Newton did
one with one variable and
then in the mid early 19th century, it was
extended by Raphson, this is the,
this is the British-centric view of how
the world went.
I'm sure that there's other versions of
the history.
And so, sometimes Newton with more
variables than one vectors is
called Newton-Raphson method, okay, but
now we're in the early 19th century or
something like that.
So, you know, this is not new.
Now the, oh, by the way, many variables in
1850 or
whenever Raphson did this would be like
three or four, right?
Because, by the way, if you are, I mean
that would be like, a super big
problem because I guess, you know how you
solve linear equations in 1840.
We know, you know how to do that.
We fast forward to nine, the 19, you know,
well, let's say to the early, early
computers.
So it's the 50s, it's the 60s, right?
And there yeah, it was a big deal to solve
a system of linear equations
with like 100 variables and 100 unknowns,
I mean, that was a really big deal, right?
That's right, so in fact, there are people
who have, you know,
these same old story like maybe the world
market for
computers will one day approach six or
something, I don't know.
You know, same sort of thing with linear
equations, that people said things like,
well, you can imagine possibly solving a
hundred variables,
with a hundred unknowns, but it wouldn't
seem to have much meaning or, you know,
you can't imagine that, right?
So, okay, of course, people say this all
the time, right?
Or that kind, they make that kind of
statement.
Okay.
So, in the 60's, and this is mostly in the
West what happened is that
Newton's method kind of went out of favor.
And the reason was everybody focused on
oh,
my god, you have to solve this equation
here, instead of linear equations.
And you, you wouldn't want to do that for
more than a hundred variables, right?
So that, that was the argument.
And there are actually a whole bunch of
methods,
which are actually quite good methods.
In fact a lot of them are called
quasi-Newton methods.
And the whole idea is to get around this
terrible past of solving a system of
linear equations.
Everybody got this?
Now, of course, these days, that's all
nonsense so
you go up to like a couple of thousand and
it's not a problem on a laptop, right?
It's a non-issue But what it misses is the
following.
If, if there's a structure in the Hessian,
that's where smart Linear Algebra comes
in, okay?
And so, let, we're going to look at that.
And so, there are lots of cases where
you'll say,
well, we would never use Newton's method
and you look at it.
And the Hessian is, like, you know, banded
plus rank 5.
And you're like, I can actually do an
iteration in about 80 microseconds.
So, again, if you know what you're doing.
So, okay, let's, let's move on.
So, how, how would you do this?
A very good method would be this.
You just do a Cholesky, you form the
Hessian into a Cholesky factorization.
And it turns out that, by the way,
that the Newton decrement is one of the
parts of this.
I mean, not surprisingly, right?
It, it's the norm of, of the, of L inverse
g.
That costs, you know, n cubed over 3 flops
for an unstructured system.
And if h is like sparse, right, a specific
case that would be banded.
This would be way less.
For example, if it's banded, this is o of
n, right?
So that mean, for example, on that laptop,
this laptop here,
I can easily knock off a Newton iter, a
Newton step
on something where the bandwidth is ten
and it's a million variables.
I can knock if off and I don't know what,
I have to do the arithmetic but,
you know, it's way, it's measured in
milliseconds, okay?
Whereas, if you don't know that, it mean
you're cubing a million and, you know,
and incorrectly concluding that Newton's
method is useless.
Everybody see what I'm saying here?
So, this is why you want to know about
linear,
this is why you want to know about
numerical Linear Algebra.
Okay alright.
So, here's an example and in fact, this is
the last thing you, you have to do,
there's one more thing but it's related to
it.
You should know some numerical Linear
Algebra.
And that means that there's a part of your
brain that's all set up now.
And like, it should release endorphins
when you see things like band you know,
arrow matrix, right?
You should look at that and go oh, that's
great.
Oh, you should, everybody know what I'm
talking about here?
Right?
If you see things that are like, I don't
know, you know,
diagonal plus low rank, you should say,
oh, boy.
I know, step back.
I'm an expert, I know how to handle this,
okay?
Everybody, okay, do you now what I'm
saying?
So, these are all the things, so you
should understand, you know, sparsity and
things like that unless it give you a good
feeling and stuff like that about how to,
you know, that, that there's some,
something you can do, right?
Some problem is on a graph, if there's a
sparse graph and you look at it.
Okay.
But the next thing to do is to relate that
back to the optimization problem, right?
So, and specifically Hessians.
So, here's an example that shows you how
to trick,
that tells you how the structure in an
optimization problem translates into
sparsity pattern in the Hessian or
structure, not just sparse-dependent.
Here's an example.
Let's take a function, which is this.
It is a sub, it's separable.
That's a separable function, right?
By the way, you know, this could be
regularization.
That could be an L, you know, but it's not
an L1 norm, because
we're doing Newton's method, but it could
be some kind of regularization, right?
Some, some function of the individual
things plus a function of
a linear of a linear, of an affine
combination, okay?
Now, a function like that, if you work at
what the Hessian is, it's this.
The Hessian of a separable function is
diagonal, right?
Why, because I mean, partial, partial xi,
partial xj is 0, right?
If you take partial xi, you get you know,
[UNKNOWN] prime of xi, it hasn't do an xj.
So, so basically, I mean so these are the
maps you want to make in your brain.
That things like separable, means diagonal
hashing.
By the way what is block separable imply?
Block separable means I can chunk my
vector up into chunks, you know,
maybe 5 long.
It doesn't matter.
I'd, I'd chunk it up and my function is a
sum of functions of those chunks.
What does the Hessian look like?
It's block diagonal.
And block diagonal would be one of the
things you should be
triggering endorphins.
in, in at least in the section of
your brain that does numerical Linear
Algebra , right?
Because it's way ease, it, you should say,
I can solve that fast, right?
Because you can, right?
By the way, why is it you can solve block
diagonal things fast?
You can do blockwise inverse.
And so, you can say, I can do a blockwise
inverse.
I can do all in parallel, right?
I could, I can have different threads
doing each one.
yeah.
All these things are true.
But, maybe another way to say it is this.
The cost of, if the cost of solving a
block, which it's like n cubed, it's
convex, it follows instantly that if you
break it up, you're going to do better.
So that's, that's it, so it's actually
convexity that tells you that, alright?
So okay now when you see this, it's
something like that.
The Hessian is, is this.
This is just simply a formula for the
Hessian.
H zero is the hessian of the psi here, psi
zero evaluated at Ax plus b.
By the way this formula for the hessian,
these are things that are sort of,
we put them in kind of an appendix of the
book because it's,
it's a pain to work them out.
And I'm going to give you some very
practical advise so please listen now.
When you see something like that, like a
log barrier,
you might want to do something like
calculate the Hessian by hand.
Why not?
It's just a second derivative.
How hard can it be to calculate partial,
partial xi and then after that partial,
partial xj?
It's reasonable right?
And by the way, at the end of the day, I
mean, this is probably not a bad thing to,
you know, I mean you should check it,
right if or whatever.
Or I mean the ones in the book are correct
so
you don't have to check those but, you
know, anyway.
Everybody, do you know what I'm saying?
Okay, so here's my advice for practical,
yeah, don't do that, okay?
You will be very sorry.
Use the Chain Rule absolutely whenever you
can, right?
So usually, size 0 is something real
simple, right, like size 0 could
be something like, you know, the square
root of 1 plus, you know, y transpose y.
There you go, that's a nice differentiable
function.
That's size 0 of y, okay?
Now, that, go ahead and take partial yi
and partial yj, please do, right?
That makes sense.
But the minute you put these as and bs in
there, you're, there's no way,
you're every going to come out of this
with anything correct, so, okay, so.
And by the way, I sometimes have to remind
myself this, because I look at something,
I"ll start taking partial derivative and
then I'll hear my
own voice saying don't do this, you're
doing some, don't do this, okay?
so, okay.
Alright.
That you can, anyway.
Trust me, this will be relevant for you at
some point in the near future.
So, okay.
So the point is, here, now you stare at
that and you realize that if a is if,
if, a here is, is is wide, right?
Then, that's low rank, right?
So, a function of a low dimensional affine
function, the Hessian of that is low rank.
In fact, the rank is exactly equal to the,
the size of the intermediate variable,
okay?
So, I'm just and, you know,
there will be other things that you will
connect, and things like that, but,
you want to get a mapping from a problem
to sparsity patterns.
And then, of course, once you're, know
about sparsity patterns,
you want to understand how to exploit that
sparsity pattern in solving linear
equations, right?
And so, this will take you quite far.
okay.
So, here, you know, I mean, of course,
this is the message, right?
Dumb Linear Algebra says H is dense here.
Of course, it's dense, right?
If you add a, a low rank thing to
anything, it's going to be dense.
I mean, well, with high probability,
right?
It's you add and then you do this, and
it's like n cubed or something like that.
But, if you do the right thing which is
just,
it's, it's, it's just exploiting the
diagonal plus low rank you'll end up
solving this in actually, linear in n as
opposed to n cubed, okay?
This is a big difference, right, because
n, you know, problems are not interesting
until they have a thousand variables or
more and they can have a whole lot more.
And so, if you take here n equals a 100 k,
this gets super interesting, right?
So, it says that that problem, I mean, if
this if the height of a is 10 and
n is 10,000, that's easily within striking
distance of a laptop, maybe even a phone.
Okay.
So but for that you have to know the, you
have to know Linear Algebra.
You actually have to know Linear Algebra.
Okay.