Part one of the course was basically,
well,
all the analysis and the mathematics
behind convex optimization right?
So, convex analysis, the basics there the
most important thing there you needed to
know are things like convexity of a whole
bunch of atoms.
And a lot of, and a lot of these
composition rules and
other rules, these are good to know about,
right?
then, there was a section on the anatomy.
Of the anatomy of optimization problems of
the anatomy of optimization problems and
some of them had names, right?
Like you have linear programs, and second
order comp programs, and
geometric programs and things like that,
right?
In some sense, those names matter less and
less.
You should know that already because with
things like CBX a lot of
the transformation of a problem that has
no name into some problem that has a name.
It can be automated or is part, at least
partially automated.
Still you need to know the name, so that I
don't know, you can talk to other people,
but that's the idea, and then of course,
there's duality.
So in duality is sort of a big field by
itself.
And it's, it's really nothing but
an organized way to come up with lower
bounds for problems, period.
That, that's what it is.
In fact, it's a quite a trivial way, in
some sense, to come up with them.
But it's an organized way.
And what is shocking is that in, for
convex problems, it's generally speaking,
not always, but that these are little
minor details without with a constraint
qualification, it's sharp, right?
So that these lower bounds are actually
sharp.
But they will see lots of advantage, you
will see lots of uses, you will see,
by the way, if you look, if you take other
courses,
you'll see examples where people use
duality all the time.
They won't even say it.
Right, I mean you take a wireless course
and
there you're trying to figure out how to
do, you know, assign powers to channels or
whatever and they'll call it something
else like water filling or something.
But now that you know the secret, you'll
just look at it and say oh,
that's that, that's called duality, right?
Or, you take an information theory course,
they're telling you about how to
allocate bits to something, and you look
at it and you go, that's duality.
So, okay.
Duality also has, there's a lot of
aesthetics in duality where it's useful to
recognize that problems that can at first
look very
different are actually intimately related,
right?
So and this will come up when we look at
applications a lot.
So for example, we read things like,
again, if you're in statistics or
if you have taken some advanced machine
courses, you would know things like this,
but you get weird things where, you know,
duality of,
sort of you get maximum likelihood
estimation problems.
The duals are these max, or things that
look like maximum entropy or
Kullback–Leibler divergence type things,
right?
And so, I, by the way, if you don't know
what I'm talking about, that's fine.
I'm being very obscure now, but I just, I
want to just point out that this is
going to permeate lots of things you've
seen.
And actually, in various areas, it's
completely well-known.
I mean people know these things.
okay.
So, now, we're going to start another
section of the course.
It's the middle section and honestly this
is the pay-off.
So, I mean, the truth is you've already
seen enough.
You're already being paid right now, I
mean, the homework is now fun,
it's useful and so on.
Well, [LAUGH] that's my opinion, you're
the one doing it, but, but
I still say it's fun and its useful and
stuff like that.
This is really the pay-off of the course,
what we're going to do is for
the next couple of weeks.
We're just going to look at various
application areas, you know, one by one.
And we'll look at some topics,
some will be obvious our first topic here
is going to be totally obvious.
Actually, some will be less obvious,
I mean we'll look at some weird
geometrical ones and
some ones in statistics and stuff like
that, and they'll be,
they won't be totally obvious.
actually, watch out,
because some of the most useful material
is in the totally obvious stuff like
the stuff we're about to do is shockingly
elementary and unbelievably useful.
So so this is it.
Oh, this is also, by the way,
the material that's not in any traditional
course on this material, right?
because the traditional course segue
immediately from convex analysis to
basically deadly boring, long complicated
proofs of complexity of algorithms.
All right.
So this is the part that's missing.
So, okay.
So we're going to start in.
By the way, the, these problems have been
categorized into gross areas.
This is approximation and fitting.
But we're going to see that this'll
overlap, of course,
with things like statistics.
I mean duh, most, a lot of statistics is
basically fitting models, which is,
in some sense, approximating data.
So we'll see connections between these
things, right, you shouldn't be surprised.
Also, I should add that in the lectures
here,
we're just going to cover some of the
high-level stuff.
There's a lot more material in the book,
and you should absolutely read it,
well, let me put it another way: we will
hold you absolutely responsible for
everything in the book.
So we'll exercise a reasonable fraction of
it through the homework, not all,
because it's just too much.
But we're, we will work with the,
our working assumption is that you will
have read all of it, so okay.
So we'll start with just this very general
idea of approximation and, and fitting.
And we'll start with norm approximation
and then something which is
a vague dual of it is least norm problems,
and then something that combines kind of
both regularized approximation and then
we'll look at robust approximation.
And this is sort of this is relatively
new, this is stuff from the last couple of
years or last decade or something like
that.
So, okay.
So norm approximation.
Well I mean the simplest case is just
this.
We minimize the norm of Ax minus b, right?
And you have your data is a matrix A
usually with m bigger than n, so
it's taller than, it's a tall matrix,
a skinny matrix and this is just any old
norm on Rm.
So when we instantiate or specify the
norm, it becomes a specific problem,
it becomes regression or least-squares,
that kind of thing.
Okay, and now, when we're doing this if x
star is the minimum of this oh, and
I should warn you right now the minimum
doesn't have to be unique, you know that,
of course.
For the two norm if A is full rank, it's
unique, right?
But, in fact, for other norms it's
absolutely false.
So if you do one norm minimization,
infinity norm minimization,
it's incredibly common that there are
multiple optimizers.
So here, this just, this notation, it, I
don't mean,
I don't mean to suggest that there's a
unique one because there need not be.
Okay.
So, what's an interpretation?
Well, there's lot's of interpretation, the
first one is geometric.
Basically, what it says is vectors of the
form Ax were x varies,
sweeps out the range of it.
All right, so that's a subspace.
And it says, then it says you have a fixed
vector b, and so the question, and
then you have the, the distance as
measured by the norm between b and Ax.
And so, basically, what you're saying is
please,
this basically says the optical value of
this thing is literally,
it is literal the distance of B to the
range of eight.
So solving this problem is the same as
saying find me
the distance under the norm, norm, here b
to range of A so that, that's what you do.
So that's what it is.
And and you say find a point closest to
this, right?
And here, I didn't put v, so it's not
technically wrong.
If I had put any article in here, it would
have been A,
and then, it would have made it right.
So, okay.
Now another fit another, another way, this
comes up is in estimation.
So in estimation it goes like this.
It says, I, I, I want to estimate some
parameters x, okay?
And what I have is I have linear
measurements of x.
That's y equals a x, but they're corrupted
with noise.
And that's the, so I add v, right?
And so now,
if I ask you to guess x interestingly,
implicitly, you are guessing v.
That's really what you're doing, because
when you guess x,
then y minus Ax is v, right?
And so, the problem of guessing x is the
same as guessing v.
And we'll see that this is exactly the
statistical interpretation as well, right?
So you're basically guessing that.
And so, what we're doing is something like
this, we're intuitively here,
we'll do it quite differently when we do
statistics, but
here, we're saying intuitively that among
possible v's smaller is more plausible.
Smaller v in norm is more plausible than
larger V, right?
So that, that's the implicit assumption
here.
And in that case, you would say that
solving this problem would give
you something like the most plausible
value of x.
Right, because it's the one where the
implicit,
when you are implicitly guessing v, it is
smallest as measured by the norm.
Right, so that, tells you about, plaus,
you know, plausibility, it's,
it's the least implausible, or something,
okay.
Another one is optimal design.
So here, x is a set of design parameters.
That you could fiddle with.
These could be a force profile, for
a vehicle, it could be all sorts of
things, right?
Then, you have a linear process, so "X"
causes the results, "Ax",
then you have a target, which is "B" that
you want to hit.
If you can hit it, fantastic.
But if you can't you have to get, you have
to compromise and simply get close.
And then, how do you determine, what your
happiness level is, or
really, we should say your irritation
level, right.
So, how irritated will you be, if you want
b,
little b and get Ax, and we'll measure
that by a norm.
So the norm encodes your irritation level.
And then it says the best design is, is
obtained by solving this problem here.
Because it gets you closest to what you
want, measured by your irritation and
we're measuring irritation by a norm.
Everybody got this?
So these are, I mean, don't overinterpret
what I'm saying because what I'm saying is
completely trivial.
So, if you think for a second, I better go
think about this for
a second, you're overinterpreting it.
I'm saying nothing deep.
And that's going to continue, by the way,
for
a few more things I'm going to say about
this.
So it really is this simple.
Okay okay.
Now, let's substantiate some specific
examples.
If you take the two norm, you get least
squares, right?
And that's the analytical solution of it.
I mean, you know, if A is full rank,
it's just the least-squares, it's a
transpose a and a transpose b.
Right, so that's your least-squares
solution.
oh, in that case,
I should say that the problem has lot's of
names, it's called regression.
In statistics least-squares,
I guess it's called least-squares fitting
everywhere else.
Okay?
So, that's the,
the so there's probably some other name
specific fields for this, but I,
I can't remember what they are right now.
Okay.
But interestingly, we can do other things.
If you take an infinity norm,
then it's called, it's actually got lots
of names actually.
If you minimize the norm of Ax minus b
infinity,
it's called Chebyshev approximation is one
name.
Another name is minimax fitting, right?
And, it's actually quite interesting what
minimax fitting is and
it's it has its uses, right?
It basically says I, I want to fit a
model, but what I care about is
the absolute maximum error, like not the,
well, not the sum of the squares.
I care about the absolute maximum, right?
And that would be minimax fitting.
It's got lots of applications.
interestingly, least-squares of course is
used by zillions of applications, right?
It's the basis of, it's the workhorse of,
you know, giant fields.
It's pretty much it's the workhorse of
statistics, right?
I mean, pretty much, right?
All the advanced stuff people do that's
coming on, online a bit, but
bottom line is most people are doing
regressions, right?
And if you're snickering, making fun of
how unsophisticated people are in
statistics, don't, because for example,
control is the same way.
All of control, and
I mean look, there are some advanced
control methods, that's fine.
Are they working?
Yes, they're working.
But the bottom line is that most control
is kind of least is variations on
least squares.
Signal processing, image processing,
again, don't make fun of them,
it's mostly least-squares.
Are there more advanced methods coming
online?
Absolutely, right?
But mostly, it's done by least-squares, so
interestingly, what you find is,
this is discussed almost not at all in any
standard curriculum.
Bottom line is that the modern viewpoint,
in my opinion is, it turns out, we're
going to find out later, computationally,
this is no harder than that.
Shocking, isn't it?
It's absolutely no harder, right?
But no one knows it, because everyone in
this room has been exposed to this,
probably in multiple contexts, right?
In some class on Fourier series, on some
class on linear algebra, probably in other
classes, you've seen this and probably no
one has seen this I'm guessing.
So okay so anyway, back to the main thread
here.
That this, you can solve this problem as a
linear program.
Now that may or may not be relevant but,
and
because many times, an automatic system
will do this for you, right?
But nevertheless, it can be written as an
LP.
What there is not is there's not a formula
like that, and
that's why we don't teach it in some of
the more traditional courses.
All right?
So, okay, here's another very interesting
one.
It also has a very long history.
It's the sum of absolute values sum of
absolute residuals approximation use
norm one that says minimize, this.
That's extremely interesting.
Again, no formula, you can solve it as an
LP.
We'll find out later, the computational
effort, of solving this, and
this, it's basically the same.
It's the same, there's no difference,
right?
I mean, there's an aesthetic difference,
if you're locked in a 19th
century aesthetic, there's a big aesthetic
difference, but computationally, none.
This is really interesting, this one.
It's an example of what we're going to see
later is a robust estimator.
The properties are shocking, and it's
actually,
things like that are form the basis of,
actually, a lot of modern statistics, and
machine learning, and a lot of other
things.
So we'll, we'll, we'll see that.
So it's quite different and, you know,
these are not new.
The fact, well, this is Chebyshev, and I'm
not sure, I'm sure there's a Russian name
we can attach to this, and it would be
traced to the 30s and 40s.
And in fact, at Moscow State University,
I'll check with my friends and
find out what the correct name is, but
there is surely one.
And you know, so these are not new things,
they've just kind of languished in
obscurity until the last decade.
Now they're the height of fashion, of
course, and depending on,
you know, different, various fields.
Okay, so
now we're going to look at sort of a
generalization of, of norm minimization.
What we'll do is this we're going to just
to make the notation easier,
we're going to introduce Ax minus b.
We're going to call that the residual,
assign a name to it, r, okay?
And then, what you'll want to do is,
essentially, you want all the entries of r
small.
In fact, if you can get all the entries of
r zero, that would be ideal, right?
Because you'd have, I dunno, I mean,
you got exactly what you wanted, Ax equals
b, right?
So, but let's, assuming that's not the
case,
you're going to have to compromise, and
you can't have all the residuals 0, right?
So what we'll do is we'll penalize values
of R by function phi.
That's just a function from R to R, okay?
That's just, that's it, and so we're
going to minimize the sum of
the penalties, you know, you can divide by
m and get the average penalty.
I mean, it wouldn't make, it wouldn't
change the problem, but
give you a better interpretation or
something, okay?
So, now you can choose phi and, and
please don't overinterpret what I'm going
to say, because you're going to want to,
but actually it really is as trivial as
I'm saying.
So here it is.
You use phi to shape how irritated you are
with the residual of a certain size.
That's it, okay?
So for example, if you take phi is the
square function,
then that tells you something like this,
if a residual is my,
I'll ask you, if phi is the square
function, this is least squares.
And, and that implicitly says that if
residuals is small, how irritated are you?
Yeah, very little.
Everyone got that?
So that very means it's small.
It's small squared.
Okay, now, in least-squares, if the
residual is big,
how much does it irritate you?
Very much, thank you very much [LAUGH].
And the very is not casual, right?
It's not okay, right, so, so that's kind
of the idea behind least-squares, right?
That, that, you know, you have a residual
small and
you're like fine if it's big, not cool,
right?
So, all right, and, and just don't
overinterpret this, right we'll,
we'll, by, we'll have multiple
overinterpretations when we do statistics
about densities and all sorts of crazy
stuff and maximum likelihood, but for
now, take everything sophisticated out of
your mind and we're just doing this way.
Now, if I take phi as the absolute value,
I get L1.
Let's talk about that.
If I take in L1, an absolute value
penalty, then if a residiual is small,
how much does it irritate you?
Let's compare, how, if you're, if you
compare that to the square,
how much does it irritate you more, much
more, right?
So in least-squares, a small residual
irritates you very little.
I'm going to try to say it correctly.
And, but in L1 norm, right, irritate, in
the absolute value, it says,
you're irritated a little bit, but
relatively speaking, that's a lot.
I mean compared to other squares, right?
Okay how about this with absolute value if
you've got a big residual how irritating
is that in least squares?
Very.
And in absolute value?
It's irritating without the variable.
Everybody got this?
Okay.
So I mean, look this, I know this, this
sound, it really is this dumb,
you'll, you'll, it really is, trust, trust
me, but this is unbelievably useful.
Right?
Because I think what has not been
recognized, recently, you know,
until relatively recently and
it's not by any means fully recognized
now, is the following fact.
That least-squares is the one case where
you get some silly 19th
century formula, nineteenth?
But all the other things we're talking
about,
you can solve just as easily, right?
And so people haven't looked at them.
So, all right.
So let's look at some things.
We just talked about the quadratic in
detail.
here, let's do something else.
Here's dead zone linear, that's this
function right here, look at this,
it's it's linear, and then it's got a
dead,
what people call a deadzone in the middle,
so between plus and minus 0.25.
Someone you should articulate,
what does that mean about how you care
about residuals?
Well, in this case, it's very specific.
If it's less than some threshold, it
doesn't irritate you at all.
And, and in particular, that goes two
ways.
It means that a residual of point,
of .001 is absolutely no better than a
residual of 0.25 here.
None, right?
By the way, there's plenty of applications
of this and it doesn't, it doesn't,
you know, you can think, they're going to
come to you, like, pretty quickly.
you, if, if you have, like a an analog
digital converter and you, you make
a measurement, then, you know, being off
by something less than you're your, your
lsb or least significant bit, it's not
better, I mean it's, you're not better.
All you know is that this signal value is
in some interval,
you don't know anything else.
Okay, and the fact that it's linear once
you go outside the deadzone,
let's talk about how much you care about
larger residuals.
So you'd say, look, I don't, you know, who
likes large residuals?
No one.
I don't like large residuals, but
you don't go nuts about it as with the
quadratic.
That would be the explanation.
Everybody got this?
And by the way, we're anthropomorphizing
all this, but
what we're going to find out is things,
this does exactly what you want, right?
So, okay.
So here's another weird one.
Here's log barrier with a limit.
So this is just an expression, it doesn't
matter what it is.
I can tell you what it is, it matches the
quadratic almost perfectly over plus
minus you know, over, over a pretty big
range.
It matches the quadratic very closely, but
then what happens is it accelerates and
goes up to plus infinity.
Someone explain that to me.
It means that I do not even want to
discuss the possibility of
residual more than plus or minus one I
won't allow it, right?
But for smaller residuals it's just like
lee squares okay so
these are the idea now, the whole point of
this is
that you would craft your own your own
penalty function, and let's just try one.
Suppose I'm doing least-squares fitting or
regression, so I,
I just want to minimize, I want Ax to
equal b.
But suppose I said that I care about, take
the residual r.
And then overfit, let's say that being
above is okay.
I don't want to be below.
I, I, really I, I, I'm, I care four times
as much about being below.
So, you can interview me and you can say,
tell me about your residuals.
And the model and the data that you
want to fit.
And I'd say, well I want it to fit.
And some, then you'd, some would ask,
well, what about, how do you care about
big residuals?
And you'd say, I don't like them.
I don't.
And of course, I don't like them,
you say, but I mean,
will you go way out of your way to not
have a big [INAUDIBLE], you don't know.
If we have to have some big ones, well
have some big ones.
Okay?
You should get,
you should, we just nailed, by the way,
the asymptotics of the, of
the penalty function, and then you'd say,
well tell me about under and over fitting.
Is it symmetric?
You know what under and overfitting is, it
means you look at an entry of b and
you look at an entry of Ax, and you
compare the numbers, right?
If you say I don't care, I mean, above,
below, it doesn't matter to me.
And you, but suppose you said, no actually
there's an asymmetry there.
It's much worse to underestimate.
So if Ax is less than b, that's bad.
Right, how bad?
[INAUDIBLE], got reasonable factor for
something, it's five times worse.
By the way, there's a bigger picture here,
which actually fits with all of
observatio that the idea is not to focus
on the L grid that produces x.
What you do is, your tools are, is the
problem.
You formulate phi and
the optimization will carry out your
wishes to he extent that it can, right?
So, that's the idea.
So, you should express your wishes in
fitting, by setting a penalty function or
something like that, then let optimization
sort out the details.
Everybody see what I am saying?
I mean they're totally obvious things,
but, believe me,
they have not been, they have not been
internalized by
the vast majority people doing kind of
mathematically sophisticated things.
So, let's look at a, here's an example,
very simple.
Let me just generate a random data problem
with a hundred
measurements thirty parameters that we
want to estimate.
These are and then we, we just solve
various problems.
We'll do one, we'll do one norm, we'll do
least-squares regression.
We'll do a deadzone-linear, and we'll do
this analytic center, what did I call it?
I forget what I just called it log
barrier.
Okay, yeah, log barrier.
So we'll do log barrier.
By the way, the name of the point is the
analytic center, we'll get to that later.
But, okay, so what's plotted here, let me
explain what's plotted.
This function here, so
each of these, that's one norm, two norm,
well, square, deadzone-linear log barrier.
And you see the actual function plotted on
some scale here.
So this function tells you, kind of,
your irritation at having a residual of
that level, 'kay?
And then, what's shown here is the
histogram of
residuals that you get, right?
So you get different Xs in each case,
right?
And you get different histograms.
We'll start with least-squares, because
this would be the most,
this is kind of the starting point for
everything.
Here they are.
Well, it's kind of nice.
You get a lot, bunch of, get, a bunch that
are out here.
You have a few that are big, not so big,
you know.
But they're all bunched in here.
Okay.
Let's look at the L1 case.
You get something, bizarre.
And it is completely explained,
intuitively, by what we talked about.
The first thing you see that catches your
eye is, that's a different scale.
Is, you've got this giant pile of Xs, that
sorry, of residuals, that are flat 0,
and by the way, it's not that they're
small, they are actually zero, 'kay?
So and okay, so I'll give a very simple
intuitive explanation for this.
The incentive to drive a residual to 0
holds up until it's 0.
So, if you're, if a residual is at this
value,
there's still a strong incentive to reduce
it, okay?
Now, that's completely false for
quadratic, because the smaller a residual
becomes, the less incentive theory.
And incentive is just the slope of this
thing, it tells you,
it says, you know how much benefit would I
get in reducing the objective to
make that residual slightly smaller?
And the answer in least-squares is you
have a diminishing residual
benefit, right?
Here it holds up to the very end.
Okay, and the result is a whole bunch of
them become 0.
By the way, for those of you who've taken
machine learning class,
a statistics class, whole bunch of
classes, you'll recognize this.
You should have already have heard about
things like L1 and sparsity and
things like that, and we're going to see,
you're going to have in
your head burned a connection between L1
and sparsity where things are actually 0.
[COUGH] And in fact, it turns out it's not
L1, it's just the point.
It, it turns out the point is here, so
our, the one we looked at before, our,
our asymmetric one would have the same
property.
All right, but the other interesting thing
is this.
Look at that, there's a residual out here
which is like one point eight.
And you didn't get that in the L2 one,
right?
Because 1.8 is a big residual, and in
these squares you care about that a lot.
1.8 squared, right?
And so, again, I'm anthropomorphizing, but
in these squares,
pushing these down here was a good
trade-off in terms of these things,
split and moved all around here, and so on
and that sort of stuff.
I mean, this is all just
anthropomorphization of all this, but
this is the idea, okay here's
deadzone-linear.
And you see something very very
interesting,
that if your residual is between plus and
minus 1 half, we don't care at all.
One half, a residual of 1 half is,
in terms of irritation, no better, no
worse than 0.
That deadzone, deadzone-linear says
there's an incentive to reduce a residual.
The incentive entirely disappears once a
residual has hit one half.
Right?
And in fact,
that's what's happened, right?
So, these are sort of residuals, that,
well, you know, why not?
But they weren't forced to be between
there, they just happened this way.
And here is the log barrier, and
sure enough, as required, they've all been
crushed down here.
So now let me introduce some really cool
stuff you can
make cool, Frankenstein-like.
We can cut up penalties and re-sew them
together and
make, you know, things that I guess don't
come up obviously.
Here's a The very famous one is the Huber
penalty function.
The Huber penalty function is this.
It's, quadratic, up to a, a threshold,
where upon it, it transitions to linear.
And so, this is the Huber function here
with threshold M.
actually, it's a very important function
in, you know, for
I would say 80% of where people use
least-squares right now,
my guess is that in 80% of those cases,
the application would be improved.
The performance in whatever the
application would be improved if it
was replaced with a Huber, and no one
knows that, right?
I mean people know that,
people do advance statistics, they always
do this kind of stuff, right?
But in lots and lots of other areas they
don't know that.
So that's the Huber function.
First, let's just talk through what it
means so the Huber function so something
like this if you are below the threshold
of the residual is below the threshold,
it is identical to least-squares,
basically says, it's least-squares.
But if you go over the threshold, it's
radically different from least-squares,
and what, what can you say about a Huber
penalty as opposed to least-squares?
It looked like an L1, and it is a penalty
that it, it's more relaxed.
So you would say something, you could just
guess this,
you would say that if you do Huber
Approximation, let's say,
you'll end up with something like this,
compared to least squares.
It will be, it's going to be,
if everything, if all the residuals are in
the threshold, below the threshold, it,
it's just exactly the same as
least-squares, but what it will do is
it's going to be much more relaxed about
having a couple of outliers.
So it will actually allow a couple of
outliers.
It's not going to like it, but
it's not going to go insane, like least
squares will.
And it won't, it won't actually ruin
everything else.
It won't increase all those better things
to try, to, to improve one, okay?
So it turns out this is a robust
estimator.
We'll see lots of, we'll see lots of this
in the future, but
it's a robust estimator.
It works unbelievably well.
And so let me show you, the kind of thing
it works on.
So, here's a, here's a picture [COUGH]
with, you know, 42 points, okay.
So, 40 points are obviously scattered on
that line, you know, on a line.
And, these are two, you know, obvious
outliers, okay.
So, and we just made the data, just, just
plot it so you can see it.
You know, obviously for fitting data at
two dimensions you don't need any fancy,
you use your eyeball to do it.
So, that's not what this is for, okay.
This is just to illustrate what happens,
okay.
So there's your data If you do the least
squares fit, you get this dash line here.
Everybody see that?
And the discussion is extremely simple.
It's basically look that is so big, that
when you square it, it's gigantic.
It's extremely irritating and least
squares will actually bend the fit to
reduce that big number which you're
squaring and
it will take a hit on all those other
numbers.
Everybody Got that?
Okay.
Now, and by the way,
in your head, you can take these two
things, and you can move them this way.
You can make them much worse.
I can make the least, I can make the least
square thing actually flip over and
have the wrong slope.
Okay?
Now by the way, if you think.
I mean, of course, in our plotting a silly
data with like, you know, one varia-, it,
it's goofy, right?
But the point is, you got the same thing
when you are fitting things like,
things in dimension, in, in very high
dimensions, like dimension 100.
At which point, by the way, your eyeball
is no good, just for the record.
[LAUGH] so, and it's, so, so the Huber fit
is that Is the dark line here.
Right?
And it's false to say that it's
unaffected.
That is actually false.
Because I could also show you a fit where
I remove these two.
Right?
And then, and that black line would move
very slightly.
Okay?
So, and, and, and, would, would then fit
those things perfectly.
By the way, that's also a standard
two-step procedure in outlier.
You first use something like a Huber or
robust estimator to guess which are the
outliers, remove them and refit, so
that's, that is the whole, I mean a whole
lot of stuff on this.
So this is a, this is this, by the way
these, this thing works so
well for a lot of serve practical data,
you know, if you blabber on and on and
on about things like big data and stuff
like that.
So things like, things like these, these
robust estimators are absolutely critical
in, in a situation like that, right?
Because when you have a billion pieces of
data, and
you know a thousand of them are complete
and utter nonsense.
There's out liars, that can render lease
squares utterly useless.
And these things will just power through
it.
Actually in Shocking ways where you can
take a prob,
we'll have some homework problems on this,
but it'll be shocking.
You take something, you add in outliers at
the 10, 10% of the data will be outliers,
20, 30, and that's usually a threshold
point where it fails.
But you can get just absolutely sh, and
it.
A lot of times you have to double-check
that what you're looking at is
the right thing.
You think maybe you've used the true
parameter, not the estimated one.
These things work so well.
So, and this is something that, you know,
it's in, it's implicit in a lot of
modern statistics, it's implicit in a lot
of machine learning and things like that,
so it's a, but it's a very good thing for
ev, in my opinion, everyone should know
about this, these, these kinds of things,
So we'll look now at something it's like
the dual of the approximation problems or
norm approximation problems.
And that's a least-norm problem, and the
basic idea is, is this.
Here you have a quality constraint, so
in this case A is not generically tall,
it's generically wide.
So, A is a wide matrix.
And this says that I have something like m
equality constraints on x, presumably not
enough to complete constrain x, I mean
then it's a silly problem as
one feasible point, and then among the xs
that satisfy ax equals b, we're going to
choose the one that has minimum norm, and
you've probably seen this in some class.
If you took 263 this was a least norm
problem, it was the two norm there.
So what's the interpretation of this, and
of course I should say something here,
when I say equals argmin, if this norm is
strictly convex, and
that would be the case for a two norm,
then it's unique, of course.
But it can easily be not unique, right?
So we should say something like, well,
one notation would be x star is in Argmin,
because one, one,
one notational convention is that argmin
returns the set of minimizers.
So by x star equals argmin, we just mean
it's a minimizer.
So the geometric interpretation is this.
We have an affine set that's generically
given by the set of x
such that Ax equals b.
So we have this affine set, and what we
want to do is find the point.
Closest to zero in that set, right?
And a simple completely elementary
variation on this is
where we project a point in, a non, in a
non-zero point on, onto set.
So that's the idea it's a, it's a
projection of zero.
Onto the affine set.
Estimation is this.
The idea in the estimation interpretation
is something like this.
We interpret b equals Ax to mean that we
have m perfect linear measurements.
So there are, there's no noise.
Nothing, they're perfect.
And then, but we have n parameters to
estimate.
And we have more parameters than we have
measurements.
Right, so I have 150 parameters to
estimate.
I have 50 measurements or 100
measurements, something like that.
And that leaves me basically 50 unknown
dimensions or something like that.
So Ax = b in that case.
We interpret as the set of parameter
values are consistent with
the perfect measurements, right?
So this, if you were to put a comment
here,
you'd say something like "consistent with
measurements", like, like this, right?
And the, the assumption is the
measurements are perfect.
Right?
So, that would be that.
And then the interpretation of minimizing
the norm is,
you then choose most plausible, right?
Choose the most plausible point.
Right?
And here implicit is the outfollowing
idea.
That the larger x is, the less plausible
it is, right?
So that's, that's the idea.
In other words, you're in some situation
where there are many parameter values
consistent with the measurements.
So, nobody, any, anybody who chooses a x
with a x equals be cannot say to
another person who chooses another x that
satisfy x would be that they're wrong.
What, what one can do then is just talk
about which is more plausible, or
something like that.
And so the idea is that the norm is here
used as a surrogate for,
I should say implausibility, because the
larger the norm the less plausible it is.
And, by the way, we'll connect this
possibly even later today,
we'll connect this to a statistical
interpretation.
Another one is design.
So here you think of x as a bunch of
Design variables.
These are inputs for example, this could
be forces that you apply to a vehicle or
something like that right?
It could be voltages or current drives
that you're going to send to a motor, or,
or current drives that you're going to
send to an antenna.
Right, something like that.
Then a x gives you something like the
result.
Right, so this, this gives you the result.
So, and it might be something like this,
if you choose 150 forces to apply, maybe
at different times, different actuators.
But actually all you care about are maybe
six or eight things at the end, for
example the position and momentum at some
final target time, something like that.
Right.
In which case Ax gives you the result Of
the action X.
Then b is actually your desired action, so
any x that satisfies a equals b is valid.
That's basically, find me a set of forces
that will take my spacecraft,
move it over to here twelve seconds later,
and
arrive here you know, with this position
and momentum.
Right, so that would be, lots of x's do
that And here what you're doing is
you're saying please find me an efficient
one, one that minimizes a norm.
Could be two norms, could be one norm.
One norm would be closer to fuel usage in
a lot of cases, something like that.
It could be infinity, it could be anything
like that.
Okay, so this, this just interpretations
of the problem
minimizing the norm of of x subject to ax
equals b equality constraints.
Right.
Oh, I should say that one nice thing
about.
Our approach to these, which is simply to
look at that and
simply say, that's a convex problem,
period.
Right?
One nice thing is, you can mix and match
if all of a sudden comes,
somebody comes back and says oh dear, you
know, I need to add some constraints here.
Like for example the xs have to be between
plus and minus one.
It's not a big deal for us, we just add
those constraints.
Right?
So.
Okay.
I'm not showing them here just for
simplicity.
Okay, let's look at some specific examples
of least norm problems.
Here's one, the most famous one, is you
take the two norm and
in fact what you really minimize is not
the norm but
the two norm squared, not the two norm but
the two norm squared.
And this is the same because minimizing
the two norm squared and
two norm is the same.
it has the same solution.
And this, the optimality conditions you
work them out That the KKT
conditions are linear, a set of linear
equations.
So you can solve them exactly, and there's
a formula for it if A is full rank and
all that kind of stuff, and you've seen
that in 263 or
some other linear algebra course.
Right?
So, and that's why this is, this is,
of course, extremely widely used.
Right?
Because it Fits that, fits,
it fits everything.
Right?
Looks like it's simple,
fits the 19th century, you know, formula
model and all that kind of stuff.
Okay.
Now you can do other things,
which is actually quite interesting.
You can do things like this: you can
actually take the L1 norm, and
this is a very interesting problem.
This says minimize the norm of X one,
subject to Ax equals B.
OK.
And this is something, actually, that's
quite in vogue right now, and
maybe has for five, maybe ten years now.
It has no analytical solution, in general.
Well, I mean, except in very silly cases,
has no analytical solution, So
it's got various names.
This one's basis pursuit, and let me ask
you.
In view of the discussion we had last
time.
Last time we talked about a penalty
function and how the shape of
the penalty function has an influence on
the distribution of residuals.
That discussion transposes perfectly to
this situation.
Right?
So here,
the idea is that if you have a penalty
function,
here the penalty is embarassingly simple,
it's the absolute value.
But what it does is that's going to shape
the distribution of X's.
And what I'd like to know from you is,
what do you imagine the solutions of the
basis pursuit problem look like.
What you would expect, and turns out, in
fact, to be true,
is that when you solve this problem, most
of the xs are zero.
M'kay?
And I mean, there are various ways, you
will observe this is as a,
as, as an empirical observation.
And in fact, you can prove various things
about that and so on, and so forth.
so, in fact, this is a heuristic for
getting a sparse solution of ax = b.
Right?
So, okay.
And this is going to be a theme,
it's going to kind of follow us through
the rest of the course, and so on.
So.
Okay.
We'll see a lot about this.
okay.
So, well, we've already been talking about
this, but
the least penalty problem, says that you,
you choose a penalty function phi,
here, and then you minimize the sum of the
penalties, subject to Ax equals B,
and then you would, you would choose To
shape to get an x that you like.
Right?
And by the way, this is something quite
interesting about it because it had
something to do with how people don't talk
about it a lot, that is the question of,
sort of, the entire design flow.
How do you use like convex optimization,
this kind of thing.
And in fact, there's a big trend across
many fields,
to move away from something that's a
direct solution that says "oh you know,
I want a sparse solution, so here's what
you should do with the data," towards one
where you put one level of indirection in
between.
And what you do is you form an
optimization problem.
And what the user does is mess with the
And then you let some numerical method
work out the actual solution.
Right?
So, I mean this is a big trend across
many, many fields.
Right?
That, for example, in areas like control,
signal processing, even statistics, you,
you move away from this idea of Here's
what you do to the data, and
instead, what the designer of a method is
really doing,
is actually designing an optimization
problem.
You change parameters here and there, if
something's too smooth, or something's not
smooth enough, you add a little
regularization, and you crank that up.
But you're not, you as a user are not
actually figuring out exactly how to
transform your data into your estimate or
something.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So this is, I mean this is a very big,
it's a big picture observation but
it's it's happening.
Okay.
Well, the parent of these two problems,
least norm and then norm approximation is,
is just regularized approximation.
And in fact, there's even a more general
parent.
The basic idea, it's a regularizaiton, is,
it's ubiquitous, across lots of fields.
and, it, it's basic.
The correct way I think to think of it is
it's a bicriterion problem.
And it basically says, I care about two
norms, each of which I would like small.
Right?
So
the norms are, this is the most
traditional setting.
The first one is something like Ax minus
B.
That can have lots of interpretations,
depending on if you're doing a statistical
model or, or data fitting.
This is your misfit.
X is your model.
Ax minus b norm is a measure of how well
your model agrees with the data you
have observed.
That's, that's, that's, that's something
like misfit or fit.
Your x is basically how big are your model
parameters.
And we'll talk in
a minute about why would it be that you
would want small parameters.
After this some very good reasons why you
would want small parameters, well,
like many good ideas it can be justified
from like five different,
completely different points of view.
So, let's look at some of them.
So the idea here, essentially, is you're
saying, "You know what?
What I want is a good fit." I want "AX" to
be about "B", but
I want to do it efficiently.
I want "X" to be small, so this is the
essential idea.
Oh, and again, these ideas are all very
simple, so if you're not following -
don't over-interpret what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is so simple that there
are no subtleties here.
None.
So, okay.
So, when would this come up?
Well an estimation it might be something
like this.
You'd say, well I happen to know, I mean
what I'm observing is y equals Ax.
So, Ax minus y or Ax minus v or
something like Ax minus b if b is
something that I measure.
Is, is V.
And so this is something like the norm of
that this thing.
And you know that that's small.
But I had prior knowledge that x is small.
Right?
So, and
that's, that's what this term does for me.
Right?
So that, that's what that says,.
You can have optimal design.
You could say, actually, I don't insist
that AX equals B.
I will give up on AX equals B.
I will simply get close enough, close
enough?
Well this is a bicriterion problem, so you
have a whole paretooptimal curve, and
you will determine where to operate on
that curve once you see the curve.
Then you'll look at it and say okay, fine,
I don't need to dot, I mean, if I'm
within three millimeters that's actually
fine, especially if that allows me to use
one quarter of the fuel I might have used
otherwise, right, something like that.
So there the idea is you're willing you
don't even, you,
you're willing to not have Ax equals b,
you'll get up a little bit on that.
and, hopefully you'll take, as a benefit
for not doing that as exactly, small and
efficient small likes, so that's the idea.
Another interpretation, is this, is,
robust approximation.
And this is something we're going to talk
about later,
this is quite a modern interpretation and
it's extremely important, and
the idea is something like this.
You really just want to get a model, so
you really want norm ax minus b to be
smaller.
That's really what you want.
Problem is you don't quite know A, right?
This is extremely typical, right, that the
As are measured or
something like that, you don't quite know
what they are.
And by the way, it's, this can happen in a
design setting,
it can happen in an estimation setting.
Right?
In a design setting Someone, you say, "you
know what, I,
I do know, I know the moment of, you know
I know the moment of inertia.
I know the mass of the vehicle, the CG, I
know all these things pretty well." But
actually only about 1%, no better than
that.
And what that says is if I apply a bunch
of control surface deviations.
To an aircraft and I ask where will it be
in 22 seconds the answer is actually
technically you don't know, right?
because I don't know there is plenty of
air I mean hopefully you have a pretty
good idea of what it's going to be right?
because otherwise you're going to be in
pretty deep trouble but the point is
it's really like a cloud of where it might
be depending on what it might be doing,
everybody see what I'm saying?
It should be a tight cloud, one hopes,
right?
But the fact of the matter is, you don't,
you don't know exactly what's going to
happen, so this is -- that's the idea.
So then you say, well,
what's interesting about this is how much
is your x affected by changes in A?
And that we can even work out, I mean this
is going to be an intuitive one.
We'll look at this more carefully later.
But, so what you do is you think of A as
being sort of the nominal one and
delta is a, is a matrix, presumably small.
Which is basically your error in A.
Right?
So, this is, this is what you have.
So if, for an aircraft this is,
this is the nominal model.
That assumes that your estimate of the
mass, moment of inertia, you know,
blah blah blah, all these things are
perfect.
Right?
They're, they're double precision perfect.
This is basically a var, these are
variations due to the fact that you know,
these things are manufactured, things vary
by 1%,
you know, all sorts of things happen.
Right?
That's what the delta is here.
And if you look at this equation we're
going to work this out but
it is very simple what you get is ax minus
b and then plus delta x and what you see
very clearly is the following is that the
errors in A multiply x and so for
example suppose I chose X to be 0 How much
would that be affected by model errors?
By the delta?
Not at all.
And
you can see immediately, I'm just very
intuitive, but the basic idea is oh,
by the way, these are sometimes called
multiplicative errors.
That's a name you will hear, and it makes
perfect sense because it's an error in A,
which then multiples your choice x.
So, it's a multiplicative error, and
a multiplicative error it's, it's, it is
in your, you want to be less sensitive to
a multiplicative error Then here's what
you want.
You want X to be small.
The thing.
Everybody see this?
And so this is why a small X would be
preferable.
Right.
That, it would, it would be that,
it would be less sensitive to errors in A.
That was a long description.
I, that's not supposed to be fancier than
what I just said, but that's the idea.
And I can give you yet another
interpretation now, but I mean in,
in some sense all these interpretations
come around to the same thing.
Another one is this, you have y equals you
have a model like this estimation.
You have y equals Ax plus v.
But the truth is, you really have
something like this.
Right?
You really have a non-linear model/g.
However, near, you do, near where you're
looking right now?
Y equals ax plus v works.
That's provided x is small.
Okay?
So the idea there is this,
this sort of tells you your nominal error
based on your say, linearized model.
This says, please have X small, because
the smaller X is,
the more accurate, the more I trust My
linearized model, right.
And in fact, in that case, the term that
constrains x either via regularization or
as an additive term in regularization or
as a constraint.
If it's a constraint it's called a trust
region constraint,
which is a beautiful term, because it
basically says, please estimate x,
I want norm Ax minus b small, but I want
norm x small.
And someone says, why do you want norm x
small?
Do you care?
Then you go actually no, I don't care at
all how big the parameter is.
Problem is, I have to add that there
because if "x" gets bigger,
my model "Ax" is no longer accurate.
Doubting this?
I, I'm, tha, got, got, got the idea, it's
very, it's pretty straightforward.
Okay.
All right.
Let's look at some simple cases.
I mean, so, how do you, how do you solve a
bicriterion problem?
You scalarize, right?
This is the simplest method.
And so you'd take the norm of Ax - b plus
Gamma norm-x.
For us, that's a convex problem, no big
deal, we solve it.
Okay?
So that's fine.
And, and Gamma is a positive parameter.
You sweep it from 0 to infinity and at the
two extremes you would get you can get
the extreme points by solving a constrain
problem or something like that.
Okay.
And, so
this traces out the, the trade-off curve.
a, a very.
A, a very traditional method is to square
the two.
You get the same trade-off curv.
And by the way that's something you would
want to check.
Right?
That in fact, the,
the curve of solutions here parameterized
by delta is identical to the curve of
solutions parameterized by gamma here.
Right?
So, in fact, you can even how delta and
gamma are related, right?
And it's not totally straightforward and
it has to do with the particular problem.
But these are two parameterizations.
Okay.
So if these are 2-norms, and
the reason generally one squares a norm, I
mean there's several reasons.
But the most traditional is when you
square a 2-norm, you get a quadratic
function, which is nice and smooth and you
know, the derivative is linear, and
you, you know, and then Then all your you
have a formula for the answer, right?
OK.
So, most famous there is,
is Tikhonov regularization.
Oh, and I should say in statistics it's
called ridge regression is
the name in statistics.
Maybe another one, but it's called ridge
regression.
And this just turns into a single
least-squares.
I mean, you can solve this analytically of
course.
Two norms.
Right?
so.
And, the solution you can either make it,
stack it, and make a big least squares
problem, or
you just get, sort of an analytical
solution like that.
Okay?
And, and that's the thing.
Now, the, horrible, reason, to use this.
The, the, the, the one that, that I don't
like at all,.
And is in fact probably, the most Common
use of regularization is,
someone says, what are you doing, you say,
I'm doing, I'm, I'm adding regularization.
Why?
And you'd say, because without it,
I was getting numerical, my solver was
sending complaints to me.
Right?
So everybody see that?
If you add delta here, this just, this is
just now,
works perf-,it has to work perfectly.
You can never get a complaint that says,
you know, inverse condition number big or,
you know, numerical error, or something
like that.
It's not going to happen.
Can't get something singular working
position.
So let's look in the example.
And this example actually it's, it, it's
very simple.
But it's, it's going to be an example,
actually, of.
It's sup, meant to illustrate exactly what
I talked about earlier,
this idea of a design flow.
Right?
How, how do you use these things, right?
And this'll be one from, you know,
control, if you like.
This could just as well be statistics it
could just as well be anything else.
Image-processing, video-processing, it
could be anything.
And you could construct a similar story.
Could be finance, right?
So let's look at this.
Here's the idea, I have a convolution
system, so I apply an input u,
scalar input at various time intervals.
It could be a force I apply to something,
it doesn't matter what it is, right?
And, something I call the output is a
convolution of the input with some
convolution kernel, or in EE dialect
that's called an impulse response, okay?
But that's dialect.
Standard term is convolution kernel.
'Kay?
So, and in mixed company you should always
say convolution curve [UNKNOWN] Okay,.
So, the input design problem, is choose
this input u, so
that y does something you want.
And, you know,
this is just going to be a very simple
example to show what a typical design flow
looks like.
So Here it is.
What I want to do is I'm given a desired
trajectory, and I want to track it.
That's it.
So, and, and I, I want to make, I, I have
to give a measure for mistracking, and so
I'm going to call that J track and if,
if you can't think of anything if nothing
immediately comes to mind.
Then you should just use the squares,
just historical, to follow in historical
tradition, it's not a bad thing, right?
I mean, by the way, if I were to make this
the sum of the absolute values,
it would change the result, and
you could even kind of guess what would
happen when you, when you do that, right?
If I were to make this the infinity norm,
right?
That you would call it something like mini
max tracking error.
You might give a, a name like that.
And you would get different results as
well.
Right, so but here we just take the
squares and make it simple.
Okay, Now at the same time I want you not
so big, right.
So, I am going to introduce an objective
called the magnitude, Jmag.
And these are, well, by the way,
if you look at these, they are quadratic
forms, right.
So, so far, right, because they're square,
they are squares, their sums are squares,
and I will take an input very this is,
tells me how.
well, I shouldn't say something about how
wiggly the signal is or
something like that, and it's going to be,
the sum of the difference, of the first
differences here, right?
and, and now I can ask some questions,
like when would J track be 0,
which is its minimum possible value.
It means you have -- your Y is equal to Y
desired.
And you -- yes.
And a good name for that is you might, you
might say that you
interpolate The desired thing or you might
say you achieved perfect tracking meaning
that the output absolutely tracks what it
is that you required, okay?
So that would be that when would the input
magnitude objective term be 0?
When u=0.
Okay?
So, in which case,
by the way your tracking error would
simply be some wide desired square.
Right?
Because your output would be 0
with that point.
Okay, and how about input variation?
When would that be 0?
Constant, exactly.
So, if you were to crank up The
coefficient on input variation, very high.
you would expect to see inputs that were
constant.
Right?
And at the same time they're attempting to
track things like that.
Okay?
And you could go on and on.
For example you could have a second finite
difference,
which would be something like a smoothness
measure and
that would be something like ut plus 1
minus 2ut Plus UT minus 1.
That's I, I don't know if you recognize
that but it's the all,
it's the famous, you know, minus 1 2 1,
and the tri-diagonal matrix or something.
It's a second difference, right?
And then, and that would give you
something smooth.
And when would that be zero, by the way?
Linear.
Exactly, so if U, U looks like that or
that, that would be zero.
Right?
So Okay great.
So what we'll do is we'll just make this a
regularized least-squares problem.
We'll take the tracking error plus delta
times the derivative error plus aeta
times the magnitude error.
And, I mean this is a least-squares
problem, right, so
we just solve it, right, this is idea.
We get a least-squares problem.
And then the idea now is that delta And
aita are knobs that you will fiddle with,
to get something that you like.
Right.
And you could,
you could do this in a formal way, and
actually do 10 values of each.
I mean it's a trivial problem, you could
do 10 values of each.
And then just make a, a big 10 by 10
matrix and actually plot all these things.
[COUGH] Look at them whatever you like.
You could have two big knobs in front of
you that labeled, you know, Delta and
Eta or two sliders or whatever on some
user interface and, and
you can fiddle with them and see what you
like.
Alright, so that's the idea.
Okay, so.
Quick example here.
Here is some, here are three pareta
optimal solutions.
Right?
So the first one has delta equals 0 and
that means that we,
we're putting 0 penalty on the variation
in you.
Right?
So, fine.
we're, and we're putting a small weight on
the sides of you, that's eight small.
And, here's the input, and the output.
And, two things are plotted in the output,
you can't see there's a dashed curve,
here, which shows you the desired one.
The desired one is just this kind of
square wave thing.
That was dialect.
It goes like, it jumps up, and then jumps
down.
Right?
Like that.
So that, that's the desired one.
And you can see if you look at this, that
we're tracking quite well.
Well you can see there's little errors
right at the transitions and so
on, and this is the input that does the
trick, over here.
Right?
So that's the input, and
you can see the input gets this high as,
you know, almost 5 positive and
it jerks down to like minus oh, I don't
know, 7.5 or 8 there.
Okay?
So that's, that's it, and
you can see that also the input Is quite
wiggly.
Right?
So, fine /g, that's just one point down
the tradeoff curve, right?
Then you'd say, well, in the second, in
the middle, what we're going to do is
we're still going to have no derivative
here /g, but we're going to crank up eta,
and we expect, so that means we're
going to add more penalty To the size.
And so what we expect is the size of you
to come down, and
by the way we're going to pay for that in
tracking error.
Right, so, and in data if you look on the
right you can see here, you know,
the tracking error probably is mostly
accumulated around these end points and
it's pretty small.
Here you can see,
there's some pretty, you can actually see
some pretty substantial tracking error.
Here.
Everybody got this?
The differences, look at this, instead,
we've basically halved th input, right, so
with half the input, [NOISE], so
if this is good enough for you, great, I
mean this is kind of the idea, right?
And finally in the, in the last one what
we're going to do is we are going to,
and we're now going to turn on a, a bunch
of smoothing regularization, and
again, you pay for it in terms of
tracking.
Eh, maybe this is good enough for you,
maybe not, and now, but
you can see immediately what happens
things like these,
which rack a big bill in the derivative.
Cost function, now we're smoothed out and
you get something like this, okay?
So this is not supposed to be complicated.
It is not complicated, it's simple, but
the idea is this is what you'd do.
And you would typically sit there and turn
knobs and see what you like.
And this could be any applicationary.
This could image-processing, where you
turn a knob and
you go no no no too smooth, and you crank
it down the other way.
And now some of the noise comes back.
And then, you turn another knob, and this
is how this goes.
So let's look at another area.
It's, it's also very simple, bicriterion
problem.
It's signal reconstructions.
Quite straightforward.
It's this.
What I have is I have, I'm given a
corrupted signal.
That's x, you know, corrupted.
Okay?
And what I would like to do is to
come up with x hat, which is supposed to
be an estimate of this corrupt well,
it's an estimate of the signal before it
was corrupted.
Okay?
And that's what I'm going to do.
And so at I want "x" to be close to "x"
corrupted, but I don't want it to be
equal to it because its been corrupted,
and what I'm going to do is
I'm going to have a second function here,
which is known as, it's got lots of names.
It's a regularization function, or
sometimes people call it a smoothing
regularizer.
Okay?
And so that's this function phi of X.
X hat.
And the idea's by looking at a trade-off
between these, I'm going to do some,
this is a principled way to do smoothing
or something like that.
To smooth a signal.
All right.
And the model is something like this.
You have some unknown signal.
You absorb a corrupted version and then
you're going to solve this problem and
examples would be something like this, you
know so
simple quadratic smoothing would be you
simply take the differences [UNKNOWN] like
we did in the previous example Some of the
absolute values,
that's called a total variation
regularizer.
So that's completely standard, so, that's
actually a standard term.
Let's look at an example.
I use simple example, right?
So, here's some signal it's 4000 time
samples or
whatever you like but this is the original
signal and this is the corrupted one.
And this one's kind of goofy because No.
Taken the signal, you've added some, and
you can see that,
that the difference between the signal
and, and, and the, the corruption.
You can see that the, the corruptions very
like high frequency or
something like that, okay, so, that's, so
it's kind of obvious, right.
So here what you do now is we simply use a
quadratic smoother and
what would you get would be things like
this so
this is with a the little big of smoothing
this is what you would reconstruct this
would be substantially more and even more
still Right?
So, that's the idea.
And you might say, that's a little bit too
much, and then that's just about right.
Right.
Now, now unfortunately, for
smoothing problems like this there really
aren't any particularly good ways,
to choose The level of smoothing you do,
except maybe aesthetically.
I mean you have to have some side
information, right?
Or, you could have some cases where you
actually knew what the exact signal
was, right?
So then you could actually do reasonable
things like cross-validation.
Here's one, and this is much more modern
-- by the way,
total variation reconstruction, this was
introduced maybe, only 1990s.
So this is pretty relatively recent.
And it's, it's actually quite interesting,
and quite stunning.
In fact, I've tried to get some audio
recordings of this.
I mean, I haven't tried that hard.
I should, because they're amazing, and I'd
put them on the course website or
something like that.
Anyway, I'll explain that in a minute.
So here's a picture.
What I have is, here's the original
signal.
It's got the smooth component, but these,
these kind of jumps every so often.
I mean, this is all just made up.
Right so, this is just to illustrate, what
happens.
Right?
So, here we have this signal, and, so
you, and then we add this high frequency
noise to it, [COUGH] like that.
So that's the corrupted state.
Right?
Now, one of the problems here is that you
don't have this
frequency scale, separation.
Right?
Because, the original signal,
has these jumps.
And a jump, again if you know about forier
analysis and all that kind of stuff,
roughly it is going to contain a lot of
high frequency, so
you don't have the spectral separation of
the underlying signal and the noise here.
And the result is if you do quadratic
smoothing, which in fact is
a linear operation It's just a low pass
filter frankly is what it is and
what you get is this if you do some low
pass filtering well,
sure this gets smoothed out, that gets
attenuated but you can see as you crank it
up to smooth out more, you can see exactly
what is happening here.
That a transition that was in fact a
single value Has now widened, and
now it's taking place over, ooh, that's a
lot, you know, 50 or something.
Right.
So, a transition that was,
that, that went in like 1 time sample, is
now happening over 50, right.
So, by the way if this where audio This
would make something sound very muffled.
If this was the attack caused by a drum,
right, someone hits a snare drum.
You would get something that looks like
that.
And if you smooth it like this, and
instead of the attack rising in 10
samples, 48 khz or something like that,
instead of 10 samples it goes at 1000.
It just sounds like a thud, it doesn't
sound like a drum anymore, okay?
So, all right.
But let's do total variation de-noising.
So total variation de-noising does this,
and
actually, we can see a lot of things here
that you would predict.
So the first is this: this is where you
would put a lot of total
variation de-noising.
[INAUDIBLE] and you're beginning to see
something pretty cool.
When you crank up something which is
basically the L1 norm of
the difference of x hat t plus 1 and x hat
t.
Again You should start now and
by the end of the course it will, should
be completely ingrained in second nature.
But you, you want to make connections
between things like L one and
sparcity, right?
And that's the very simplified model.
But it should really be kinxed and
Sparsity, right?
So lets look at L one and Sparsity.
When someone says please minimize you
know.
Well it's part of it right?
If they say please minimize this, right?
What you would expect is that if the
coefficient in front of this is
high enough, right, that a whole lot of
these numbers would be zero.
And that says that if you do total
variation.
>> Denoising, you should expect a
piece-wise constant signal.
Because a piece-wise constant signal is,
that's what it means.
This is like a derivative, this first
difference.
And if you have sparse derivative, it
means you're piece-wise constant.
Everybody got that?
By the way, its just were the second
difference, and I put an L1 norm And
I minimized.
What would you expect to see.
Piece was linear, exactly, right.
And if I took the third difference, what
would you get.
V y quadratic.
And by the way those would be splines just
for the record.
You get splines.
Okay?
So this is sort of the idea.
Now here what's happened is you are
tracking this, right.
But what's happened is regularization is
so
high that things like that just got
constant, right?
You've, you've lost the fact that this is
varying here, right.
Oh I should add also kind of a cool thing.
If you do this on images, Is a grayscale
or
color stuff, you get very cool stuff and
things start looking cartoonish.
Right?
Because you have a whole bunch of,
you have a, you have whole regions where
it was one color or one shade or, or
there was some gradient.
It's just like now we're placed flat.
So I think you can even imagine what this
looks like.
Right?
So.
So this is, so that if you do total
variation Regularization,
on an image -- what happens is, at first,
you have a million pixels.
You probably can have a million gray scale
values right, I mean, no reason for
any of them to repeat, right?
If they do, it's an accident.
You turn up total variation regularization
on an image and
they'll jump down dramatically.
And after a while you'll have only a
thousand, and you keep turning it and
then at some point you'll have like ten
grey levels.
Right?
But it'll still be completely recognizable
as the image you wanted, right?
But anyway, so, I'm just saying these
things apply to everything, right,
you'll see these all over the place.
So here you can see this is where we might
have maybe not quite enough Total
variation regularization because you can
see that there is some squigglies there
and this is kind of the proverbial just
enough, right, something like that.
Finally it's a big thing we'll look at the
idea of robust approximation.
So here we've already seen hints at it,
right, so the idea You want to minimize,
let's say, (?) x minus b, but the problem
is you don't know a.
Now, I should add,
this issue is universal, in actually all
optimization problems right.
That you have data in an optimization
problem, and
you know, we can talk a little bit.
Say some generic things about data, you
know, when data,
when values that are zero, one, minus one,
Sometimes 2, -2, 1/2.
Things like that.
Those are probably really those numbers,
right?
Because it may be some coefficient that
makes sense,
like you're basically saying, you know,
this thing's equal to that.
And that would reveal itself as a 1 and a
-1.
And that's really, really, probably are
zer, 1 and -1.
Any other constant other than the ones I
just named and maybe a handful of others.
Directly speaking they have a providence
and
you can trace it back to models of things
or measurements or experts or
econometric models or eh, mechnaics or
psychics or something like that right?
and in fact if you trace them all the way
back you'd say oh,
that came from a finite element
calculation or
blah, blah and by the way That means they,
those numbers are suspects.
Right?
I
mean they could be accurate two three
significant figures.
Maybe five, right?
Maybe one, right?
Or in Economics, the sinus suspect right
[LAUGH] or something like,
I mean you just don't You know, so there's
places where it's dominated, right,
I mean, you know, there's extremes here
right?
so, all right.
so, the point is though that in all these
cases you have,
there, there is error in the data, I mean
that's just, period right?
And there are ways to handle it simply,.
Simple methods that, we've seen one
already.
Regularization is essentially a method to
chose x's that are not
extremely vulnerable to changes in a.
For example, that's a really simple
example of a robust optimization problem.
But there are plenty of others, right?
By the way, how is parameter.
>> Variation handled in real life.
So what do you think is by far the most
prevalent method for
handling the fact that your parameters are
not known?
In real, in the, in real life, I'm talking
about when people actually solve things.
>> [INAUDIBLE] What?
>> Ignore it.
Thank you.
That is absolutely correct.
That is by far the prevalent method.
Now, That's okay, in my opinion, provided
you do one thing.
Which is, which, which then take, makes
this okay.
What would that one thing, be to do?
It's the least you could do.
So you've just solved a problem.
You assumed that all your data was
accurate.
They're double precision numbers.
You got them from, you know Bob or
whatever, some other intern, doesn't
matter.
You got the model and you did it.
What should you do now.
Generate a new A.
With the entries changed by a plausible
amount.
Everybody got this, right.
And you just simply test the, the x you
found before.
With the new A.
And if things are way off now,
then you know that you cannot ignore,
safely, robustus/g.
Everybody got this.
I mean this is incredibly simple, but it's
unbelievably important.
It's actually shocking to me, how many
people don't do this.
Right, so, this is just completely
standard.
Oh, wow, I've got a fantastic, a fantastic
force sequence to land an airplane,
you gotta see this.
It's just unbelievable, yeah.
People don't even notice it when they're,
you say okay, fine, here it is.
You absolutely have to go back.
And change the model, change the total
mass.
Move the center of gravity and
re-simulate the same thing with these
changed parameters.
And you have to do 10 hundred of these.
You know, after which by the way,
you know absolutely nothing, I might add,
technically.
But I mean from a Strict point of view,
right?
But at least you've done the common sense
check.
Everybody got this, right?
If you, if you come and say, I've got a
trading strategy, it's unbeleviable.
And they go, really, and you go,
oh my god, you should see what it did last
year, unbeleviable.
And then you'd say well did you try it on
the year before, yeah, no.
The main method, traditional method is for
handling uncertainty in data is to ignore
it.
And I would say actually that's a
perfectly respectable option.
Provided you do a posterior analysis of
the effected variation.
Then it's, then it's totally legit.
I mean, assuming the posterior analysis
reveals that it works fine.
Okay, now the next step is to have a
heuristic that kind of,
kind of is a heuristic for
making sure that things don't get too
wacky when the parameters change.
That'd be like regularization, absolutely
fine.
Again, you do a posterior analysis to
understand if it works.
And the new thing, this has been coming
up.
Maybe in the last, could be 20 years, but
then it was done by a handful of esoteric,
you know, work by academics.
It's now coming on mainline, main,
mainstream, it's this.
You simply take into account the
uncertainty directly in
the problem statement.
Okay?
And so, that, these are called rob, that's
robust optimization, and
this is a special case.
Okay.
Now we're jumping back to the specific.
That was the background,
we're jumping back to the specific problem
we're looking at.
So you have to have a model for how A
varies, right?
And in one, it's stock-, it's stochastic.
You would say A is random and you would
describe its distribution.
And the distribution could even be finite.
Like you just say it's got 25 values with
these probabilities, right?
By the way, that's an extremely reasonable
thing to do.
Because what you do, is if you track the
provinence of a,
and it came from other measurements and
data, then what you do is you'd go back to
someone there, it's like cross validation
or something, if you know what that is.
But you'd go back and you say here's a
model for my chemical process, and
you go, great.
how' did you get it?
You go from data.
And you go, you know what?
Fit me a separate model for every day of
the week.
I'd like you to fit a model for you
chemical process for
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday, Saturday, Sunday.
Right?
You get seven models now.
Now, by the way if you look at these a, so
now you have a Monday, a Tuesday, a,
by the way if they're all completely
different, you should just turn around and
go away.
Because basically you're hosed, there's
nothing you can do that,
there's nothing intelligent, this is not a
place for us to be doing anything.
Right?
because it basically means it's.
There's no consistency and it doesn't make
any sense.
Okay, fine.
So hopefully, all the entries, of a
Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday, there're close.
In a worse case, in a, in a worse case
robust, fitting or
approximation problem, you would do this.
You would say I'm not going to use a
stochastic model.
Instead, what I'm going to do is I'm
simply going to, I'm going to have a set
of values of A and I'm going to, I'm
going to judge my fit by the worst case.
Right?
And by the way,
there's everything in between these two.
Right?
So these are just two, and
there's incredible,
you know complete nonsense silly religious
wars between people who.
You know, I mean, and it makes no sense
out of a context, right?
And in, in any particular context,
it makes tons of sense as to discuss what
would be a reasonable robustness model.
But outside of a, context-free it makes no
sense whatsoever.
Right?
Mostly what you do, oh and this, oh this
is sometimes called mini-max.
Mini-max fitting.
this, that doesn't have a name.
Yeah it does.
It's called stochastic optimization.
OK.
So, that's the idea.
Now, solving these problem is tractable
only in special cases.
I mean, in a lot of cases, it's not
tractable at all.
But some are.
Here's a super duper simple example.
We have a matrix.
It has a one parameter variation.
It has A0 plus uA1.
>> And u varies, you know, let's say
between 1 and
minus 1 something like that, right?
So basically, in matrix space, you'll have
a little line segment, right?
You know, hopefully it's not a giant one,
right?
But you know, it's a little line segment
and
of course, in a more realistic one it's
varying in a ball.
I don't know, but this has a line segment,
that's it, right?
So, okay.
And you could actually easily imagine
where the dominant variation is
one line, right?
Because it could be some process that you
run.
And in fact to first order it's mostly
affected by, say, ambient temperature.
And so the ambient temperature goes from,
you know, ten c to 35.
And that changes the model.
I mean things like this happen all the
time.
Right.
So, what you do here, in this case, you
can solve all these problems, all of them.
And so, here are, this shows you a couple
of the solutions.
So, X nom simply ignores it entirely,
minimizes this.
Then, what you do is take this X, and I
calculate the norm,
here As a function of you and that's
plotted here so this is Xnom and
the nominal point is right here and look
at that of course by definition it has to
get the lowest value at this is the
nominal value, sure enough it does.
It gets the lowest value.
It's right there but then you see as U
changes, you start paying for it right?
By rising costs, okay?
So here's sot, the X stocastoc.
That minimizes the average over the
interval (-1,1).
So over here to here, that gives you this
one here.
Sorry, this one here, this, this one here.
This is a stochastic, right?
And you can see that, it, you pay for it
in nominal performance, right?
The stochastic one dip not as well.
So the nominal performance is a little bit
worse.
But now as u varies out to be 0.7, -0.8
you're actually doing much better.
Okay?
So everybody, I mean, this is kind of
clear, but that, that's the idea.
And the final one shows worst case.
And that's this last one.
It's very flat.
You've paid for the cost.
In nominal cost.
You do much worse than if it's nominal.
But if you look at the mini max over minus
one, one, you do very well.
Right, so this is just to illustrate very
simple thing.
Okay so we can also handle, I mean, some,
I,
as an example of, in anything as an
analytical solution.
That would be stocastic robust lee
squares.
So let's work that out.
This is, this is absolutely traditional,
and it It's kind of cool, actually, and
it relates to something we were talking
about earlier.
It's this.
Suppose your Matrix A has the form A bar,
a nominal one plus U,
where U is random, 0 mean, and has
expected value transposed to U as P.
Okay?
So we want to minimize The expected value
of the square of the two norms of
this thing, of course the expectation is
over the distribution of U, here, right,?
So, just work that out, I mean you expand
this thing, the term,
the cross-terms, like here, when you
expand this quadratic,
there's a cross term which is x transpose,
U transpose, A bar X minus b.
You take the expected value over U.
U has 0 mean.
Those go away.
So the cross-terms drop out in the
expectation here.
Right?
Leaving you with the nominal cost plus
this thing and you get that, and
it's super cool.
You recognize that immediately.
That's regularization.
It's quadratic regularization.
And, in fact, it's even cooler.
It basically says, if you do Tikhonov
regularization like this, what you can
claim to be doing, is you're actually
minimizing this, which is super cool.
And you say, your minimizing This thing
where, instead of thinking of the matrix
A as fixed you're actually taking into
account that every entry varies.
They are all independent and have a
variance which is I don't know something
like Delta over N I mean you can figure
out what it is, right?
Everybody got this?
So, it's actually super cool.
So if you do taken off regularization or,
or Ridge regression.
I guess if you're in statistics,
you do ridge regression, you don't have to
justify it to anybody.
But if you're in a field where they don't
have a special name for
taking off regularization, and they ask
what are you doing?
You can say oh I'm doing robustly squares.
I'm taking into account minor variations
in the As.
Everybody got it?
Now, we can do some worst-case ones.
I'm not going to go into the details here
because they're kind of hairy.
This, this is quite new.
This is something that's like 15, 20 years
old.
So let's do the case where the matrix A
actually is,
lies in an ellipsoid of matrices.
Again, completely reasonable.
and, what we really want to minimize is
the worst case.
So, it's going to be a weird thing, if you
like, its a game or
something like that, basically, you commit
to x first,
then your opponent will choose the worst
possible A.
That's what this is right?
So this is the, so something like that
and, and
there turns out, something like this can
solve exactly.
Right?
So if you work it out and
again I'm not going to go through any of
the details because they're quite hairy
and in some sense it doesn't really
Matter.
I mean you should go back over and check
it.
It turns out, that here when, one,
when the opponent is calculating what's
the worst thing I should do,
they've commit-ed to x, and I'm going to
find the, [INAUDIBLE] you end up
solving this problem, and that is a non
convex problem if I ever saw one, right?
Because the objective.
Is you're maximizing, a quadratic.
Right?
Convex quadratic.
Right.
Now, you haven't seen this yet.
Maybe you did or something but it's maybe
time for you to know this.
So, I'm going to say it.
I'm going to use this as an excuse to let
you know.
There are some generic, non-convex
problems that can be solved.
'Kay?
And, the simplest one,
has a very simple and short description
length.
Any optimization problem involving two
quadratics, can be solved globally, 'kay?
Everybody got that?
That's in the appendix of the book.
You should read it.
Or remember what I just said.
Okay, because it actually comes up in a
whole bunch of different applications,
right?
So, and, and that's convexity not
convexity.
And you know a lot, and by the way you
know this already.
If I walked up to you and
I said, oh you know please help me solve
you know this problem.
A is symmetric you know.
Right?
Something like that I said please maximize
this thing.
Right?
How do you maximize that subject to that?
Well that, that sure is no convex
optimization problem.
Right?
Because This thing was not concave,
unless A is un, un, un, unless A is, is
negative definite.
Okay, negative semi-definite.
Right?
There's no way that's never a convex
constraint.
Right?
That, that's a sphere, right?
So, that's a hideously non-convex problem.
But everyone here knows the answer, knows
this can be solved.
I mean, it's basically an eigenvalue
problem, right?
The answer is the largest, eigen,
the eigenvector, corresponding, it's the
largest eigenvalue, and blah blah blah.
Everybody got that?
Right, so alright.
This fits the thing I'm saying here.
That is an optimization problem and it
involves exactly two
quadratic functions and the general
statement is this- any
optimization problem with exactly two
quadratic functions can be solved exactly.
And so what that says is, you know if
someone says, what are you doing?
I'm taking a class in [INAUDIBLE], oh, is
it interesting?
I don't know.
And they, they say well are all problems
convexed?
You go oh no, no, no.
And then someone says name a widely used,
useful problem that's not convex?
The first thing you should mention I would
hope would be things like
singular value decomposition, PCA Eigen
vaulues, okay?
We know what this says, this says those
are convex, sorry.
So I mean it's kind of weird and obscure.
And the reason, by the way, is that the
duals
of these problems have 0 duality gap.
Anyway, alright.
So thi, that was just my weird little
aside.
But this is an advanced thing.
This is not a simple thing.
But it's an extremely good thing to know,
right?
So, and, if you include these, you'd be
very hard pressed to find problems,
any problem you can solve that is not
convex if you include these.
So that, and that is an open challenge.
So So, okay.
So, this one actually can be solved by
solving its dual, which is this SDP.
Doesn't matter.
The, the fact is zero duality gap, right?
so, okay, now it's fine.
Because you want to minimize over choice
of x.
This thing, but this thing has just been
expressed as a minimization function.
Right, and therefor you minimize both at
the same time.
You solve this SDP, and
you solve, you actually solve exactly this
robust least squares problem, right?
Here, what this is the following is, we
have the,
I mean this is a very simple thing, we
actually have, it's a two dimensional.
ellipsoid, I guess you might even call it
an ellipse or
something like that, of A matrices.
Now, you commit to X and then we find the,
we'll find
like the worst [INAUDIBLE] plot here is
the histogram of the residuals, right?
Now here we'll take U, uniformly
distributed on the unit disk.
Okay?
And we'll take several values of x.
The first is, suppose you just completely
ignore uncertainty, and
you solve the least squares problem
minimize A zero X minus B.
That's the nominal problem.
You minimize that, and you get this
distribution of residuals.
Right?
So, they're all over the place.
And You know, some of the residuals are
four and five,, and
by the way, how would you describe what
happened in this situation on the left?
Dumb luck.
That's exactly what that is, right?
You committed to an x, in fact there are
as that make the residual smaller than you
thought it was going to be.
But you paid for it over here.
Okay, now you turn on Tickenoff
regularization.
And you can even imagine, I mean, one
could even make a cartoon of this, right?
You can imagine turning off the Tikhonov
regularization knob, when at 0,
you get this distribution, 'kay?
As I turn it up,
what happens is that distribution will,
will end up looking like this.
This is sort of the best looking one, the
Tikhonov regularization way, and
you can see it did exactly what it was
supposed to do.
Right.
Tikhonov regularization is something like
a heuristic for it's a heuristic for
giving you a robust solution and
you can see and here robustness we're
going to make it very big.
You get a tighter distribution of
residuals, okay.
And in fact the expected value of this
distribution is smaller than this one.
I mean, I'm not going to work it out
because it's too simple here.
But you can see,
it's simply, from a robustness point of
view, a better solution.
OK?
So this shows you exactly what people have
known for,
I don't know, fifteen hundred years.
That you had, you had regularization and
one interpretation of regularization is to
make your solution more robust to
variation here.
OK.
Now the exact Robustly squirts the one
that minimizes the worst case
residual over this, over this ellipsoid of
matrices,
is the one you obtain by solving this this
sdp here, right?
So you solve that sdp there, and
you get the following distribution of
residuals right here.
And this is, right there, that is, that's
the number.
Right.
That, that is the optimal,
that is the globally optimal number for
the best you can do.
Right?
And so this is kind of the idea.
And I think these distributions sort of
explain everything.
Right?
About what you're,
what you're trying to do here and what
robust optimization does.
Right?
So this is the kind of, this is,
this is the idea.
Notice that when you, I mean we can
anthropomorphize this a little bit but
one thing interesting to notice is all of
these, everything over here,
can either be taken off regularized or
denominal solution.
All of those are cases where by dumb luck
you did better than
the robust lead-squares.
Right so and what's interesting though is
when you
typically push the worst case residual
down usually an effect is
that actually the best case actually
[LAUGH] goes the other way, right?
I mean this is sort of natural but, and
again what I'm saying now is extremely
vague.
These are not the arguments you would be
allowed to make.
In public but it's just something to point
out.