In this section we're going to talk about
convex optimization problems and
we'll start in detail.
We'll start by talking about what's an
optimization problem, we'll talk about
what are the parts in an optimization
problem, how do you define one.
We'll get quickly to what's a convex
optimization problem?
We'll talk about quasi-convex
optimization, and then, for
a while where going to look at just common
families of
optimization problems linear programming,
quadratic programming.
Something called geometric programming.
Then we'll look at generalized inequality
constraints and
the most famous of these is semidefinite
programming.
And finally, we'll look at the idea of
vector optimization.
That's when your objective function is
actually a vector and not a scalar.
Okay?
So, let's start.
What's an optimization problem?
Well, an optimization problem is
something.
It's described and written this way.
It says minimize.
F0 of x, that is the objective function.
X is a vector in rn, that's called the
optimization variable, or
another name for it, which is a great
name, is the decision variable.
That's wonderful because it kind of tells
you that's what you have to decide.
So f0 of x is the objective, here, you're
being told minimize.
What that means, of course, is this these
smaller F0 of X is, the happier you are.
It, it is, that defines what it means to
be better.
And then, there are constraints.
This says subject to, and you have
inequality constraints,
these are of the form FI of X is less than
0, and there's M of these.
And there are equality constraints.
Also subject to h i of x is less, is equal
to 0, and there are p of these.
So here, f0 is the objective or cost
function.
F i these are the inqualties,
these are called the inequality constraint
functions.
And hi are equality constraint functions.
And, although we'll see many,
many examples I can say a little bit about
where some of these things come up.
Usually f0 is an objective, or a cost, and
in any case it's something that you
want to make small, and you're happier the
smaller it is.
The inequality constraint functions f1,
often these will have to do with something
like a resource limit.
And so, this will tell you something about
a resource limit, or
really how much under the resource limit
you are, the, the the capacity.
And what this is usually has the
interpretation of
don't violate a resource limit.
hi of x, equality constraints tend to be,
again we'll see tons of examples, but
these might arise in things like balance,
that one thing has to balance another.
For example, a market has to clear, that
means that the total amount sold has to
match the total amount that's being
bought.
Something like that.
Right, so that's where you would get
these, and we'll see lots of examples.
oh, I should mention one thing.
That is, that you can also maximize a
function in
which case it's not called a cost
function.
If you maximize an objective function,
the objective function is often called a
utility.
That's one name for it.
But it can also be something much more
specific like profit, or
something like that, or, or
some other quantity that's obviously good
depending on the application.
Right, and entire fields, we'll use
preferentially either minimizing
a cost or, maximizing a a utility or
profit or something like that.
Right, so and you can joke about what that
means about the people in those fields and
like, you know, what their psychological
makeup is, or something.
It's not a big deal, because if you wanted
to maximize a utility,we could then,
we could minimize negative utility.
And it's useful to have a standard, our
standard will be minimized.
Because will have a lot of equations that
later involved,
constructs that involve a minimization and
you have to turn them around in your head
when you're maximizing and
then you get a headache, so it's easier
just to have a fixed clear version of it.
Okay, now the set of x, for which f i of x
is less than or
equal to zero for all of them.
And for which h i of x, is equal to zero
for all of them.
Such points are called feasible.
That's called feasible set.
And among the, on the feasible set you
evaluate the objective,
this is a set of numbers, right?
It's the, it's the objective values for
all x which are feasible and
the infimum of that in set of numbers,
that's like the minimum.
That's called p star and that's the
optimal value of this minimization
problem, Oh, so for people who haven't
seen it, you can read inf as min.
Min is a completely standard function, and
it means only one thing, it has no other
meaning in mathematics.
That meaning is this,
it takes as argument, a finite set of real
numbers, period.
And it returns the smallest of them,
period.
There's no other definition of min.
Inf is in fact something like min
generalized to infinite sets.
It's something like the, its the greatest
lower bound people say.
Its the largest number that's smaller than
all of the other numbers in the set.
And then an example would be the inf of 0,
1 is 0 for example.
So, you would not write the min, except
very informally.
Okay, I should make a, let's see, a couple
more comments I wanted to make.
Oh, one is this.
It is absolutely standard that the inf of
the empty set is plus infinity.
Again, there is no no variation in that,
that's, that's always as is.
And if you do that, various rules about
infimum hold in this case.
And if a, if a set is unbounded below,
that means that, for
example here, there are x's Which satisfy
all the constraints but for
which f zero of x can be made as negative
as you like.
Right?
Then you waould say the problem is
unbounded below and we would simply say p
star is minus infinity.
So that's the idea.
I mean from an optimization point of view
I guess that's the best thing that can
ever possibly happen although what it
really suggests is that your
model is wrong.
It hasn't been set up correctly or
something like that.
By the way this has got a very amusing
name in some cases right?
There's at least one case I know where if
when p star is minus infinity,
it's referred to as Euphoric breakdown,
which I think is just a great term for it.
It means, it means that, it means that,
that you can be as happy as you like.
Anyway, I won't go on.
Right.
That's b stars infinity.
Okay.
So, this is a optimization bottom standard
form.
Oh, and I wanted to say one more thing.
Never confuse the mathematical operator
min, which is a function that takes as
argument a set of, a finite set of real
numbers and returns the minimum.
And this word minimize, they are
absolutely different,
although some people kind of use the same,
same word for it.
I don't approve of that.
It's not so bad as long as they know what
they're doing but they're different.
Minimize is not min.
So min is a function that takes something
like this, right?
Zero minus one two right and it gives you
minus one.
There's a function.
Minimize you should think of as Is as
something that is
part of an optimization problem.
And the way I think of this optimization
problem,
it is not a number; this is a number.
This is not a number; this is an object.
It's an, it's like, it's an optimization
problem object, if you like to think it,
of this, in terms of, like,
object-oriented programming.
That's an object minimized Is,
is a key word that introduces an attribute
of an optimization object.
That's what it is.
So this is saying that problem, you know,
dot objective, is f0.
That's what it's saying.
Subject to again is something that's a
keyword that tells you what follows that
is a set of constraints for that problem,
okay, and so you wouldn't say
you would never say this optimization
problem has, you know, is three.
What you can say is that its optimal value
is three.
That makes sense.
Okay.
So we should talk about the idea of an
optimal and locally optimal point.
You say X is feasible if you're in the
domain of the objective and
you satisfy all the constraints.
Now that implies you're in the domain of
all the constraint functions.
Right?
And a feasible x is optimal if its
objective value is equal to
the optimal value of the problem.
Okay?
So that means well, just what it says.
It means that X is, gets an objective
value that is as good as
the least possible value among all other
feasible points, right?
And we'll let X opt be the set of optimal
points.
It could, the X opt can be empty, notice
there is no optimal point,
it could have a single entry, could be a
singleton, as a unique optimal point.
And it, it could actually be an a set with
two, three points, finite number of
points; or it could be a set with an
infinite number of points, right?
So, in convex optimization, the second one
can't happen, well, sorry, the third one.
It can, if you have two points a-, and
then, in, for a convex problem,
which we'll talk about shortly it means
that you have an infinite number.
So, but we'll, we'll talk about that later
in a bit.
Okay.
Now, locally optimal is a point which had
the following property.
It says that there's a positive r so
it's that if I add the constraint, that
you are no farther than r away from x.
So x is the point that we're going to
certify as locally optimal.
Then x really is optimal for this problem.
Something like that.
So that's, that's what it that's what that
means.
So let's see what that means, here, let's
draw a function looks like this.
Draw in fact Our function will be this
one, x cubed minus three x.
That looks like this.
It's got a, it, at plus 1 it's here.
Sorry, that's at minus one.
Right?
And at plus one it's got a local minimum.
And the claim is that this is a local
minimum because if I
were to add the constraint that you're
between here and here.
Then for sure that value is that's x
equals 1 is the optimal point for
that problem.
Okay.
Let's look at some simple examples.
So, first it says let's minimize 1 over x
and here x has to be positive, right?
That's because that's the domain.
That's the declaration of the domain of f
0.
And in this case there's no optimal point,
right?
because we, goes something like this,
Here's here's x, and the point is that the
larger x is, the smaller 1 over x is, and
you can make this number as small as you
like.
You cannot make it 0.
You want to say, you would like to make it
0 by saying x equals infinity, but
that's not allowed.
So the infimum of these points is 0.
Okay?
But there is no point x for
which 1 over x is 0, so this, this this
thing has no optimal point.
Okay?
Another one would be minus log x, so minus
log x would look oh, something like this.
But it would come down at 0.
At 1 it would go through the value 0 and
then it would keep doing down.
Very slowly, but it keeps going down.
And, it goes down as low as you'd like.
That says p star minus infinity because
the infimum of all these points,
you just take x again as big as you like.
Next example is going to be X log X
negative entrpoy, so
for negtive entropy here I'll draw that.
The negetive entropy function looks like
this and goes up like that alright?
So for this function and the domain is all
positive numbers here This really,
really does have an optimal value.
It's achieved at, sort of, 1 over E,
the value 1 over E and the value is minus
1 over E, right there.
Right?
So, this is, this is an example of a
problem where these first 2
are pathologies of different kinds.
And this one is the first one,
where it's had sort of has a
non-pathological answer, right?
So it says, if you want to minimize
negative entropy, or we could say if
you want to maximize entropy you would
take x equals 1 over e as optimal, right.
Oh, I should say this log of course is a
log base e.
Not log base 2, um, [COUGH] okay.
This example we've already seen.
This is the one, where it goes up and then
down and then up again.
That's a locally optimal point, but p star
is minus infinity.
One thing that will come up at various
times in this course is the idea of
implicit versus explicit constraints.
So, implicit constraints are the
constraints, as an in, we don't really say
this, but the domain of a problem is the
intersections of the domains of the,
all of the fi including zero, that's the
objective function and
all the constraint functions and all the
equality constraints.
And so we'll call that the domain of the
problem.
And what it means is that if you ask
about,
if you propose an x that's outside the
domain of the problem.
It's it means it's inappropriate, it's
inappropriate because what it means is
if you're outside the domain of the
objective, it says I,
I can't even evaluate the objective to
tell you whether or not it's good or bad.
Right, so now in our, when F0 is convex
and we use infinite valued extensions.
There's a seamless way to handle this and
what we do is we simply say.
It's plu, we return plus infinity for
being outside the domain, that works just
fine.
In the general case, though, you might
return a token that says something like,
out of domain.
Okay.
Now on the other hand, these are explicit
constraints, right?
So, it says, these, when you actually say
for example, you know,
F1 of X has to be less than or equal to,
that's an explicit constraint.
It says, please evaluate F1 and
then compare that number to zero sorry, to
compare it to zero.
If you are less than or equal to zero,
it's just fine.
If you are above zero, it is completely
unacceptable.
Right, so by the way, you can, there's a
subtle difference here, and
probably this is not a bad way to think of
it.
There's actually quite a different thing,
it's two different types of
bad things happen if you propose in an
optimization problem a point which is
out of the domain of the problem, versus
one in that is infeasible.
Right, so, in one sense I would say that
the first one is a little bit worse.
I mean, practically they're the same
thing.
So, if you propose an x, and it's just,
like, you, and, and it, and
what's returned is a message that says,
this x,
I can't even evaluate the constraint
number 3.
I don't even get a number, right?
I get something like a nan, nan, which is
not a number, right?
So then you can't compare that to 0, or
something like that and so, that sort of,
in some sense that's worse, I, maybe this
is just, maybe this is just subjective,
but that's worse than actually having F3,
having all the functions evaluate.
And then having one of const, inequality
constraint functions be positive.
So, okay.
Now a problem is unconstrained if it has
no explicit constraints.
Does not mean, I mean you could, you could
have implicit constraints.
Here's an example of a function like that,
or of an example.
Is minimize f0 of x, subject to, sorry,
minimize f0 of x,
which is the sum of minus log bi minus ai
transpose x.
Okay?
So here's the, just one f0, there are no
fis.
None.
No hi's.
And so here, there's there are implicit
constraints that the arguments to
the log have to be positive.
Right.
So you have to have bi
strictly bigger than ai transposed x.
If it's equal to 0, or worse negative
you're just out of the domain and log.
If you're using the extended value
extensions and everything's implemented
correctly, and you evaluate something
where this evaluates out to minus .2.
Then it might just correctly return, plus
infinity for minus log at that term.
So that's an example.
Okay.
So a feasibility problem is a, well it's a
simplified one, and
it's sometimes written this way: you'd say
find x and
then subject to a set of inequality
constraints.
Inequality and equality as well.
These are both optional, well I guess we
could have a short discussion about
unconstrained feasibility problems, right.
So those are, those are very easy because
any x is, any x is optimal.
Okay.
So this is a,
this is a feasibility problem.
And actually it fits in the general
framework in a very simple way
because it's exactly the same as the
general problem where you
minimize an objective that's just
identically zero.
It just works.
Everything, the semantics, just works
perfectly, because here's what happens.
If you have a point that is feasible for
the feasible, I mean, if it satisfies the
constraints, right?
Then, well, the objective function is 0.
Right, and so if you, if,
if this problem is feasible, the set of
feasible points will be non empty.
And that means there'll be a point whose
objective value is 0.
If you're feasible, the only objective
value you can have is 0.
So, it's optimal.
So any point, any point that's feasible is
optimal, and the converse is very simple.
If this is infeasible,
it says that there's no point that has
where that satisfies all the constraints.
Right, therefore the optimal value is
define to be the infimum of
the function which always returns 0 over
the empty set, and
that happens to be plus indicated by
convention.
I mean it looks strange but it actually
all just works out fine.
Okay.
So finally we get to the formal definition
of a convex optimization problem.
So that's something like this.
It says it's an optimization problem, but
it's a, so
it inherits everything from an
optimization problem, all the notions that
you have there, like feasibility,
optimality and everything else.
But there are some constraints.
The constraints are this, the objective
function and
all inequality constraints have to be
convex functions.
So that's one requirement, and
the equality constraint functions must be
half-line right?
So it's a normal for people to write it
this way, but
if you'd like you could write this as ai
transpose x minus bi.
you would define this to be gi of x and
that's equal to zero, something like that.
Okay?
And so, but
your this would be you'd define these
functions this way.
But it's more common to write it that way,
okay?
And if f0 is, if the objective is
quasiconvex,
then the problem is called a quasiconvex
optimization problem.
Now, the quality constraints here, which
have to be linear.
Well, which is kind of informal speech for
affine, right.
Because there's a lot of situations where
you talk about linear equalities and
what you really mean are affine equalities
but people have been calling them
linear equalities for hundreds of years so
we'll stick with that.
In that case, it's, it's typical to
collect those into a matrix, right, so
that Ax equals b.
Each row is one equality constraint in the
problem written out
with the equality constrainsts listed out
separately.
Alright, so, okay.
And people would call this someth,
I mean you might call it a vector equality
constraint.
It doesn't matter.
Okay.
Now, one very important property here is
that the feasible set of
a convext optimization problem is convex.
So in fact is the optimal set, right?
So, and that's very easy to see.
The feasible set is simply the set of X
that satisfy AX equals B,
and then FI of X is less than or equal to
0.
And that's going to be a convex set.
Actually it's very easy to show directly,
but you know it anyway.
It's a sublevel of convex sets, and it's
an intersection of that's an affine set.
The, the, the, set of feasible points for
a x equals b and for
each of the convex functions.
Here, it's a sublevel set which is convex
and
therefore it's an an intersection of m
convex sets, n plus 1.
N sublevel sets and 1 affine set defined
by the equality constraints.
Okay.
So let's look at an example.
And actually it's meant to bring out a
very imporatnt point.
And that is that convexity is an attribute
of the description of the problem.
So this is actually very important.
It is not.
So there's a more abstract definition of
convex optimization,
which is a convex optimization problem,
is,
is a problem where you minimize a convex
function over a convex set.
Right?
We'll see that this is one, this example.
But it is not a convex optimization
problem by our stricter definition.
It depends on the description.
So here, let's look at the problem,
it says minimize, it's a problem with two
variables.
It says minimize the sum of the two
squares, but
you know what the objective function looks
like.
It's a, it's a bolt so it kind of goes up,
and it says minimize the norm of x or
minimize the norm squared of x.Subject to,
the first constraint says f1 of x,
that's going to be x1 over 1 plus x
squared that's less than or equal to 0.
Well it doesn't take long for
you to figure out that's not a convex
function of x 1 and x 2.
It just isn't, okay.
And the last equality constraint is this.
It says x 1 plus x 2 squared is 0.
Well, X1 plus X2 quantity squared is
definitely not a convex function.
Would you look at it carefully and
you realize these two constraints define a
convex set.
Why?
Because to say X1 plus X2 squared is 0
is the same as saying X1 plus X2 is 0, so
that's just a, that's a line.
Right?
This constraint x1 over 1 x2 squared less
than or equal to 0.
This thing is positive, so you just get
rid of it, since x1 less than or
equal to 0, right?
So in fact the feasible set is a ray, it's
just a ray, and it's perfectly convex.
So this problem is minimizing a convex
function over a convex set, but
it is not a convex problem by our strict
definition, right?
So our strict definition is extremely
simple.
It's basically problem dot objective dot
is convex, you call that method.
And if it's, if it's not, then it's end of
story.
Right.
After that you iterate over the
constraints and
you check if every ineqaulity constraint
function is convex and if the answer is
no, it's all over and then check every
equality constraint function and
every single one has to be affine okay so
that's our, that's our definition.
So we would say that this problem is
equivalent to this problem.
And we're not going to use I mean we're
not going to go
into a fancy formal definition of what
equivalent means.
I think like you would in a CS Theory
class.
Instead we'll just say, we'll have a
informal definition.
The informal definition is this, that two
problems are equivalent if from one u
can readily compute the solution of the
other.
Right and vice versa right.
So eh, here it's extremely simple the
sense in which this problem Is
equivalent to that one.
It's a, here's, here's the method that
does it.
It's, you simply copy x.
So, if you solve this problem then the
solution of that is also a well,
a solution of that is a solution of that,
and vice versa.
If you have a solution of this, it's a
solution of that, alright.
So I, I guess that satisfies this general
idea that it's easy to
construct the solut-, because there's
nothing to do.
Okay, this problem is convex because the
objective is convex function,
the constraint you check the inequality
constraint.
You look at the lefthand side, the lefhand
side is x1.
You ask whether the function x1 is convex,
it is.
Done.
You look at the constraint, at the quality
constraint function.
You ask whether X1 plus X2 is an affine
function, it is, done.
So, that said, that's a convex.
And the, this'll be important, it'll come
up at several points.
Okay.
Now.
Here's a you know, very important fact
about, and
basically elementary fact, about convex
optimization.
And that's this, any locally optimal point
of a convex optimization problem is
globally optimal, alright.
So, it's a very basic fact, it's very easy
to show.
But it's very important, actually it's
quite interesting.
It says that if, if you cannot improve,
if, if you find a point where you
cannot walk, there's nowhere around you
where you can improve over what you have.
Then you don't have to look farther
afield, I mean that's what this says.
We'll look at the proof, and in fact
instead of the proof I
might just draw a picture and then that'll
make everything clear.
So here's what we're going to do, I'm
going take a point and
I'm going to say that x is locally
optimal, here, and
what I'll do is I'll take I'll imagine
that y is globally optimal.
By the way, when you talk about local
optimality and you want to
make sure you mean just optimality, you
say it is globally optimal.
So here I'll say y is globally optimal and
not only that, it beats the local optimum.
So this says, this says that there is a
locally optimal point x
which is actually beaten by another point.
It's that simple.
What I'm going to do is draw the line
segment leading x to y and
we'll look a a point.
That goes on that line segment here,
right.
So if I take theta equals zero, I start at
x,
and as theta goes up to one, I approach y.
And what I'll do, is I'll take the, oh I
should, I should mention something.
Both x and y are feasible, for the convex
optimization problem.
This z is a convex combination therefore
its feasible.
So that there's no doubt about
feasibility.
So we only have to worry about the
objective function.
So lets look at the objective function.
Lets just plot f zero as a function of
Theta.
Well its going to look like this.
Here's here's theta equals zero, here's
theta equals one.
When theta equals zero I'm going to plot f
of z.
And Z in turn depends on theta.
So, F of, if I take 0 then that
coressponds to Z equals X and
I get some F of X so, there we go, that's
F 0 of X here okay.
then I look at 1 then z is y.
and I take that.
And by def, by our assumption here it's
smaller so this is f zero of y.
Okay?
But now, let's go back and look at this
the local optimality of x.
That says.
Yet there's a little range like that where
in that range you certainly can't,
you are not,
you can't do better than that Zero of X
because that X is locally optimal.
So that say that whatever happens in the
funciton,
it has to be above that little horizontal
segment.
Okay, so, that's that's the idea so, now
now we got a problem.
And it's a geometric problem I mean we
could work the proof is 3
lines alegbraically but the picture is
actually maybe better.
The problem is this F zero restricted to
the line segement between X and
Z that's a convex function of theta.
And now we got a little problem because we
have a convex fucntion of
theta that starts out flat and somehow
ends up lower and
you can't do that and your eyeball tells
you that.
If you can work it out algebraically it's
3 lines and it's an equality and
stuff like that.
At some point there's no way a convex
function can start out flat and
end up down here.
Just can't do it.
So.
Okay.
So I'll, that's my, that's my picture,
proof, of this.
Okay.
Now we can work out, the optimality
criterion for a differentiable function.
This is useful.
It's a good way to start.
Later in the class when we talk about
duality, we will work out
optimality conditions for full general
case with all the constraints, everything.
But for now, what we're going to do is
we're going to just work out
some very simple ones actually based on an
inequality for
differentiable functions and it's this.
A point X is optimal, this is for the
special case of the objective being
differentiable so it says if the following
is true the gradient of F 0 X.
Is transposed times y minus x is bigger
than zero for all feasible y.
So, that's the that's the condition.
And a picture would look something like
this.
This dark set, this is the feasible set,
okay?
And these curved, these dashed lines here,
those are the level sets of f.
Right?
So, these are, this is f getting smaller,
so
as you, as you go down these level sets
that's f getting smaller and so you're,
the semantics of an optimization problem
is that you want to, you want to move as
far as you can, sort of to the smallest
level curve of f0 while staying in here.
And this, the optimal point is clearly,
it's unique and it's right there.
Right?
One thing you notice that, again just
visually,
it's very easy to show even without it
without appealing to any,
any sort of visual stuff, is visually what
you see is that the,
is that in fact the, the tangent to x is
orthogonal to the gradient there.
Or in other words, the gradient is an
outward normal for x, negative gradient.
Okay?
And so, that's what this says.
This says that the gradient at an optimal
point, here,
defines a supporting hyperplane to the
feasible set at that point.
Right?
So, and
there's some special cases we can do.
Like, for example let's do the case where
it's unconstrained.
So, there are no constraints.
There's no, there's no constraints.
So all feasible y just means all y.
What under what conditions would it be
true that the gradient of f,
0 of x transpose, y minus x, when would
that be bigger than 0 for all y?
Well?
>> I don't know, let's figure it out.
>> [INAUDIBLE] That would work, if the
gradient were identically 0.
In fact, that's, that's the condition.
That's if and only if the gradient is 0.
Why is that?
Well, if the gradient weren't 0, actually
suggest a y.
That ends the story right away.
How about this one?
How about Y equals minus T, times the
gradient F of X, right there.
There you go, OK?
So if I plugged that in, then the first
term Here is minus t,
times the norm square of the gradient.
Now t is a parameter.
I can take it as big as I like, right, and
I will, I can certainly arrange it to be
big enough to make this inequality true.
Right?
Therefore the only option is that that, is
that the gradient itself vanishes and
we have reconstructed the, you know, the
high school condition, right?
The gradient vanishes.
Well it's a little bit different from my
school.
Here's why.
Because here it's a necessary and
sufficient condition, right so,
there's it's a necessary condition.
It's sufficient because of convexity.
OK, so that's, we've reconstructed
gradient equal 0 is the con-, is the nec-,
in this case the necessary and sufficient
condition for optimality.
Okay, how about an equality constrained
problem.
Well here, you want to minimize F 0
subject to AX equals B and
here you can work out the, the conditions
it's not very hard.
But it says X is optimal if and only if
there's a point in the domain where
AX equals B and The gradient of f0, right
plus a transpose nu equals 0.
Now, you should recognize this as
something like a,
this is Lagrange multipliers.
We will talk about this in complete detail
when we talk about duality.
But, that's, so, but it's a hint.
And this comes just from the same the same
argument.
That basically, the argument would go
something like this.
You must have the gradient of F, F zero of
X.
Transposed, Y minus X.
That has to be positive for all Y that
satisfy AX equals B.
Okay?
But wait a minute, because X also
satisfies Ax equals B.
Right so, that says if I take the
difference the difference is between X and
Y is the null space right?
So we can re write it this way we can say
the condition is grad X 0 of X
transpose times Z is positive for all Z in
the null space of A.
Alright because.
If Y satisfies,
AX equals B it's a generally element that
satisfies that right?
And X satisfies AX equals B and we do that
because it's our second assumption here.
Then the differences in the null space of
A and vice versa I should add.
Okay?
This says that the gradient has to make a
non negative.
With every element of the null space.
But the null space is a vector space, so
this couldn't, if this were positive,
right?
If this were positive for some z, minus z
is also in the null space.
And if I plug in minus z, I get something
negative.
So the conclusion here is that in fact,
you have to have grad f0 of x has to be,
it has to have a 0 inner product for all
elements in the null space of A.
OK.
That we can write.
That says graph f of zero of x is n.
The null space of a perk.
I'm just rewriting that's a macro.
That's the definition.
If you make a zero in your product with
everything in a certain set You're in
the perp of that set, the orthogonal
complement, that this.
And this thing,
you'll remember from linear algebra, is
the range of a transpose.
Hey, that says that I can write grad f
zero x as a transpose times something.
And I, and there's something I'm going to
choose, I can write anything I like, but
I'm going to write it as, how about
negative nu, there.
OK?
And I'm done.
Right?
So just using linear algebra, and
the general optimality condition, we
re-covered high school, what is this?
Maybe not high school, okay, Lagrange
multipliers.
Oh except for one very important
difference, this is necessary and
sufficient here.
OK.
Here's a little bit more involved,
I won't go through the derivation but its
minimization over non negative or than.
So you want to minimize f zero of x
subject to x bigger than zero and
if you work out the conditions its Quite
simple, it's this.
X has to be bigger than or equal to 0, but
that, well that's feasibility.
And the followup, whenever xi is 0, the
gradient, here, the partial derivitave
of f0 with respect to xi, has to be bigger
than or equal to 0.
Right, and so you can actually figure out
what that means.
If this number where plus 1, it says that
if you propose to increase xi
a little bit, if you move it a little bit
away, it says that the function goes up.
What you can't have is you couldn't have
this thing negative.
Because that, that would say then if you
move a little bit in that direction,
the function value would go down and you
just got a better point.
Okay?
So I think this is, I mean it's intuitive,
but
you could just, you can work it out
directly from the conditions here.
Well, the condition is very simple read f0
of x transposed y minus x
has to be bigger than or equal to zero for
all feasible y.
Ok, so we've already said a little bit
about equivalent complex problems, and
I'll say actually just a little bit more.
And we'll actually catalog some
interesting typical.
Equivilant pairs of problems, right.
So we'll use an informal notion of
equivilance.
It's not the formal equivilence of
reduction of one problem to another that
you see in computer science, but it could
be made formal but there's no reason for
us to do that.
So the idea is, two problem w-, a problem
it is equiv-,
two problems are equivalent if you can get
the solution, if from the solution of one,
you can get the solution of the other with
modest work, and vice versa.
In other words, what you could do if you
want to think in a very practical way,
you can think of this.
If someone handed you a solver for
one, you could write a wrapper That would
be a solver for the other.
And you have to have wrapper go both
directions.
Okay?
So, in other words, if you say this
problem is equivalent to that, you have to
be able to provide the wrapper that says
give me an instance of this problem and
then, gimme the solution of an instance of
this problem,
I'll get a solution of this problem.
And vice versa.
Okay.
So let's look at some examples.
By the way we're going to use all of these
things, so,
there, there actually we're going to use
them later, there, it's quite important.
So the first observation is this,
eliminating equality constraints.
So the way you do that is this.
You have ax equals b, but we, we know what
all x that satisfy ax equals b looks like.
It's a, that's nothing but a,
an affine set, and we can go to a free
parameter representation.
So pre-parameter representation says we
first find a point that satisfies Ax
equals b.
Oh, let me ask a question.
Suppose on that, that step fails, so I,
I attempt to find a solution of Ax equals
b and there is none.
What do I do?
If Ax equals b has no solution.
I can actually return, like, I can say I
actually don't even, I didn't even look at
F 0 or FI, but I can tell you for sure
that your problem's not feasible.
Because no point satisfies your quality
constraints, okay?
Otherwise you find 1, and you compute a
matrix, F,
whose columns are span The null space of
a.
And the the general solution of Ax=b looks
like this, it's x=fz + x0.
Now normally the columns of f would be
chosen to be independent, but that's
actually totally irrelevant, in which case
they're a basis for the null space of A.
So what it is is you compute Matrices.
A matrix F and a vector x zero.
X zero is by the way called a particular
solution.
And, I don't know what the name is for F.
A basis, basis for the null space or
something.
I don't know.
Anyway, so, that says that the gen, a
general vector x that says A x equals b,
that happens if and only if there exists a
z.
So that x is fz plus x0.
Okay?
I back substitute that and my new problem
looks like, like this here.
And here we make a couple of comments.
First of all, the following is true.
This function is convex in z.
Because it's pre composition of convex
function with an aft line function.
These functions are convex in z for the
same reason.
So, the objective and
the inequality constraints in this
transform problem are convex.
Okay.
Now, no, then.
How would it work,
how would you solve, how would you solve
this problem if you had a solver for that?
Well, I mean it's extremely easy.
You take an instance of this problem, you
compute f and f0,
you solve this problem here.
And then, that gives you Z, and then you
reconstruct X using this formula.
Alright?
So that's, that's the whole,
that's how you transform this, very
simple, right?
Oh, and you can go and and vice versa, so
that's how that works.
oh, but I do want to emphasize, this
problem and
this problem are equivalent, they are
absolutely not the same.
Right.
And so, if we call this prob and prob 2,
then for example if I say prob dot
equality constraints.
Right, and let's suppose that lists the
equality constraints,
what comes back is AX=B.
What happens if I take prop two dot
equality empty.
Yeah an empty list comes back because
there are no equality constraints.
So that tells you for sure those two
problems are not the same.
They are equivalent but not the same.
OK Now, by the way a lot of people think
it's a very naive view,
by the end of the course you'll know why.
It's a very naive view that you should
always eliminate equality constraints.
The naive view is that you should always
do that because look,
this is simpler this thing.
Right?
In fact it has fewer variables, right?
Because if x had dimension 100, and b has
dimension 30,
I'll assume everything is full rank here,
z has dimension 70.
Right?
So, so,
it's, of course you would rather solve
this,
because that's a problem with fewer
variables,
it's got 70 variables as opposed to 100
variables, that's number one.
And number 2, this one doesn't have any
quality constraints so
it's sort of structurally it's simpler,
too.
So you wouldn't imagine there would be any
compelling reason why
you would prefer to solve this one and
we'll see later in
the course there's a very compelling
reason and, in fact, it's the opposite.
In general, you would Almost always prefer
to
solve this because you could always do
this.
If you do that if it were computationally
advantageous.
We'll talk about that later.
So okay, however that that relates to this
the next thing.
You can actually introduce equality
constraints but
some people refer to this as unelimination
So, to eliminate variables
means to take an equality constraint, get
rid of it, and so on.
To introduce equality constraints,
you're actually doing unelimination, it's
the opposite.
So here's an example.
You want to minimize f0 of an affine
function subject to f i
of an affine function, unless they're
equal to 0.
So I just introduce A bunch of, a whole
bunch of new variables, right.
Which are the y zero, y one, up to y m.
And I re-write the problem this way here.
And here's the new problem, right.
And so again, in the niave view, this does
not look like progress, right.
In fact, if you saw this problem you might
immediately,
you might immediately Eliminate the y's
and end up with this thing.
Right?
It doesn't look like
progress because here.
Here's a problem that had no equality
constraints and
you have created from it an equivalent
problem that not only has equality
constraints, it has more variables.
Right?
Because the variables here are x and
y 0 up to ym.
Right?
so it doesn't look like progress.
But, you'll see later, Things like this
actually, of very good things can happen.
Sometimes.
In some context, when you do this.
Okay.
Here's another one, is introducing slack
variables for linear inequality, so
here I want to minimize, say, F0 of X,
subject to linear inequalities Here, and a
very common trick here is the following.
Is I replace these inequalities, linear
inequalities with linear equalities and
I say ai transpose x plus si equals vi.
Right?
So that's an and of course, and
then I simply require si to be positive.
And this is silly because if you look at
this thing,
si is of course vi minus ai transpose x.
So saying, the i transpose x is less than
b i is saying s i is bigger than or
equal to 0.
So, that's it.
So,
what you would say is something like this.
It says that if you can handle linear
equality constraints and
non-negativity, you can handle general
linear inequality constraints.
And this has several implications.
One implication has to do with solvers.
It says that instead of writing a general
purpose solver,
you can really focus on something that
thing are easily transformed to.
Okay.
Another variation has to do with an
epigraph form and
this one looks almost laughable but we'll
take a look at it.
Instead of minimizing F zero vex subject F
Y vex less than zero X equals B.
What we'll do is we'll introduce a single
new variable Called an epigraph variable,
it's a new variable, t.
And we'll simply add a constraint that
says t is bigger than of zero of x.
Okay?
Now I mean this is really dumb, right?
Because look, this constraint, oh which by
the way is convex,
it's convex in xt which are the variables.
Because if zero of x is convex, minus t is
a convex function, it's linear.
So, this function here is convex.
'Kay?
So you look at this, it's kind of dumb,
this constraint here says nothing more
than t is bigger than f0 of x.
T appears nowhere else in the optimization
problem.
Therefor if you fix x and you say what's
the best value of t?
The answer is well its t should equal f
zero of x.
Why?
Because that's the minimum that's
the smallest value t is allowed to go but
the objective is to minimize t.
You could turn this around and say
something like this if someone solve,
you would say something like this, if you
solve this problem Over x and t,
then at the solution, t is equal to f0 of
x.
Peroid.
Right.
If it, if it weren't, then basically the
person who alleged to solve it is a liar.
Right?
So that's, that's the idea.
Now, you might say, this is ridiculous.
Like, what?
But actually, if you take a good look at
this, it's very interesting.
What it says, and some people say it this
way This says, that some people write and
say this, they would say that projective
is universal for convex optimization.
That's what they'd say, cause what that's,
this objective is linear.
I mean, t is a linear function of x comma
t.
So what that says is that if you build a
solver.
For linear objective, and
you can handle, of course you have to be
able to handle the epigraph right?
But if you can handle the epigraph, then
all you have to worry about is, is,
again making a solver that does, that
handles linear objective and
that's going to simplify a whole bunch of
things if you have linear objective.
We'll see later.
But that's it.
So that's why people would say a linear
objective is universal for
convex optimization.
I should say something about these
transformations.
People who do this kind of stuff mostly
know all of these transformations and
they don't tell them, and they're not
written down anywhere -- well,
they're written down on these slides and
in the book and everything -- but
basically, you're just supposed to know
them.
Right.
So, your, and if you don't know these.
So someone would say oh, I need a solver
for this.
Someone would give you something else.
It would actually solve a transformed, an
equivalent version of your problem.
And you'd say, no, no, no, my objective is
something more complicated and
you're just supposed to know this.
Actually, we'll We will see a lot of these
transformations can be automated,
and that's what CVX does it for you.
Okay?
All right, next simple equivalents is
a partial,what's called a partial
minimization.
So partial minimization says you, you have
a problem or
your minimizing f zero Two variables,
right?
X1 and X2, right?
These are block variables, so
I've simply taken X and I've blocked them
into two pieces, X1 and X2.
And subject to say an ineq - a bunch of
inequalities only on the first one.
I mean, and we can have equality
constraints and things, but that's fine.
OK.
Then what it says is, we can roughly
speaking, we can minimize F0 Over x2,
which yields a function of x1.
So I take f tilde of f zero tilde of x1,
right, is this, it's the minimum over x2
of this function.
Now that's convex because convexity is
preserved under partial minimization.
OK and then we have a problem that looks
like this.
By the way if you take a problem with a
big old,
with a big sequence of these instead of
two you have n of them and
you eliminate them one at a time, this is
dynamic programming.
So just you've probably seen this.
So that's just what dynamic programming
is.
Its absolutely nothing more than that.
You want to minimize over a bunch of
variables You know, minimize over 1,
and then the second one, and the third,
and so on.
So that's, it's just something like that.
These right now are all very abstract,
these equivalences.
So they, they probably mean nothing right
now.
But we'll see later either in the context
of applications or
in some other setting where there's a
target that we would say that we could
reduce this thing to, by a transformaton
to this specific named problem.
Then we'll see this will make more sense.
So Quasiconvex Optimization, here
minimizing a quasiconvex
function subject to convex inequalities,
okay?
Now, one thing you have to watch out for
is you can have a locally optimal point
that is not optimal.
In quasi-convex optimization.
So, in this case, that point there is
absolutely; the idea that
the derivative there is 0, it's absolutely
flat.
It is definitely locally optimal.
So, however, it's clearly not optimal
because if
you minimize you might can get something
like that Right, so, so
some things are true for quasi-convex
optimization other things not.
In particular, local optimality does not
imply global optimality a quasi-convex
optimization.
Okay, so how do you solve such problems?
And the typical, the general technique is
this,
If a function is quasi-convex, what you do
is you write it.
in convex functions,
right?
So the idea is you make a function phi t,
phi sub t of x.
It has to be convex in x for each t.
And we arranged that the t sublevel set of
f0 is the zero sublevel set of phi t.
In other words, you have a representation
that looks like this.
So you represent the sublevel set of f0 by
a convex inequality.
That's the idea.
That, that's what I, that's what it, and
by the way you can show abstractly that
for any quasi-convex function, there is a
such a representation.
Frankly, that's not very interesting,
because in any particular case,
there's something simpler.
So here's an example.
Let's take a ratio of a convex over a
concave function Where both are positive
-- well, p is bigger or equal to zero and
q of x is positive on the domain of f0.
That's a quasi-convex function.
How do you check that?
Well, what you want to do is figure out is
the set of x such that f0 of x
is less than t.
Is that thing convex?
Now if T is negative, it's convex because
that is is what?
It's the empty set, right?
So this is the empty set which is convex.
If T is positive then I'm going to
substitute for F0 P over Q so
this is just P of F over Q of X is less
than or equal to T Q is positive So
therefore, I can multiply through this
linear inequality, and
I can write that as P of X, minus T Q of X
is less than 0.
I'm done.
Because that is a convex function.
P is convex, Q is concave.
T, with T positive, which is our
assumption now Is non-negative so t, q, x,
t times q is going to be concave.
Minus, switches conves and concave.
Sum of convex is convex.
This function is convex.
Okay?
So,
that, this would be the representation.
This would be the fi t of x.
Notice that it is not convex in x and t
jointly.
But for any fixed t, which is bigger or
equal to zero, this is a convex function.
And the sublevel said gives you the
sublevels out of f zero.
So, that's the idea.
Okay, so, what do you do with that?
Well the idea is very simple.
This says that we have a convex
representation of a su, of a sublevel set.
And what we'll do is we'll just vary t and
check feasibility of the convex problem.
So that's all you need to do.
SO here it is.
If you want to do
quazi convex optimization, it works like
this.
We'll take, the, what we'll do is this is,
this is the, this is the, part that
describes the sublevel set.
The t sublevel set of the object, the
original objective 0.
And so what we'll do is we'll,
we'll choose, we'll a target, we'll, what
we'll do is we'll guess a t.
We'll solve this convex feasibility
problem.
If that feasibility problem is, well, if
it's feasible.
Right?
If the result is feasible,
then we have found an x [COUGH] that
satisfies all the constraints here and
this because it satisfies this that means
F zero of X is less than or equal to T.
If this is infeasible then we know the
following.
We know that there is no X that satisfies
all of these constraints and
has F zero of X less than T.
And that tells us instantly that P star,
the optimal value of the original problem
is bigger than T.
I'm being informal.
Okay?
So, if you want to do
the careful analysis you can look in the
book or something like that.
But I'm, I'm being informal here.
It's actually says it's bigger than or
equal to p star.
And if it's infeasable it says p star is
bigger than t.
And so now you simply use the bisection
method.
So the bisection method goes like this.
You start with an upper and
lower bound on possible values of the, of
the of p star here.
You start with these upper and lower
bounds, and
then you, you take you have an interval
lu, that contains p star.
And you simply evaluate [COUGH] you check.
For t, for t in the middle of that
interval and it's either feasible or not.
And either way your interval goes down by
a factor of two.
Okay, and this tells you that it takes you
know, exactly U minus L,
that's your initial uncertainty in p-star.
It takes exactly that Log 2 of that
divided by
epsilon iterations to Converge to within
epsilon of p star.
Right?
And in fact,
when you terminate, here's what you'll
have.
You'll have some very interesting things.
You'll actually have a certificate.
What you'll have is you'll have an x
that'll satisfy,
it depends on the last iteration, if the
last iteration was, let's say,
feasible You'll have an x [COUGH] with a
sublevel set where you'll,
you'll have an x that's feasible and has
f0 of x less than t.
That's, that's the final value of t.
But you'll have a slightly smaller t.
Epsilon smaller, less than epsilon smaller
t where you, you, you've solved this
convex feas- infeasibility problem, and
found it to be infeasible.
And so that constitutes a proof.
That f0 could not be less than your t
minus epsilon.
And so that's what you end up with.
So that's how you solve a quasi convex
problem.
Okay, what we're going to do now is we're
going to talk about problem families.
With names.
Night, so we do this for a couple of
reasons.
One is historical and in fact it actually
has less and less value as we
move forward cause things like CVX will
automate a lot of the transformations for
you but for various reasons you should
know these problem classes.
You can also know them because there'd be
special solvers for
each of these classes right so for
many reasons historical if none other You
need to know about these problem classes.
Okay, and will start with linear program,
in some sense it is the simplest possible
general convex optimization problem.
General in the sense of having constrains
and other things.
So it says all functions are Fi.
F0 and all FI.
And in that case, that says you minimize
an affine function,
subject to linear inequality constraints,
well, affine but we say linear.
And linear equality constraints.
So that, that's a linear program.
Now, there's some silly things here, for
example this D is a constant.
And so, you don't really need it, right.
You could remove it, it, a d does not
affect the solution.
And in effect the way you write something
without the d, you don't need the d,
is you strip the d off, solve the problem,
add d back in to b star when you return,
the solution to the, to this problem.
Okay.
Now that's a, what's a convex problem.
And the feasible set [COUGH] is a
polyhedron,
because it's defined by linear equality
constraints and linear inequalities.
That's a, that's a polyhedron.
So this is a picture in r2, so, it's a
picture in r2 and You know here each of
these, this each of these is one is a row
of g h less than or equal to h.
That's what each of these is.
This is a problem with at least one, two,
three, four, five, six constraints and
c points in this direction.
Therefore minus c points in that direction
and
the semantics of optimization is Please
move as far as you can in this direction.
Right, while staying feasible.
And so there's, there's, the optimal
point.
In this case it turns out to be unique.
Right, so that's a linear program.
So, the picture here is simple you [COUGH]
obviously do not need any, anything
to solve convex optimization linear
programming problems with two variables.
Right?
So the I mean, it's good to draw it this
way.
That's fine.
But you should understand that, and
you can pretend to visualize a polyhedron
in r100.
You should at least pretend to.
I mean, and you know generally what it's
going to look like.
You know it's going to look like the,
the surfaces are going to be like hyper
planes and are 100.
And they'll be edges and there'll be
corners and points.
They're like vertices right but you know
we should all
really understand they were all faking
when they did that right?
Because if you take you take a polyhedron
with you know with a hundred variables And
50 linear inequalities, something like
that.
You have something, the number of vertices
the,
the number of edge, you know points like
this is exponential.
And would be for a problem that size
extremely large, right?
[COUGH] So, but it's still useful to
pretend that we can visualize.
So, it looks something like that.
Okay.
That's a linear program.
Now, what's important about linear
programming, well it's a convex problem.
It can be solved unbelievably well, right?
So, this is basically a completely mature
technology.
THis has been done like very well since
1948.
And so, if you have a linear program with
a couple thousand variables and
a bunch of constraints.
It's just that something you could solve,
I mean, depends on the number of
constraints and sparsity patterns and
things, but you can solve that
extremely fast, and with total reliability
on small things, very quickly, Okay?
So that, that's why you would want to know
about this.
So that's linear programming.
Okay.
So let's look at some examples.
And the first one is historical.
So it goes back, well, to 1948.
And so we're doing it just because, you
know, it's historical.
And here it is.
So the original problem was something like
this.
It says you want to choose quaniitites x
one through x n of n foods.
OK so these are the variables and your
going to make a diet out of these.
Right?
So it'll be a hundred,
three grams of this, fifty grams of this,
you know zero grams of that, something.
And one unit of food, let's say a gram,
costs cj.
And it has a nutrient amount aij.
Like for example, you know, nutrient one
could be protein.
Right, so this tells you that a gram of
this has,
you know, a third of a gram, 300 mg of
protein.
It doesn't matter, you know, nutrient two
can be a vitamin.
I mean, it doesn't matter.
You get the idea.
Okay, and so the idea is your going to
construct a diet which is a combi,
which is a mixture of these foods.
By the way no one, you're not supposed to
visualize this.
Like putting these things in a blender or
something.
Cause you'd come up with some brown goop
or something.
Anyway, so, it's not suppose to be
appetizing.
That's a, yeah, I guess to make it
appetizing that's a nonconvex constraint.
But we'll, we'll talk about that later.
okay, so what you want to do is find the
cheapest of healthy diet.
So in this case you'd minimize the
transposed x,
that is of course the total cost, and
subject to ax bigger than b that says
that you have here ax is a vector that
gives you a list of the nutrient amounts.
There so for example entry one in AX would
be the total protien,
say the next one is vitamin B entry two of
AX would be the amount of Vitamin B or
something like that okay?
And, then B here is the minimum allowed
Level of that nutrient, okay?
Oh, and this is rather important, we have
to have,
we only allowed to do non-negative
quantities.
Right, so again you can't do negative
quantities,
you can't go short as you might in finance
on a diet.
I mean Let's not go there, actually.
Okay.
We'll just, we'll leave it there.
But.
Okay.
So that's the problem.
Oh, and here, this problem is still not
quite in our standard form.
Right?
But
this is the kind of thing you get used to,
people get used to.
They don't do it.
So let's go ahead and put this Fully in
our standard form.
I'll do it once and then maybe never
again.
Here it is; You would rewirte it this way.
Minimize, c transpose x and let's just go
all the way, plus 0.
[COUGH] So 0 is the d decomponent.
And now we have to write these as a set of
Linear inequalities.
Right?
So we'll write it this way, oh, and the
linear inequalities, you know, like all
inequalities our standard is that it's
less than or equal to, so I'll rewrite
this as minus ax I guess I'm allowed to
write it in this case like that, right?
I could go Ax minus B is less than or
equal to 0, like that and
then I can write minus X is less than or
equal to 0, right?
And I'm still not done.
I mean this is kind of goofy but let's
just do the last step and then we're, and
then we'll quit on this problem.
So, the last step is I would write that
whole thing together as minus A and
I times plus, or however we're, however,
it doesn't really matter.
Minus B 0, there.
There we go.
Okay, so there we go.
That's the official C, that's D, I forget
what that is, maybe G,
and maybe that's H or something.
And we have it in our canonical form.
So things like this, people don't even say
that, they just say, that's an LP, and
then they, it's your problem to switch
around.
Okay.
Next problem is quite.
This one is only for
historical I mean that's the only reason
we mention it, right.
Although, actually, it turns out an LP
like this.
I mean, something like a diet problemer's,
it's,
actual, I mean is modern versions of it
that are quite real, quite practical.
Eh, so one example.
Would be something like this.
Uhm, [COUGH], you should say that, you've
contract.
These would, these would represent
contracts.
X is the amount of effort you put into
some, job, or something like that.
And then you might want to do something
like minimize the cost.
Of complying with a bunch of contracts,
and it would be the same.
By the way, you cannot s-,
you really can't solve these problems by
hand if there's like more than,
if there's like you know, more than 20, 30
foods, and four or five nutrients.
I mean, you really cannot do it, I mean,
well, you could do it.
And in fact, I guess, in the 50s, 60s,
70s, and even 80s, maybe even 90s
students were tortured with With actually
solving things like this by hand, and
I'm not kidding.
That probably goes on now at some places,
possibly even here.
I'm not sure.
But
anyway, of course that's completely silly.
But the point is, you can actually solve
these by hand if it's tiny, but
even it's just small, you can't do it by
hand.
Anyway, it's silly.
You shouldn't.
Okay.
Next one we're going to look at is a
piecewise-linear minimization.
Alright, so there you want to minimize a
function which is piecewise-linear.
It is the maximum of a bunch of afine
functions.
So it looks something like this.
This This objective function here.
It's, you have a bunch of functions like
that.
These are affine functions and the minimum
is that piece-wise linear function and
you want to find a minimum of it, okay?
Now I want to first mention a couple of
things.
The first is that does not look an lp.
Right when yo look at this problem,
the objective, the whoel point of an LP is
that it's objective is linear.
This objective is highly non-linear.
There we've got a problem right there.
So if you ask is this an LP the answer is
it absolutely is not.
It's not an LP.
So, that's a that's, that's the first
thing you'd rem-.
Now, I should mention something else
you've already seen this idea that there's
a very easy way to create a piece wise
linear approximation of a convex function.
You would evaluate if it's differential,
for example,
you evaluate its gradient at a bunch of
places that gives you a lower bound.
You take the maximum of it that's still a
lower bound and it's a good approximation.
Everybody got that?
So, this is actually a cheap and dirty way
to solve a convex optimization problem.
You have some F zero.
You know you don't have any other way to
do it.
You evaluate its gradient or draw some
pictures.
but in any case you get a piecewise-linear
approximation of it.
And then you will see we transfer this to
an LP and solve it, okay?
So, here it is as an LP.
It's just that it's nothing but the
epigraph representation.
Introduce a new variable.
This is an LP, right?
So, that's what it, cause here you're
minimizing a linear function.
t is the linear function of xt.
Subject to these are linear inequalites.
Now again you know to get this exactly
right you'd put the t on the left hand
side and all this sort of stuff.
We're not going to do that oh and
most people they would actually call that
an LP.
Well some people would.
A lot of people would.
If, people who have to
deal with piecewise-linear minimization
they would say that's an LP.
And that's slang, it's informal.
And what it means is this problem is
equivalent to an LP.
And, and the practical implication is
enormous.
It says basically, since LP solvers are
extremely reliable, extremely efficient.
It says basically, we can solve that
problem.
That's the practical implication of it,
I mean a theoretical implications as well
but that's the practical one.
Okay.
So our next example of a linear programmer
or
I should say a problem that can be
transformed to a linear program is
the problem of the Chebyshev center of a
polyhedron.
So what is it?
Well, I have a polyhedron, so that's a,
defined by a set of linear inequalities.
So that's, that's, here's the linear
inequalities and here's my polyhedron.
And what you want the Chebyshev center of
this is defined to be the center of
the largest ball that fits inside.
Okay, so that's this point here.
Right?
In this case, that's the Chebyshev center.
So you really want to choose the center
and maximize r.
Subject to the constraint that the ball
fits inside.
Now actually, before we go on, I want to
mention a couple things about this.
The first thing is this.
The problem clearly has applications
immediately cause basically whats it
saying is another way to say this by the
way is to
say find the point inside the set that is
deepest inside it.
Has the largest distance to the outside.
So in other words if you were going to
target for a manufacturing process And
these constraints define the acceptable
region, and you wanted to have margin, so
that if during the margin, manufacturing
process, things varied and
you wanted the highest margin you would
choose the Chebyshev center.
Okay?
[COUGH].
So this is already a problem,
that has applications.
Now the second is before we get into it I
want to point something out.
When you think about a linear program, the
whole point about a linear program is
that all the functions that define it are
Affine.
And so what should light up in your brain,
is, is, things, or
the pictures you should see in your mind,
are flat things.
Hyperplanes possibly with edges right,
because we have mul,
we have inequalities and that would define
edges but
you should That is not, I can tell you
there are a lot of things
you can say about a Euclidean about a ball
and a two nor but,
generally speaking, if something writes
down a two norm,
you're not talking flat.
Right?
[COUGH] That's almost the canonical
definition of curved.
So, if someone writes down a ball, and
someone walks up to you on the street and
says I have a problem, and the first thing
they say is if they talk,
if they use the word Euclidean ball It's
probab, you would just think, now
that doesn't sound right because linear
programs pertain to thins that are flat.
So, all I'm trying to do is set you up to
say that this doesn't sound like This is
going to end up as an example of a linear
program.
Obviously it is, otherwise it wouldn't be
in the lecture here.
But, my point is, it's not at all obvious
why this would be the case or
that this should be the case.
And in fact there's good reasons why you
might imagine this didn't,
this wasn't going to happen.
All right, with that preamble, let's take
a look at the problem.
What does it mean for.
Every element of this ball, here,
to satisfy, a linear, a single linear
inequality.
And that says, here's a transpose x is
less than b.
And we want to know, what are the
conditions on xc, and r.
Under which this ball sits entirely in
that half space.
That's the question.
Okay.
Well let's find out.
Well that's the same as saying we'll write
the ball this way.
Its the same as x c plus u where norm u is
less than r.
That's the ball.
It says that all of these numbers have to
be less than bi.
Okay, well it, let's take a look at those
numbers.
Well the first, it doesn't depend on you
so that just comes right out.
So we want to find what's, what is the
mark,
what is the largest possible value of ai
transposed times u.
Well, and we can vary U over everything
that has length up to R.
That's the Koshi Schwartz inequality tells
you the following.
It says that A, I, transpose U this is
less than or equal to the following.
Norm A, I.
Right.
And then, over Mu right?
But that is less than R norm AI 2 that's
it shorts an inequality okay.
However there's the a converse to the
cosher schwarz inequality.
The converse when do you get equality
here?
And the answer is oh that's easy it's when
you.
Is aligned with a i.
In this case that means u is a i over norm
a i and
then we have to multiply this by r.
There we go.
So for this value of u which indeed
satisfies this it is
true That you get an equals here.
And so, that's that, that's the largest
possible value of
the inner product of ai and u over this
set of us.
Okay, and we write, write this down.
Again, it doesn't look like a linear
inequal, it doesn't look like an in,
inequality, because we see this 2.
But we take a deep breath and stare at
this for a while, and
we realize, that is sure, that's a, that's
a 2-norm, but its argument is a constant.
This is a number.
And if we look at this and we think of
just x, c, and r,
as sort of the variables here, that's a
linear inequality.
So, we have a linear program.
It says we should maximize r subject to,
that means find the largest radius,
subject to this constraint.
And if you were writing code, you would
put a comment there, and
then after the co-, on the, after the
comment, you would write the following.
You could say, this is the condition under
which.
Ai transpose x is less bi and for all x in
b xc r.
So that the, that's the ball with radius,
center xc and radius r, right?
And that's it.
It's that simple.
So finding the Chebyshev center of a set
Of a polyhedron given by a set of
linear inequalities.
It's a linear program, right?
But it has a lot of implications.
It says you can do design centering, and
things like that, using linear
programming.
I should say, linear programming, we'll
see that,
that's part of the theme of the course,
but things like linear programming is,
can be done very effectively even for
relatively large problems.
Okay.
Here's a, a significant sort of
generalization of linear programming is
what's called linear fractional
programming.
It's a quasi convex problem.
And it's this.
We have linear inequalities, linear
equalities.
And the objective is what's called the
linear fractional function.
It's a ratio of two Afine functions And
there, we do have to say, the domain is
one of the half spaces and
the convention is it's the half space
under which the denominator's positive.
Okay?
So that's a,
that's called a, a, some people call it a
bi affine function, I do, no they don't.
Oh, some people might.
By the way, in some In some small sections
of
mathematics people would actually refer to
that as an Afine function.
so, if you did projective geometry you
would call that afine.
Okay.
in any case, it's for us it's linear
fractional, is one name for it.
Okay now that is a quasi-convex
optimization problem.
How do we know that?
Well, all we have to do is look as what
does it mean to say that f
zero of that is less than t.
Right, there's the sub-level set here.
And f zero is this ration the denominator
is positive, so that's the set of x for
which, and I do, I should add that, the
denominator is positie, right.
Right?
And I clear it and I get c transpose x
plus d times t times e transpose x plus f
is less than or
equal In this case, let's see.
I, I said this is less than or equal to t
and that's less than [INAUDIBLE] 1.
Okay?
So that, that gives me that.
Sorry, did I get that right?
No.
There we go, now it's right.
Okay?
So, that's the condition and
I'll close the brace.
Okay?
So this is for any fixed t that
expression, that inequality is a linear
inequality, so that tells you that the sub
levels set is an open half
space intersected with a closed half
space, and that is a Convex set.
In fact you don't get points like this on
the boundary, but okay, that's fine.
Alright, so you can solve this by, by
section.
It turns out that there's a very clever
trick,
which allows you to solve this linear
Fractional program by solving a single LP
instead of solving oh let's say ten LPs.
If I solve ten LPs by bi-section I can
make my error in the objective go down by
a factor of 1024.
That's two to the ten.
But you can actually solve it exactly in
one.
I won't go into the details the arguments
a bit long.
But you'd have to make the argument.
And it basically is this.
You solve the following LP.
You minimize c transpose y plus d z
subject to g y less than h z.
A y equals b z so
these are all completely legit and in fact
these are all homogeneous.
Well no sorry that ones homogeneous and
the only thing that unhomogenizes it is
this constraint E transpose y, plus fz,
equals 1.
So, I won't go into in the book, it's
described in great detail how it is
that solving this LP actually solves this
linear-franctional problem.
Okay.
Generalized linear-fractional problem is
the maximum of a bunch of
linear-fractional functions.
It's the maximum anti-quasi convex
functions so it's quasiconvex.
Fine.
And therefore you can solve it by,
by section.
And in fact, in the, in this case in
general there's no
transformation that allows you to solve
this with one linear program.
[COUGH] Actually, that's maybe not known
or something like that.
But I'm asserting it.
Uh, [INAUDIBLE] I'll say it this way.
I don't know of a way to gen- to,
to write a generalized linear fractional
fun- problem as a single linear program.
OK, very, very interesting example of
this,
this problem is the so-called Von Neumann
growth model.
So in the Von Neumann growth model, the
way it works is this,
is we have variables x and let's say x
plus.
These are variables and they have to be
bigger or equal to zero.
So that a squiggly bigger or equal too,
their non-negative and
what xi represents That is the, activity
level of sector i, in an economy.
Then, if you put the plus there, that is,
that's the activity level in sector i of
the economy in the next period.
For example the next year, let's say.
Okay?
Next quarter.
It doesn't matter.
Well, it does matter if you actually do
this, but for us it doesn't matter.
And so that's the idea.
And a sector might be something like you
know, transportation or
defense or something like that, right?
OK, so here is Von Neumann's model.
It says it says if you look at x i plus
over x i,
that's a beautiful interpretation.
That is the growth, well if its bigger
than one,
that's the growth in the ith sector of the
economy.
Because x i plus is the economic activity
in the next period and
x i is in the current period and the
ratio, what was the ratio?
If that's 1.05, you would say that the
economy grew,
sorry, that sector of the economy grew by
five percent.
Okay?
Now by the way, if that's 0.96 you would
say that it shrunk by, it,
it contracted by four percent.
Okay?
And The Von Norman objective is this, you
take all sectors of the economy and
you look a the minimum across all sectors.
Right?
So, and
then that is something you want to
maximize.
And that sounds great, kind of egalitarian
minded, so very nice,
it says that basically, so for example if
this objective Is 1.04, that's great.
That means you have four percent growth in
all sectors.
That's what it means.
If this is .92, that's not great,
because it says at least one sector shrunk
by eight percent, contractive.
Okay?
Now we have to talk about the constraints.
Well, of course, they're the constraints
that X,
X0 that X is X plus is bigger or equal to
0.
The Xis are, by the way,
are positive already because the domain of
this implies that.
And so will the next constraint, but we'll
get to that.
Then it says, there's a constraint that
couples X and XI, and that's this.
So AX, A is a matrix that when you
multiply it by X,
it's Ith component gives you, the amount
of,
the amount of goods consumed, Due to
activity sector X.
Alright?
So that could be,
it doesn't matter what the goods are.
But, you know, it's a set of goods that
could be natural resources.
It doesn't matter what it is.
Okay?
Natural resources may be
a bad example actually.
It's the, it's the amount of, of goods.
This is produced.
Okay?
Then B is a matrix that when you multiply
it by an activity level,
tells you the amount of good consumed due
to that level of activity, right?
So, that's the idea.
So for example you take electricity would
be one of these entries, right?
And then.
b, one of the rows in b,
let's say the first row represents, let's
say, energy product, this would be, so,
the first row of b times x plus, gives you
the amount of energy which is produced.
That's also for example, because it It's
assumes you have to store it or
something like that.
But, okay, anyway.
Alright.
And this constraint says the following.
It says that the amount consumed in the
next sector has to be,
can be no more than the amount produced,
sorry, the amount pro, consumed in
the next period cannot exceed the amount
that is produced in this period.
That's what it means and you could add it,
you could add something else here.
You could add a constant which would be
some stock of stuff you had of
these resources you had before hand and so
now the problem is to solve this and that
indeed a generalized linear fractional
program because instead of Maximizing,
we could minimize and then it would be the
maximum and you'd switch the ratio and
it be the maximum of a bunch of linear
fractional functions.
And you'd have a generalized linear
fractional program.
And the idea would be to determine the
activity to maximize growth rate of
the slowest growing sector.
Okay?
And we can actually, that means, you can
solve it by solving some lps,
In fact by doing bisection on lps.
We'll move on to non affine problems, and
we're going to follow actually not really
the modern Flow, but
we're going to actually follow here the
historical flow of these problems.
And so people had branched out, big
generalization, yet
you still had linear inequalities, linear
inequalities, but
you have a quadratic objective and it has
to be convex, okay?
So convex quadratic.
You do have Something called indefinite
quadratic programs,
it's a totally different deal, not a
convex problem.
Okay?
And those also in general very hard to
solve.
Okay, so this is a convex quadratic
program, or if you just say quadratic
program the default is that it's convex,
when you talk to people about this.
Okay, so that's a quadratic program.
And, the, the the only difference is this,
here's your feasible set.
It's a polyhedron, here.
And the objective function now though is
quadratic and
the level sets are ellipsoids, right.
So here are some level sets drawn, these
are,
this is increasing values of the
objective.
And in fact there would be a center.
I don't know if it's going to be somewhere
around there.
and that's where this thing has it's
minimum value.
Assuming P as positive definite that would
be at the point P inverse Q.
Minus p inverse Q, that would be the point
that minimizes this unconstraint.
And so, the idea is to go is to slip down
these curves.
Go as low as you can while staying in the
set.
And in this case.
That would be the optimal point okay,
actually very interesting observation for
a linear program you can always find an
optimal point on one of these vertices and
here it's right smack in the middle of a
face.
That's a quadratic program and you can
solve these very well.
Okay, let's look at some examples.
Well, uh, [COUGH] here's the,
well the most basic context optimization
problem is, least-squares.
So minimize norm, A x minus b, two norm
squared.
It's also called regression.
It's, well, okay, it's least-squares.
And its got a linear, it's got a just an
analytical solution, right.
It's just It's A inverse b,
sorry, A dagger b and that's A transpose A
inverse, A tranpose b.
That's assuming A is full rank.
Okay?
So, that's if you that's if A is full rank
and skinny.
But in general, it's given by the
pseudo-inverse, the Moore-Penrose inverse.
And what we can do now is we can add
linear constraints.
So that's very cool.
So you add linear constraints to least
squares and what you get is,
this objective is quadratic.
It looks like this, it's x transpose times
a transpose a,
that's positive semi-definite, right?
Minus, and then this will be transpose x,
and this is 2 A transpose b.
transpose.
Right?
And then plus norm b squared.
You're minimizing, so this doesn't really
matter.
Okay?
There, that's a convex quadratic
objective.
And I can add constraints.
For example, I could bound x between
numbers.
I could say I can have a regression
problem.
And I can say, please fit,
my data b with a linear combination with
the columns of a.
But I don't want any,
any of the coefficients in that linear
combination that can never be more in
absolute value than, they have to be in
between minus one and one there we go.
I could say, find me the best fit here,
where the Xs have to be bigger or
equal to 0, right?
So that's basically this says, find the
closest point B to a subspace.
If I constraint X to be bigger or equal to
0,
it says find me the closest point to B in
a convex poly, in a cone.
Right, which is A times X where X is
bigger than or equal to 0.
[COUGH] Oh and another fascinating example
of this,
we'll look at many of these later but
here's a really cool one.
Let's do Lee squares and some people,
there's a name for
this it's called like I think isotonic
re-regression Alright.
That's the constraint that these are
ordered, like that.
Alright, there's no analytical solution
for
the best x that increases, but which
minimizes nor makes minus b squared.
There is no analytical solution for that.
But that's, you can solve this by a q p, a
very simple q p.
Right?
It says let's minimize this quadratic
objective,
that is a set of N minus 1 linear
inequality constraints.
Things like X 1 minus X two is less than
or equal to 0.
Okay, so.
So you can do regression, and you can add
arbitrary constraints to regression, and
you get a Q P.
Arbitrary linear constraints,
inequalities, equalities.
OK.
Now another interesting case is when you
do mean variance trade off.
So lets look at that.
Lets suppose that we have a linear program
with random costs.
So c transpose x is the c transpose x is
the objective Here.
But we're going to say that C is a random
variable.
In other words, you it, it's a set of
prices let's say.
You don't know the prices.
I mean, presumably you know something
about the prices, but
they may not be what you think they are.
And we're going to model those prices as a
random vector.
And we'll imagine that C as mean value C
Bar.
Right, so that's the mean price.
And then it has variance so
expected C minus C Bar, C minus C bar
transpose is sigma.
Is covariant sigma.
So So c bar and sigma describe a some of
the statistics of the cost.
Right?
Okay.
Now what we'll do is we'll minimize here c
bar trig/g, that's,
that's the mean expected cost and
that's plus gamma times, that's the
variance, that's what this does.
Gamma is a positive constant here, it's
positive and
it's called the risk aversion parameter
because the large you make gamma,
it says, the more you care in this case by
charging yourself,
it irritates you that the variants of the
cost are high.
So that's what this is.
So that's the idea and you would solve
this problem for
various values of gamma and look at it to
see where you would be comfortable.
Where where where your comfort is in
trading off risk.
This is generally associated with risk and
this would be something like just cost.
Okay.
Okay, now something in between or the next
step up is you say well look at
the objective can be quadratic why not the
constraints?
Okay, fine.
That's called a qcqp.
Again, this is the historical Evolution so
these days I guess out of historical
respect people still talk about QCQP's but
never the less we'll see that there's
something that subsumes this now a days
that's a generalization even more of this.
So QCQP is a quadratically constrained
quadratic program and
all of these matricies have to be positive
semi definite because all of
these functions are convex.
OK, so that's the, that's a QCQP.
Notice that this includes QP as a special
case,
because I just take all of these Pi's to
be 0, OK, and
by the way that includes LP as a special
case too because I take this P0 to be 0.
So the three problem classes we've looked
at so
far which is linear programming, QP, LP,
QP, QCQP.
They're growing, right?
We have LP, this is very rough but you
know what I mean.
That's a subset of QP and that's a subset
of QCQP.
So that's the, that's the picture so far.
Okay.
We're going to look at something even
Bigger.
It's called second-order cone programming
or S-O-C-P.
This is the modern one.
Okay [COUGH] now second-order cone
programming looks like this.
It says minimize the linear function,
that's kind of like a L-P,
subject to equality contraints.
Well, they have to be linear, it's convex.
And then subject to the following.
There's a two norm And an affine part.
And you look at that, and it sure looks
like, it looks like,
kind of a QCQP or something like that.
I'll get to that in a minute, but.
So let's take a look at this.
Basically, each of these constraints,
that's called,
this is called a second-order cone
constraint.
And basically it says the following, it
says Ax,
Aix plus bi comma ci transpose x plus di.
That's in the second-order cone, okay?
So it's the image under an affine mapping,
right.
It maps A, it maps x into, into this pair.
And so you know, well, it's affine
mapping.
And then it says that has to be the second
order cone.
Or another way to say it is it's the
inverse image under an affine mapping of
a second order cone.
So that's what a second order constraint
is.
If I took for example, I mean I can either
take the dimension to be low, or
I could take ai to be to make the
dimension ni one.
I could take ai to be zero or something,
and this, this will recover an lp.
And in fact I can express any qc qp this
way, and
any lp this way because I just don't need
these terms and I have an lp.
Right?
So that's it.
And this is, so this is more general than
QCQP and LP.
Now I want to mention something here which
is interesting.
Now for us, we say that's a convex
problem.
And why do we know that?
Well, we look over here at the constraints
and the objective is linear problem.
And we look at the constraints here and we
say, well this is convex.
And then the right hand side is affine.
So I could just as well subtract it and
say nor
may I X plus BI minus CI transpose X minus
DI less than or equal to zero.
But that function is convex, cause its a
norm.
Norm of affine is convex so that's convex.
Now the.
If you are in the pre-modern era of
optimization, here's what would happen.
People have encountered two norms for
hundreds of years.
Gauss did, I mean Gauss wrote a book about
two door minimization, right.
That lead the least squares.
And that's you hint.
In the classical view when you see a to
norm there's something that you want to do
very badly to it.
You want to square it and the reason is
this.
A two norm is not differentiable when the
argument is zero.
I mean after all a two norm Let's do one
dimension.
It's an absolute value, right?
So this doesn't look good.
And if your whole world view centers
around differentiability of
things like that, then this is bad.
Not good.
Okay, but if you square this.
[SOUND] The square of a norm expression,
like Aix plus bi, 2 norm squared.
That is a quadratic, that's a convex
quadratic function.
That is fantastic, that's, it's convex,
number one.
And number two,
this is even better, it's smooth; there's
no There's no point any more.
I mean, if you square the absolute value,
you get the square.
Right?
It's nice and smooth.
Okay?
You can take gradients, derivatives,
whatever you like.
Okay.
So you look at this thing and
you say, well, you know what I'm going to
do, I'm going to square it.
Because it's irritating me or something.
So you'll square it and you'll get this.
See I transposed X plus D I.
Now this is not quite, oops I got to
square that.
Now this is not the same as that because
we still have to
add the string C transposed X plus D I Is
bigger than or equal to 0.
These two together are exactly the same as
that constraint there.
Okay?
And it's looking really good because I
would subtract this and write that as less
than or equal to 0.
And I, I'm in a great position here
because now I have a, that's quadratic.
Quadratic.
Less than or equal to 0.
Linear inequalities I got a QP, QCQP I
should say.
Okay, so that, this is what you would want
to do, now can you do this.
Well it all looks good and there's only
one minor problem with that and
that is this the Quadratic part of this
matrix is exactly this one,
it's Ai transpose Ai minus, ci, ci
transpose.
[COUGH], sorry, that's right.
Okay?
So that's what it is.
Alright, now.
That's positive, semi-definite, so is
that.
But the difference is not necessarily.
Oh, but if the difference is positive,
semi-definite, great,
you have reduced your general SOCP to a
QCQP.
But [COUGH] if this is not positive
semi-definite, You don't have.
You have a QCQP, but it's one with
indefinite matrices.
Right?
So, and that sort of makes it hard.
Now of course it's easy, but you don't
know that.
So, all right.
So, let me summarize I should say that in
the older more historical, conventional
view This, a norm, a two norm,
without a square on top irritates you
because it's not differentiable.
And you'd have an urge to square it.
If you square it, you would get a,
a problem that is quadratic, that's grated
smooth but it's not convex.
So, ok, alright so that's a, this is SOCP.
So let's look in the example of SOCP.
Oh and I should say that if you were
tracing the history,
quadratic programming we were at about
1952, '53.
QCQP not long thereafter.
We are now, well it depends, I mean we're
in the nineties let's say.
Late eighties not it would be the very
beginnings, you're in the nineties maybe.
Something like that.
So you're in the modern era when you talk
about SSCP.
So, let's look at an example.
Let's take a linear programming problem,
here it is.
Minimize this.
And [COUGH] let's get, let's suppose that
there's uncertainty in c a i and b.
That's the problem data.
Now, you know,
of course, in any real application there
will be uncertainty in these.
Eh, that's not true.
There are some example where there would
not be.
For example.
suppose That you are trying to verify some
mathematical conjecture, right?
And then, then in fact the data are exact.
But other than some, except for that one
case, right?
In any practical application, all of these
things derived from Well your problem,
they derived from your problem right?
So and there I'l just have a little side
discussion about problem data.
0's and the coefficients they are probably
really 0 and they might not be right?
That might just be your way of saying
small.
Think numbers like 1/2 minus 1.
You know, plus one those maybe or exactly
ones minus one.
Every other number, if you see a .236 or a
1.682 or
something, all of those numbers have a
providence.
They trace back to something, right.
They trace back to some combination of if
it's a physical thing so
it's Young's modulous times the distance.
Right, it's some coefficent of thermal
expansion.
If this is finance, it will trace back to
some parameter and
a model like the volatility or the mean
return or something like that.
So, in all cases like that, those numbers
are suspect, right, and
it should be the case that if you vary
them, a little bit.
The solution does not change wildly.
Okay?
So, if it does change wildly, then, it
tells you that,
solving this problem is as a practical
matter Useless, right, because I,
I could hardly tell you oh, I've got a
wonderful way to land an airplane,
it's absolutely unbelievable, wait til you
see it.
And they'd say how'd you do that, well, I,
I solved a linear program and.
Well, that's great.
And I'd say, there's only one minor
problem with it,
you need to know the mass of the airplane
to seven significant figures, right.
So if you, if If there's any error in the,
in the seventh or
sixth significant figure in the mess then
it won't work at all.
Well, I mean, that's just stupid.
It's not, that's just a non solution.
It has no practical use anyway.
All right, so all of that was just a long
aside about variations in problem data.
So, and there's a new trend now where
people are explicit about the data.
Variations in data.
And we're going to look at that now.
So, for simplicity, let's just assume that
the data,
that the only thing that's going to change
is a.
So for some reason we know c.
Actually, we already looked earlier at the
problem of c being unknown.
We interpreted that as prices, or
something.
So let's assume it's only a than changes.
You can interpret a,
by the way, as something that tells you
how much resources you consume.
Okay.
Now the deterministic model says something
like this.
It says that I have some sets, e i, Let's
say an ellipse or
something like that and it says that each
AI is in that ellipse.
And I'm going to insist that constraint
hold for every single possible AI.
So that's my constraint.
Some people call that a worst case model,
well cause that's what it says.
It says I want my resource consumption to
not exceed my resour,
the resources I have.
My consumption should not exceed my
resources even in the absolute worst case.
So that's that.
Now another model is the stochastic model
and that says that these AI's
are random variables and the constraints
have to hold with some probability.
For example I don't know 90%, 99.
Typical ones would be in fact things like
these are the ones of interest right?
There's not that many of interest frankly
Right?
[SOUND] And there's maybe one more,
something like that, right?
These are the three of interest.
Now, you might ask, why do I say these are
the only three numbers of interest?
And, it's very simple.
You don't, you don't care about like s-,
0.7, right?
That says, yes, I'd like those constraints
to hold 70% of the time.
That, that does, that doesn't make any
sense, right?
Because, well, it doesn't make, it
doesn't, you want it to fail?
You want it to be violated 30% of the
time?
I don't think so.
Okay.
Nine five its just kind of your way of
saying I wanted to usually be
satisfied often.
I want it to be rare that its violated.
You know like once in twenty times.
Okay.
This says no I want it actually rarer than
that, one in a hundred times and
this is basically your way of saying I
want it to be quite rare.
I'll accept a violation but it should be
like one in a thousand times but
already this doesn't mean a whole lot.
[COUGH] Because when you put numbers like
that on here it sort of
has a different meaning.
Because this says you better be very
certain of the distribution of
these things and
when these are just in practice, in order
to assert that a probability is.
0.001.
If it's 0.0% you better be really sure of
details of your distribution.
And I can tell you that in practice the
one thing that people do
not know about distributions is the tail.
Right?
Period.
So, I mean, there's no way somebody can
say oh, yeah, yeah.
So that's why you don't talk about
something like this.
Now they do, okay?
But when they talk about that, you have to
understand,
they don't really mean the probability
that you violate is less than .01%.
They don't believe that, I mean, let's
hope they don't believe that.
What they really mean is this is a
surrogate for
saying, I really want that to hold, like,
very, very often.
That's what they mean to say.
Okay I really care about the exact value
of that number.
Okay, so that's the stochastic model.
Okay, let's look at the deterministic
approach let's see how that works.
Let's say that the ellipsoid.
Okay these are ellipsoid that contain that
describe possible values of the AI.
Oh, and you ,might ask how do you get
these.
Well these are problems we'll even look at
in this course.
How do you get this ellipsoid?
Well, the answer is you'd look at a 1.
Right?
That's a vector that
characterizes the resource consumption of,
you know, for the first resource.
And what you do is you go get a model of
this thing from Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, and you get
different AI's.
And you get a year's worth.
You have 365 vectors AI.
And if they're all over the place then
it's time to give up and go home.
But if they're kind of reasonably,
tightly concentrated you might fit an
ellipsoid over that.
We'll see exactly how to do that later in
the course.
You'll fit an ellipsoid over it and that
would be your ellipsoid.
So so you have an ellipsoid, it's
characterized by a center and the matrix
PI which is positive well here we haven't
yet assumed it's positive semi definite.
is, it's, we'll say it's, well actually it
doesn't have to be non-singular.
that, it's, it's an ellipsoid, this is a
generalized ellipsoid, P has less than
full rank, it means that there is some
dimensions in which AI is known exactly.
Okay, the robust lp says you, this
constraint has to hold for
all ai in an ellipsoid.
But wait a minute, what's this?
That says that ai bar plus pi u transpose
x,that's the maximum
value of this thing here.
Has to be less than b.
That has to be less than bi.
And that's gotta hold for all u, but we
can just multiply this out.
Right, that's ai bar transpose x plus and
then that's the norm of PI transpose x.
And that's from the converse
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality.
So basically it says this constraint
becomes that., We now sit back and
take a look at it.
At what we have.
Linear objective, that constraint is
linear plus norm of aphine/g.
2 norm of Afine, less than constant.
That's an SOCP.
Right?
And that's it.
And, by the way, the meaning of this.
You know, this is something that not, you
know, only some people know
about SOCPs now, but 25 years ago, you
know, 15 people knew about them.
Okay?
Or maybe 20.
So, it's an extraordinary thing, cause
they,
there's a very practical, the practical
conclusion is, we can solve this.
With extreme efficiency and reliability.
In effect, this is already happening, most
fields, many fields that use
linear programs are switching to SOCPs
just to handle the robust case, OK?
And let me say a little bit more about it,
it's actually super cool If I get rid of
this,
this says simply make the inequality hold
when I put in the center of the ellipsoid.
But that's not right because a is going to
vary, and I want some margin there, right?
So this is to be interpreted as the
margin.
What it is, is it's a beautiful thing that
tells you that depending on x,
it tells you how much margin to leave.
And the answer simply is p, transpose x
norm 2 right?
And as an example, let's go to this thing.
Suppose x is zero, and I ask you.
Do you have to worry about variations in a
i?
And the answer is no and I'd say really
even if a i changes hugely and
the answer is no not at all because a
transpose times zero is zero.
So if x is zero you,
you're, you don't have to worry about
variations in a, right?
Where as if x is big you do, because well,
roughly they're getting multiplied by, you
get, they get multiplied together.
This thing says that the margin has to
scale with x and
it even scales with the shape.
If you, if x moves in the ellipsoid is
very big Then you have to
have more margin than if you moved in
another direction.
Okay that's it says summary is this,
you can solve deterministic robust LP via
SOCP.
Okay let's look at the stochastic
approach.
Well the stochastic approach Is this ai is
Gaussian with a mean ai ai bar and
a covariance sigma i, that's Gaussian.
Then that's a Gaussian scaler random
variable, right.
And that says that the probability that
the constrained holes is simply
the cumulative distribution function of
the normalized version of it.
So that's the margin Divided by, this is
something that has
that's a variable that has you know, zero,
one it's N zero one here.
Oh, sorry, yeah it is.
That's an N zero one variable.
And sorry if I put an AI there it's and N
zero one variable.
And then this simply gives you the
probability right?
Okay, so the robust LP, which looks like
this.
Becomes the following, oh, and we have to
be very careful.
It's this, to say that this is bigger than
that you need this probability here, to be
bigger than that if this is this thing
here is an increasing function of course.
With X, and it says that you have to have
this here.
Now the problem is, if this is,
if this thing is negative then this has
the wrong sign, right?
Otherwise, if this is positive, that's the
second order cone constraint.
If it's positive, and that's exactly For
eta bigger than one half, right?
So it's quite beautiful what this says, so
the interpretation is this.
If you say solve me the stochastic linear
program, with gau,
let's say Gaussian, Gaussian AI.
And with confidence level eta.
That means I want the constrains to hold
with probability eta.
And we already discussed what etas you're
interested in.
You're interested in 0,9, 0.95, 0.999,
something like that.
These are the ones you're interested in.
Okay.
For those, you get an SOCP.
You solve it.
But what's super interesting about this is
the following.
Is, mathematically it says that you get a
context problem provided eta is
bigger than half.
Right, so you get a very strange things.
Let's right down some values of eta here.
Let's have 0 point 1 and 0 point 9.
Right?
So this, this asymmetric interest in
whether we can solve this problem.
That's interesting because that's robust
optimiation.
That says I want the constraints to kind
of hold 90% of the time.
They can violate 10.
I don't want this.
I mean unless I'm in, unless I'm
absolutely desperate.
This says please find an x for which each
consraint holds one in 10 times.
So, you don't do that.
I mean, well, it all comes down to risk
aversion, right?
if, if you adverse to risk, this is quite
bad, right?
If your sucess rate is 10%.
Now, by the way, if you're, if you're in
some, eh,
this is some active, huge desperation, you
might take 10%.
But, generally we're not interested in it.
And that's super good, because guess what.
You can't solve that problem anyway.
You can solve this one because its an s of
c p.
These are actually quite difficult
problems and you can't solve em anyway.
So you get this weird asymmetry.
There's two problems.
We as a practical matter these are the
ones that we really want to solve and
we don't really care about these And then
as fate would have it,
it turns out the competition complexity of
the two problems is hugely different.
And it turns out, the one we want to solve
is exactly the one we can solve.
The one that we don't really want to solve
is the one we can't solve anyway.
So I don't know.
It's kind of cool.
I mean, you might imagine a world where we
would have 2
versions of various problems and there be
the ones we want to solve,
the ones we don't want to solve, the ones
we can solve, the ones not solved.
And yo might imagine they might split as
0.25.25.25.25, right.
So, in other words, Whether or
not we can solve a problem is independent
of whether we want to solve it.
But and this is just as a weird, I mean
don;t take any of these too seriously.
But as a weird observation, the following
holds.
There's strong correlation between the
problems that we want to solve and
the one we can't.
So, it's bizarre, but it's to be true, and
this is an example of it.
The next application we're going to talk
about is geometric programming.
And this is fun because it's in a
different group,
a different typeof convex optimization
problem.
It's one Then in one form, it's natural
form is actually not a convex problem so
it's a problem well, we'll see it's not
convex but you change variable and
it becomes convex.
So that's what's interesting about the
next class of problems.
So that's geometric programming.
So first a couple of definitions in
geometric programming you were referred to
a monomial as a function that looks like
this it is a Product.
Their variables, the variables are all
positive in geometric programming so
they're all positive numbers.
Its a product of these variables, each one
raised to a real power.
So these coefficients a one, a two, up to
a n,
they can be negative, they can be
fractional, anything and
the coefficient has to be positive and
this is called a monomial.
Now I should say that there is a
definition of monomial.
Its been used for a hundred or maybe more
than probably more than a hundred years in
mathematics and this is like it but its
not at all the same thing.
A monomial in mathematics is a single term
polynomial but
here these coefficients a one through a n
Have to be integers,
non negative integers and the coefficient
in front, c, can have any sign.
So unfortunately, if someone says
monomial, you have to
determine whether that's in the very
narrow context of geometric programming Or
whether that is in the broader context of
just mathematics.
Anyway.
So, we'll call it a monomial.
Now a, a posynomial is I mean in addition
to being very, very awkward nomenclature.
And it's supposed to be a combination of
polynomial and positive.
So anyway, who knows why this term was
coined?
It was, this was coined in the early 60s.
And it's simply a sum of monomial.
So it has a form that looks like that.
and, and it's not quite the same as a
positive polynomial.
however, if you have a polynomial with
non-negative coefficients.
That is a posynomial.
But posynomials is much broader because it
has, these coeffecients can be negative,
the, sorry the exponents, and, they can
also be fractional, which is not true for
a polynomial.
Okay.
And finally we get to a geometric program,
that is an optimization problem that looks
like this and
at first it's, there's going to be
something a little bit strange about it.
Its minimize a posynomial because all the
f's are going to be posynomial,
subject to posynomial inequalities and the
right hand side is one.
Well it has to be one because a monomial
and a posynomial the value for
any partiuclar x is actually going to be
positive.
So the value's positive so They, you could
never have x less than or equal to zero.
I mean if you did, the problem would be
easy to solve, there's no,
it's infeasible.
So it's less than or equal to one and then
a bunch, and
then the equality constraints have the
form of a mononomial equal to one, right?
So this is very, very different from what
you would C in a convex problem.
In a convex problem of course all equality
strains have to be affine.
Here's one where these are decidedly not
affine.
Oh, one other connection to things people
talk about in
areas like mechanics people talk about a
scaling law.
That's another name by the way for
something like a scaling law.
it says something like F scales as x1 to
the 1, x2 to the minus 2.3 or
something, and so that's a scaling law.
So some people would even call a monomial
a scaling law.
Okay, so that's a geometric program.
And it is obviously not a convex problem.
I mean for example, square root of x.
Is a mononomial, which is of course
therefore a posynomial, so
I can minimize square root of x.
But the square root of,
the square root of a variable x it's a
concave function, it's not convex.
And of course you could add things like
this, x1 x2 equals 1.
The product, that's obviously not convex
so, but this is a gp.
Okay.
Now, the interesting thing about GPs,
which are not convex, is that they can be
transformed to be convex problems.
By actually, you take two changes of
variables, and
they're both very interesting.
And I'll, I'll say what they are.
The first is this.
All our variables are positive, so As
actually happens,
I mean a lot of people have just figure
out for other reasons.
when you have a problem setting where all
variables are possible.
But it's actually often a good idea to
work with the logs of the variables.
Fine.
And in fact, that's correct.
If someone is talk, telling you about a
scaling log,
they'll plot something on a log log plot.
The fact that the second log, that would
be the log on the horizontal axis.
That is used.
It's a logarithmic scale.
that says that you should really work at
the log of the variable.
So, well we'll take yi's to be the log of
the variables.
And that means they're unconstrained.
They're not constrained to be positive.Oh
I should say,
that there is an implicit constraint.
That a monomial and posynomial domain is
positive, right?
And it actually has to be strictly
positive.
If any of these alphas are negative, of
course.
Okay.
Alright, now if you take a monomial and
you take [COUGH] and
you write each xi as e to the yi, and you
take a product of e to the yi as if I
take something like e to the y1 to the a1,
and I take this product times e
to the y n to the an, and I put a c in
front of it.
That's the minomial expressed in the y
variables.
But you know what that is, it has the
form.
I'm going to write it this way; e to the,
this is exactly,
e to the a transpose y plus b, where b is
log of c, the constant.
And that's of course where we need, this
is where we need c to be positive.
Right.
And so that says that a monomial in the
variables y,
these logorithmic variables, is actualy an
exponential of an affine function.
Okay, so if you take the log of a monomial
you get an affine function.
When it's expressed, when it's expressed
in terms of the logs of
the original variablces so you would say
something like this monomial transforms do
an affine function with two logrythmic
transformations.
The first one you work not with the
variables but
with the log of the variables that is sort
of before.
Cause you transform the variables.
You then also transform the monomial
itself.
The monomial itself transforms.
You take the log of it, and that
transforms this into, so
you do a posterior, and a prior
logarithmic transformation.
And you end up with something that's
affine.
A posynomial, that's something that looks
like this.
That, well it's the same thing.
Each each of the monomials looks like
that.
It's an exponential of an affine function.
You sum them.
That is afterall what a posynomial is.
And you take a log and you see something
super cool.
that the log of a posynomial expressed in
logarithmic variables.
Is the log sum x of an affine function.
That's it.
So actually its really cool.
Binomials have been transformed by a duo
logarithmic transformation into
affine functions and posynomials have been
transformed into convex functions by
duo logarithmic transformation.
By duo I mean that you take the log of the
vaiables and work with those and
also you take the log of the So that gp
converts to this problem.
It's minimize log sum exp of affine,
subject to log sum exp of affine less than
0, and affine.
And Sure enough, it is a convex problem,
right?
And so the meaning is this,
the practical meaning is that if you see a
GP we can solve it.
We can solve it globally, we can do every,
no, we can do anything you want,
We can do it, we have strong guarantees,
we can find a global solution.
All sorts of things like that.
It's basically.
And sometimes people say GP is convex.
Technically, that's false; this is not a
convex problem.
And if I were to write down an instance of
it,
this, generally speaking, is not a convex
problem, right?
You can do things like minimize the square
root of a variable.
You can handle Equality constraints, lets
say that x one times x two equals one.
These are not convex constraints and yet
we can solve this by change of variables,
transformation of variables.
By the way you don't, when you actually
solve it the data is the same so
not much changes.
So in other words in the GP, so the data
are the same.
In to describe a GP.
What I have to do is for each monomial
term in the object, in the objective and
the constraint functions, and for each
monomial in the equality constraints,
I have to give you the coefficient and
exponents.
But that's t he same here.
Right?
And they simply are the coefficients here.
So, so it's absolutely no different.
OK.
Now you know what a GP is.
And what's interesting now is, it turns
out, this is something that, you know,
it goes back to the 60s, a few people know
about it.
actually, remarkably, it was not known
widely that this was
a complex optimization problem actually
even into the 80s.
So there'd be people who'd write articles
saying something like,
they'd invented a new method for GP and
they could solve a problem Well, you know,
with up to fifty variables in mere
minutes, or something like that.
So it was only, yes, it was indeed in
Moscow that it
was observed that this transformation
makes this a part of convex optimization.
So any method for convex optimization can
be applied to GP.
That tells you, you can solve GPs with
tens of thousands or many more variables.
Using just completely basic methods.
Oh I should also mention, there's actually
a wonderful the original book on GP
which in fact popularized not only the
term GP but
also this bad nomenclature, monomial and
posynomial.
The book is absolutely wonderful.
It goes through and it actually talks,
it describes a whole bunch of GP's
applications to like you know,
power transformer design and all sorts of
other stuff.
And in fact the book focuses on problems
you can solve exactly.
Right, so they reduce it to this, and
they have maybe two constraints, three
constraints, and something like that.
And they, they solve these things exactly.
And the very last paragraph in the book.
Just truly wonderful.
The very last chapter says that, it says
that it says that,
that solving gps in, in cases when you
can't do it by hand, and I,
I mean literally by hand, you know,
calculus.
You get out your old pen and paper and
start writing derivatives down and things
like that.
It says that it's entirely possible that
by programming computers correctly
A computer could automatically solve a GP.
So, I mean, anyway, I thought that was
kind of cool.
And it turns out, that was from, that's a
book from 1961 or something like that.
The answer is, you fast forward whatever
it is, 30, 40 years.
The answer is, you bet, and that's exactly
what's happened.
Okay.
So
what we're going to do now is actually
just look at,
we're just going to look at one example of
a GP.
It is a non-trivial one.
And it's, you know, taken from a book from
mechanicial, mechanial design.
And it's designed to [UNKNOWN] a lever
beam.
So here it is.
We're going to design a beam that looks
like this.
Its going to have segments here and each
of these beams, they're going to
be connected and then I'm going to simply
put a force at the tip of this beam.
I should say what our variables are.
Our variables are these beams.
We can do the height so you can see the
height here That's HI.
What you can't see is the width, because
the width would come out of the page here.
So that's the, the width of the, of it.
And what is completely clear is sort of
that,
the stronger, this cantilevered beam.
It's, it's bigger.
Then it's, I mean it's, even if you have
deeper segments and wider segments.
It stronger, it's stiffer, and its stiffer
means that if apply this force at
the tip it says that the beam will deflect
less, right?
So roughly speaking, what happens is, I
can put a lot of deal in my being,and I
can put a big force it will deflect only a
little bit, or
I can make these things pretty wimpy and
you know flat, and, and
very weight very lightweight but the point
then is it'll be quite flexible.
You put of force and it will bend quite a
bit.
Right and you probably also have some
basic intuition about it.
For example, if you thought about these
things mechanically and
if you fiddle with things build things
with wood or anything else.
You probably have some intuition telling
you that height gives you
more stiffness than width.
Right?
You probably,
you may know that if you're trained in
mechanical engineering, you for
sure know that, or civil engineering, you
know that.
But even if you don't, you should have
that intuition, right, that, well,
think of it this way.
If I take a 2 by 12, it's a whole lot
stronger if I push, if I set it end up,
like this, push on this end, then if I
turn it flat like that, and
push on that end.
It's a lot stronger.
So, anyway.
So the variables are we're going to
calculation,
we're going to optimize the
cross-sectional area of each segment.
So it's actually kind of an in interesting
beam, right.
It can actually change shape.
It can be deeper and it can taper to
something thinner.
I mean who knows what it is right.
And here's what we want.
We're going to minimize the total weight
of this thing.
That's the total amount of steel I mean if
it's made out of steel.
And that weight is usually a surrogate in
a design like this for cost.
Something like that.
So, it's the tot, we'll minimize total
weight.
We'll have upper and lower bounds on the
width and height.
You'll have a maximum and a lower and a,
and a minimum for each one.
And we can do upper and lower bound on the
aspect ratio, so
you can't make something that has an
aspect, you know, that looks like this.
Right?
Where it's super thin and too high and
you can't make something that looks like
that.
You probably wouldn't want to make
something that looks like that, but
you can't do it anyway.
So we'll have as, we'll have upper and
lower bounds on the as, aspect ratios.
What we'll do is we'll have an upper bound
on the stress in each segment.
So in each segment here when you load it
there's actually a stress here and
I I'm not going to go into what that is or
I will tell you exactly how its
calculated and I guess if your background
is in ME you would know these formulas.
We're going to have an upper bound on the
stress cause you know one one of the very
simple models of Mechanical failure is
that you have a maximum allowed stress and
if you exceed that you start getting
platsic flow or something like that, but
it doesn't matter for this problem we have
a maximum amount of stress and
we have another bound on verticle
deflection on the end of the beam.
That's here and that's going to be
soemthing like a surrogate That is
a surrogate for how stiff the structure
is.
if, if it deflects a lot, that's bad; it's
not stiff.
And if it deflects a little bit, that's
good; it's a stiff structure, okay.
And the variables are the widths and
heights, just to, to remind you.
Okay?
So alright, now the objective looks like
this, it's it's the sum of W I H I,
all the way up to H N W N, that's cross
sectional areas, and if the length,
all these things have the same length, so
you could multiply these by L.
And I guess to really get a weight you
then multiply by density of steel or
the, whatever the material is.
I mean, it, that's just a positive
constant, so we're not going to show it.
But look at this function.
It's a sum.
Well, it's actually to help you transpose
h.
That for sure is not convex, in w and h.
There's absolutely no doubt about it.
I'll tell you what this thing is though.
It's quadratic, so that is a quadratic
function of W and H.
But it is definitely not, I shouldn't have
used the word definitely, it is
definitely not convex, because the matrix
is not positive semi [UNKNOWN], right?
This is an It's a, it's a term, looks like
that.
There's sort of an i and an i and a 0 and
a 0, and this is your wh.
Right?
And so, this is, indeed looks like that
this quadratic form is this.
But of course this thing has split Eigen
values and
it's not, it's neither convex nor concave.
Right?
So the point here is just to show,
this is not a convex function.
Now, what is interesting is this a convex
function if
you work with the variables log w i and
log h i.
So if you work with the logs of the widths
and the heights, it's convex function.
Okay.
Now the aspect ratio and the, and the
inverse aspect ratio.
These are monomials, because this is
really h i to the 1 Wi to the minus 1 and
if you like you can put in all the other
h's and w's but to the zeroth power.
Okay, so that's the monomial, these are,
these are monomials, these things, okay?
So those are monomials, therefore by the
way, they're also hosinomials, right?
So for example if I tell you that the
aspect ratio has to be limited to 3 to 1,
no more than 3 to 1, I can write hi over
wi less than 3.
That is the same as one-third hi of wi
less than one.
That's a monomial constraint.
Now, the maximum stress on a segment is
given this way.
It's 6 times i, i is the segment number.
And I'm missing some constants in here,
right?
Some, you know, things like Young's
modulus and various other things.
There's things I'm just missing.
I'm not showing here.
And that doesn't matter.
i is the length the, is the.
Section number.
It basically tells you how far out the
beam you are, the [UNKNOWN] beam.
And it's divided by wi over this is
positive constant times wi
over hi squared.
That's a monomial, right.
So if I wanted to limit the maxium stress
that is absolutely a monomial,
that that is a monomial function.
Now the vertical deflection is to
calculate, you actually have to
calculate the vertical inflection and the
slope at each of the segments.
And these are done recursively, and it's
by a set of equations that works this way,
and they work backward from the tip, and
it says something like this,
it says VI Is equal to 12 times i minus 1
times this thing.
And I, I, I certainly won't go into any of
this, or where this comes from.
That's, that's that.
And then, y i is then given by this
formula, here.
And you start with vn plus 1 is yn plus 1
is 0.
Right.
And here E is Young's modulus.
And what, what we're going to do, the way
I'm going to argue that vi and yi
are posynomial functions and I'm going to
use And a very important property and so,
these are obvious things, but let me just
mention them.
The product of two monomials is a
monomial.
That's the first thing.
That's, that should be clear.
In fact, le, let's just go back because
it's just a set of simple rules.
If you take a product of two monomials,
you get a monomials.
You take the product of the coefficients
in front and
you add the, the associative coefficient
exponents.
Okay?
Posynomials are, are closed under sums.
That's clear.
Positive scaling.
That's also clear.
That's also cle, clear for a pot,
monomial.
And also things like for example, you can
take the square of a posynomial.
That's posynomial.
See you have all sort of obvious Rules
about how you can add hm,
things like that.
For example, here's another one for
monomials.
Ready?
The ratio of two monomials is a monomial.
Well, that's kind of obvious.
Because you just simply divide one of
these by the other, and
you can work it out.
Okay.
So, so there's a bunch of,
you know, rules that tell you about which
things are closed under which operations.
Okay.
Now let's look at these equations.
These things start at zero.
I mean in some sense that's a null monome.
It's not really because for a monomial the
coefficient's supposed to be positive, but
in any case.
Let's look, let's look at the first one
which is v n and y n.
So these just go away because they're all
zero.
And we look at that and that's a monomial.
On the next step, if you look at v sub n
minus 1, y sub n minus 1,
what you get is you get something that
looks like that.
And you're using the fact that that is a,
that these are monomials here.
That these are monomials, it's a monomial
plus monomial, that makes it a posynomial.
So By induction all of the Is and YIs are
posinomyials, okay so that's what it
means and that's very interesting because
we're interested in YN.
That's the deflection at the end, so Y0.
Okay, so, we right it this way,
we're going to right Y1 sorry, we're
going to right it this way.
We're going to minimize this that's a
posinomylia Subject to,
this is the way to say w is less than w
max.
That's a maximum width,
that's a minimum width, that's a maximum
height, that's a minimum height.
You need a segment, this would be the
aspect ratio maximum, and
the aspect ratio minimum.
And then, here I would have this is the
stress limit, that's also very simple.
So far everything has been simple but here
this one, we use the fact that y1 is
a posynomial function of the w's and the
h's, and it's given by that recursion.
Right?
So, By the way, the same as in LP people
will write down an LP,
not in the standard form because it's
kind of weird.
They actually wind it, they write down an
LP in general as,
I mean where in the convenient ways So
people don't really write these things.
You would just write that.
And you would say that, that's a GP.
No problem.
Cause everyone in
their head would know how to convert this
to that.
And if you have a, if you have a, a
modelling system.
Like cvx.
You just write things like this and that's
automatic to transform to that.
So you would just write stuff like that
and
you would write things like that, a ratio
and they would say that's a monomial and
you can have monomial less than a constant
and monomial bigger than a constant.
So something, you don't write it, you
would rarely write it this way unless you
would raw call A GP solver where you had
to produce the data in the canonical form.
These days with things like CVX there's no
reason to do that.
This is a waste of your time, so.
The next topic is generalized inequality
constraints, and
let me explain a little bit about what it.
What it is before we start.
What we're going to do, is we're going to
look at these constraints here, and
we're going to generalize these functions
to be vectors.
Okay, so that means up to now they've been
scales right, so f,
if you evaluate F three of X, that's a
number.
And the requirement, this is less than or
equal to zero.
So if F three of X is, you know, minus
0.01, that's fine.
If F three of X is plus 0.01, that's
infinitely bad.
What we're going to do now,
is we're actually going to allow these
things to be vectors.
And we're going to see, what does this
mean.
You know, we'll figure it out.
Now, though we do have inequalities.
These are inequality with respect the the
cone.
And so we'll have an inequality with
respect to a cone.
And a requirement here to be a convex
problem is you have equality constraints
as the only equa, have to be linear.
And the inequalities, here you have fi is
convex, is ki convex.
Right?
so that means that
Jensen's inequality holds but with respect
to the inequality induced by k i.
OK and there's several there's several
forms for these.
Usually they're quite simple but
of one that's very common now is something
called a conic form problem.
Some people would even call this the
modern cononical form for
a convex optimization problem.
Its this You minimize a linear function,
subject to linear equality constraints
and, an affine function is negative, is,
less or equal to 0 in respect to a cone k,
and the idea here is, if you take K to BR
plus to the M.
This describes a completely general linear
program.
But the idea is now you swap in a
different cone and
you get a different problem family.
We'll some very interesting ones in a
minute.
A lot of these things have names.
We will see some of them.
And these are mostly things that have come
up in the last 15 years.
Something like that.
The most famous by far is a so called
semi-definite programmer FDP.
So this is the following problem.
It looks deceptively simple it says this
minimize a linear function subject to
linear quality constraints and inequality
that involves just Matrices.
A single one.
That's it.
So it just says take an affine function of
matrices,
that's x1 F1 plus x2 F2 plus xn Fn plus G.
That's a symmetric matrix.
And you insist that that be negative
semidefinite.
There.
Oh, by the way, a constraint of this form
is called a linear matrix inequality and
the idea is if I were to make this, this
inequality here an ordinary inequality and
make everything a scaler this would be a
single linear inequality.
But now I simply capatilze the epson gs.
So the left-hand side is now a symmetric
matrix, and
I take the inequality on R and I make an
inequality on symmetric matrices, and
I get the so-called linear matrix
inequality.
So, minimize the linear function subject
to quality constraints, and
a single LMI, that's what these are
called.
That's a semidefiniate program.
And that's an example of a convex
optiumization problem with
a vector inequality constraint.
M'kay?
So, now there's a couple things we should
say because important to know.
Now it turns out, you look at this and you
say you just want an inequality and
the answer is something like this; If you
have multiple independant.
LMI's, I mean they're not independent,
I mean if you have multiple LMI's like
this: linear matrix inequalities.
You can always throw them together and
make one big one and
it's a very simple thing.
All you do is you put these together on
the diagonal of a bigger matrix,
like that and the off diagonals are just
zero.
And you're using the stunning fact that if
you
have a Block diagonal matrix then it's
positive semidefinite.
If and only if each of the blocks is
So the point there is that most people
realize that you can have multiple,
multiple LMIs and that's the same as
having one.
So people still just say its an SDP.
Okay.
Now it turns out SDP generalizes most of
the classes we've seen so far.
Not GP.
But other than that, it generalizes them.
For example, LP, you can write as an SDP.
You can write SOCP as an SDP.
Of course, that's, one's a stronger
statement than the other,
because you can represent an LP as an STP.
Sorry, as an SOCP.
And an SOCP can be represented as an SDP,
right.
So you can say things like we have the LP
and SOCP embeddings as SDPs right.
And this has,.
I mean, it doesn't really, it has some
implications.
if, if and when some indefinite program
solve, solvers are completely perfected
this will be beautiful because you'll just
have one solver for everything.
And if it, you'll just, if it's an LP
you'll form a certain type of STP and
solve it, but Okay, So here is a linear
program minimizing C transpose X
subject to X less than or equal to B.
And here's a semi definate program that's
equavilent what we do is we use a stunning
fact.
The diagonal, a diagonal matrix that's
positive semi definate if any only if.
All of it's entries on the diagonal are
bigger or equal to 0.
So, this is simple.
It's kind of silly, you know, so you would
say what's an LP?
And you could say, well it's an SDP but
with diagonal matricies, but
I mean, who cares?
OK.
SOCP is a little bit more interesting, so
how do you do that, how do you write this
SOCP As an SDP and
the answer is quite interesting, it goes
like this, this constraint,
that's a second order cone constraint,
that is a nonlinear constraint on x.
Well of course it's nonlinear, and it's
not even, it's not affine/g, right?
This is affine but that, of course, is not
affine.
And so what we're going to do is we're
going to write a non-linear,
non-affine function or constraint as a
linear matrix and equality.
That's quite interesting because a, you're
going to get some, the advantage you're
going to get something that's linear, or
let's look at it.
So you write it this way.
Now that's the identity, that's a scaler
That's a vector, that's a vector and
that's a scaling.
And it asserts that, it says that and
this is going to be by the sure
compliment, alright?
That's the sure compliment, idea.
And the sure compliment gives you, well it
tells you
various things about when a block Matrix
is positive semi definite.
And so that'll work this way.
This matrix is positive semi definite,
when, and we can write it either way.
There's two ways to do it.
But one is to say something like this.
You would say that it's, it's, when this
matrix is positive semi-definite, That's
multiple identity so that simply requires
CI transpose X plus DI bigger than 0 and
the short compliment of this matrix in
respect to that which is the following.
There's lots of ways to say it,
you can also start here but
you'd end up with something like this CI
transpose
X plus DI plus then So you have
to have that.
And there's a minus sign here I'm sorry
here we go, there we go.
So that's the shared compliment.
The shared compliment, well lots of ways
to say it, but it's something like this.
It's, it's, this, lots of ways, this minus
this times that inverse times that,
right so you get something that looks like
that.
Right?
Now this thing is positive so I can
multiply through by this, and
I get Norm ai x plus bi squared, here,
it's on the other side, is less than or
equal to this thing squared.
And I take the square root and I invoke
this, and I get exactly this, okay?
So that's the idea, so
you would say that you can embed A second
order cone program as an SDP.
Okay.
Let's look at another problem.
It's again quite, quite interesting.
Let's minimize the maximum Eigenvalue of a
symmetric matrix which is
an afine function of a variable x.
Eh, so for example I could have a matrix
and I have some entries in it.
That I'm allowed to choose.
Some are fixed, some I can choose.
That they would have this form.
And the question is, how do you choose
those entries.
In such a way to, as to minimize, so
as to minimize the maximum Eigenvalue of
this matrix, right?
And before we start in on that, I want to.
Point out and you know this is convex,
right,
because that's one of the main things we
looked at we looked at
the maximum eigenvalue being a convex
function of a symmetric matrix and
a is an affine mapping so by composition
rule, that's a convex function.
But I want to point out how complicated
this is.
So If you were to tell somebody how do you
calculate this objective.
The answer would be well, you form this
matrix a.
Okay?
Then you calculate its characteristic
polynomial which is a, it's a,
by taking a determinant.
And you get this giant thing with n
factorial terms and
you collect all the terms and you get like
s to the n,
plus No trace A of X times F to the N
minus 1, and you'd get these coefficients.
Then you'd be asked to take, to find all
roots of that.
There would be N real roots, and you can
find them.
Now, you may know that there's no formula
for these roots, if N is 5 or bigger, so
just, it's not, there's not even a formula
for this, right?
There's a quadratic formula, there's one
for cubics, one for
quartics, there isn't one for quintics,
okay?
And then finally, you'd take all these
routes, and you'd take the largest of
them, and that would be the largest, that
would be the biggest eigenvalue, okay?
So the point is, this is very complicated.
In some sense.
It, well, if you describe it the wrong
way, it's very complicated.
But it turns out this is nothing but an
SDP.
It says minimize, a scale or T subject to
A of X is less or equal to T I.
And that's it.
Right?
And that's a matrix in equality and the
reason is this; The maximum eigenvalue of
a matrix is less than T if it only have A
Is less or equal to T I in a matrix sense.
The argument, you could make lots of
arguments,
you can argue with the eigenvalues or
however you like, but this is just
correct.
Oh, and I should say, this isn't quite in
LMI form, right?
Although, people would accept this as an
LMI because the left and
right hand sides are both affine.
You would want to, you would subtract it.
You'd write a of x, say, minus t i.
And that, that would be it.
The, there would be full LMI form.
But that's the same as this.
So, but the way, what's the upshot of all
this.
Semi-definite programs are not quite
tractable.
They're solved all the time.
I mean it's not as, it's not like linear
program.
You know.
So it's not like it's It's used everywhere
and it's super duper reliable.
It works like quite well.
And so that's a sense in which you would
do something to an SDP, and
in it's sort of solved.
So what that says is you can minimize the
maximum magin value of a matrix,
of an affine, affine-dependent matrix.
Okay.
We can do matrix norm minimization.
Again the trick is through the is through
sure compliments, right.
So the idea is you minimize the two norm
of a matrix.
That's a submetric maybe not even square
matrix, a.
Well, this is the Maximum item in A
transposed to A, and then the square root.
And here A is a matrix that's affine in
the variable x.
That's equivalent to an SDP.
Let's see how: you rewrite it as minimized
t,
subject to this matrix here being positive
semi-definite.
And again the trick is your compliments,
this matrix is positive semi-definite if
and only if -- we'll start here -- ti is
bigger than or equal to zero,
that requires t to be bigger than or equal
to zero, and ti minus a of x transposed,
times the inverse of this, times that is
positive semi-definite.
And that's exactly these inequalities
here.
RIght?
And this inequality is also is really
interesting.
That says this is exactly the same as
saying that lambda max of a transpose a is
less than or equal to t squared.
That, that's what this says.
Well, that is what we did on the previous
page.
Also, it's clear.
Okay?
But this, so therefore if I take the
square root, I get this, and the t,
the power goes away.
And that's exactly this, right there, so
that's the, in fact it's the epigraph.
So a fancy way to save this is that the
matrix two norm The matrix, the matrix
additional or the maximum singular value
its epigraph has an LMI representation.
That's how you would say this.
That's a sophisticated way to say this,
right?
And it's, it's really cool, so
it says you can transform a problem
involving a matrix norm.
To an STP.
I mean that, that's cool.
By the way, this is exactly how cvx works.
So in cvx you can write down the norm of a
matrix, it understands that,
that's convex.
If you minimize it, what happens is
exactly the argument here,
is converted to one of these block 2 by 2
matrices.
And if you wanted to you could even go in
and look at it.
You can trap the call before the cone
solver is solved, is, is called but
you would actually see this matrix there.
Okay?
Okay.
All right.
Our final generalization.
Of optimization problem is a bit more
complicated.
It's vector optimization.
So what we're going to do now, just to set
the context the last generalization we
looked at was we said what if these
constraint functions were not.
Were vectors and so then in turn we had a
standard idea of what it means for
a vector inequality to hold.
We'll do something a bit more comlicated
here, and
you have to be on your super-duper on your
toes with respect to the semantics.
We're going to minimize a vector function.
And By the way,
a lot of people just say well let's
minimize a vector function, and then.
But the thing is you have to say what that
means.
So, we'll say what it means in a, in a
bit, but
it's, it's not completely obvious and it
turns out you can have several meanings.
Okay.
So a convex vector optimization problem
looks like this.
You minimize with respect to a cone.
An objective that is a vector.
Right?
And we'll leave the, the, ineq, the
inequalities as scaler and, and
the equality constraints there of course
just linear.
Okay.
And, but the real question is what does
this mean.
And what you have to do then is you have
to go back to the original semantics of
Of an optimization problem.
So on optimization problem the semantic
goes like this.
You give me x, and somebody else gives me
another x.
Okay, x and x tilde.
The first thing I do with each one is I
evaluate fi of x.
And I check.
Do I alwaysget a number that's less or
equal to zero?
If I don't, I instantly throw that x back
at that person who gave it to me and
I say.
Not feasible, it's completely
unacceptable.
Okay?
The, I, by the way,
the same thing would happen if they gave
me an X that was out of the domain.
That's even worse, I would say, "your
point is so
bad I can't even evaluate the third
inequality constraint function." Okay?
And then I would check I would check to
see that hi of x is equal to zero.
By the way that is a typo.
So I would check then to see if hi of x
are equal to zero for each one.
If they are that's fine, if not then I
throw it back.
If both x and xy~ are feasible, so they
pass these tests.
Then how do I compare.
How do I say one is better than the other
and
the answer's extremelly simple in standard
optimization.
I evaluate the objective, right?
If you like to think of an objective as
having units of dollars, go ahead.
It's a cost.
Anyway, whichever one is less.
As a smaller objective is better, it's
cheaper, it does,
it satisfies all the constraints and it's
cheaper, it's better.
if by the way, if their different, if x
and x silly are different, and
have the same objective, I can't say which
one is better.
I, they simply, as far as this problem is
concerned, they are the same.
So that's the idea, now the problem here
is this,
If that's a vector I have to have a way of
saying one is better than another but
as you know if you have two vectors in a
vector inequality you can
have the very awkward situation where
there incomparable.
So that can and does happen and that's the
interesting part.
Now when that doesn't happen its easy to
say.
If there, if for example this is a two
vector and
you're minimizing with respect to r plus
2.
That simply means that each of the entries
should be smaller than the others and
if you come back and one person has one
more than the inequality/g,
one is better than the other, then it is
clearly better.
But we'll see what the other idea is.
Okay, so what we'll do is we'll look at
the set of achievable objective values,
now that's a vector, that's the point.
So for every feasible point conceptually,
we will simply record the, the objective
you attain and we'll call that O, for the
set of all objectives and here it is.
By the way For a scalar optimization
problem this is the simple thing.
It's a subset of the line.
There's the line and O might look like
this.
I mean it could look like that.
I mean it's absolutely going to be
connected in this case, so
it will be an interval.
Okay.
It'll look like that.
Then you'll say Okay.
I for a convex problem.
Say that's what it is and, and, and, you
know, if there is one.
If this is achieved, I guess I've drawn it
as achieved.
Then whichever x corresponds to that
point, that's optimal.
Okay.
But here it's a set in r, too.
Like, for example this one, or this one.
Okay?
And then we say the following.
X is optimal if this is the minimum value
of that set.
Now remember what the minimum value said.
The minimum value says that this point is
comparable to every other point in
the set, and is less than or equal to it.
In the cone sense.
So, these are, these are two pictures with
respect to r plus 2.
And it would say that there's a, a, a
point here which is comparable to
every other point up here, and less than
or equal to it, which means in fact, it,
it means that all these points are upper,
up and to the right.
Okay?
So that means, that says it's optimal.
And, yeah, by the way [COUGH] it's a very
strong form of optimal.
It says basically that you can minimize
Both this objective and
this objective simultaneously and you get
that point and
by the way if that happens that's
wonderful.
It usually doesn't.
The more interesting cases that o might
look like this, something like that.
Now its more interesting because we can
say is there we
can ask is there a point In this set O,
that is comparable to all other points in
O and better than it.
And the answer to this is there a point
where this, in this set, where every other
point in this set is up and to the right
and the answer is no, there's not.
But remember we have a weaker sense.
This is minimum and this is minimality.
Right so there's mini, minimum and
minimal.
And so we'll say that F zero of X is a
minimal value of O of X
then we're going to give the name Pareto
optimal.
That goes back about a hundred years.
Now Pareto optimal, it's subtle, it says
the following.
It says that there is no point in the set
that is better.
Okay?
Now, on the line all two, any two points
on the line are comparable.
And so these two, these two concepts of
optimality merge into one.
But in a vector optimization problem
that's actually not true --
they're different.
Here for example, in this case this point
is Pareto optimal.
And the reason is, there is these, if you
look down and
to the left, again this is with respect to
r-plus squared, left and down.
Those are all the up the values which are
better than the one you have.
Better means, by the way another name for
this like in economics is,
it says that better is dominates.
So you'd say that, for example this, this
point dominates that one.
Because it's, it's objective values which
is a vector is less than or
equal to that one.
So all of these points on this curve here
are Pareto optimal and
then from here on down.
Right?
These are not, and certainly that's not.
And one way to say it is something like
this.
If a point is not Pareto optimal, then
there is a better point in the set.
Okay?
So Another name for not Pareto optimal is
dumb.
It's a dumb choice because it says that I
can find a feasible point X
which beats yours unambiguously.
Right, that's it's less than or equal to
in the, the cone.
Okay.
Now a very common case of this is just
multicriterion optimization.
That's that's when you have your comparing
with respect to the cone, non negative or
than and one way to think of that is
vector optimization.
That's another name for it.
The objective is a vector and
you think of each of these As a separate
objective function.
Right so, for example these might be you
know in a circuit design,
this might be power and area or something
like that, you might have two of them,
you might have two or three, power, area
and delay for
a circuit and then you'd, well then these
are all things you would want to be small.
And so that's kind of the idea.
In finance these would be things like cost
or negative profit and
the second one might be some kind of
measure of risk or something like that.
You want low risk and you want high
profit.
Which isn't low and negative profit.
So a naturally criterion problem with two
that's called bicriterion Ok so
you think of these two different
objectives and the idea is you
want them all to be small and you'd say
that a point is optimal if this holds.
If whenever x is if x is if x is optimal
if whenever y
is feasible you have f zero of x is less
than or equal to y and
what that means is It means that you have
simultaneously minimized all objectives.
Now that, by the way, rarely happens,
right?
This is what happens very often.
A point, which is feasible, is Pareto
optimal if the following is true.
If you have another feasible point that is
less than or
equal to this one, That in fact they're
equal.
And that's the idea.
So roughly speaking, if you have Pareto
optimal points it
says that there's a tradeoff between the
objectives.
That's what it says.
So let's do a simple case, regularize
these squares.
That says I would like ax -
b 2norm squared to be small That means I
want good fit.
But I also want the norm of x to be small
too.
Now, in this case we can characterize
exact what o looks like,
I mean we don't have to do it but here it
is drawn.
So the idea is -- look!
-- there's an x that achieves that value.
Now that's not very interesting, right?
Because it's basically It achieves a
terrible value of fit right and
at the same time its quite large.
So it hasn't done very well on anything.
Right?
So
now all our focus is going to end up being
on this little part right here OK and
on that little part right there this
boundary is Pareto optimal and
we can even say what the different ones
are.
For example this point right here, it's
very interesting.
It achieves a value of the size of x of
zero.
And so what, what x is that correspond to?
It can only correspond to X equals zero.
And so this tells you, at that point, but
10 is the value of norm squared of b,
okay?
I mean, the numbers don't matter, but
that's what it is.
All of these points in here are Pareto
optimal.
And you would say, there's a trade-off of
fit versus size of x; that's a,
that's the trade-off.
And another name for the, this Pare-, this
Pareto op-, this Pareto optimal curve is
the optimal trade-off curve of fit versus
size, for example.
So, this is the idea.
A very famous case of this is in finance.
So risk, return, trade-off and portfolio
optimization.
This is due to Markowitz.
And this is the early 50's, right?
Very early 50's right, '52, '53, something
like that.
Okay?
And the idea heere is
we want to minimize two things.
This is negative, profit.
Right.
Or negative return, mean return.
And that is return variance.
So here, x gives you an investment
portfolio.
So x i is the fraction of things you
invest in, asset i.
Then p is a vector of These are asset
price changes .It's the, it's a return.
And that's modeled as a random variable
with mean P bar and covariance.
So the mean return is P bar transpose X,
that's this one.
And this is the variance.
And so what this says is, I want small
variance and I want a large return.
By the way, it's traditional to put in One
of the assets is cash or T bills or
something and that's supposed to be 0
variant right, so
that's the, that's traditional in this
model.
Okay so here if I solve this problem this
I can work out the trade off curve here
and we'll see why, how to do that shortly,
but you'd get something like this.
You'd plot it Here you don't plot the
square root of x transposed sigma x,
which is the standard deviation.
That's like the risk, and that is the
return, right?
And so it would say that, for example,
here's something where by investing all
of your money in whatever is the most It
the most riskless option that
appears to be the fourth asset here cause
that's at 0 here's the,
it's all in X 4 and that gives you a
return of you know 3% and almost 0 and
maybe even exactly 0 risk so that would be
T bills, not now by the way but
maybe 15 years ago.
And then as you move up here you can see
these are the optimal points these
correspond to different points here
probably.
These kinks over here.
And you'd say that this is the preeto
curve by the way it's traditional to
draw it this way and
not the usual way, and the reason it goes
up like that and the reason is good.
Is up and here good is to the left.
Right?
Because you want low risk, high return.
Okay and so if you were to switch this
around and
make it a negative that would be going
kind of the way that you expect.
Okay, so that's a this is a very classic
example of a two multi-criterion
optimization with two criteria and in fact
you call that a bicriterion problem.
Okay now, scalarization.
How do you find Pareto optimal points, and
the answer's pretty easy.
You choose a vector, landa, which is
positive in the dual-cone, and
you solve this ordinary scalar
optimization problem.
Now what's cool is if this is a convex
problem here The original one was
a convex vector optimization problem.
When you scalarize you get a convex scalar
optimization problem which we
can solve and the meaning is really
simple.
What it is if you take,
if you take a value of Lambda, if you take
Lambda like this That's the normal.
And it says, basically goes as far as you
can in the minus land of
direction while still being in the O.
And so what you're going to do is your
going to get the tangent there.
So lambda sets the slope.
And then what you do,
is you find the point that it tangent to
the set of achievable values.
And here it is for one lambda and here it
is for Another value, lambda one and
lambda two.
Now and what is always true, convex or
not,
is that if you carry out this procedure
you get points that are Pareto optimal.
That, that happens always.
Of course if it's not convex you can't
solve that problem, but
if you could you'd get something that was
Pareto optimal.
What is very interesting is that when the
problem is, the original problem,
is a convex vector optimazation problem
you get almost all Pareto-optimal points.
And the reason is roughly speaking iit's
because o is convex.
That's actually false.
O is not necessarily convex but it's
lower, the, we care about the lower left
part of it, or roughly speaking, and that
actually always is convex.
We'll get to that.
Now, for multi-criterion problems when you
scalarize,
you are simply minimizing a weighted sum
of objectives.
I mean, this is very old idea, it's so
intuitive that people don't even say it.
I mean, ever since you took any class on
anything people would say what are we
going to minimize?
We'll minimize this thing plus little bit
of that.
You add some regularization and you add,
and
someone says what's that coefficient
there?
And you say that so weight you mess with,
right?
So, it's weighted minimization, right?
So here that's the interpretation of land
is it's the vector of weights,
that relate these objective functions.
And this you know, nice economic
interpretation for example you can
think of this F1 up to FQ, these as being
some kind of cost or consumption.
But they could be in different units.
I mean they could, one could be in
kilowatt hours and
another one could be in dollars.
It could be a direct cost.
And now you have to add them up.
And you can actually think of the lambdas
as a set of prices.
For example, in that case, well,
if the first one were dollars, lambda 1
would be 1.
If lambda q, if Fq is in kilowatt hours,
lambda Q has a beautiful interpretation.
It's a price.
It's the price in dollars per kilowatt
hour.
And it's whatever needs to happen if you
want to include the physically units in
the lamba you're welcome to too.
But it's whatever has to happen so you can
add these up and
put them on the same scale another
interrputation is that these weights
are more abstract they just tell you how
much you care, how irratated it makes you.
If lambda, if, if the different ones.
So there if you have lambda 1 as 1,
and lambda q is 10, that's as someone
says, What's that all about?
And you say, well that just means that I
find a unit increase in fq to be
ten times more irritating than a unit
increase in f1.
So they're, they're just realtive weights.
Okay.
Now when to apply to
the regularized least-squares problem,
well you just get this.
I mean, and there's our,
there's our friend, well I guess in
statistics you call this ridge regression.
Because you're minimizing a traditional
least-squares objective.
And you add plus gamma times the norm
squared of x,
and that's the least-squares problem, and
for any gamma we can solve this.
And this will trace of this curve like
this.
It won't get you exactly that point and
since gamma,
since we're insisting gamma is positive it
doesn't get you This point, either, but
as gamma goes to 0, you get closer and
closer.
And as gamma goes to infinity you get
closer and closer to this point, here.
That's the, that's the that's the idea
here.
okay.
So, that's scalarization.
And in finance, if you apply it there,
what you end up min,
you minimize a that's negative return,
mean return.
Plus gamma times x transpose sigma x
that's risk and so
people would normally write that this way.
That you would maximize p bar transpose x.
That's your that's your mean return minus
x gamma x transpose sigma x and
this has a beautiful name, this is called
risk adjusted return right?
There's your return, which is really an
expected return, and
this is a risk adjustment, meaning that
they are subtracting from
the expected return something that
penalizes risk.
And by the way gamma has a beautiful name
in this case: gamma is
called the risk aversion parameter.
You turn it to get different portfolios!
And if you turn it Very low, if gamma's a
small number, you'll end up
with something that has very high return,
and probably high risk as well.
And if gamma gets really big,
you'll end up in this problem, basically
putting all of your,
concentrating your portfolio in low-risk
investments, or something like that.
So these are, this is the idea.