Today we're going to look at applications
well geometric problems.
And again some of these are very, very
simple and so we actually skip them.
Things like computing projections of a
point onto a convex set.
Doing things like calculating distance
between two convex sets.
These are just to simple to even mention.
So we're going to skip those although
they're, they're kind of obvious by now.
Now an example of that would be how do you
compute the distance between two
polyhedron, right?
So without even writing it down you should
know by now that's just a qp.
You know you minimize norm x minus y two
norm subject to,
you know, a x less than b and f x less
than g.
Okay, so we don't cover that kind of stuff
because it's too simple.
Instead we're going to focus on stuff
that's kind of less obvious and
really I mean quite interesting and very
useful.
So the first topic is going to be the
Lowner-John ellipsoid and this,
this is not obvious, although these have
been know for about 100 years.
Although not, nothing was known about it
computationally, right,
this was not a algorithmic thing, this was
just theory.
Until maybe 20 years ago.
So basic idea is you want to compute the
minimum volume ellipsoid that
covers a set, and it's completely general.
So I have a set, C.
And what I want to do is compute the
minimum volume ellipsoid that covers it.
So, that's, that's the idea.
By the way there's tons of applications
with this, right.
One would be to give a C could be very
large, very complex.
And instead all you want is sort of a
summary of, of, C a, that is a,
is, is a smaller right, and so.
To describe an ellipsoid takes on the
order of N squared,
in fact N squared over two perimeters to
describe a an ellipsoid in R, N.
So that's sort of an compact way to do
this.
And this approximation covering a bunch
of,
when you're covering a bunch of points.
It's a conservative one I guess so
you'd say you going to cover more then
just the points.
Alright, now generically you can solve
this problem.
I should be more careful about it.
We can generically write this as a convex
optimization problem.
So, computing the minimum volume
ellipsoid.
But that's going to be an expression that
comes up in
the constraints that may be handled,
depends on
that being tractable before this becomes a
tractable convex program, right?
Oh, and I guess we've we're far enough in
the class that it's time for you to, we,
we can actually be more honest here.
And, admit things like, there are non
tractable convex optimization problems.
This is kind of obvious, right?
'Cuz if I write a convex optimization
problem.
But for example, to evaluate the objective
or
a constraint function, is itself
intractable.
Then you're in trouble, right?
So, okay.
So what we'll do is we'll,
there's a very carefully chosen
parameterization of the ellipsoid.
And we're going to write it as this.
It's the inverse image of the unit ball
under an affine mapping, right?
So, so, we're going to take the ellipsoid
e to be the center points for
which the two norm of av plus b is less
than one, right?
So that's the inverse image of the unit
ball under the affine mapping.
A v plus b.
Okay, now here a here a of course could be
anything well I mean it has to be square.
Well it wouldn't even have to be square
but we can without loss of
generality we're going to take a to be
symmetric positive definite.
Now the argument there, I'm just going to
go over it very briefly here, so
this is going to be obscure, but hopefully
you can follow.
The argument is this.
Here I can multiply a and b on the left by
any orthogonal matrix, and
it will define the same ellipsoid.
Everyone agree with that?
Because it doesn't change, it doesn't
change the norm, but
if that's the case I can take an arbitrary
non-singular matrix.
Multiply on the left by an appropriate
orthogonal matrix and
make it symmetric positive definite,
right?
And the way you do that, again, I'll just
talk through it because it's,
I don't know.
We're far enough along.
If we can do this, we can go faster.
You just take the singular value
decomposition of A.
So you have u sigma v transposed and
you multiply on the left by like you know,
v u transposed.
And that's an orthogonal matrix and
it converts into a symmetric positive
definite, okay?
So that's the idea.
Now the volume of this ellipsoid is
proportional to the determinate of
A inverse.
In fact the constant of proportionality is
exactly the volume of the unit.
Right?
Which actually doesn't for
minimizing, it hardly matters what that
is.
It's something, it's got some Pi's in it,
some gamma functions, or
factorials and things like that, but it
doesn't really matter.
It's proportional to the determinant of a
inverse, right?
Because when you, when things map under
aphi mappings, or
linear mapping, aphi mappings, volumes
transforms like determinants.
Okay?
So now the problem looks like this, it
says minimize.
Over variables, A and b, log det A
inverse, right?
So that's the log of the volume, well up
to a constant, right?
Because it's an additive thing.
Subject to the condition that every point
C is in this set.
And one way to say that is that for every
point in C,
the norm of Av plus b is less than one,
right?
So and you can write this, this way or
you can write it as, I could remove the
soup and say for all v and c.
Okay, and that would be the, the
condition.
Right, so that's the, that's the
You might ask, why does it say in
parentheses here, over ab?
Because these,
well this kind of problem generically ends
up with maximally confusing notation.
And then of course, norm, norm of linear,
is convex.
And this is true for any v.
So, supremum.
That's pointwise supremum.
That's convex.
So, okay.
So here, that's a convex optimization
problem.
And it computes the minimum volume
ellipsoid that covers the set c.
Now, the question is whether it's
tractable or not.
And it's tractable precisely when.
This constraint is handleable, right?
So here's a simple case where it is.
There's actually a whole bunch where it
is.
I mean, not a whole bunch, but there's a
bunch of cases where it's tractable.
But here's one where it is.
Let's look at this.
Let's take c to be a finite set.
So I have a cloud of points.
And I want to compute the minimum volume
ellipsoid that covers it.
Right, so that's the idea.
So here, well that's very simple, because
the, v and z is nothing but a,
it requires that each, each of these
points is in the set.
And so you get this.
And of course that's the Lowner-John
ellipsoid for
a polyhedron described by its, its
vertices, right?
So what that says is, if I give you a
bunch of points like this and
then you calculate.
Then you take the convex whole, right?
Then computing the minimum volume
ellipsoid that covers that
is an entirely tractable convex problem,
okay?
So by the way these things are, are not
obvious here.
So for example if I, I could give you an
ellipsoid described as, sorry a polyhedron
described as the convex hull of a set of
points, so as I could give you vertices.
And I could ask, find me the maximum
volume ellipsoid that lies inside it.
That's, that's another natural problem
that we'll look at shortly.
That's, that's actually in b hard, okay?
So, so these things are,
I mean you really have to be very careful
with these things, right?
Depends on the description and it depends
you know, whether it,
it's extremely easier or extremely hard,
depends on the description.
Okay, so that's the Lowner-John ellipsoid.
Well the duel roughly of that is the
maximum volume inscribed ellipsoid.
So here, we have a this time the set has
to be convex.
I mean it doesn't have to be convex, but
then it's actually quite intractable,
right?
So we take a convex set.
And then the idea is,
we want to find the maximum volume
ellipsoid that sits inside it.
Okay?
And we do that this way.
This time, we're going to parameterize the
ellipsoid as the forward image as
opposed to the inverse image of a unit
ball under an aphi mapping.
So here, it's the set of points bu plus d
where u is in a unit ball.
Right?
So by the way there are lots of different
parameterizations of ellipsoids as general
linear algebra that would go between the
different cononical representations right?
It would be elementary linear algebra like
square roots of matrices,
things like that.
What's interesting is they all have
different convexity properties.
Right?
So the problem would be convex in one, but
not the other.
So, whenever you have problems in.
When you optimize over ellipsoids, they're
actually kind of fun.
Because it's not,
it's not like a problem where something's
just given to you on a platter.
You have to figure out the appropriate.
Representation to make it convex.
If, if, if it's, if it, if that even
exists.
Right.
So.
Okay.
So here's the forward image.
And in this case the volume is
proportional to the determinant.
We want to maximize it, so we maximize log
log determinant, right?
Which you recognize as tractable, because
log determinant is concave.
And here the condition is this.
This condition right here is simply this.
Right?
So that's the, that, this condition here
says that if you take the image, the unit
ball, and you multiply b by it,
add d, that this set lies entirely in c,
so that looks like this, right?
I mean this is just a long and complicated
way to say that for
all u of norm less than one, bu plus d is
in c, right?
I guess this is, it's written this way so
we can verify instantly that this is
convex, right?
And the way to do that is very simple.
This thing, that expression is linear and
the variables, which are b and
d, I see that the indicator function,
that's of course convex.
So that's convex.
So for each u, this is convex.
That's a suprimum of convex functions, so
that the left-hand side is convex.
So you have a convex inequality.
Okay, so again, once again the issue is
the following,.
Is this, is evaluating that function
tractable right,
in these very simple cases where it's not.
Here's one if I simply give you a finite
number of points and I ask you does that
hold there, that's actually, that, that
one is actually going to be hard.
Right.
None that I find a never point, sorry.
The convex hull of a finite number of
points.
That's actually np hard.
Right?
So so
sometimes it's tractable, sometimes it's
not.
But here and has kind of a pretty duality
here.
What's interesting is It turns out
remember that, computing the minimum
volume of ellipsoid is tractable the
cononical cases when you get the vertices.
So computing the maximum volume of
ellipsoid is tractable and
again almost es, esthetics almost requires
this, right?
Because just to make it pretty.
It's the dual representation of an
ellipsis,
of a polyhedron which is in fact given by
its linear inequalities, right?
So, so what happens is here.
If I give you a polyhedron defined by
linear inequalities,
then this is really simple because
basically you're asking, when is it true
that a i transposed times b u plus d Is
less than bI for all u less than one.
Right.
That's the question.
What are the conditions on B and D under
which this holds, right?
And this is actually relatively easy to
work out.
Right.
So you have aI transposed d
that comes out fine, and then here, you
need to calculate, you know,
what's, what's the largest possible value
of that.
But that's easy.
That's the converse [UNKNOWN] inequality
right?
Because it says you have a you have
something which is b a i, and then you
take an inner product of b a i with a
vector u whose norm is less than one, you
want to know the maximum value of that,
and the answer is the norm of b a i right?
That's [UNKNOWN] the converse of
[UNKNOWN], okay?
So that problem translates to this, that
is again, you have to be on your toes
here, because the variables are B and d,
which parameterize the ellipsoid here, and
that otherwise, these are just completely
legitimate constraints.
That's clearly a concave function that
you're maximizing.
And the inequality here, again, with B and
d, that's a linear term here.
That's linear in B, right, and so that
norm terms, so
these are second-order constraints.
So there's actually some very interesting
things you can show about these
ellipsoidal approximations.
so, let's take a convex, you know,
bounded, nonempty interior set, and
it's the following, that there's actually
this basic efficiency.
It says that if you take a set, so
here's one, here's a polyhedron given by
its vertices.
This the loner John Ellipsoid, the minimum
volume ellipsoid covers it,
it says that if you take that loner John
Ellipsoid and
you shrink it by a factor of N, that's
this space dimension, right?
About its center.
That's guaranteed to be inside the set,
okay?
Everybody got that?
And so actually what that says is that you
can,
I'm going to say it something like this,
it says that any convex set in RN can be
approximated within a factor, in fact
here, I'll leave and try it this way.
Within a, it can be approximated within a
factor square root n by an ellipsoid.
Everybody got that?
Now I mean you might not like to factor
square root n.
But the point is, that's what that is.
Everybody or anybody, by the way that
statement is completely false.
I mean you can talk about things like with
other, with other classes of.
Geometric objects, right?
You could talk about things like a
bounding box, right?
And it's just completely false, right?
All sorts of other things you might
imagine.
Things, data structures to describe,
regions in rn.
And it's just not, not the case.
I mean, there are others, right?
One would be like a simplex, right?
So that's another one.
Now by the way, in this example, you can
see that that factor of two.
I mean this is in space dimension two,
right?
In here, you can see the factor of two was
not needed.
It's quite likely, I mean in this case,
take a look at it.
Here, I mean we can eyeball it, okay?
Probably, you didn't have to divide by
factor of two, but
by you just divide it by like 20, 30
percent.
And you're inside, okay?
And by the way, that factor is an
interesting number.
You might recall that, you know, how
ellipsoidally approximable the set is, or
something, I don't know.
So, everybody see what I'm saying here?
So it just guarantees.
By the way, what's the worst possible set
to approximate by an ellipsoid?
What is the convex set that is the worst
possible one.
Simplex, there we go, okay?
So, let's do triangle.
Like this, you know?
There's your minimum bounding ellipsoid's
a circle.
There, there it is.
And in this case, guess what?
You have to shrink it exactly by a factor
of n, before it fits inside.
And that tells you that this factor of n
cannot be improved.
Okay?
So the least ellipsoidially approximable
convexet is a simplet.
I've drawn it this way but in fact all of
these ellipsoid approximations methods,
they're actually invariant under affine
transformations.
Right?
Because if I take a set if I multiply it
you know by
applying an affine transformation, what
happens, volume transforms under
affine transformation just by a
determinant, by a constant.
So you get a commutative diagram.
You know, if you take the original set,
affine transformation, optimal ellipsoid.
Then apply an affine transformation of the
optimal ellipsoid, and
you get the optimal ellipsoid for the
second case.
You get a commutative diagram.
Okay?
So it's, in other words, you might say
something like this.
Extremal volume ellipsoidal approximation
is affinely invariant.
Everybody got that?
That's actually quite important.
actually, it's quite important in
practice,
right because it says that if the x's
represent things, and
you actually don't have any idea how the
scales should go together.
I mean if, if it means nothing to you then
there are plenty of cases like that then
it says, you'd have, I mean you should
probably whatever your method is should be
a finally in variant so.
Oh, I should say something like this, if
the, if the polyhedron Is is symmetric.
Symmetric means if x is in the set so is
minus x.
Right?
So an example would be a normal.
Then it says you can this factor is not n
but square root n.
Okay?
And I said something obscure at first.
I said any convex set can be approximated
by an ellipsoid within a factor square
root n.
Alright, so let me explain what I was
saying.
That, that, that's kind of I, I,
I take the minimum volume one and I divide
it by square root n, right?
So I put the one that's geometrically in
the middle.
And what that means is for any convex set
I can bruise a convex set,
which has the property that if I expand
it, square root M I cover, and
if I shrink it square root n, I'm inside.
Okay, so actually philosophically, it's
quite interesting.
It's a, you could, you can argue something
like this.
Ellipsoids are universal approximators of
convex sets.
Yeah?
I mean, square root of n is not a
fantastic, by the way,
core, it's the fourth root of m for
symmetric right.
You know, you might not like that, but the
point is, it's a constant.
Right and that's it.
I mean, it's even a constant that doesn't
grow that badly and
all that kind of stuff.
So, so this is actually interesting and it
kind of explains a lot about how,
why things like quadratic methods would be
so prevalent.
By the way one one interesting thing you
can say here is the following.
Any norm on RN, can be approximated by a
quadratic norm,
within a factor of N to the one fourth,
okay?
And that's interesting right because it
says that anything, any norm, and
there is some very sophisticated norms,
right?
Because it says that every
single one is approximate within.
Into the 1/4 by a quadratic one.
Right?
So that tells you actually, I think to me
this is sort of a philosophical,
this explains why least square, why using
least squares for
the past two centuries people have gotten
pretty far right?
This, this at least explains it.
Next topic is centering.
So, I mean in here there's tons and
tons of applications of centering, I'll
just address that first.
You've seen a couple already,
even in the first couple of weeks we saw
yield maximization.
So yield maximization says that you're
running a manufacturing process.
You want to tell your machine to target a
certain set of like critical dimensions.
Lets say an I C manufacturer but since
you're pushing it.
Right?
You're pushing it absolutely to
the limit of the technology when you say,
please make this critical dimension one
nano-meter, it's going to be off a little
bit and things like that, so
there's going to be variations.
And so there you have a, a, a [UNKNOWN]
that describes the acceptable,
acceptable critical pairs, you know,
combinations of critical dimensions.
And what you want is you want to tell them
that you want to target,
you want to shoot for is something deep,
deep in that set so
that when you have variations away from it
it, you're still in it.
Your yield is high.
Okay?
So we, we looked at all that.
So, so that comes up.
And we've even seen some of these
problems.
So here's one.
Find the center of the largest inscribed
ball.
That's the Chebyshev center.
And that's this problem.
I give you a polyhedron described by
inequalities.
And I say, please find me the ball of
maximum radius that fits inside, and
the center of that we're going to call
that the Chebyshev center, and
it's the point deepest in the polyhedron.
Right?
And that's clearly defined.
It's the one which has highest depth,
highest distance to the exterior.
Right?
That's this.
And that's an LP.
I, that was actually one of our first
examples when we look at LP.
And it was a fine example because it
doesn't look like it should be
an LP, right?
'Cause well, it looks like an LP while
you're drawing the, polyhedron outside.
But the minute you draw a ball that should
not evoke LP.
Right, that is an LP.
A more sophisticated one is the center of
the maximum volume ellipsoid.
Actually, that's quite interesting because
this one is
actually invariant Under affine,
coordinate transformations.
Right?
Now that may not be relevant to you,
right, if, if, your coordinates are things
you know about.
You're intimately familiar with them, and
you really do know the range of each one
and they all have separate meanings.
Good for you.
An affine invariance doesn't mean
anything, right?
But in a lot of cases, that's just not
true, right?
These are sort of arbitrary coordinates,
these might be features or
something like that, and you don't know
the scale or anything.
You pick a reasonable scale and that's
about all you can do.
So this is one.
This is the center of the maximum volume
ellipsoid.
There's one that we are going to be
looking at very much in
the next couple of weeks.
We'll see this, it'll take a while, but
maybe in three weeks, two and
a half weeks, and that's the analytic
center.
So this is a good time to look at it.
So the analytic center actually not a,
it's not a function of the set.
It's actually a function of the
description of the set.
So technically I don't know.
It's, it's, it's not the same as limited
volume ellipsoid and
all that kind of stuff.
So here, here's what it is.
Suppose I have, a set of convex
inequalities, and equalities.
Then, I simply form the following problem.
I minimize the sum of the logs of the
minus FIs.
The FIs, of court, minus FI, well it has a
perfect interpretation.
It's the margin [COUGH] in the IF
inequality, right?
because the, the third inequality says F3
has to be negative less than or
equal to zero, right?
So if F3 is minus 2.1 you have a margin of
2.1.
So these are the margins here.
Right?
Positive means you're in the interior of
the set.
Well, relative interior because of this.
Okay?
So here this is the log, it's the sum of
the logs of the margins.
Well it's the product of the margins,
right?
So this says maximize the product of the
margins.
That's, that's what this is.
Okay?
So this is, and this comes up in a lot of
things.
That's a convex optimization problem, of
course, right?
Because minus log minus arg.
Is a convex increasing function, right?
I mean, you have to trace through the two
minuses to see what happens, right?
The first minus changes the sine, the
modifinicity, and
it changes concave to convex.
And the second one change, flips the
modifinicity, okay?
So, or makes it go back to be increasing.
Right?
So, so the, by the composition rule.
This is a convex function here, and
that's called the this function is called
the log barrier.
Right?
So its a barrier function, right?
And the meaning of that is that,
on this set of points where this is
strictly less than zero,
this things finite as you move that point
towards any point where one of these goes
to zero, one of these margins goes to zero
and the product goes to infinity, right?
Well, certain some of the negative log
minus,
negative log margins goes to infinity,
right?
So this, actually, is extremely easy to
solve, I mean, it depends on def,
I mean, it depends how F is given but
we'll see this later.
But it's not a property of the feasible
set, it's actually, it's a function of
the description of the problem, and that
will be clear in a minute.
But for fun, let's just look at the
analytic center of the set of
linear inequalities.
So these are a set of linear inequalities,
like this, and
what's plotted here are various things.
These dashed curves show the level sets of
the log, this is the log barrier,
and what it's showing here are the level
sets of the log barrier right?
So actually if you say what's the level
sets, what,
where are they equal, where's it equal to
1,000.
You get a kind of a cool little app, you
know a curve.
A smooth curve here which hugs the
boundary of this thing very
closely, right?
And then as I decrease that number, this
number is one by the way,
when I decrease that number to one it's
looking more ellipsoidal.
It's not.
And as I keep going lower and lower and
actually the heshen.
The hechon of this thing at the analytic
center is actually a good
ellipse quadratic summary of the shape of
this set.
Right?
So that, that, that's a good,
a good way to do that alright.
So actually in a lot of cases where you
know, you know how to do something if
you had a quadratic representation or
something like that.
We'll see optimization methods where this
is the case or
statistical methods where this is the
case.
But you don't have anything like that.
What you have is a complicated convex set,
that, one option is to do something like
this.
And, I mean, another option of
course is calculate maximum volume
ellipsoid inside it and so on.
Okay?
Now, it turns out here there are
guaranteed approximations, right.
So, one is this.
It turns out that if you form the
following, so
the inner ellipsoids is you go to the
center and you take
the ellipsoid given defined by the hpshen
of the analytic center that actually.
With the one here, that always lies within
the set and
this one always lies outside the set,
covers the set.
This is a worse approximation ratio than
the maximum volume one, right?
And the reason is this.
This number here is m, let's call it m
squared.
You take the square root and that gives
you the expansion size, right?
So it says, that if you, I mean, it says
this.
It says if you take this thing here that's
shown in dark its shaded here.
That ellipsoid is inside the set, and if I
expand it by a factor m,
which is by the way not the ambient space
dimension its actually the number of
inequalities but the number of
inequalities is at least n plus one,
because it takes n plus one inequalities
In rn, to get a bounded region.
And if you have n plus 1, you have a
simplex, right?
So that's the so this is a worse
approximation ratio.
So I mean it's not clear that matters,
right?
Oh one question here, here I have let's
see one, two,
three, I have six inequalities.
but.
Analytic center its not a function set its
a function of the inequalities.
What if I added a new inequality that
looked like that?
So it says please stay on this side of
that inequality.
It shifts left.
Exactly right and in fact the following is
true.
Given a polyhedron actually for that
matter just given a set
I can take any point on the interior, and
pile up a bunch of, this is a,
you could call that a redundant or
irrelevant inequality, right?
It doesn't do, it doesn't change the set.
So I can pile up redundant inequalities,
and I can, I can get you,
I can get any point in the interior to be
the analytic center, right?
So all that says is analytic center is a,
is an attribute of the description of the
set, not the set itself.
Okay?
Okay, so technically it's not, it's not a
question of geometry.
Right?
It has to do with the description.
Okay.
Another topic is linear discrimination.
So, and if you've had a course on sort of
machine learning or
something like that, or modern statistics,
you'll, you've seen things like this.
So here's the problem.
This is actually also quite an old
problem.
I think it goes back at least to the 40s.
Something like that.
I don't know how old the perception
algorithm is but so
you have a set of points, x one through x
n, y one through y m, and n sum r n.
And the idea is to determine whether they
if you can separate them by
hyper plane and if so find such a hyper
point, right?
And there's actually a few tricks here,
you want to watch very carefully in
the next few minutes because you will be
doing these things yourself.
And the arguments are, well they're not
totally subtle but, I mean you,
you have to, listen, all I'm saying is you
better listen.
Okay?
That, that's the right way to do it.
So here, I'll, I'll go over it a bit
slowly.
So what it is, is You really want to know,
whether or
not, this set of inequalities is feasible.
Now, the first thing you notice about
those inequalities is their strict.
And you might say, hey, wait a minute,
I've been doing this class for
a long time we haven't see strict
inequalities before.
Right?
And
then you might say something like this.
You might think about it for a minute and
this would generally, it would generally
be true the following would be true.
If your problem, if the difference between
a strict inequality and
a non-strict inequality, like changes your
problem,
that's kind of a mathematical pathology,
right?
You know what I'm saying?
Right?
If you say, hey I just built a you know,
I, I, just built machine that gives you
know, the correct dose on a,
on a tumor or something like that, and I
can satisfy these inequalities.
And someone says, oh you know, what are
they, which inequalities can you do?
You say I can do the non strict ones.
They say no, no, it has to be strict.
I mean, it just makes absolutely no sense.
Eh, no sense whatsoever, right.
Because the difference between, in the two
is, I mean, it can hardly matter that,
if it turns out, the difference between
putting 49.999 grays on some,
some tumor vocso, and fifty.
If that really makes a difference, well
then give up and go home.
Because this doesn't make any sense.
This is not the real world.
Right?
Or that would be something like in
finance, at a hedge fund.
You come back and you go, oh, great news.
I can, I can, I can get this return with
this risk level.
And they go, equal, equal to the risk
level or less than?
I mean, the answer is, your risk model is
so ridiculous, it's just totally made up.
So the point is, if somebody is telling
you there's a difference between strict
inequality and non-strict inequality, it
just makes no sense.
Everybody following this?
Okay, right.
So, let's apply that common sense
principle here.
Let's take this and go like this, like
that, okay?
There you go.
Now you tell me,
now, now, the good news is the problem has
become actually substantially easier.
So the answer is a equals b equals zero is
feasible, okay?
Everybody, everybody got that?
Okay?
All right.
So, so that then, so, the, the the
standard method, right, didn't work here.
Okay?
So that means that
the common method doesn't work.
Okay?
So let's do something,
here you have to be a bit more subtle.
What you do, is you observe that these
inequalities are homogeneous in a and b.
Okay?
So that's, in other words, if,
if there's a and b for which ai transpose
x plus b is positive, then I
guarantee you, there's a and b for which a
transpose x plus b is bigger than or
equal to is, sorry, is bigger or equal to
one.
Okay?
Why?
I
mean you just scale them all up until it's
true.
Right?
So what it says is,
we replace this with this, and
I would strongly recommend that you go to
a quiet place, and
make sure you understand the exactly the
semantics of what went down there.
Right, right?
It is not the same as saying that a strict
inequality is the always same as
replacing with a one.
Right?
So you have to make the observation that
these are homogeneous,
that I can scale them, and they're, then
this is, then they become equivalent.
Okay?
That's the, that's the idea.
This is a bonafide set of linear
inequalities,
in fact that's a linear program in a and
b.
Right, so interestingly questions about
linear discrimination it took a,
unfortunately a shocking, a much longer
time than it should have for
somebody to look up one day and say oh hey
that's a linear program.
Right so, so, sadly, historically but it
really did.
In fact, whole algorithms were worked out
to solve these kinds of things before it
was understood that other people had
worked out other whole algorithms to
solve these kinds of things and so on and
so forth.
I mean now I think,
well there's even a legacy of that in
current machine learning,
I mean there's some weird, anyway I, maybe
I won't go, I, I won't go any farther.
But, so, okay.
Alright, so what does this say?
This says that if I give you a bunch of
points, pairs of points, and
you know, these might be like labels or
something like that.
Then it says I can now, by solving an LP,
I can determine if they are, you would say
linearly separable.
Or linearlly discriminable, right?
So, you could test and if you can, if they
are, you can exhibit or
deduce a the separating hyperplane.
Now you can optimize over that hyperplane.
We're going to see that next, right?
Like you could, you know, find the
smallest one.
Or we'll see all sorts of things you could
work, you could optimize now, right?
And what would be the idea behind this?
Well, it might be something like this,.
This is a giant pile of data.
Here.
In fact you'd call this you'd say labels.
Right?
So you'd, these would feature vectors.
Right.
So, this is,
I look at let's say one billion emails.
Right, each one is labeled as either spam
and not spam.
So, that's spam and that's not spam.
Okay?
How do I know that?
Because I watched when someone junked
something or something like that.
I got a pretty good idea of the labels.
And let's say each of these is I have a
feature that's let's say I'll be
safe here.
Let's make it just like five, 10,000
features.
Right?
For each email.
And they could, a lot of these features,
these features are kind of obvious that
they were what you think they would be.
They would be things like word counts and
things like that.
All r ight, so you take a billion of these
points some X's, some Y's.
Right?
And then you'd want to know in R 1000 or
10,000, whatever we, however many features
we decided there were,
you'd like to know if there was a hyper
plane in between them.
And, but if there were a hyper plane.
Then, you, then it'd be easy because now
you'd take that hyper plane,
a new email comes in, you compute its
feature vector, find out which side of
the hyper plane you're on, and either
announce it's spam or not.
And in fact even the distance to the hyper
plane would tell you something,
like if it was way off.
In on one side you might say with high
confidence that it is spam or not.
Everybody, got this?
Okay?
Now actually,
you'd be quite nervous if in fact it
separated.
Right?
There'd be something deeply wrong but
in this case at least that's abstractly
the idea of the use of
these types of things.
Right?
So.
Okay.
We will get to that.
So it turns out actually a very simple
varia, very simple variation on
this produces something that's actually
extremely effective.
Right?
So.
Okay, so the first thing we're going to
look at is this.
If you, you have a set of linear
inequalities, right,
that just detects the hyperplane.
But the point is there's lots of hyper
planes that separate two clouds of points,
if they're separable.
If they're linearly discriminable.
There's lots of hyper planes.
So, by the way there's lots of ways you
could choose a hyper plane
that separates them.
Right?
There's lots of reasonable ways to do it.
One way would be to do some kind of
robustness thing.
And what one, one would do that, what you
would do something like this.
You can imagine, the, the hyper plane is a
transpose z plus b is zero, right?
But instead, what we could do is we could
take the points where that's one and
minus one, and everything in between those
two parallel hyperlinks, that's a slab.
Right, and they can very reasonably asked
to find the compute the maximum with
the slab, it separates the two points
right?
And by the by what's the nice about that I
mean some people calls it maximum margin
classify right the reason is maximum
margin is puff up each of these points.
By a ball still classified correctly, and
the amount you could puff 'em up by
is the largest possible, and still
maintain correctness.
Everybody got that?
So it's maximum margin classifier.
Okay.
Completely reasonable, right?
But the width of the slab is exactly two
over the norm of a.
Right?
So
that's the, I mean if the norm of A were
one, then, well, A transpose x plus B,
literally is the signed distance to the
hyper plane.
If the norm of A is one.
If the norm of A is big, then, in fact,
the slab is small.
Right?
So, okay.
So then it says, please, let's maximize
[COUGH] two over the norm of a2.
That's the same as minimizing norm, a2.
And so you'd say, minimize the norm of a2
subject to these inequalities and
now we get a QP.
And that, that's the maximum margin
classifier,
if I'm saying that correctly in whatever
dialect that is.
Oh, and I guess they would do this.
This is not, yeah you'd have to square the
objective,
you'd do something like that, right?
It'd be the same thing, okay.
okay, so now now if two sets are
separable, linearly separable we at
least have a nice an utterly reasonable to
way to to find a hyper plane
that separates them that's kind of luck it
clearly has some good properties.
Okay.
Very interesting thing is to look at the
dual of this, and we'll do that quickly.
So I, I just mechanically worked out the
dual of, of the separation problem.
So the dual of this problem right is
maximum margin problem is exactly this.
It's maximize this function subject to,
and
here what you see is something very
interesting.
I get two sets of I get two sets of of
Lagrange multipliers Lambda, and Mu.
They are associated exactly with the two
sets of linear inequalities right?
For the the x's and the y's.
I have these kind of inequalities go the
wrong way.
And you get some very interesting
constraints.
I get a norm constraint here.
These are, well those are, inequalities,
so
these things are non-negative, and I get
this equality constraint here.
So, again, everything is homogeneous here,
so
what we're going to do is the following,
is I'm going to normalize, these things,
here to be, I'll, I'll take both of these
to be one.
Whereupon, lambda and mu become, well,
they're probability distributions.
Or they are, I dunno.
They're convex mixtures.
Right?
They're,
they're numbers that are not negative and
add up to one.
But if these are numbers that add up,
non-negative and
add up to one, these two things are really
simple.
They are elem they are arbitrary elements
in the convex hull of the x
point cloud and y point cloud right?
And so that says i can rewrite the problem
to look like this, and
its really, beautiful.
It says, it basically says,
take the convex hull of x point cloud
convex hull of y point cloud, and
actually calculate that's an arbitrary
point in one and arbitrary point in other.
And it says, this is the [UNKNOWN] I mean
minimizing t subject to same,
you just minimize this thing here.
It's, it's actually says, find the minimum
distance between two
ellipse two polyhedra, described by their
vertices.
Everybody got that?
So that was it.
It makes perfect sense.
So now you know when are two,
when are two point clouds separable,
linearly separable.
The answer is, and straight from duality
is this, if and only if,
the convex holes don't intersect.
That's it, okay?
And that's duality.
Right, that's exactly what duality is.
This doesn't say anything, but
it's just fun to look at.
Right?
So, okay.
Now we're going to get to a real case, and
in fact, it's one of those things where
you just add one more, one more feature to
this, to the problem, and then
it goes from being mm maybe not so useful
to off scale unbelievably useful.
Okay?
So those Taken a modern statistics or
machine learning course, know what's
going to happen now.
So, but anyway, so if you just sit tight,
everything will be fine.
Alright.
So what you do is this.
And in fact, I want to, before we even get
into this,
I want to talk about, let's start the
story this way.
I give you some x's and I give you some
y's.
These are spectors for spam, and for not
spam.
You calculate whether there's a separating
hyper plane and there isn't.
Right?
And that's probably good, right?
Oh by the way, if the two point clouds are
like totally, you know, if,
if they're totally on top of each other so
there's no difference, that's not good.
That means you've picked some pretty poor
features.
Okay?
Right?
But this is the point is that two point
clouds are there.
They do, the two, the two convex cells
intersect.
Period.
In other words, there are spam-feature
vectors that penetrate into
whatever the non-spam territory.
Ev-, everybody, I mean, this is just the
picture.
Okay?
And so
the question is, how would you let's skip
what I have on the slide here.
What would you imagine you might want to
do.
So, you have a, a million linear
equalities that you want to satisfy, and
they're not mutually satisfiable.
Yeah.
So I have a whole bunch of
inequalities that I want to satisfy.
I solve and LP, and I announce with total
confidence, there is no hyper plane.
I cannot satisfy all these inequalities.
It's impossible.
So the natural, I think one of the most
natural things you might want to do next
would be to say okay, fine.
Find me a hyper plane that minimizes the
number of inequalities you violate.
Now if you want to think about a, a
classification problem.
That's the number of misclassifications,
right?
And by the way, if that number were like
.5% you'd be very happy.
You wouldn't, but okay.
At, at, at, at some point in time in the
past for spam detection you would be,
you would've been very happy.
Right?
For a lot of problems you'd be delighted.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So you'd, so you'd, so then the problem is
to figure out which ones can you not,
how do you minimize the number?
Okay. Well. And by the way,
then you might ask yourself, what kind of
a optimization problem is that.
And you would find out pretty quickly that
that is NP heart.
So I give you a set of inequalities, and
I ask you to satisfy as many as you can,
it's NP heart.
Okay?
Fine. Okay. So then you say, let's see,
maybe there's a heuristic for this.
And what does this mean?
This means that the violations are sparse.
You, you know, if there's going to be
violations, and
by the way, the L1 norm should be the
right thing here.
Because it says, you know, it, it, it's
got a V.
I mean we'll see it's not quite an L1
norm, but
it's exactly this, actually it is an L1
norm for something that's positive.
Yeah, it's something, it means what you
want is something that keeps up
the pressure to drive you to zero.
But, if you have to violate you shouldn't
go nuts.
[INAUDIBLE] It should not be a function, a
penalty that grows,
it should, should grow lineally, okay?
Okay, so so that's the idea.
So, in fact, that leads you immediately to
the following.
Let me do it this, I'll write it another
way.
I'll write a i transpose, x plus b.
I want that to be bigger than one.
Okay, so I want this thing to be bigger
than zero, that's what I want.
Now I know that I can't, I actually can't
choose an A and B.
Well, that one and the other ones were so
all these inequalities hold, everybody
following this?
So I want the, if that's positive I'm
totally happy Right?
So you might do something like this.
You might form AI transpose, xb minus one,
the minus part.
Okay?
If you satisfy that inequality, that
gives, there's no bill here.
You don't pay anything.
Right?
But if this thing becomes negative, then
you start paying.
And you pay linearly.
Ever, so, what, what function is that?
That's a function that looks like this.
Right.
Looks like that.
Right?
And this is called the margin, in the
inequality.
And what this says, if your margin's
positive, no charge whatsoever.
If it's negative you charge linearly for
negative margins.
Right.
Everybody sort of following this.
Okay, now when you look at that, and by
the way, it helps to turn your head
about 40 degrees, then L1, your L1 part of
your brain will light up.
Okay?
I mean its the same thing, right?
And so
by the way this is called hinge loss, is,
is the name for this in several fields I
think that, that in both and, and modern
statistics and machine that's hinge loss.
And so it suggests that actually doing
something like this,
adding that in would be a great idea.
Because, you know, I mean, it doesn't look
like L1.
But by the time you see this, I mean,
it should evoke, L1 is not to be taken
literally.
Although a lot of people do.
This is L1.
Right?
Actually it's a linear plus L1, so
it actually, kind of is.
But you look at that, and, and sparsity.
The sparsity part of your brain should be,
lighting up.
Okay.
Right.
And what does it mean if this is sparse?
It's super cool.
If, if that's sparse, it says the
following: it says that you satisfy most.
It means that, that misclassifications,
these are not, by the way,
misclassifications there's even a little
extra there, because the one,
without the one it's misclassification.
Right?
This says that misclassifications are
sparse.
That's exactly what you want.
Everybody.
Following, I mean that was a very long
story.
But the idea is, I just wanted to give,
I just wanted to give the whole, like
everything about what you're doing here.
Okay so that's what this is.
U is a slack variable here, I mean this is
the way,
this is the traditional description of it.
Actually this is at, a more modern
description.
You don't even introduce u's.
because, you just look at it, you say it's
convex, done.
Right?
That's the correct way to do it in my
opinion.
But we'll do it the traditional way.
The traditional way is you say I would
like to satisfy this inequality and
this one, it's determined that you cannot.
And then you go, oh, okay, fine.
Then you add in slacks.
Now the slacks are, by the way, nothing
but these things, right?
So a slack is something it says, fine,
I'll subtract something from the one to
make it easier to satisfy this, and I'll
do the same here.
I'll make the inequality easier.
These are the use in these, those are
[UNKNOWN].
And then I'll minimize those, and by the
way,
you'll find out this problem is absolutely
identical to the problem of this.
Plus of course, the opposite ones, the,
for the y's, right?
So you get exactly the same problem, okay?
Everybody following this?
Okay, so.
That and, and you should even think of
this its a beautiful thing.
You should think of this thing as we l1
type heuristic for
solving the following hard competorial
problem.
Finding a hyper plane its satisfies it's
many, you know,
it misclassifies as few as possible,
right?
That's the correct interpretation of this.
Okay?
And you get something like that, you know,
here's a case.
Okay.
Now, the only thing you have to do now is
you put the two together and
you have something kind of famous.
Right?
So, and I guess the traditional one,
I think the traditional one would look
something like that, but
you get the same tradeoff curve.
So what you do now is this, is you put
slacks in to minimize, for the for, for
actually misclassifying right?
And then at the same time you can also
think of this regularization, by the way.
So here traditional l two regularization
turns out to
have a beautiful geometric interpretation.
Because when you're minimizing the norm of
A,
I guess you'd call it the weight vector,
or something like that.
If you're minimizing over the weight
vector, it turns out, that's equivalent
to, geometrically, to saying, don't look
for a hyper plane, look for a slab.
And in fact, maximize the width of the
slab,
which means that you've separated them
well.
Everybody kind of seeing all these things
go together?
So, I mean, for people who've seen this
before, that's fine, you may not have seen
the geometric interpretive full geometric
interpretations, but now you have.
So, it's actually kind of, kind of cool.
So, this, this is given the name support
vector machine.
Here, you have a parameter and the
parameter is very simple.
It trades off, the parameter, now I'll
describe it geometrically, and
there are statistical interpretations of
all of these, had to go into them.
But there are, so, the geometric
interpretation is quite beautiful.
lambda, or gamma, here, sorry, trades off
the width, of the slab.
and, and this is going to be very rough.
The number of inequality violations.
Okay.
And that's what it does.
Right?
And so you can imagine what, what, what,
what turning that parameter will do here.
This is unbelievably widely used.
I mean, not as much as least squares or
something like that.
But it's catching up.
Let me put it that way.
So it's used tons of places, everywhere,
all the time.
Right?
So,
you couldn't possibly get through a day.
here, except if you're like hiking in
Yosemite or something.
And maybe even then you couldn't.
when, when something you did didn't run
through a support vector classifier.
I mean, I not, it'd be, you have to touch
no electronics, and
I don't what else you, you'd have to do.
So, but it'd be very hard, very hard to
do.
Certainly don't pick up your phone or
anything like, don't read email because
then it's all over.
so, anyway, so, yet these are good things
to know.
Okay.
Let's look at the idea of nonlinear
discrimination.
So, here, I, we've been looking at linear
We can just as well look at nonlinear
discrimination.
Because, in fact it turns out that the
fact that the class line was linear,
was totally irrelevant.
All that mattered, was that it was linear
in the parameters.
Right?
So nonlinear classification says, find me
a function f that is,
you know, positive on the xs, negative on
the ys.
Okay?
So, so, here's one approach to it.
Actually, there's multiple approaches
here, one which doesn't fit in this theme,
but we could talk about, but don't have
time to, would be sort of kernel methods.
But we're not, instead,
we're going to look at something that's
just much simpler and
it fits with the theme of convex
optimization.
What you do is you simply take a set of
basis functions here.
And, y-, what you're going to do is you're
going to look at a,
at a, a finite dimensional, set of
candidate functions.
That's all.
And, you know?
These are the, these are basis functions,
right?
F1 through fk, right?
They could be anything you like.
So it could be, polynomials.
They could be weird exponentials.
They could be things that, that pertain to
your particular problem, right?
I don't know, I don't know why but I mean,
you know, could be, this could be
prolatespheriods or something like that
,or vessel functions of some order.
I mean I don't know.
They could be anything, right?
This could be the Igon functions of some
of some partial
differential operator right?
Doesn't matter right?
It just suppose to be functions,
you're going to linearaly combine to do
separation.
Okay.
So here it's the same thing you just end
up with absolutely nothing whatsoever is
different, I mean nothing.
Right?
So that's, that's what you get.
And so this tells you you can do fun
things like this.
You can say [COUGH] please separate my
points quadratically, okay?
And that says find me a quadratic
function, that's a,
that's a general quadratic function.
And what's being asked is that you should
find P,
Q and R those are the variables that
separates your points.
Okay, so Here's an example of
quadratically seperable points, right?
And this, by the way,
goes back to our question of what would
you do with those ellipsoids.
This would be if you had two types of data
you had places where let's say
a pilot flown and came back.
Let's suppose that's the things inside.
And these are the ones where, there was no
recovery.
That's a little bit gruseome.
Sorry.
Okay.
So, something else.
But that's the idea.
Okay?
And, so this would be the case.
It's a, and it's a linear program.
To compute and, to compute actually just
quadratically separation, now,
quadratic separation by itself does not
require, there's no curvature constraint.
Right?
So in fact, in this case, you could, you
might as well, you could if you just do
straight quadratic classification, you
could actually be looking for a hyperbola.
That separates them.
Everybody following this?
Right, and if, you know,
depending on what your data is that could
be completely reasonable and interesting.
Everybody got this?
If you want to insist that, for example,
if you say find me an ellipsoid that
covers these points but not those, then
you simply add a constraint.
That says that the p is less than or
equal to, actually you would add p
negative definite for
example to get an ellipsoid or the
exterior [UNKNOWN] b p positive definite.
That's homogeneous and that translates to
this, okay?
And now you have an STP.
Is everybody following this?
So this is the idea.
I mean here's a quasi convex problem.
It says here's two sets of points and
this says please separate them by the
minimal degree polynomial in r two.
Everybody got that?
And without even saying anything you
should understand that that is
quasi convex.
Why?
In fact, how was that done?
How was that figure done?
You take the two set of points and what's
the first thing you try to do?
You first try to separate them [INAUDIBLE]
by linear, and you can't.
Because we're looking at the data, you
cannot, okay.
And that doesn't work, so now you try
quadratic.
And you cannot, okay?
Then you try cubic, and you can't.
And then you try quartic, and you can't.
Everybody, so that's, that's the idea,
right?
So, I mean I don't know why you'd want to.
And by the way, I mean one of the nice
things about these sort of convex
formulations is, you know, we're showing
you the simple ones, but
in fact you can just, you know can, it's
like cooking.
You can add stuff in, and things like
that.
I mean for example, here, suppose instead
you want to say yeah.
This is, oh yeah.
This is what I want to do.
I really want to do that.
But you know what, it doesn't work exactly
and
I don't mind if a few end up
mis-classified.
Everybody following this?
So what do you, what would you do?
Yeah, yeah, the u and the v, the slacks or
whatever you like.
And then, you know, and then, and
then you have a parameter that would trade
off of various things.
But I mean, so that, that's, that's
exactly what you do.
You'd add in u and v and then you'd end up
computing an ellipsoid and there would be,
hope if you're lucky.
Couple of points outside, couple of,
couple of points on,
on either side of the boundary that went
the wrong way.
Everybody got this?
So it's, it's okay.
So that's, I mean, you get it.