And let me first say a little bit about
how all this,
how everything fits together, how all, all
the computational stuff fits together?
So we, one way to view it, is you start
with this.
You start with solving quadratic equations
with linear equality constraints.
How do you minimize a quadratic with
linear equality constraints?
What does it reduce to?
Is linear equations, right?
And then we, I we know how to solve linear
equations.
Actually know quite a lot about how to
solve linear equations.
Okay?
All right, so that's just like done.
Right?
Well, one way to view Newton's method is
this.
I ask you to, to minimize a smooth
function subject to equality constraints.
And what it effectively does, if you look
above, you look at,
say what is Newton's method doing.
You could even write it so it was clear,
this is what it's doing.
The answer is it's solving a sequence,
a short sequence of quadratic equality
constrained minimization problems, right?
I mean maybe, I mean if you were to
profile Newton's method,
what you'd find is it's solving linear
equations.
But the linear equations it's solving are
actually solving a equality constrained
quadratic minimization problem, right?
So, so then you could say well we have now
extended we, we can now solve
smooth equality constrained problems by
reducing that to solving a sequence.
Right?
In fact not a long sequence, right?
But a sequence of quadratic equality
constrained problems which in
turn are linear algebra.
Already got this?
Well, guess what?
Now we're going to go to inequality
constrained problems, and
here's, guess how we're going to do it?
We're going to take an inequality
constraint problem, and we're going to
reduce that to solving a short sequence of
smooth minimization problems.
Okay?
So now you have a stack.
Right?
And the stack'll look like this.
You have an inequality constraint problem,
you will solve it by solving a ten,
20, [INAUDIBLE] number doesn't matter,
right?
But it's not like a gigantic number,
You going to solve ten, 20 smooth
minimization problems.
How are you going to solve those?
Each of those is going to be reduced to
solving, again,
a modest number of quadratic equality
problems.
Everybody got this?
And solving a quadratic equality problem,
that's actually something we have an
actual method for.
It's called linear algebra.
Everybody, so this is the whole big, this
is the full, big picture.
Actually, you wanted, you could put
something on top.
And the on top would be the kind of stuff
that CVX does.
That, that takes your original problem,
which you may have all sorts of
non-differentiable functions and things
like that.
And automatically does the transforms to a
problem which you can handle, that has,
for example, smooth constraints and smooth
objective.
Right?
So, for
example, convert your problem to an lp.
In an lp all your objectives and your
constraints are smooth.
Everybody see, what I'm saying?
And now you see the entire stack.
Right, that, that's it.
That's the whole stack.
Okay?
So, okay.
So that's the big picture.
And that's what we're going to do today,
or part of today.
All right.
So, we're going to start with this
problem, inequality constraint.
And you know, the, the, the equality
constraints are just going to float along
everywhere we go, and I, you can even
almost ignore them.
And it's even, when I look at examples,
I'll probably ignore the Ax equals b.
But it just floats along, and, and doesn't
really hurt anybody.
Besides, we can handle it, right?
In fact, it's the Ax equals b that
persists at all levels of the stack.
Right?
When you go down the Newton's method,
it's just linear equations, right?
Each iteration of Newton's method, it, it,
it fills in a row of, okay,
if we take image is linear, so, linear, or
another way to say it is,
if you write the, if you write the
linearize me method on, that,
when you have Ax equals b, and you call
that method on Ax equals b, very simple.
It just returns itself.
'Kay, so, and that persists all the way to
the bottom of the stack.
Okay, so we're going to make, we'll make
some assumptions.
We'll assume that A is [COUGH] is full
rank.
Right?
So we don't
have redundant quality constraints.
And we'll assume that there's a, there's a
solution.
Right?
That there is an x that satisfies this.
And we'll assume a strict feasibility.
I mean, you don't even need a lot of this
stuff.
But just, these are sledgehammer
assumptions.
and, by the way, this is the, this is the,
I mean this is so.
This is actually the Slater condition
essentially, here.
You don't need any Slater conditions for
equality constraints, right?
Because the reduced slate, the modified
Slater condition says you
can ignore actually equality, linear
equality constraints.
Well, that's the only kind of equality
constraints you can have, and
linear inequality constraints.
So, we ignore those entirely.
And this says simply that, that the oh,
that the domain the interior of
the domain, actually intersects, well,
actually, sorry,
the domain is open because we're assuming
they're differential.
Right?
So, but, so,
since the domain intersects the equality
constraint.
And, and this says things like strong
duality holds, and, and
the dual optimum is attained.
Okay.
So what are examples?
Well, linear programs, quadratic programs,
QCQPs geometric programs, right?
Geometric programs, all the functions are
things like log sum x.
Entropy maximization.
So you say you want to maximize entropy
you get something like this right, so
that, that's a problem looks like that.
That's asking to maximize entropy or
minimizing negative entropy, and Fx less
than g and Ax equals b.
You can even interpret, if you interpret x
say as a probability vector,
it doesn't have to be normalized here,
but assuming it were, this says please
find me the maximum entropy distribution.
That matches certain expectations exactly,
and
satisfies inequalities on other
expectations.
That, that, that's what this problem is.
That's one way to interpret it.
Okay.
And this, this'll work.
This is fine.
oh, as I said you may use one of the
transformations the kind of
ones that CVX would use to take a problem
with non-differentiable objectives
constraints and transform it in fact in a
completely mechanical way
to a problem that doesn't have, that where
all the constraints are smooth.
Like for example, you transform it to an
SOCP or to an LP.
Right?
Okay.
now, [UNKNOWN] programs, things like
SDPs and SOCPs are actually better handled
as problems with generalized inequalities
although they will work here too provided
you express them in a smooth way.
There's actually, there's some really cool
smooth ways to write down
SDPs for example.
We've already seen the log barrier, but
the key is to start with your original
problem and do something really weird.
It's this.
We're going to take the inequality
constraints and
were going to put them in the objective,
and what we are going to do,
is we're going to take I minus, that is
the indicator function of R minus.
So that's a function that looks like this:
it's zero and
then it goes to plus infinity, if you go
positive.
Okay?
And that simply says, it, it says that if
you take fi of x, and
if it's less than 0 this returns 0, and if
it is positive it returns plus infinity.
A plus infinity and an objective is
basically saying it's infinitely bad
which is to say it's unacceptable.
Right?
So this is the,
the right, that's the idea.
Okay?
So now you can't apply Newton's method to
this directly,
because this is like big time
non-differentiable.
Right?
because you've got this thing that
goes like up to plus infinity.
Okay?
So so what we're going to do instead,
is we're going to make a surrogate that's
smooth.
Okay, and the surrogate that's smooth is
the log barrier, so
you'll form 1 over t minus log minus f.
These are functions that look like this.
Okay?
They, they look just like that.
Right?
These are, and these are increasing val,
so this, this one that hugs this, the true
function closer is with a higher t.
Higher value of t.
Okay?
So, now this one, that problem, that's
Newton ready.
Right, that's ready for Newton with the
equality constraints, because it's smooth.
Right?
And not only that,
at least visually, the approximation
improves as t goes to infinity.
So, it looks like we have something that
will do the right thing.
Everybody got this?
Now, before we go any farther, I want to
point out,
when people tell stories like this, you
should be deeply skeptical,
because usually stuff like this doesn't
work, right?
This is like, you're sitting there and you
come along and it, it's not working.
And someone says, what's wrong?
You say, oh, I can't solve Ax equals b.
And the person says, well why?
And, and you say, that's because my matrix
a is is singular.
And you go, oh, well, gee, that's too bad.
And then you say, what does it represent?
You say, oh, it's a measurement apparatus,
something like that.
And you say, oh, is it that apparatus on
the desk over there?
And you go, yeah, give me a hammer.
And you just tap the desk next to it, and
you say, a is now non-singular.
Everyone understand what I just said,
right?
So, because if you take a, if you take a,
a singular matrix, And you perturb,
if you take a random perturb, in fact,
take any entry generically,
take the sixth, seventh entry, and add 1e
minus 19 to it, and
with probability 1, the matrix is now non
singular.
Everybody following this?
Right?
Okay, so the question is, you know,
does that solve the problem?
The answer is, well, no, of course it
doesn't solve the problem.
The matrix is now non-singular.
But it still has a condition num-, it has
a condition number of like 10 to the 19.
So all the problems you were going to have
when it had a condition number infinity,
are still there.
Everybody following this?
Right?
So people who just come along and,
like, perturb your problem.
So look at this, someone says I want to
solve a problem that's my true,
this is my true irritation function here.
It express how I feel about each fi.
I mean, it, it expresses the semantics of
a hard constraint.
It says if fi is negative or 0, I'm just
totally cool with it.
Tot, totally cool.
I, it's neutral, it means nothing to me.
But if it's 1e minus not, you know, minus
19, that's completely unacceptable.
That's what the semantics is, right?
And someone says oh, yeah, no problem
gimme some sandpaper.
I'll just go down to this corner down here
and I'll just sand it off.
I'll start with some number 80 sandpaper
then I'll go to 120, and
some 400 and you know.
Everybody know what I'm saying, right?
You sand if off and somebody says what did
you just do and you go,
oh yeah, your function's now
differentiable.
And it's no different from, I mean, for
all practical purposes, the same as what
you had before.
Everybody following this?
And you go, go ahead.
Let, let's apply your Newton method on it.
Tech, technically that's correct, isn't
it?
I mean, if you take something that looks
like that, if I sand the bottom off.
I have to sand the sides a little bit too,
to make it a barrier, right?
I mean, actually, this does it effectively
right here.
I don't have to use sandpaper, it's just,
I just use, I, I used 1 over t,
I take t equals 10 to the 9.
Everybody following this?
Okay.
And what's the problem with that?
Like the guy who bangs the hammer next to
the, you know, the sensor suite?
What, what's the problem with this?
Why can't it, why aren't we just done
here, or
why should you be deeply skeptical?
So your suspicion is, though it may, it's
actually true that if I take
t equals 10 to the 9, I get a pretty good
approximation of i minus, right?
One, one that one could even argue is,
is close enough for for any practical
purpose.
That, that, that's actually true.
But the problem is that that function is
actually just about the worst thing in
the world for Newton's method, right?
Because it, because it's not close to
quadratic or
another way to say it is, it's third
derivative is big, right?
Or, it's non-quadratic.
I mean, or, or it's, here's another one.
It's second derivative changes wildly when
you get near the barrier.
Right?
And that's another way,
of course, of saying the derivative is big
or something, right?
So, so that says Newton's method will
work, and it will take 10 to the 9 steps.
Okay?
Everybody following this?
All right.
So, I'm just saying,
you should be very skeptical about things
like this, right?
because it just doesn't work that way,
when usually when someone walks up to you,
and you say, having a problem?
And they say, oh, no problem.
We'll just appro, we'll just smooth this,
we'll sand this thing off, and
now it's differentiable.
And, and then, they walk away.
You should be suspicious.
I want to say that, we have seen this
story be,
you have seen this story before, in a
different context.
And so let me tell you the context you saw
it in.
It was this.
This is the function that really captures
how we care about constraints.
It's this thing here, right?
But do you remember what happens in a
Lagrange Duality?
You approximate this function by this,
right?
And the slope there is lambda i.
Okay?
Now the point is, nobody would be tempted
to look at that and
say, yeah, that's a pretty good
approximation, right?
So, but the shock was that Lagrange
Duality kind of worked in some sense,
that, that an approximation this bad of
this thing actually yielded something,
but at a high level, it's the same thing,
the same, or the same story is behind
Lagrange Duality, that's behind well, the
logarithmic barrier, right?
because it, the story starts this way.
This is what you care about, this thing.
And then you say, let's replace it with
something.
In Lagrange Duality, you replace it with
something that's linear.
And people say, wow, that is a crappy
approximation.
And you go, yeah, but I'm leaving open the
following possibility, I can change,
I can wiggle the lambdas, right?
That, that's, that's the secret in
Lagrange Duality, right?
What was weird was Lagrange Duality ended
up having like a really good ending.
Right?
So you can, this is, all I'm saying the
story is the same.
Here instead of saying we're going to
replace it with, with a, a linear thing,
and wiggle with the slope, we're actually
going to replace it with something that
actually plausibly is, or might be, an
actual approximation of this function.
By the way, all this hints that duality is
going to pop right out of what we're
doing, and you shouldn't be surprised,
because the stories start the same way.
In fact, at an abstract enough level, the
stories are exactly the same.
You replace the true irritation function,
which is this thing, with some kind of
smooth approximation.
In Lagrange Duality, it's the smoothest
thing you can get.
It's a line.
Here, it's some log barrier.
Okay.
All right.
Oh, so let's look at the log barrier
function.
Well, it's convex and we know that.
And its derivatives, let's work out what
these are, right?
So the gradient of this is, well,
the gradient of, of minus log minus f is
this thing, right?
And remember, fi of x is negative, so that
that's, this is a positive, so
you, whenever you see minus fi of x, it's
a positive number.
Okay?
So, this says, this says that the gradient
of the log barrier is a positive scaled
sum of the gradients of the functions.
Remember that, it's going to come up.
That's what it is, right?
Oh, and what are the scale factors?
Depends on how close you are, how tight
that, what margin you have.
That's the margin, minus fi is the margin
in the inequality, 1 fi less than zero,
it's minus 0.2, your margin is 0.2.
Right?
Fi can increase 0.2, before you're
infeasible.
Everybody got this?
So that's the, this is one over the
margin.
So the scale factor's in front are the on
over the margin's.
Okay?
And the Hessian looks like this
that's just for reference, because we're
not actually going to use that.
But just so you know what it is.
Right?
By the way, you see here a set of rank 1
terms, and
then the actual the sum of the Hessians.
Okay.
All right.
So, if I take a problem and I minimize
here.
Oh, by the way, we had to draw the
picture.
We were minimizing f0 plus phi of x.
Yeah, that's the same thing as minimizing
tf0 plus phi.
Why do we do that?
It, because the self-concordance stuff
will work out later better or
something, but it doesn't matter.
I mean, in fact, most people,
put their 1 over t there and by the way
they call it capit too.
So it doesn't matter, you'd figure these
things out.
okay, so this says we are going to
minimize tf0 plus phi, so
it's Ax equal to b.
That's total, we're totally ready for
Newton here, so we know exactly how they
compute that no, not a problem.
Right?
Now, we do expect that when t gets
gigantic you know,
this is Newton's going to have some
trouble.
We'll get to that.
Okay.
So this thing is, it, it turns out that
you can show that the log barrier is
strictly convex, as long as the feasible
set is bounded.
Right?
And it, and we're going to just assume
that, the feasible set is bounded, and
then that says that the log barrier is
strictly convex, so
that this is a unique point.
And in fact, if you minimize this, that's
called x star of t.
And it's a path, right?
Because for each t, you get a minimizer,
right?
And it's called, that's called the central
path.
The path of central point [INAUDIBLE]
points or something like that.
That's a central path.
And, so the picture would look something
like this.
We start with an LP.
Here's one inequality, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, whatever it is, six
inequalities, and these dashed curves show
you the level sets of, of the barrier.
Right?
And then it goes up to plus infinity, so
you should be visualizing that,
that the barrier goes up to plus infinity
at the boundaries.
Okay?
And then, what we're doing is we're adding
we're adding t times
c to the, to the point, minimizing, and so
that's sort of the analytic center.
That's the point that actually,
the analytic center maximize, minimizes
the sum of the negative log margins.
That maximizes the product of the margins,
so it's a point deep inside the set.
That's the analytic center.
So it starts here which equals zero.
And then as you crank up, as you crank up
the scale factor in front of the c.
It says minimize the barrier function.
But also start putting a stro-, now it
says start minimizing t times c.
C is the actual obj-, c transpose x,
c transpose x is the actual objective you
want to minimize, right?
So, so what happens is very interesting.
Oh, what happens is the more you crank up
t, the closer you come to
minimizing C transpose X, but you will
never leave the feasible region.
Right?
In fact
you'll never leave the strictly feasible
region.
The reason is the barrier which is by the
way this is why it is called a barrier.
The barrier goes up to plus infinity and
no matter how big t is,
you'll move in the direction minus c tran,
minus c, but at some point, you'll get to
the point where it's no longer worth it to
get close to the boundary and you'll stop.
Everybody got this?
So the central path might look like that.
I mean, it's kind of silly, because it's
an lp in two variables or
something, but anyway, that's, that's what
the central path looks like here.
Okay.
And that's the that's the idea.
Okay?
So that's [INAUDIBLE].
Now, it turns out if you're on the central
path surprise, surprise,
you get for free dual, dual points for the
original problem.
So, let's see how that works?
If you're on the central path, it means
you minimize tf0,
plus sum minus log, minus fi of x.
So, you minimize this thing.
Now, let's take the gradient of that,
right now.
Well, you get t grad f, f0, and then you
get the derivative of this.
I'm going to ignore the second term,
which is the e the equality constraint
Lagrange multiplier part.
That's this thing.
I mean, that just works.
And this thing, the gradient of that is
this thing right here.
Now you stare at that for a minute, and
you realize, hm, that's interesting.
It's, in fact, the first thing we're
going to do just for
fun, is we're going to take this t and put
it back over here.
You know, frankly, it probably should have
been there anyway.
Right?
So we're going to get rid of that t and
we're going to divide this by t as well.
Okay?
Okay, like that.
That's what we're going to do.
And now you look at this and you say, hey,
that's interesting.
On the central path, here's,
when you compute a point on the central
path, strangely, you have the following.
You have the gradient plus a non-negative
weighted sum of the gradient,
this is the gradient of the objective,
plus a non-negative weighted sum of the
gradients of the constraint functions, And
then plus a transposed times an equality
constraint dual variable that's zero.
That should sound familiar, because guess
what?
That's actually Lagrange duality.
Because look at this, it says that if you
formed, if we take these numbers here
to be the lambdas, and we take this to be
nu here, then this thing reads
gran f of 0 plus sum lambda i grad f of i,
plus A transpose nu equals 0.
But the first, this first term, is exactly
the gradient of this with respect to x.
Right?
So, that's what it says.
So this says something amazing.
This says that if you compute a central
point, whether you like it or
not, what pops out are dual variables.
Okay?
Now remember that in, you know,
a lot of cases it's not easy to find dual
variables, right?
I mean, if you take like an LP, which
works here, right?
Most, you can't just pick some positive
vector and some other vector.
I mean, there's equality constraints that
have to hold.
It's like a transpose lambda plus c equals
0.
So the fact is that, if you just pick a
lambda and
an LP, it's not going to be dual feasible.
Or another way to say it is, you would
say, here's my positive lambda and
my nu, please tell me my lower bound.
And it will come back and go, I got a
lower bound for you,
it's minus infinity, which is the, which
is the universal lower bound, right?
You don't even have to hear the question,
before you can give that as a lower bound.
Right?
So, so what's at, so it's not trivial to
say that it's not to find dual feasible
points or anything like that.
But this does it, right?
So you, any point on the central path
gives you a dual feasible point.
Well, if you have a dual feasible point,
you should have a strong urge to do the
following.
If you have a dual feasible point,
you should think, that gives me a lower
bound on the optimal value of the problem.
So let's evaluate the lower bound.
Let's find out what it is?
So, let's do that.
Well, so, we'll take, this, this dual
feasible pair, and let's,
let's work, it says simply that that's
dual feasible.
Well, I mean, this is true, even if it's
not dual feasible.
Dual feasible means that this thing is
bigger than minus infinity and
therefore nontrivial.
Right?
So, let's work out what g is.
Well, it's just L evaluated at these
points.
But that's, that's f0 of x star of t and
then plus sum lambda i star fi.
But lambda i star is actually 1 over fi of
x star times t.
They cancel.
This is just m over t.
It's nothing more.
Right?
And so you get this.
And it's actually extraordinary, this,
that's g.
And the duality gap, x, x star is of
course, strictly primal feasible.
Right?
And it's got the value f0 of x star.
But it says that when you center, if you
do analytic centering, you get two things.
You get a point which has an objective
value f0 of x star of t,
but you also get dual variables that
certify,
that this number is a lower bound on the
optimal value.
M the, the gap, people call that the
duality gap, is exactly m over t.
Okay?
Everybody, it's crazy, I mean, it's just
arithmetic here.
I mean, not arithmetic, I mean,
it's, it's completely, there's nothing
complicated here, right?
Just take some derivatives, make a few
observations, and that's it.
So that says, if you minimize tf0 plus
this log barrier of x,
subject to Ax equals b, then it says two
things will come, you will, when you
write the Newton method or whatever from
that, there'll be two return things.
An x, which is strictly feasible, and a
du-, and
a pair of dual feasible vectors lambda and
mu and
the associated gap between the upper bound
on the objected value which is f, fx0,
f0 of x star, and the gap which is g of
lambda star nu star,
the difference between those two will be
exactly m over t.
Okay?
So, that's cool.
By the way, what this says is we now know
that this kind of hand waving intuition
about, you know, we, we looked at this, we
looked at this thing.
And I looked at this and I said, oh, hey,
look at that.
If t gets bigger,
you get a better approximation to the true
thing we care about, right?
And I said, so, I mean this sounds
reasonable,
if we take t big, you're getting close to
the original problem.
Right?
So, that's all hand waving and I can make
up other stories like that and
they're totally wrong.
This means it's actually completely
correct and it's very specific.
It says that if you, calculate x star of
t, that is, so you minimize this func-,
you minimize this objective, subject to
that equality constraint.
Which we know how to do using Newton's
method.
Then it says the following.
It says if you do that, then you will have
computed a solution to
the original problem which is at most, m
over t suboptimal.
Everybody got that?
Obviously now if t goes to as t gets
bigger, you're done.
So, couple more interpretations.
This is actually probably the dominant
modern interpretation.
So the modern interpretation of, of, of,
if you look at interior point method,
if you go, you know, pull some book or
something like that, I don't know.
This is the way the story would go.
They would say, here are the, here are the
KKT conditions for
an inequality constraint problem.
Well you better have that, that's primal
feasibility.
Right?
You have to this, right, that, that's
another one.
And you have to have the following, here,
you have to have complement,
complementary, and that says this, right?
That, that's equal to 0, so i equals 1 to
m.
Right?
And this says that for
each constraint, either the Lagrange
multiplier is 0.
Right?
Would, and that would, that must occur if
that constraint is, has margin, right?
If fi is actually negative, right?
Then the Lagrange multiplier has to be 0.
And you know that for many, many reasons,
right?
Or, that if the Lagrange multiplier is
positive, the only other
option it says that constraint must be
tight and tight means fi is 0.
So this is complementary slackness, I
think is.
Well it's both, yeah that complementary or
complementary slackness.
Okay?
So and we look at this and
then you have to have this.
Right?
And so here's what's really cool.
When you center with parameter t, here's
what you get.
You get something, you get an x, x star of
t, that satisfies this.
As a matter of fact, it satisfies the fi
of x is strictly less than 0.
Right?
Because you're minimizing the sum of
the minus logs and blah, blah, blah,
right?
Okay.
So you get this,
even with a little margin.
You get a lambda that's strictly positive,
because it's, I forget what it is,
it's mi, it's 1 over t times minus fi, and
the fi's, well, okay, that's never 0.
Okay, so you get, you get, you get,
you get, satisfy this strictly, this
strictly you satisfy this exactly.
And here, instead of a complimentary
slackness with 0,
the product of all the lambdas and minus
f's are 1 over t.
Okay.
Well, I mean, you can check, because we
defined lambda,
remember we defined lambda as, like, 1
over t times minus fi.
So that says that, that says that lambda
fi is, like, 1 over t.
So, so what it's there and now you can see
and argue again.
If' t gets big, you know,
it says so, you're almost there, it's sort
of these you check off.
Right?
So you get all of these.
And the only thing here is a set of zero
you get 1 over t.
And then the idea is we let t go to
infinity.
And, we're now satisfying the KKT
conditions.
So that's, that's kind of the idea.
Oh, and you would hear,
so, if you actually find yourself hearing
somebody talking about these things.
I mean, I hope you don't, but if you do.
Somewhere then this will be referred to
when you
replace the complementarity condition
lambda i,
fi equals 0 with a 1 over t which
traditionally they would called kappa.
Those are referred to as the modified KKT
conditions, and
so that story goes like this.
Here is the problem, here the KKT
conditions.
We modify the KKT condition so that 0
becomes a kappa and
now we say we're going to apply a Newton's
step to the modified KKT condition.
And guess what that It's the Newton step
for the problem we just looked at.
So, okay.
Everybody got this?
So that's it, okay.
And you can get some other
interpretations.
You don't need to know any of these
things, but
they're just kind of cool to help
understand what it is.
Here's one.
So let's forget the equality constraints.
Let's suppose you're minimizing you are
minimizing f0
subject fi versus 0 that's the log barrier
so let's center.
You can think of it this way.
I like to think of it as tf0, that's the
potential of a force field and
the force field is minus t times the
gradient.
Right?
So it's, it's actually a,
a potential, and then, minus log minus fi,
that's the barrier term associated with fi
less than 0.
That's, that's actually the potential of
this force field,
the force field which is 1 over fi times
gradient of fi.
Right?
And then the optimality condition for
minimizing, this is that.
And that's that all the forces balance.
Right?
So, and I mean, it's dumb, it's saying
like, look, let's minimize, you know,
this potential plus these potentials, and
each of these is a logarithmic potential
associated with one constraint.
Okay?
So it's like a force field interpretation,
and for a liner program, you get something
even cooler, a very simple interpretation.
The objective is just something like that,
tc.
And if you like you could think of it like
This,
I have a constant force field in the
direction minus C.
It's live gravity except it's, the
magnitude is t and I can turn it up.
So I can turn gravity up and up and up.
And it is constant force field, it just
pointing the direction minus C and
I have the ability to turn up gravity,
okay.
Now, the other planes the Ai, those
things.
The, it turns out that the,
this is the thing whose, that's the force
field associated with the logarith,
logarithmic barrier associated with just
Ai transpose x minus b is less than 0.
Or, a i transpose x is less than b, right?
That's the force field.
It's a beautiful force field.
It ports, it always points away from the
plane, and
it's actually a beautiful thing.
It's with exactly an inverse distance
magnitude, right?
So, for example, if that's a linear
inequality that says please stay on
this side of the linear inequality,
it says that the force field here will
point away from this thing,
and in magnitude be inversely proportional
to how close you are.
Okay, so as you move closer, you get a
very strong repulsive force.
Right?
So, it means like you've sprayed these
planes with some repulsive stuff, I don't
know [INAUDIBLE], I don't know.
Actually I don't think there's anything in
physics that actually does this.
But you can pretend like there is.
Right?
So, by the way,
it's not correct that you spray it with
charge.
There's, there's no physical thing that
will actually make that analogy right,
so at least that I know of.
So, that's it.
And now you can actually visualize what
the force field is, it is very simple.
For example, at this point you are
actually being acted on
by five five things right, five forces,
but the,
the force field is pretty much in that
direction, because, because you
are right up under the shadow of a very
strong one and so that's dominating.
Right, and so what happens now is the
analytic center
is when you got all these repulsive fields
all around you and
you retreat to the center where all these
forces balance.
Okay, and now they all, all they are
balance.
I mean, that's, that's this, this point.
I mean, actually here it's not the
analytic center,
we have turned t up a little bit, it's t
equals 1.
Right?
And so it goes minus c.
And when you, makes this thing bigger,
right you move to a new equilibrium point.
Okay?
So.
I, this doesn't do anything.
It's just a way to think of all this
stuff, right.
I mean, otherwise it's just too fast, you
know, so, it, and
I mean, it's actually not a bad way to
think about what these things are doing.
Right?
So, okay.
Now we get to the barrier method.
So, oh, and let me say, let me give a
little bit of preamble.
Okay, so simply choosing a big, a big
enough t, and
minimizing using Newton's method, That's
called, it actually isn't called, but
I decided to call it that, the umt.
That's unconstrained minimization
technique, and I,
I'll tell you why I decided to call it
that.
It's because it's a weird, retro,
historical reference.
Okay, so that's the unconstrained
minimization technique.
Weirdly, it actually works fine.
So it's actually an awfully good way,
if you're solving lps, But to some
relatively low accuracy, so
t doesn't have to be gigantic, it's an
excellent method, you're right.
Newton method, and you go at it.
It just works, right.
Everybody, so, it just works, right?
And it just always, you know you get the
minimum, you get the duality gap.
It returns primal point, dual point,
everything, and
the gap is exactly m over t.
And if you wanted that to be 1e minus 3,
or 0.01.
Right, depending on your application,
that's exactly what it will be.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
Works pretty well.
now, it doesn't if you ask for a high
accuracy, or something like that.
Then it doesn't, it, it doesn't work.
Hey, we all, it works, it just takes
10,000 iterations,
if you implement it in infinite precision
arithmetic.
So.
okay.
So there's actually a,
a method And it's a, it's a general idea,
and, and so the other name for
the barrier method, by the way, from the
'60s, is SUMT, SUMT.
That's sequential unconstrained
minimization technique.
Beautiful name, right, because it says
exactly what it is.
Well, except we added the equality
constraints.
But, for all practical purposes, those
aren't, you know, so.
Equality constraints don't hurt you.
There the unconstrained referred to no
inequality constraints.
Everybody got that?
So that's a beautiful thing.
There's a book written on this like 1969,
Sequential Unconstrained Minimization
Technique.
Okay, so, and if you, if you just fix t
and
solve it once, that's now, I decided to
call it UMT.
Okay, so all right.
So, that the sequential method, that's the
barrier method and that works like this.
So you are, you are, you are start with
some, some point it's feasible here and
what you are going to do is the following
and some point T, you know that's
parameter MU this is a very simple method
and you are going to do the following.
You are going to compute X star of t by
minimizing this thing subject to
a equals b then you going to update.
That's going to be your new value of x and
then you're going to quit if m over t,
which is exactly the gap is less than
epsilon, right.
And then you would return.
By the way, both x and the and the dual
points, right, because.
That's what you should return if you write
a solver,
you should return the dual points as well.
Okay, and you increase t.
Now the key here is that you use Newton's
method
to minimize this starting from the last
point.
That's the key.
Okay?
So that, that's, that's the key here.
Right?
And there's a name for this and there's
beautiful pictures for this.
Like, so for example, another way to,
another name for
methods like this, this method, in fact a
method like this.
Another name for this, beautiful name, is
path-following method.
For optimization.
Absolutely beautiful because, you know,
here's, here's the central path,
right, going into your solution, right?
And a path following method says you're
here.
That's a certain value of t.
Let's take you know, mu equals 1.1.
Okay, then, what happens is, you, starting
from this point,
you apply Newton's method and you bump
around for
a bit and then you end up there, and, and
this is, this is, x star of t, and
this is x star mu t, right, that's the new
point, and
you can see what you're doing, you're sort
of following this path.
Right?
So, and, there's an, actually, there's a
name for these methods and it's actually,
it's actually there's a very good thing to
know about these, these methods.
So, actually there's a beautiful to the
name for a, let me describe,
this is something, this is something
again, you don't need to know this, but
it's actually a very good thing for
you to know if you do any kind of math or
anything like that.
There's a, a general family of methods
for, for solving a hard problem, right.
And it's called a homotopy method, 'kay,
and the way it works is very simple.
You have a hard, something you want to
solve like a set of equations, or for that
matter, an optimization problem, but you
have a set of equations you want to solve.
And they're hard to solve.
So what you do is you introduce a,
a parameter into the equations, that, it's
a knob that you turn, 'kay.
And it has to be continuous or,
as you turn the knob, the, the equations
deform continuously.
And now the traditional ranges of these
values for the knob are zero and one, and
so the idea is, when the knob is all the
way up at one,
you got the problem you wanted to solve.
That's the traditional parameter value.
When it's zero, the idea is it starts from
a simple problem.
Everybody following this, right?
And then the,
now, the method I'll describe, the
homotopy method, is very simple.
Here's what you do.
You set your knob to zero, you know the
solution already.
Then you set the knob to 0.05.
Okay?
Well, the problem is now close to an easy
one, and you knew the solution for
the easy one, so you use something like a
Newton method to try to find it.
By the way, what would you do, if you, if
Newton method failed to find that point?
Yeah, you'd back off, instead of 0.05,
you'd go to 0.025, right?
Now, in this, in this particular case, you
don't have to,
because no matter how you set this thing,
it's going to work.
Although it might take too many Newton
steps, so
you might do something like, I'll set it
0.05.
If I don't converge in 15 steps, screw it,
I'm going to back off.
It means I, I, it means I stepped too
aggressively along the path.
Everybody following this?
Okay.
So, then you're at 0.05 and you set, now
you set data equals 0.1 and
you apply Newton method again and
hopefully you get there.
Everybody following this?
And so, and then there's a beautiful book,
I think the subtitle of the book on this
is Pathways oh, something like,
homotopy methods, subtitle is Pathways to
Solutions.
I mean, come on, that's like too cool,
right?
This is a homotopy method, right?
It's, it's when, but there's a difference
between a general homotopy method, and
a general homotopy method, when you
increase that parameter,
you're actually not sure you can actually
solve the problem, and
there in a general homotopy method goes
like this.
If, you know, if not solve problem, right?
Then it says, back off back off the
parameter increase.
Everybody understand that one line?
Okay.
So that's a general homotopy.
Here, you can't fail.
Right, because we can set t equals 10 to
the 9.
And at least in theory we can fail.
Now there's a practical idea of failure
that might be that it takes more than ten,
20 newton steps, right?
So I just mention that.
Okay, so here it, so it's extremely
simple.
That's the idea.
Now, mu, that's, that's the amount by
which you increase.
Oh, sorry, the,
the typical homotopy method the
traditional parameter range zero to one.
Zero, zero is your problem, one is done.
' Kay, so our, our parameter range is like
zero, infinity, okay, or one, infinity.
Something like that, okay, so that's, but
so what that that's the difference, but
I thought it, I thought I'd mention it,
right.
Okay, so now what we do here.
Is, you're going to increase t, which is
actually a measure of inverse gap.
You're going to increase t by a factor of
mu.
Now, if you're really sort of follow the
idea of, you know a homotopy method
following the central path towards the
solution, you know, Pathway to Solution,
if you really kind of follow that image,
you would think of mu as being 1.05 Right?
That you, you'd increase mu 5%, you know,
start, and you'd hope for a couple Newton
steps and it's all over, right?
That, that would be, and there's actually
a name for methods like that.
Those are called short step path following
methods.
Okay, so you Google that, you'll find 50
papers.
Okay?
Their long step ones is where you're much
more aggressive in updating the parameter.
And the choice of that mu, which is how
much you update the parameter value that,
that's sort of like how aggressively you
update, there's a tradeoff.
If you make mu tiny Then presumably every
time you
are solving the new problem is basically
the same as the problem you just solve.
You're you're within the range of
quadratic convergence, you do one step.
And the fact there are methods based on
that they're called,
those are the short step path following
methods and they choose mu so
small that you are always in the range of
quadratic convergence, right.
So that, so literally one Newton step.
Increase mu.
One Newton step, increase mu.
So that's, that, these are short step
methods.
Long step methods don't do that, right?
And it turns out actually that as a
practical matter different values of
mu are actually better.
10, 20, 30, I mean, actually fairly
aggressive ones, even 100 or something.
Okay?
Okay.
You're going to,
if you're going to stop At at duality gap
epsilon, your duality gap,
when you finish centering, is always
exactly m over t, right?
If t has been increased by mu each time,
you just take the log, you know,
base mu, whatever it is, and that tells
you, you know exactly the number of
outer iterations to achieve duality gap
plus an epsilon is this, right?
So, gets, and kind of a beautiful thing.
You can see that if mu is 1.05, that's a
small thing in the bottom, right?
And you take a lot of iterations.
If mu is 100, it's a lot fewer outer
iterations, right?
because actually every time you do an
outer iter, sorry,
an outer iteration, outer iteration is a
centering.
So every time you do a centering,
your duality gap goes down exactly by a
factor of mu.
So if mu is 100, that says, you start with
a duality gap of, you know, 100.
Next step it's 1, then it's 0.01, 1e minus
4, 1e minus x, okay, that kind of thing.
Right.
On the other hand, with mu as 100, You,
you, you got some,
you got some serious Newton heavy lifting
to do, right, because you're starting from
one problem, but the, it's not that close
to the prob, to the next problem, and so
you, you know, who knows how many Newton
steps you're going to have?
And in fact, what happens in a general
homotopy method, which is,
what you don't want to happen is the
following.
As you approach the target, the problems
get harder.
This is what screws you, and this is, by
the way, why it doesn't work to just go
sand something off in any way you like, so
that's, that's a, that's what happens.
If you just go ahead, great idea, homotopy
method, you don't have to know anything.
Let me have your problem, I'll just sand
these things off,
I have a parameter that controls how much
sand paper I use.
Well, actually it's the grit of the sand
paper, right?
So I start with 80, I go to 120, I go to
400,
I go to 8, you know this kind of thing.
I guess they don't make grit.
They probably do make grit for like
lacquers and
thing like that in the thousands right,
but okay.
So, then you know, the problem,
the down fault of a completely general
homotopy method is very simple.
It's that as you increase,
as you get closer to the solution, the
problems get harder and harder.
So, you're increasing mu, let's go from
zero to one.
You know, let, let's take a parameter
theta going from zero to one,
that's the traditional range.
You know, I go from zero to 0.1 no
problem.
0.2, 0.3, now I start getting to 0.9,
and instead of two Newton steps, it's now
taking 20.
And now I go to 0.92 because I've had to
back off and
it's taking 100 Newton steps and you can
see this is not going well.
So that's the downfall of why just
constructing a general purpose
homotopy fails.
Okay, we're going to see something amazing
happens here.
And it's very specific to the log barrier
and so on.
Okay, so, this is the number, total number
of,
of, of of outer steps you're going to do,
obviously.
And then, you're going to multiply this by
the number of
Newton steps required to solve the
centering problem here when t is
mu times the previous t starting from the
solution when it was t.
Okay?
Now, if you use the classical analysis,
Something bad happens, right?
If you go back to the classifal classical
Kantorovich analysis of Newton's method,
you will actually find that these problems
are getting harder.
Well, okay, they wouldn't assert that,
because they understood well that they
were simply producing an upper bound on
the number of steps, which is valid.
I guess they would un, they would stay at
the, the correct way to say it is.
The complexity and that the upper bound is
growing.
Right, so what happens is when t gets very
big here, L gets big.
The Lipschitz condition, we and
we know that because you know what you're
really doing is you are placing something
looks like this, where something that's
curve, you know look like that.
L is going to get really big and the
prediction is, is that as you increase t,
sure, the problems get harder and harder
and
like, first you're doing 10 Newton steps,
then 50 then 100, then it all falls apart.
Everybody following this?
Okay, so that's the classical analysis.
But let's, let's take a pause and let's
just run the method and
see what it looks like.
So here's the method.
Here's an inequality form lp, and what's
crazy about it, so
this is, you know, 50 variables, right?
And here, here it is,
and now, you have to understand, I have to
explain exactly what these are.
This shows duality gap, and these are like
little staircase plots.
And when I, what I have to,
what you have to understand is, I'm
counting Newton iterations here, and so
the width of a tread is the number of
Newton steps required, right?
So I don't know, let's look at this one.
This one is, that's 20, that's, that's
like, I don't know,
eight Newton steps, right?
These things.
This is for mu equals 50, and that's where
mu equals 150.
Okay, now the height of one these stairs
is when you finished entering,
you just reduce the duality gap always
exactly by mu by a factor of mu, so
on a log duality gap plot, you go down by
a fixed amount.
So the height of the stairs in each case
is exactly the same as log mu,
well it's mu on a log plot.
Everybody's got this?
Okay, so now you can see, mu equals 2.
By the way, we'll see that if you're doing
complexity theory, right, so
you want to prove that it's a polynomial
type method,
it will suggest taking like mu equals
1.01.
What do you, what would it look like if it
was 1.01 here?
Well, first of all it would be one Newton
step for sure every time, right, and
it would be a, this would be like a little
staircase going like that, right.
And it would go you know, it would work,
okay.
And, you know, but so what's weird here,
so now you can see everything.
Here's mu equals 2 and you can see that
this, the,
the, the treads are short, meaning you're
not making, you're taking two,
three steps, I don't know here you crank
this up to 50 and 150,
and you're taking like eight Newton steps,
but you're making a big progress in gap.
Right, so, right.
Now, here's what's weird.
Let's just focus on this guy like right
here.
You just reduce the duality gap by a
factor of 10 to the 8.
Okay, for all practical purposes, you just
solved that LP.
That is an LP with 50 variables.
'Kay?
With 100 constraints.
That's a polyhedron that has got a
absolutely gigantic number of vertices.
Right?
Our 50 is a big place.
Okay?
This says, you just solved the LP in 30
steps.
Okay?
Now, that's ridiculous.
I just want to point that out.
That means you're in 50 dimensional space.
You actually stopped and asked for
directions 30 times.
And said excuse me, which way should I go?
And the answer came back from some Newton
thing, or something like that.
Which is like go in that direction, right?
That's what you did.
30 steps later,
you've found your way to one of the, who
knows how many vertices this is.
But the answer's a lot.
You found you're very close to the
vicinity of the optimum.
Everyone following this?
So that's that would be like in R3 asking
for
directions like twice or one and a, I
mean, you are asking for
directions in a substantially fewer number
than the dimension.
So everybody realize how ridiculous this
is.
Right that's an R50.
Here's what's cool.
Guess what this plot looks like if you do
this with 50,000 variables?
They look exactly the same.
They're the same.
'Kay, they look exactly like this.
It's the same thing, it's weird.
Now, this is like a plot of the number of
iterations you need as you vary mu.
And something pretty weird happens.
If you make mu too small, over here.
Sure you're going to take a lotta steps.
By the way if we continued this, this
starts going up like that.
Okay?
But this is very cool because what's
happening across this range of mu,
this is super good news because mu is an
algorithm parameter, right?
And it's super good news,
because it means the good performance
persists across a wide range.
Now, what, what's happening here is very
interesting.
As you vary mu,
as you increase mu, what's going to happen
is the treads get, are getting wider.
But the stairs are getting taller, because
you get more, you get you get
more duality gap reduction every time you
center, it takes you more Newton steps.
Miraculously, you multiply these two
effects out and it's constant,
everybody see this and that's just a
ridiculous number, I mean 30, 30 steps.
These are in fact the numbers that you
have been seeing for the whole quarter.
If you pay attention, you probably don't.
But if you paid attention to things like
what's reported when Sedumi and
SDPT3 run is, you can now actually
understand many,
most of the columns of what's being
printed out.
I don't know if you've noticed, but
if you give the super duper easy problem,
it's 10, 10 iterations.
Usually it's 25.
It can be 30, and if you give it some
weird things,
some SOCP right on the boundary and it,
you know, whatever, it can take 40.
I don't know if you've been watching, but
that's, that's what this is.
Right.
By the way,
a bunch of the other entries being printed
out, you should also understand,
because things like primal residual, dual
residual, things like that, so, okay.
Everybody.
So this is actually pretty cool stuff.
All right, so here's a GP.
Guess what?
Looks the same, 'kay.
The same.
This is with log sum x, bunch of log sum,
that's, that's a geometric program.
Here's a bunch of LPs.
I think this is the problem you're
going to solve, and
this is what it looks like.
This is, for each one, You get a bunch,
you get 100 instances for each problem,
size, and you solve it.
so, this here is a problem with,
I guess 1000 constraints, and 1000 and
2000 variables, okay.
And you can see by the way, in all of
these simulations,
the absolute maximum number of iterations
was something like 30.
I was at 31.
That's it, okay?
Everybody, this is kind of the scaling.
By the way, this scaling law continues.
Oh and I should tell you how this works.
The theory, we'll get to it in a minute,
the theory says this thing scales like the
square root.
That's the best bound known to date.
Okay?
It says that as you get bigger and
bigger, the problem goes like square root.
That's enough, by the way,
for our polynomial time complexity
theorists to be happy or something, right?
So that's fine.
This is the scaling.
And I'll tell you a little, let me just
tell you a little bit about,
about this, and we'll, we're going to quit
here for today, but I,
I want, I want to say a little bit about
it.
You see these pictures?
Guess what.
The pictures look the same.
If these are anything, lps qps actually,
we'll see later,
we'll extend this to do semi defininte
programs, things like that, sdps, sopcs.
It doesn't matter if it's a problem from
signal processing,
from control, from finance, from machine
learning.
They all look the same.
And, I was going to say something about
this,
this thing, this thing, this empirical
thing, continues.
Because I have a friend In Glasgow who
solved an LP in exactly this form with,
I think it was something like a billion
variables, on some gigantic, ridiculous,
gigantic machine, one of these IBM blue
jean things or, right?
Okay?
I just, go ahead, I said, what method do
you use?
He said just standard, standard method.
And I said, how many iterations does it
take.
And the number?
>> [INAUDIBLE]
>> Eh, you're close.
It's 24.
This is the amateur,
what you're seeing here is the amateur
implementation that's, you know.
By the way, all these implementations you
can find on, I mean,
on the book website you can find our code.
So the pedagogical amateur implementation
gets 30, the really cool ones get 21, 24.
So just 24 steps.
It was identical.
Right?
Now, I should add something about this.
This is the number of steps, but the
number of, the time for
a step is not constant, you know, duh.
Because a step is actually solving a least
squares problem.
Everyone agreed?
Because it's solving a Newton system.
What's a Newton system?
It's solving a least squared, it's
minimizing a convex quadratic, that's,
is another name for that, it's called
solving a least squares problem.
Everybody following this?
Right.
So the difference between this guy who
solved a billion variable problem and us
solving a 100 variable problem, you know,
that's like over here [LAUGH] somewhere is
considerable.
I, I solved my 100 variable problem in
100, 100 microseconds, and
oh, each iteration for him, by the way,
took something like 90 minutes, okay.
And the lights in Glasgow dimmed while it
was running, okay.
And the downstream river like, was like,
really hot or something like that,
so, but the point was, it was just 24 of
those, so it was 24 times 90 minutes.
Ever, right?
So, so actually,
this is actually super duper interesting,
because what it says is the following.
It's kind of weird.
It makes full circle with the whole
course, back to least squares, right?
So, when you come into this class, you
know about least squares.
I mean, everybody knows about least
squares.
And you shouldn't make fun of least
squares,
because like all sorts of crap is made to
run really well with least squares.
All sorts of image processing, like pretty
much all of actual statistics that's used.
I mean, right?
All of control, all sorts of stuff, is
least squares.
I mean, you, you throw in regularization
and some other tricks,
you fiddle with the weights, you can make
a lot of stuff happen and it,
basically 20th century engineering was
done with least squares.
Okay?
Period.
And a lot of now, too.
Everybody on board with this?
And then you say, well, why do you take
this class?
And you go.
Well, you know, that's, that's traces back
to, to Gauss.
We're going to learn that you can do kind
of the same stuff but
now have inequalities and constraints and
you can really say what you want.
Everybody following?
I mean, that's kind of what the class is
about, right?
Here's the joke.
At the end of the class, someone says,
okay, fine, I, I, I believe it.
I can do monotone regression now.
I can solve all sorts of sick, sick things
and, you know, crazy machine learning
things, with, I don't know, all sorts of
weird hinged losses I.
You know.
You can do signal processing and compress
sensing, all this crazy stuff.
I can do finance, with like, three halves,
power, transaction cost, model.
All this crazy stuff.
And, someone goes, whoa, that's cool.
How do you solve it?
And, you know what this says?
The answer is, you solve 20 least squares
problems.
Everybody got that?
So what that says is, if you, if you're
solving, you know,
the classical, you know, older,
mathematical engineer's sitting there,
what are you doing, lqr, I don't know,
Kalman filter.
And then, what are you doing?
Well, I'm adjusting some things, like
covariance matrices or
weights or costs or something like that.
They're tweaking it to make it work.
Right?
So, then they'd say, well, what are you
doing, and
you go, I'm doing convex optimization.
I don't have to say these things are
between zero and one,
or I don't have to tweak things to make it
between zero and one.
I can just say I want these variables
Everybody following the story?
Okay, and they go, huh, how do you do
that?
And I go, by solving 20 least squares
problems.
So, it's kind of embarrassing that they're
so close.
Now, so far we have assumed that you
started with a point that was feasible and
we are going to fix that now and we are
going to fix it first in the absolutely
classical way this is from 1948 or
something like that.
So, the question is how do you find a
feasible point if you don't know one.
And lots of answers.
Here's one way, is, what we want to do is
find a point, x,
that satisfies the inequalities, and the
Ax equals b.
And the truth is, if we really want to
initiate a barrier method,
these inequalities have to be straight,
right?
So, not, it's not good enough to do this,
because the log barrier domain is these
things straight, or another way to say it
is, if you're using a barrier method,
Slater better hold, the Slater constraint
qualification better hold.
You better have a point that's strictly
feasible.
Okay, so here's your basic one, 1948, goes
like this.
You introduce a new variable, s, and you
minimize over x and
s, s, subject to fi of x less than s and
Ax equals b.
That's it.
Okay?
And, and if you look at this, you'll
realize immediately this is nothing but
the epigraph formulation for minimizing
the max.
You're minimizing max Fi.
Right?
That's what this says.
So, what happens is clear, if you solve
this problem, oh, let's discuss it.
For this problem you have, you can easily
get a strictly feasible point.
Right, so what you is you pick any x in
the domain of' fi, right.
You need, oh, you can actually relax the
ax equals b or
whatever something like that but you can
handle that as well,
let's let's even get the equality
constraint for now.
Right, but you simply take a point x then
what you do is you choose s
say the max of' f'i of' x plus 1.
And now, everyone of these inequality
holds with at least a gap of one in there.
Okay, so that gives you that gives you a
strictly feasible point.
So, you solve this method, you solve this
problem using say a barrier method and
what will happen is this.
If the optimal s is positive you're done.
Right, because you now will have a
certificate Proving that there is
no point that satisfies fi of x less than
0.
And in fact, the optimality conditions
here,
you could reconstruct a dual certificate,
and actually,
a theorem of the alternatives, an
alternative certificate, right?
So that's the case.
Otherwise, it, you can terminate the
minute s is negative.
Right, because if s is negative, you break
here, and
you've computed a point that's feasible
that's strictly feasible.
And then you go, you switch to the barrier
method.
Okay?
So this is completely it's classical.
Okay.
There's variations on it.
In fact, I think on your current
assignment,
where you're implementing one, there's
even a more sophisticated variation where
you take into account the equality
constraint.
So.
Okay.
Here's a very interesting alternative.
Now, these are called phase one methods.
I, I guess I should mention that, that the
idea is there's phase one and phase two.
In phase one, you determine a feasible
point and
then in phase two you then find an optimal
point starting from a feasible point.
Right?
So those are called phase one,
phase two methods.
actually, most modern methods use a
different thing which combines both of
them at once.
So, here's another variation, instead of
minimizing the maximum of
the functions in phase one, you minimize
the sum of the violations.
So, if you take a look at this problem
here, s is,
should be interpreted this way.
Si is something like a violation in f.
it's, it's, it's how much extra slack you
have to add to
that inequality to allow it to be true, or
something like that.
Right?
So here you're minimizing 1 to the sum of
the s's, and
this is clearly, this is exactly
equivalent to this.
You are minimizing here sum of fi of x
plus it's exactly that, so it's sum of the
positive part.
Right?
By now you should have a guess as to what
that's going to do, right?
Because in your head you should see this
and
I guess if you are machine learning you
call that hinge loss or
something but whatever it is it, it should
mean something to you.
What you would expect, and this is exactly
correct.
Is that when you solve this problem well,
if,
if there's a feasible point, the, you
know, you'll get every point here.
But if it's infeasible, something very
interesting happens.
You might get a few points up here.
Or another way to say it is you have a
sparse, you have sparse violations, right?
So that's what this will, this will give
you sparse violations, that's the idea.
So here's a quick example,
we have a set of 100 linear inequalities
of 50 variables here, right.
So it's infeasible, so there's no point it
satisfies all 100 inequalities.
If you apply the standard phase one method
this is the margin, here, right.
So, if you are above zero, that means
your, you satisfy the inequality.
Well, what you have done in the, in the
original, in the basic phase one,
the mini max phase one, what you do is you
push all of them this way and
the result is congratulations.
But you didn't satisfy, you didn't push
the margins, all the margins positive.
There is no point with that.
But what's happened is of course all the,
all the margins have piled up on the,
on the line where you're pushing, right?
And so that ended up being, you know,
minus 0.2.
So the point is, here, you got 50 out of
your 100 linear inequalities are violated.
And actually there's a couple down here,
so
it's probably more than half are violated.
Something like that.
Well, I guess it's here.
Yeah, 51.
Okay?
So 51 inequalities are violated.
When you do the sum, this sum, of
inequalities,
like the sum of violations method, you get
something very interesting.
And you can sort of see what happens.
So, by the way, how should we.
What that says is that, many of them,
right?
Are, are satisfied.
Right?
There's a big bump right there.
That's a whole bunch of things that ended
up right there.
It was just as easy.
And you have a, you know,
you have a handful out here that are the
ones you cannot satisfy, and so on.
Now, this does not compute the point that
violates the fewest inequalities, right?
It doesn't do that it's a heuristic for
that but you can see what it does.
Everybody got this?
Okay.
And by the way,
how would you interpret, what would you
say about that inequality right there?
It's an easy to satisfy inequality.
So, not only is it easy to satisfy, it's
easy to satisfy with a bunch of margin,
doesn't really cost anything, so it's
done.
Okay.
By the way, there's no incentive what so
ever for a margin to move to the right.
None what so ever because the slope of the
hinge loss is zero.
Once you've satisfied it.
Right?
So, you know,
you could put a small slope on that, if
you cared, right?
So, okay.
This is quite, it's actually, it's got a,
a ton of uses.
Uum, I mean, for example, in, in
engineering design,
if you throw together a problem with a
whole bunch of inequalities, a whole bunch
of specifications, and it's infeasible it
doesn't really help you to get a phase one
solution that violates like all of your
100 inequalities by some small amount.
It's actually quite interesting to get one
that satisfies like almost all
the constraints but a few, so it hand
selects a few, and it kind of guides you
and tells you which of the constraints
you're going to have to give up on, or
it suggests which ones you could give up
on.
Okay.
so, there's an, a very interesting thing
occurs when you're doing phase one,
and it has to do with the the complexity
analysis of it.
And in fact, this is the, the Achilles
heel of the complexity analysis of
all these interior point methods, so if,
if you do real complexity analysis
this is and, and you want to look and see
kind of where the fraud is
in complexity analysis of, of into your
point methods.
Look for a constant that tells you have
feasible the problem is right,
because the basically it, it's a bit, it's
a bit fishy.
so.
But let me explain what the idea is.
Here what you do is you construct a family
of linear inequalities like this.
Now the, the fact is, if you have a bunch
of linear inequalities, and
you run a phase one method actually, two
interesting things happen.
If the inequalities have a giant feasible
set, it'll take like ten steps,
and you'll have a feasible point and
you'll stop.
So if the feasible set is gigantic, You'll
terminate very quickly,
because there's just tons of feasible
points.
You'll find one real quickly, 'kay?
Now the flip side also occurs.
It's completely symmetric, and it goes
like this.
If the inequalities are wildly infeasible,
right, which,
by the way would mean what in terms of the
dual or alternative problem?
It'd be feasible, and its feasible set
would be big, right?
So to be wildly infeasible, right, means
that the dual
inequalities are not only feasible, but
have like a giant feasible set.
Okay?
Right?
What that means is there's tons of
certificates proving those things
are infeasible.
Everybody following this?
This is all completely hand waving, but
it's actually Good to know.
Okay?
So, in that case also,
phase one terminates very quickly because
it terminates when it
produces a certificate of infeasibility.
So again, eight, ten iterations.
20, you know, if it's a challenging one.
Everybody following us?
So, but right, if you now make a parameter
That takes you,
that perturbs the problem and makes it go
from feasible to infeasible, right?
And you tune that parameter right at the
phase transition
between feasible and infeasible.
That's where it actually gets hard to
solve, right?
And this is actually intrinsic.
I mean, there's nothing you can do about
this, right?
This, this is, it's sort of obv, it's
intuitively obvious and so on.
So so what happens,
it turns out is it's extremely difficult
to create a problem that will actually
be hard for a phase one to determine
feasibility or infeasibility, right?
If you just generate,
anything that will come up in practice
will be totally will work just fine.
It'll be ten, 20 steps, it'll be all over.
Right?
[INAUDIBLE] period, right?
Actually there are some pathologies but
their, that's it's a, it, that's a
different story, right?
It's a pathology and it's your fault
anyway or something like that.
If you're using barrier.
It, the general pathology is that you
don't, Slater is not satisfied and
that will do the trick.
Right?
But using other methods that don't care
about Slater, it,
you get you get the same thing like this.
so, what happens, So the only way to do
this is to very carefully construct it,
and you can see what's happening here,
right?
The number of steps is taking you.
And that's 25 or 30 or something like
that.
It's a bit high, but you know, doesn't
matter.
This is infeasible and then this is
feasible, and if you zoom in right as you
transition between them, you get something
like this, right.
So, now, let's think about what these
mean, right.
This is saying well, it's now taking 80
steps, here, to work this out,
that's because this problem is infeasible.
But it's infeasible in like the seventh
digit, right?
This problem is feasible in the seventh
So you know, in, in some sense this is of
no interest what so
ever in any practical application.
Right.
If your problem is feasible in the seventh
digit, you, you've got a problem, you have
a serious, practical, I mean,
it's not going to work, basic.
Whatever, whatever you think you're
going to use it for
is not going to work, right.
And the same for infeasibility, right, so.
But this is just to show you what, what
happens here.
So let's do the complexity analysis via
self concordance.
Right, and so, the assumptions are that
the, well, the sub level sets are bounded.
In fact, that follows from self
concordance, in fact.
No, not quite.
If you have a bounded feasible set.
And we'll assume that tf0 plus phi is
self-concordant.
And sometimes you assume this, for
example, for t bigger than 1, right?
This actually, we're going to increase t
so
it, if it's true for any value of t and
above, there will be, it'll be true.
For example, if f0's concordant,
self-concordant, this is true for
t bigger than or equal to 1, right?
If phi is self-concordant and f0 is.
Now this would hold for things like linear
programs, QPs,
QCQPs geometric programs, things like
that.
Now there are some cases where it isn't.
Here is one, Here is the maximum entropy
problem, right, and it is that it's not
self-concordant, but it turns out it's
really easy to make itself concordant and
actually when you think about it, you'd
realize its even the right thing to do.
One of the problems is there is an
implicit constraint here that Xi is bigger
than or equal to zero.
That's the domain of the entropy function
here, okay?
And it turns out,
all you have to do is add that and you're
back in self-concordance land, right?
The, the reason is, to the function here,
remember negative entropy is not
self-concordant.
Negative entropy plus t times the minus
sum
log xi, that is self-concordant, right.
So when you add this constraint, this
thing is self-concordant, right?
So, or sorry, tf0 plus 5 is
self-concordant for this reformulation,
and in fact, what it means is that xi
equals 0 is a problem here, right.
And what this says is you better make it
explicit, because that's actually not
a barrier for it, that's not a function
that goes to infinity as x goes to zero.
Right, so this says go ahead and make it,
call it
out explicitly instead of implicitly and
actually then the formulation works.
Okay.
oh, and I should say, before we can even
start the complexity analysis I should
start with a general comment.
The barrier method works extremely well
even when f0 and
tf0 plus phi are not self concordant,
right?
So, works perfectly well but if you really
want to understand why, I mean,
if you really want to understand why it
has to do with self-concordance, and
things like that so.
Okay.
So I'll go over the idea of this actually
it's a,
it's, it's, it's a bit complicated, so
I'll say just a few things about it,
and then this, this is something that
you'll want to go figure out for yourself.
So what happens is we, we know the number
of outer steps.
That's easy.
That's just basically log 1 over epsilon,
right, because you, you've, you,
you divide The duality gap by a factor mu
every outer one.
So the question is, how many Newton steps
does it take?
And the answer is very simple.
You are going to minimize mu t f0 of x,
right, plus phi of x.
We're going to minimize this.
Starting from the minimizer of t f0 of x
plus phi of x.
That's what we're going to do, right,
because we're, we've minimized this.
That's x star of t, right.
And then we're going to increment t by
multiplying it by mu, and
then we're going to minimize this
function.
So starting from the minimizer of this
function,
we're going to find the minimizer of that.
And Newton's the complexity analysis of
Newton's method via
self-concordance tells you that the number
of steps is less than or equal to this.
It's a constant times the starting value
of this function.
That's this here minus, if,
well if you put a plus there, that's minus
the final value.
So x is the current point, x is the
minimizer of this.
X plus is the minimizer of this, it's for
the new value of t which is mu times the
old t, okay.
So it says, you simply say it's the
starting function value minus
the final one and then multiply it by a
constant and then plus C, where C is six.
Right?
Or log log1 over epsilon, whichever,
right?
So that's what it is.
Okay, so we have to bound this.
Now, we already know what's going to come
to our rescue here
because it looks like al it looks like a
weird,
circular thing that's completely useless,
because it says.
It says how many Newton steps it take and
it says oh, no problem it's your function
value minus your final function value.
And you say well how do you find the final
function value,
you say use Newton's method but then if
you run Newton's method you don't know
how many steps it is in, it's all silly
and
of course what's going to come to your
rescue is duality, right, of course.
Right, so I, I'll go over a little bit of
this.
It's probably a bit too complicated to do
in lecture, so
it's it's the kind of thing you'll have to
work out on your own.
And I'll just say a couple of things here.
So here, when x is the minimizer of this,
and we define, if you remember
lambda i to be 1 over t times minus fi of
x,
right, and these are dual fea, these are
dual feasible points, right.
And in fact that once it give you the
duality gap exactly m over t, okay.
So, now we simply go through and
make various substitutions and I will say
a very little bit about each one but
won't go into too, too many horrible
details here.
So this says for example, that you can
represent the, you can take phi of x here,
right and write it, you can write phi of
x, here which is the minus
sum log minus fi and you can write that as
minus sum log
minus fi actually has the form 1 over ti
lambda i.
And if you're listening, and if I said it
right, which is not clear
then the minuses go away and that's like
sum log ti lambda i.
Right?
That you shove into this.
This thing is, that's minus, minus sum log
minus fi of x plus, and you put those in
and you get this thing like that.
The mu is pushed in and then taken out
here, right, because the mu is this,
you just take the mu out and you get m log
mu, and that, that accounts for it.
Okay?
So by the way, we've already used duality.
This is where we, this is where, if you
wonder where the duality came in, come in,
it comes in right there when we do this.
Okay, so in the next step, you simply use
the fact that, you know, log logx
is here, is less than or equal to x minus
1, so we do this here.
This is log that.
We write that out here.
And now a pattern starts emerging.
You see mu tf0 of x plus minus mu t time
sum lambda ifi of x plus.
And you say, oh, hey.
That is the dual function evaluated at,
that's the dual function evaluated.
Or that's, sorry, that's the Lagrangian
evaluated at x plus.
Right, so, okay so then, and then it has
to be less than or
equal to the dual function, the dual
function there,
because that is the minimum of this over
all x and in fact it's minimized by x.
So you get something like this, here and
now you're,
you're very close because F0 of x minus g
of lambda v, lambda nu,
sorry, this thing that is exactly the
duality gap, it's exactly m over t,
the t goes away, and you end up with a
very, very simple expression like that.
Right?
Now, mu is bigger than 1, and if you plot
this function for mu bigger than 1,
it looks like this.
Right, so here's, here's mu equals 1, and
what it is,
it starts quadratic And then it kind of
ends up going kind of linearly.
I mean, it's a little sublinear because of
the log, right.
But basically it's linear.
But it looks like that.
Okay actually, here's the really cool
thing about it.
When it finishes, something really weird
happened.
Everything went away.
It has nothing whatsoever to do with the
dimension,
the number of inequalities comes in as m
up here.
So, it's very simple.
It's just proportional to m and mu, that's
your parameter.
And notice that this does, this predicts,
actually, in some ways,
we're already done.
Right, because what this says now is it
says that the number,
the complexity of incrementing t by fixed
factor mu and
then using Newton's Method to minimize,
doesn't get harder as t gets bigger.
That already says this everything's there
it has nothing to do with t, nothing.
Everything went away.
And it even tells you more.
It tells you that, for
example, if mu were kept small this number
would be very small, right?
It would be like, you know, one.
And there's names for those methods.
You can choose mu so that in fact one
Newton step will suffice.
Right?
That would be even less aggressive, I
don't know if you remember our,
our, our examples, where we had things
that looked like this here.
Right?
So something like that, mu equals 2,
that's pretty aggressive, but if you
had mu equals like 1.05, it would just be
one Newton step per, per iteration, right?
It'd take you a long time, But it will be
one newton step per iteration and
that's actually predicted exactly by this
by this right here.
Right, so
and then it says as mu gets bigger you pay
approximately linearly okay.
So, now you're ready for the final
assembly, because that's our,
incredibly simple and by the way notice
completely explicit bound.
It's not one of these nonsense western
bounds, right, that has all sorts
of constants you don't know, you don't,
you know, you'd never be able to know or
anything like, you could never evaluate,
and it just makes you feel good,
because, oh, but you see it's a polynomial
or something, and then that's good.
Everybody know what I'm talking about?
So this is completely explicit.
It's just, it's a number right there.
I mean whenever gamma's 11, if you do the
fancy analysis, it's more if you don't.
C is six just six period, right five six,
okay.
this, is the number of outer steps.
That's the upper bound on the number of
Newton steps required to do to actually
carry out the centering.
And you get really cool stuff.
This thing starts when mu is near one.
This thing is like quadratic.
Then it accelerates to linear.
That's this term.
This term is really cool.
It's got a 1 over log mu in it, so as mu
gets close to 1,
this thing gets big, and of course, this
thing getting big makes perfect sense.
That says you're going to do a lot of
outer iterations, but
each one is going to be super, duper
cheap.
Right?
So, okay, so, you multiply the two
together, and
you get a function that looks like this.
So that's.
That's what, and this is, I'm evaluating,
I'm using our bound,
which is pretty poor, I think it's 1 over
gamma's 365 or something like that.
And this is for like 100 inequalities and
stuff like that, but
the point is that it actually kind of
gives you, it tells you something.
It says, for example, that you should use
mu equals 1.02.
There you go.
You should increase you should increase
the homotopy parameter by 2% each
step each time.
And this says you'll absolutely do, for
sure, less than 10,000 Newton steps, okay,
right, total.
Right.
Now, we know, I mean, empirically, you're
going to do 20, maybe 30 or 40, right.
So, something's off here.
By the way, if you re-plot.
This using not the upper bound, but in
fact the typical values,
I don't know if you remember that, but you
can just change this value of gamma,
I think you can change it to like one or
something like that.
It turns out if you do that,
you actually start getting predictions
that are completely reasonable.
You get, you should set mu equals 50 or
100 or something like that.
Of course it depends on m and all that
kind of stuff.
So so it actually does predict everything.
But most importantly, it give,
it just gives you a bound that doesn't
depend on anything that you don't know.
You know everything in this bound.
Now the numbers are big, but you know it's
a bound.
Okay.
Now if you go back here, and you look at
this thing, this thing, and
you ask yourself the question, I'll
minimize mu.
Right?
I mean, of course, m is fixed.
Your initial gap, that's m over t0
epsilon, that's, that's something that's,
that's known.
So for a mixed m and
fixed, you know, other thing, the Newton
parameters fix fix gamma and c,
and what you do now is you optimize over
mu, and here's what you get approximately.
It says that mu should be 1 plus 1 over
square root m.
Right?
Now, in practice,
you would never do this, right.
You'd have mu equals 100 or something like
that.
And I'll, in fact, I'll, later I'll tell
you,
in fact, what, you know, how, how this is
really done.
Someone already hinted at it earlier.
Mu is actually adap, I mean, t is actually
adap, mu is adapted every step, right.
But, roughly so, this is if you do that,
and if you work out what happens,
it turns out that the total number of
steps is, it's O of square root m, right?
So this is, and this is sort of the
crowning achievement, right,
of the complexity analysis of interior
point methods.
And this is for the barrier method, but
it's true for every other interior point
method.
It's just O of square root m.
Right whereas as a practical matter its
observed that its actually [INAUDIBLE] and
much more specifically its like 20 to 80
is what the number is.
Okay okay, so that's the, that's sort of
the, the,
the crowing achievement of the complexity
analysis.
Okay.
Now, what's interesting that this number
of course is multiplied by the cost of a,
of a, of a Newton step.
But a Newton step is a least squares
problem, so
you have to solve a least squares problem
every step.
So it's actually quite interesting.
It basically says, so the bottom line is,
if someone says give me the executive
summary, Interior point methods.
You'd say, oh, no problem.
Again, this is a, as a practical matter,
it would be something like this,
you'd say, it can solve a convex problem
with constraints.
It'll take about, some, a few tens of
iterations, each iteration is
solving a least squares problem that
inherits its structure from your problem.
Everybody get that?
So, that's, that's the executive summary.
What's bizarre is that's also true for
a lot of other optimization methods that
we won't look at in this course.
Right.
So
a lot of other methods like operator
splitting and other things.
Same story, same story, right?
It's also kind of interesting because it
puts it all in perspective, right?
It says that after a century or
more of people using least squares and
twiddling weights to make things happen,
you, it says that's basically what an
interior point method is doing.
It's solving 20 least squares problems,
but then it solves an lp or
some complicated other fitting problem you
have, and it did exactly what you wanted.
Right, so, it's an, I think it's a very
interesting observation.
Okay, so our last topic is to generalize
in to your
point methods to we' re just going to
generalize it to generalize inequalities.
Right and you could have guessed that
everything was set up to do this.
Right, so it is actually only one thing we
have to do I'll,
I'll see what that is in a minute.
So everything is setup to, to have kind of
very powerful notation.
So that the notation suggests what we
should do, and
there's only one thing we'll, we'll really
have to do.
So here's a generalized problem and
the difference here is that these
functions return vectors.
And then those, those vectors are not just
less than zero.
They're, well, they're less than zero with
respect to a cone, Ki.
Right?
Now if the cone is like the non-negative
[UNKNOWN], this is a kind of a fancy way
to have ordinary inequalities.
So it's not interesting.
It is very interesting when Ki is
something like, for
a example positive semi definite cone.
Right, because then this, I mean really
that's the most significant example
of a generalized convex problem, right, is
something like semi-definite programming.
Right, so, all right, so, we have to
reinvent everything to work in this case.
Actually, it's going to be shockingly
easy, right.
There's only one, one real thing we have
to do.
Okay so, The main thing we have to do is
to work out what the log is, right?
Because, in fact, what we, I mean, what we
want to do is to,
we want to write down tf0 of x plus sum
minus log minus fi of x, right, that's,
and then we want to say, minimize that.
We're going to call that x star of t, and
then when you minimize that then
t times equal, whoop, then we want to say,
t times equals mu.
Okay, and that's, in fact, we want to run
the exact same algorithm we had before.
And only one minor problem here is that
this makes no sense.
Right, so you'd, you have the logarithm of
a vector.
Okay, so, that's the only thing we have to
do is generalize the log to vectors.
Now, by the way, you can almost guess what
this is going to be.
Like, what do you imagine is the
generalization of
log to positive semi-definite matrices?
I mean, you get three guesses and the
first two don't count.
>> Log det?
>> Yeah, of course, it's log det.
So it's going to turn out to be log det,
so that wasn't so hard.
Now, by the way, for the second order
cone, it's, it's less obvious what it is.
But yeah, it's going to turn out to be our
friend log det, right?
And that's going to be good, because
that's self concordant, and
all sorts of other stuff, so, so if you
were just looking at semi
definite programming, it would be obvious
what, you know, what it would be.
It's log det.
So let's, let's, let's take a look at what
you, what you need to do.
Okay, so you have the idea, you have the
generalized logarithm, and
a generalized logarithm for a cone, it's
something like this.
It says that the domain is the interior of
the cone.
I mean, that's the same as the domain of
log is r plus plus, right?
It's positive numbers.
Well, the domain of log det capital X is
positive is,
is S plus, is Sn sub plus plus, right?
A set of definite positive matrices,
right?
So it's the same.
And, let's see.
This says, well, it's concave, right?
So we're going to require it to be
concave, like log, right?
We'll say a little bit more about that in
a minute.
And that's, that's the idea.
So, so it has to, the domain is exactly
the interior of the cone just like log.
Okay, and then here's the interesting
one.along any line it has to be the log.
So it has to look, if you restrict to a
line it looks like a log.
that essentially exactly what happens for
log det, right?
If you restrict it to a line, that's a
line going through the origin.
It actually looks like the log.
It's exactly the log.
So, okay, so it has to have the following
form.
If you scale it, it's an additive term.
But there's a coefficient in front called
theta.
That's actually going to play a big role.
It's called the degree of the, of the
logarithm.
And we'll see what's going to be obvious
things.
So here's the non-negative orthant, just
to make sure this all makes sense.
[COUGH] And here we take the logarithm on
the non-negative orthant is
the sum of the logs.
I mean this is kind of dumb, but fine.
And then you check that if I, if I scale a
vector, right, what happens?
If I scale a vector, I scale every
component.
And so what happens is basically what,
what comes out is theta, if I scale by s,
what comes out is n log s, because each of
these contributes a that e,
well, you add something which is log s,
and then you get n times it.
So the degree is n.
By the way, there's a beautiful
interpretation of what degree is.
It actually, it,
has to do with the geometry Of the set,
and it's the maximum num,
it's something like the maximum number of
scalar constraints that are active.
We're not going to look into this here,
but and that's true for
the non-negative orthant, when you get
down to the 0.0 you've got like
n planes coming in, and that's why theta
is n.
Okay.
For the positive semi definite cone,
we take log det and sure enough,
everything works there.
The theta is n.
that, that's a surprising theta,
because the dimension of the positive
definite cone is nn plus 1 over 2.
So if you really call that n.
I mean, if you call that n, then basically
it says data is square root n.
For second-order cone this is the,
the log, the logarithm for a second-order
cone, is actually interesting.
It's this.
It's actually the log of, and then you
simply form this quadratic form.
What's a bit shocking about this and would
kind of make you nervous,
it takes you a while to get used to this a
bit more spsoticated is the following.
This is a quadratic form.
That's a quadratic form.
What's the signature of a quadratic form?
Is it positive semi-definite, negative
semi-definite, what is it?
Convex?
Concave?
You should be able to see it.
Just look right at it.
It's diagonal.
And what, what's the diagonal matrix look
like?
It's got a bunch of minus 1s, and how
about the last entry?
It's plus 1.
So, this is a quadratic form.
But it's not concave.
It's not convex.
'Kay, so this doesn't, everyone See what
I'm saying here?
So you have to get used to this.
This is right.
so, and the low, but the log of that, is
actually concave.
Okay?
So this this is one of
those small subtleties, it's, but it's
actually worth knowing.
This is it, it's not, this is, this is not
obvious here.
And by the way that definitely does not
come from one of
your composition rules, right.
Because you're, because,
because the argument to log here is
neither convex nor concave.
Right, so this comes from the structure of
this particular thing.
Okay, so that.
And actually if you look at it, it's
actually really cool what it represents.
It, that represents the margin in the
second-order cone, right?
Because second-order cone says that the
sum of these things is less than that.
And so this is the margin.
It's how, in fact, probably it's close to
a distance to
how far you are from the boundary if this
is the second-order cone.
Going up like this.
This is probably something like the
distance.
I mean, you might normalize it or
something like that, but that's what it
is.
Okay.
Everybody, got this.
So, that, that's the idea.
And the log of that is concave and
satisfies this and its degree is two.
Period.
Okay.
Okay, so here's some properties.
And these are, some of these are easy.
Most of them are, actually, they're pretty
easy to show.
First is the generalized logarithm is, is
actually monotone.
Right, so, monotone, if you remember,
means that if one thing is bigger than
another Then the function value of
the first is bigger than the function
value of the second.
log is obviously monotone right?
So, but in fact to express that in terms
of the derivative,
it's that the gradient should be
non-negative in the dual inequality.
Right?
So just to that's what it is.
So this says it's monotone.
And what this says is that y transpose
times the the gradient is just theta.
It's constant, right?
That follows from this log thing and the
homogeni, that homogeneity property.
So for non-negative orthan, the gradient
is that.
It's monotone.
Here.
and, I mean, this is, this is always
positive.
Here, in the dual inequality which is the
same as our plus to the M And, and
you get exactly that.
Y transpose this is just n.
For positive semi-definite cone, the
gradient is, I mean, with some conventions
about how you represent the gradient of a
matrix, the gradient is the inverse.
Right?
That, well,
I mean actually that's kind of the analog
of log.
Derivative log is one over, so for
log debt it should, by aesthetics, be
something like one over.
So it's the inverse.
You have to be very careful as to what
exactly you mean by this though, but.
So that's what it is.
So the gradient of log det is the inverse.
The inner product right of y in the
gradient, well the inner product of
two matrices the natural inner product is
trace of the product.
And guess what trace of y times the
inverse is n, right?
Which is theta.
Okay?
So, for the second order cone, the
gradient looks like.
That, that's the gradient.
And so that's, that's the gradient, and in
fact,
if you work out y transpose times the
gradient of y, you get 2.
Okay?
So this is the, the idea.
These, these are the main logarithms we're
going to use.
There are actually some exotic other
logarithms for other sets that people use,
and it, it's, although they, they give
better complexity results in some cases,
it's not at all clear that they have any
use in practice, I mean, any,
to give any advantage at all.
Okay.
Now we can form, now we can continue this,
the analogy.
So, we're going to first talk about the
logarithmic barrier for
a set of generalized inequalities.
It's the same thing.
You simply form minus sum log minus i.
By the way if these cones were all the
same, or we could even write this as log
sum i, that would be very cool, overloaded
notation, right, very evolved notation.
Right?
Because if you, in fact, you could even
write, just log there, so
it would look exactly the same as for the
scale, as for
the scalar inequality case, right, and
then it would be overloaded.
Meaning log has a different meaning
depending on the type of its argument.
If it's scalar, it's your old friend, log,
and if it's something in a cone, it refers
unambiguously to some logarithmic some
generalized logarithm for that cone.
Right, so for example, log of a matrix
would then be interpreted as log det.
So anyway, that's what this is.
That's just a barrier function.
It's convex.
Why is it convex?
Well, I mean, again, you needed all those
properties.
You use the following.
These things are concave, and they're
increasing.
That's convex.
So this thing,
here, is actually by the composition rule,
that's actually going to be concave.
Sum is concave, minus turns it to convex.
Okay?
It's just the same as before.
It's the same reason minus sum log minus
fi is convex in x, 'kay?
So the central path is then simply this.
It is the set of minimizers of tf0 plus Fi
of X subject to X equals b.
That's the central path.
So it's identical, right.
It's the same thing and properly
generalizes, right, that if, if all the,
if these were all simply r plus then this
would reduce to what we have already seen.
Okay.
Well then, let's, everything else just
works, right, so
if you write down what it means to
minimize this thing, well, that's simple.
It says that the gradient of this plus nu
times,
here, h plus A transpose nu is 0 and Ax
equals b.
Those are the kkt conditions.
And so you get something like that.
Not, I called it w, not nu.
Okay, so this is the condition.
It's a bit harder, but
you stare at it for a while, and you get
something pretty cool here.
What you realize, and you divide by t, and
then what you
realize is that you take lambda i star and
that's going to be this thing.
But remember we have the following
property,
the gradient of the generalized logarithm
is dual positive.
Right, that's the same as saying for a
log, right it's derivative is, is
dual positive, but that's silly, because
it is the dual of r plus is r plus, right.
So you, and here we are using the fact
that it's dual positive here.
Okay?
And then what this says is that if you
minimize, if you center here,
then basically, it says that you minimize
this Lagrangian here,
where lambda star is this thing, nu star
is that,
that's identical to the other case, and
you work out the duality gap.
And, you get the same to end up taking the
gradient of this
transpose this thing and you know what you
get, you get the sum of the thetas.
So, it's just, and as the calculation's
identical and you get this.
What's really cool about this is, so
this is the analogue of' m over t that
you've have seen up till now for
the scalar inequality case and in fact the
scalar inequality case is a simple case,
you just say [COUGH] that you're, you have
a problem, you have Fi less than zero, but
that's a scalar, then you'd say well
,we'll,
the generalize logarithm will uses the
logarithm and it has degree one.
And so, you sum up 1 m times and you get m
over t.
So, what it says is that this is what
plays the role of the,
what was m over t and in fact it's really
cool it says sum of theta you,
you can even think of that is something
like as the effective number of
scaler constraints that's a excellent way
to think of what theta means.
Okay, so, so from now on an lmi roughly
speaking counts as n scalar inequalities.
A second order cones, counts as 2, right?
A scalar inequality is 1.
Everybody see this?
So, you could actually then take a
problem, a cone problem, and
say this has 237 effective scalar
inequalities.
That's simply the number here that plays
the role of what's just m in, for
example, all the inequalities were scalar.
Okay?
Everybody got this.
So it's kind of, it's actually cool.
Okay, so we get two semi-definite
programs.
So here, I mean this is the most important
case.
So here is one in inequality form.
We're going to minimize c transpose x,
subject to f of x is less than or
equal to 0.
The logarithmic barrier is log det of
minus F of x inverse.
Right, so the inverse is the same as
putting a minus in front of log det here.
The central path is it, to get x star of
t,
you minimize t times the objective plus
this thing.
And, if you take the gradient of that you
get here, tci minus,
this is the partial derivative with
respect to xi.
And, this thing is, well, the gradient of
this is like minus f of x inverse.
Right?
And then you would, if you want to know
what is like partial f,
partial xi, this is very rough, but that's
fi.
And so you'd put trace fi times this, and
you get this, this, this inequality here,
this equality here.
Right.
So that, that's the optimality condition.
You get a dual feasible point, because
this thing here if I multiply
by minus 1 over t that's dual feasible and
I get to a point Z that satisfies that.
This is the inequality form STP and the
dual is the equality form here and
I, if I simply minimize this function
using like Newton method.
I get now a, a dual feasible point.
And the duality gap is, it's really cool.
You just work out what it is.
That's the, that's the dual objective,
primal objective.
You subtract them.
That gives you the duality gap, and that
turns out to be
just using this formula here, P over T
where P is the size of the lmi.
Right, so, that's it.
So, I mean, these are yeah, it's kind of,
I mean, this stuff,
I guess it's been well-known for maybe 15
years now, 20, or something like that.
But 20 years ago, not that many people
knew about this kind of stuff.
And a lotta people didn't.
So now we have the barrier method.
Here's a hint.
It's identical.
And so it's exactly the same.
There's only one change.
I mean, what's happening is different.
The only difference is that this used to
be m and now it's theta i.
Right, so, that's, that's all it is is the
sum of the orders.
So otherwise it's absolutely identical to
the other barrier method.
And of course it was set up that way.
Right, so that it would work out.
It didn't just happen.
And that's it.
And the number of outer iterations is the
same except that instead of m, you have,
of course, the sum i over theta i.
And, actually all this, all the complexity
analysis holds immediately.
The, it all just works.
It's, it's all exactly the same.
Right, so you have polynomial time,
complexity for
solving STPs and things like that.
Okay, so let's look at some examples.
now, when you look at these your first
impression is that it's the wrong
figure that's been included, because it
looks exactly like the other one.
Right?
So but it's, it's not, I mean, it's not.
I mean they are, these things all do look
the same, right?
So I guess that's good.
So it means its it's exactly the same,
these plots look the same,
this looks the same.
By the way, this would also up here start
going up, like that, right?
So, they look the same.
As for example LP.
So that, actually, so it's a, a very nice
set of generalizations and
overloadings of meaning and things like
that, because it's not just that the code,
if it was written nicely, would look
identical.
It's more than that, actually the way it
all works would be the same.
In fact, even the empirical the way it
would work empirically would be the same.
So let's just take a look at one of these.
Here is a semi-definite program with 100
variables and, and
a single LMI constraint in, in, with 100
by 100 matrices.
Right, so if you want to picture something
like that, you're bounding some covariance
or something matrix or something like that
with a 100 variables or something.
It's not an, it's, it's not a simple
problem.
It's one that 25 years ago absolutely no
one would have any idea it could be solved
by any method, right, let alone by
something like 20 steps.
Of some quite simple method that's
probably only like 15 lines or
something like that.
so, it, it's quite a complicated problem.
And hear you can that you are actually,
these, with this very
simple barrier method, you're solving
things in like 20, 30 steps.
Right?
So real methods would do it in 20 or
18 or something like that.
Each step is solving a Newton system.
Any guesses, just for fun just to, just to
see what
the complexity of a, the computational
complexity of a Newton step is here?
Turns out it's the end of the fourth.
That's still pretty good, though, right,
for a, for a semi-definite program.
It's end of the fourth.
It turns out that it's actually not
solving the Newton system,
which is order n cubed.
It's actually assembling the Hessian in
the general case costs n to the 4th.
So, that's, that, that actually what the
complication complexity is.
That's still quite good, right?
Does it, it could have been, like the dual
has,
whatever 5000 variables that would be into
the 6th, or something.
So you'd have n squared variables, and
then you apply Newton's method to that,
you get n to the 6.
Right, so, okay.
So anyway, so these are, this is all like
it's very impressive that the stuff works.
So here is a family of SDPs, it's like the
family of LPs.
And for each of these you saw that's
actually very specific SDP.
But for each of these, you solve 100
random instances and
actually, it's not at all clear what
happened out here to 1000,
but I guess it suggests that it, it's
being reported honestly.
But it's, probably that's some numerical
issue or something like that,
but, you, it'd be nicer if it just looked
like, like it did for the LPs and kind of
just go like this, right, that, that would
be the, that would be better, right?
So.
Okay, so it's the same sort of thing.
I, I should say that SDP is still kind of
an an op,
it's, no one has, I, it's not completely
nailed yet, how to solve SDPs.
it, there are plenty of sort of SDP
solvers,
there are all sorts of special ones for
different structures and things like that.
People solve very big ones.
For example, people who work on
combinatorial optimization you need to
do STP bounds, they solve big ones but
there has not emerged what you have for
things like LP and SOCP which are simply,
kind of the best methods that just work.
This has not emerged.
So it's something people have been looking
at for maybe 20 years now and
it'd be really good if someone to, were to
like, figure out good, universal methods.
So.
That was a hint, or a suggestion, a plea?
One of, one of those.
So okay.
So the last thing I want to talk about
today.
Our primal dual in interior point methods,
right?
So, in fact, the barrier method is not
really used.
Actually it is, in a few weird places,
right?
And in fact, it's even simpler.
A barrier method with a fixed value of t
is used in a few real time things, right,
where you don't need high res, high
resolution, and
you just use Newton's method to solve
something like that.
But generally speaking, people don't do
this.
What they really do is they don't even
distinguish between inner and
outer iterations.
It's equivalent to changing, another way
to say it is you change t every step
of every, for every, you do, every one is
a Newton step.
And you change t every single time.
Instead of, you know, we go like eight
steps, satisfy a convergence criterion,
then it's, you know, t times equals mu.
And in fact the way real ones work is they
do a little bit of work to
update t every single step, right?
So that's one way.
And they also.
But however each step, always nothing but
solving a set of linearized KKT.
So the questions look like basically
identical.
And they use infeasible start.
Infeasible start Newton type things.
So you start, you don't have a phase one
and phase two.
So these are kind of the standard,
standard methods.
But the cost per iteration is identical to
the barrier method and things like that.
So they're not, they would have kind of
some minor advantages, but
not, not, not huge, huge big advantages.