And let me first say a little bit about
how all this,
how everything fits together, how all, all
the computational stuff fits together.
So we, one way to view it, is you start
with this.
You start with solving quadratic equations
with linear equality constraints.
How do you minimize a quadratic with
linear equality constraints?
What does it reduce to?
Is linear equations, right?
And then, and we know how to solve linear
equations.
Actually we know quite a lot about how to
solve linear equations, okay?
Alright, so that's like done, right?
Well one way to view Newton's method is
this.
I ask you to minimize a smooth function
subject to equality constraints.
And what it effectively does, if you look
above, if you look at, say,
what is Newton's method doing, you can
even write it.
So it was clear.
This is what it's doing.
The answer is it's solving a small, a
sequence,
a short sequence of, quadratic equality
constraint minimization problems, right?
I mean, maybe, I mean if you were to
profile Newton's method,
what you'd find is it's solving linear
equations.
But the linear equations it's solving are
actually solving a quad,
a equality constraint quadratic
minimization problem, right?
So then you can say, well we have now
extended, we, we can now solve smooth
equality constraint problems by reducing
that to solving a sequence, right?
In fact, not a long sequence, right?
But a sequence of quadratic equality
constraint problems,
which in turn are linear algebra.
Everybody got this?
Well, guess what.
Now we're going to go to inequality
constrained problems and
here's just how we're going to do it.
We're going to take an inequality
constrained problem and we're going to
reduce that to solving a short sequence of
smooth minimization problems, okay?
So now you have a stack, right?
And the stack will look like this.
You have an inequality constrained
problem.
You will solve it by solving a 10, 20,
[INAUDIBLE] the number doesn't matter,
right?
But it's not like a gigantic number,
You're going to solve 10, 20 smooth
minimization problems.
How are you going to solve those?
Each of those is going to be reduced to
solving,
again, a modest number of quadratic
equality problems.
Everybody got this?
And solving a quadratic equality problem
that's actually something we have
an actual method for.
Its called Linear Algebra.
Everybody so this is the whole big, this
is the full big picture.
Actually, if you wanted, you could put
something on top.
And the on top would be the kind of stuff
that CVX does.
That, that takes your original problem,
which you
may have all sorts of non-differntiable
functions and things like that.
And automatically does the transforms to a
problem which you can handle.
That has, for example, smooth constraints
and smooth objective, right?
So, for example, converts your problem to
an LP and in LP all your objectives and
your constraints are smooth.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
And now you see the entire stack.
Right, that's, that's it, that's the whole
stack, okay?
So, okay, so that's the big picture and
that's what we're going to do today or
part of today.
Alright, so, we're going to start with
this problem, inequality constrained.
And you know, the,
the equality constrained is just going to
float along everywhere we go.
And you can almost ignore them.
And it's even, when I look at examples,
I'll probably ignore the Ax is equals b.
But it just floats along and, and it
doesn't really hurt anybody.
Besides we can handle it, right?
In fact, it's the Ax equals b that
persists at
all levels of the stack, right?
When you go down the Newton's method its
just linear equations, right?
Each generation in Newton's method it, it
fills in a row of a [INAUDIBLE] linear.
So linear or an other way to say it is if
you write the,
if you write the linearized me, method on.
That when you have Ax equals b and
you call that method on Ax equals b, very
simple just returns itself, okay?
So, and that persists all the way to the
bottom of the stack.
Okay, so, we're going to make, we'll make
some assumptions.
We'll assume that A is is full rank,
right?
So, we don't have a redundant quality
constraints.
And we'll assume that there's a, there's a
solution, right?
That there is an X that satisfies this.
And we'll assume strict feasibility.
I mean, you don't even need a lot of this
stuff.
But, just, does your sledgehammer
assumptions.
And by the way, this is the, this is the,
I mean this is.
So, this is actually the slater condition,
essentially here.
You don't need any slater condition for
quality constraints right?
Because the reduced slate, the modified
slater condition says you
can ignore actually, equality, linear
equality constraints.
So, let's say, we kind of, equality
constraints you can have and
linear inequality constraints.
So we ignore those entirely.
And this says simply that, that the o,
that the domain the interior of the domain
actually intersects.
Well, the, I'm sorry,
the domain is open, because we're assuming
they're differentiable, right?
So, but, so says the domain intersects the
equality constraint.
And, and this says things like strong
duality holds and, and
the dual optimism is obtained.
Okay, so what are examples?
Well, linear programs, quadratic programs,
QCQPs geometric programs, right?
Geometric programs all the functions are
things like log sum x.
Entropy maximization.
So, you say, you want to maximize entropy,
you get something like this, right?
So, that's a problem, looks like that.
That's asking to maximize entropy,
you're minimizing negative entropy, and Fx
less than g and Ax equals B.
You can even interpret, you can interpret
x, say, as as a probability vector.
It doesn't have to be normalized here, but
assuming it were,
this says please find me the maximum
entropy distribution.
That, matches certain expectations
exactly.
And satisfies inequalities on other,
expectations.
That's, that's, that's what this problem
is, that's one way to interpret it.
Okay, and this, this'll work, this is
fine.
oh, as I said, you may use one of the
transformations.
The kind of ones that CVX would use to
take a problem with non
differentiable objectives, constraints.
And transform it, in fact in a completely
mechanical way
to a problem that doesn't have, that were
all the constraints are smooth.
Like for example, you transform it to a
SOCP or to an LP, right?
Okay, now, CON programs things like SDP's
and
SOCPs these are actually better handled as
problems with generalized inequalities.
Although they will work here too, provided
you express them in a smooth way.
That's actually there's some really cool,
smooth ways to write down STP's for
example.
We've already seen the logged barrier,
but the key is to start with your original
problem and do something really weird.
It's this, were going to take the
inequality constraints and
were going to put them in the objective.
And what we're going to do is were going
to take i minus,
that is the indicator function of r minus.
So that's a function that looks like this.
It's zero and then it goes to plus
infinity if you go positive, okay?
And that simply says, it, it says that you
take fi of x and
if it's less than zero this returns zero.
And if it is positive it returns plus
infinity.
Plus infinity in an objective is basically
saying it's infinitely bad.
We just say is unacceptable, right?
So this is the, the right, that's the
idea, okay?
So, now you can't apply Newton's method to
this,
directly, because the this is like big
time non-differentiable right?
because you've got this thing that goes
like up to plus infinity, okay?
So so what we're going to do instead,
is we're going to make a surrogate that's
smooth okay?
And the surrogate's that smooth is the log
barrier, so
you'll form 1 over t, minus log, minus f.
These are functions that look
like this These are functions that look
like this, okay?
They, they look just like that, right?
These are, and these are increasing, so
this, this one that hugs this,
the true function closer is with a higher
t, higher value of t, okay?
So, now, this one, that problem, that's
Newton ready, right?
That's ready for Newton with equality
constraints, because it's smooth, right?
And not only that,
at least visually, the approximation
improves as t goes to infinity.
So, it looks like we have something that
will do the right thing.
Everybody got this?
Now, before we go any farther, I want to
point out,
when people tell stories like this, you
should be deeply skeptical.
Because usually stuff like this doesn't
work, right?
This is like, you're sitting there and you
come along, and it's not working and
someone says, what's wrong.
You say, well, I can't solve Ax equals b.
And the person says, well why?
And you say, well that's because my matrix
A is singular.
And you go, oh, well, gee, that's too bad.
And then you say, what does it represent?
Say, oh, it's a measurement apparatus,
something like that.
And you say, oh, is it that apparatus on
the desk over there?
And you go, yeah, give me a hammer.
And you just tap the desk next to it.
And you say, A is now non-singular.
Everyone understand what I just said?
Right?
So, because if you take it, if you take a,
a singular matrix, and you purtur, if you
take a random perturbation,
in fact, take any entry, generically.
Take the six, seven entry.
And add 1e minus 19 to it and
with the probability of one the matrix is
now non-singular.
Everybody following this, right?
Okay, so the question is does that solve
the problem?
The answer is well no, of course it
doesn't solve the problem.
The matrix is now non-singular, but it
still has a condition number.
It has a condition number of like 10 to
the 19th.
So all of the problems you were going to
have.
when it had a condition number, infinity
are still there.
Everybody following this?
Right?
So people who just come along and
like perturb your problem.
So look at this, someone says, I want to
solve a problem.
That's my true, this is my true irritation
function here.
It express how I feel about each fi.
I mean, it, it expresses the semantics of
hard constraint.
It says, if fi is negative or zero, I'm
just totally cool with it.
To, totally cool, right?
It's neutral, it means nothing to me.
But if it's 1e minus, you know, minus 19,
that's completely unacceptable.
That's what the semantics is, right?
When someone says, oh yeah, no problem,
give me some sandpaper.
I'll just go down to this corner down
here, and I'll just sand it off.
I'll start with some number 80 sandpaper,
I'll, then I'll go to 120 and
some 400, and, you know, everybody know
what I'm saying, right?
So you sand it off, and someone say, what
did you just do?
And you go, oh yeah, your function's now
differentiable.
And it's no different from, I mean, for
all practical purposes same as what you
had before.
Everybody, following this?
And you go, go ahead.
Let, let's apply your Newton method on it.
Tech, technically that's correct, isn't
it?
I mean, if you take something that looks
like that, if I sand the bottom off.
I have to sand the sides a little bit,
too, to make it a barrier, right?
I mean, actually this does it effectively
right here.
I don't have to use sandpaper.
It's just, I just use, I, I use 1 over t.
I take t equals 10 to the 9.
Everybody following this?
Okay, and what's the problem with that?
Like the guy who bangs the hammer next to
the you know sensor suite,
what, what's the problem with this?
Why can't it, why aren't we just done here
or why should you be deeply skeptical?
So your suspicious is though it's actually
true, that if I take,
t equals 10 to the 9, I get a pretty good
approximation of i minus, right.
One, one could even argue, is, is close
enough for for any practical purpose.
That, that, that's actually true.
But the problem is that, that function is
actually just about the worst thing in
the world for Newton's method, right?
Because it, because it's not close to
quadratic or
another way to say it is its third
derivative is big, right?
Or it's nonquadratic.
I mean,or it, or it's, here's another one,
its second derivative changes wildly when
you get near the barrier, right?
And that's another way,
of course, of saying the third derivative
is big or something, right?
So, so that says Newton's method will
work,
and it will take ten to the nine steps,
okay?
Everybody following this?
Alright, so I'm just saying,
you should be very skeptical about things
like this, right?
because it just doesn't, when, usually
when someone walks up to you and
you say you're having a problem.
And they say, oh no problem, we'll just
appro, we'll just smooth this,
we'll just sand this thing off, and now
it's differentiable.
And, and then they walk away, you should
be suspicious.
I want to say that, we have seen this
story,
you have seen this story before, in a
different context.
And, so let me tell you the context you
saw it in.
It was this.
This is the function that really captures
how we care about constraints.
It's this thing here, right?
But do you remember what happens in
Lagrange duality?
You approximate this function by this,
right?
And the slope there is lambda I, okay?
Now, the point is, nobody would be tempted
to look at that and
say, yeah, that's a pretty good
approximation, right?
So, but, the shock was, that Lagrange's
duality kind of worked in some sense.
That, that an approximation, this bad of
this thing actually yielded something.
But, at a high level, it's the same thing.
The same, or, the same story is behind
LaGrange duality, as behind,
well, the logarithmic barrier, right?
because it, the story starts this way.
This is what you care about, this thing.
And then you say, let's replace it with
something.
In Lagrange Duality you replace it with
something that's linear.
And people say wow, that is a crappy
approximation.
You go yeah, but I'm leaving open the
following possibility I can change,
I can wiggle the lambdas, right?
That's, that's, that's the secret in
Lagrange Duality, right?
What was weird is Lagrange Duality ended
up
having like a really good ending, right?
So, you can, this is, all I'm saying is,
the story is the same.
Here, instead of saying,
we're going to replace it with, with a
linear thing and wiggle with the slope.
We're actually going to replace it with
something that actually plausibly is, or
might be and actual approximation of this
function.
So, by the way,
all these hints, the duality is going to
pop right out of what we're doing.
And you shouldn't be surprised because the
story start the same way.
In fact, at an abstract enough level, the
stories are exactly the same.
You replace the true irritation function,
which is this thing, with some kind of
smooth approximation.
In, in Lagrange duality, it's the
smoothest thing you can get, it's a line.
Here, it's some log variant.
Okay, alright.
So, let's look at the log barrier
function.
Well it's convex and we know that.
And it's derivatives.
Let's work out what these are, right?
So the gradient of this [SOUND] is,
well the gradient of, of minus log minus f
is this thing, right?
And remember fi of x is negative, so
that's,
this is a posi, whenever you see minus fi
of x it's a positive number, okay?
So this says, this says that the gradient
of the log barrier is a positive
scaled sum of the gradients of the
functions, remember that.
That's going to come up.
That's what it is, right?
Oh, and what are the scale factors?
Depends on how close you are, how tight
that, what margin you have.
That's the margin.
Minus fi is the margin in the inequality,
one fi less than zero.
It's minus 0.2 your margin is 0.2, right?
If I can increase 0.2 before your
infeasible.
Everybody got this?
So that's the, so this is one over the
margin.
So the scale factors in front are the one
over the margins, okay?
And the Hessian looks like this.
That's just for reference, because we're
not actually going to use that but just so
you know what it is, right?
By the way, you see here, I set up rank
one terms and
then the actual, the sum of the Hessians.
Okay, alright.
So, if I take a problem And I minimize,
here.
By the way, we had, to draw the picture,
we were minimizing F0 plus phi of X.
That's the same thing as minimizing tf0
plus phi.
Why do we do that?
It's, because the self concordant stuff
will work out later, better, or something.
But it doesn't matter, I mean, in fact
most people put the one over t there.
And by the way, they call it kappa too.
So, it doesn't matter.
You'd figure these things out.
okay, so this says we're going to minimize
tf0 plus phi, subject to Ax equals b.
That's, we're totally ready for Newton
here.
So we know exactly how to compute that.
Not a problem, right?
Now, we do expect that when t gets
gigantic you know.
This is Newton's going to have some
trouble.
We'll get to that.
Okay, so this thing, it turns out you can
show that the log barrier
is strictly convex, as long as the
feasible set is bounded, right?
And, and we're going to just assume that,
the feasible set is bounded.
And then, that says that the log barrier
is strictly convex.
So that, this is a unique point.
And in fact, if you minimize this, that's
called x star of t.
And it's a path, right?
Because for each t, you get a minimizer,
right?
And its called, that's called the central
path, the path of central point or
something like that, that's a central
path.
And so, the picture would look something
like this.
We start with an LP you know here's one
inequality two,
three, four, five, six some whatever it
is, six inequalities.
And these dash curves show you the level
sets of, of, of the barrier, right?
And then it goes up to plus infinity, so
you should be visualizing that.
That the barrier goes up to plus infinity
at the boundaries, okay?
And then, what we're doing is we're adding
we're adding t times c to the, to the
point, and minimizing.
And so that's sort of the analytic center.
That's the point that actually, the
analytic center maximize, minimizes
the sum of the negative log margins that
maximizes the product of the margin.
So it's a point deep inside the set.
That's the analytic center, so it starts
here with equals zero.
And then, as you crank up, as you crank
up,
the scale factor in front of the c, it
says, minimize the barrier function.
But also start putting a strong, now it
says start minimizing t times c,
c is the actual, c transposed x.
C transpose X is the actual objective you
wanted to minimize, right?
So, so what happens is very interesting.
Oh, what happens is the more you crank up
t, the closer you come to
minimizing c transpose x, but you will
never leave the feasible region, right?
In fact, you'll never leave the strictly
feasible region.
The reason is, the barrier, which is, by
the way,
this is why it's called a barrier the
barrier goes up to plus infinity.
And no matter how big t is you'll move in
the direction minus c, minus c.
But at some point, you'll get to the point
where it's no longer worth it
to get closer to the boundary and you'll
stop.
Everybody got this?
So the central path might look like that
and
it's kind of silly, because it's an lp of
two variables or something.
But anyway that's, that's what the central
path looks like here.
Okay, and that's the that's the idea,
okay?
So that's a simple [INAUDIBLE].
Now, it turns out, if you're on the
central path surprise, surprise.
You get, for free, dual, dual points for
the original problem.
So let's see how that works.
If you're on the central path, it means
you minimize tf0 plus sum,
minus log, minus fi of x.
So you minimize this thing.
And lets take the gradient of that right
now, well you get t grad f,
f0, and then you get the derivative of
this.
I'm going to ignore the second term which
is the the equality constraint Lagrange
multiplier part.
That's this thing.
I mean that just works.
And this thing, the gradient of that is
this thing right here.
Now you stare at that for a minute and you
realize, mm-hm, that's interesting.
It's, in fact the first thing we're
going to do just for
fun, is we're going to, take this t and
put it back over here.
You know frankly, it probably should have
been there anyway, right?
So we're going to get rid of that t and
we're going to divide this by t as well,
okay?
Okay, like that.
That's what we're going to do.
And now you look at this, and you say, hey
that's interesting.
On the central path, here's,
when you compute a point on the central
path, strangely, you have the following.
You have the gradient plus a nonnegative
weighted sum of the gradient.
This is the gradient of the objective,
plus a nonnegative weighted sum of the
gradients of the constraint functions.
And then plus A transpose times an
equality constraint dual
variable that's zero.
That should sound familiar, because guess
what?
That's actually Lagrange duality.
Because look at this, it says that if you
formed, if we take
these numbers here to be the lambdas and
we take this to be nu here.
Then this thing reads grad f of 0 plus
sum,
lambda I, grad f of i plus A transport nu
equals 0.
But the first, this first term is exactly
the gradient of this,
with respect to x right?
So, that's what it says,
so this says something amazing this says
that if you compute a central point.
Whether you like it or not what pops out,
are dual variables, okay?
Now, remember that in, you know,
a lot of cases it's not easy to find dual
variables, right?
I mean if you take like an LP which works
here, right?
Most, you can't just pick some positive
vector and some other vector.
I mean, there's equality constraints that
have to hold.
It's like a transpose lambda plus c equals
0.
So the fact is that, if you just pick a
lambda in an LP,
it's not going to be dual feasible.
Or another way to say it is, you would say
here's my positive lambda and my new.
Please tell me my lower bound and it will
come back and
go, I got a lower bound for you, it's
minus infinity.
Which is, which is the universal lower
bound, right?
You don't even have to hear the question
before you can give that as
a lower bound, right?
So, so, what's it, so
it's not trivial to say that, to find dual
feasible points or anything like that.
But this does it, right?
Any point on the central path gives you a
dual feasible point.
Well, if you have a dual feasible point,
you should have a strong urge to do the
following.
If you have a dual feasible point,
you should think, that gives me a lower
bound on the optimal value of the problem.
So let's evaluate the lower bound.
Let's find out what is, so let's do that.
Well, so we'll take this, this dual
feasible pair and let's,
let's work, it says simply that that's
dual feasible.
Well, I mean, this is true even if it's
not dual feasible.
Dual feasible means that this thing is
bigger than minus infinity and
therefore non-trivial, right?
So, let's work out what g is.
Well, it's just L evaluated at these
points.
But that's, that's f0 of x star of t.
And then plus some lambda i star f i.
But lambda i star is actually 1 over fi of
x star times t.
They cancel.
This is just M over T.
It's nothing more, right?
And so you get this, and it's actually
extraordinary.
This, that's G.
And the duality gap, x, x star, is of
course strictly primal feasible, right?
And it's got the value, f0 of x star.
But it says that when you center,
if you do analytical centering you get two
things.
You get a point which has a objective
value of f0 of x star of t.
But you also get dual variables that
certify
that this number is a lower bound on the
optimal value.
And the, the gap, people call that the
duality gap, is exactly m over t, okay?
Everybody, it's crazy.
I mean, it's just arithmetic here.
I mean, not arithmetic, it's, it's
completely true.
There's nothing complicated here, right?
Just take some derivatives, make a few
observations, and that's it.
So that says, if you minimize t f0
plus this log barrier of x subject to a x
equals b.
Then it says two things will come, you
will, when you write the Newton method or
whatever from that.
They'll be two return things, an x which
is strictly feasible and
a du, and a pair of dual feasible vectors,
lambda and nu.
And the associated gap between the upper
bound on the objective which is that f
of x 0, f0 of f star, and the gap which is
g of lambda star, nu star.
The difference between those two will be
exactly m over t, okay?
So, that's cool, by the way, what this
says is, we now know that this
kind of hand waving intuition about, you
know, we, we looked at this.
We looked at this thing and I look at this
and I said, oh hey, look at that if t gets
bigger, you'll get a better approximation
to the true thing we care about, right?
And I said, so, I mean that sounds
reasonable,
if we take t big, we'll get close to the
original problem, right?
So, that's all hand waving and this, I can
make up other stories like that and
they're totally wrong.
This means it actually completely correct
and it's very specific.
It said that if you calculate x star of t,
that is, so, you minimize this func,
you minimize this objective subject to
that equality constraint.
Which we know how to do using Newton's
method.
Then it say's the following.
It say's if you do that then you will have
computed a solution to
the original problem.
Which is at most m over t sub-optimal.
Everybody got that?
Obviously now, if t goes to as, as t gets
bigger, you're done.
So, couple more interpretations.
This actually probably the dominant,
modern interpretation.
So the modern interpretation of, of if you
look at interior point method,
if you go, you know, pull some book or
something like that.
I don't know, but, the, this is the way
the story would go, they would say, here
are the equal, here are the KKT conditions
for an equality constrained problem.
Well, you better have that, that, that's
primal feasibility, right?
You have to have this, right?
That, that's another one.
and, you have to have the following, here.
You have to add compliment,
complementarity and that says this, right?
That's equal to zero so i equals 1 to m.
And this says that for
each constraint, either the Lagrange
multiplier is zero, right?
Would and that would that must occur if
that constraint is has margin,
like if fi is actually negative, right?
Then the LeGrange Multiplier has to be 0.
And you know that from many, many reasons,
right?
Or, that, if the LeGrange Multiplier is
positive, the only other option,
it says that constraint must be tight and
tight means fi is 0.
So this is complimentary slackness, I
think it,
it was, yeah, it's complimentary or
complimentary slackness, okay?
So and we look at this and then you have
to have this, right?
And so, here's what's is really cool,
when you center with parameter t, here's
what you get.
You get something, you get an x, x star of
t that satisfies this,
as a matter of fact it satisfies the fi of
x is strictly less than 0, right?
Because you're minimizing the sum of the
minus logs, and
blah, blah, blah, right, 'kay?
So you get this, even with a little
margin.
You get a lambda that's strictly positive.
Because it's real, it's like, I forget
what it is,
it's mi, it's one over t times minus fi.
And the fi's, well, okay, that's never 0.
Okay, so you get, you get, you get, you
get, satisfy this strictly, this strictly.
You satisfy this exactly and, here,
instead of a complimentary slackness with
zero, the product of all the lambdas and
the minus f's are one over t, 'kay?
Well, I mean, you can check because we
defined lambda.
Remember we defined lambda as, like, one
over t times minus fi, so
that says that, that says that lambda fi
is like 1 over t.
So, so what it says and
now you can see you can argue again, if t
get's big, you know it says.
So your almost there it sort of these,
these, these, you check off, right?
So you get all of these, and the only
thing here is,
instead of zero, you get 1 over t.
And then the idea is we let T go to
infinity,
and we're now satisfying the KKT
conditions, so that's kind of the idea.
And you would hear, so, if you actually
find yourself hearing somebody
talking about these things, I mean I hope
you don't, but, s if you do, somewhere.
Then this will be referred to when you
replace the complimentarity condition,
lambda i, fi equals 0, with a 1 over t.
Which traditionally, they would call
kappa.
Those are referred to as the modified KKT
conditions.
And so, that story goes like this.
Here's a problem.
Here are the KKT conditions.
We modify the KKT conditions, so that,
that 0 becomes a kappa, and
now, we say we're going to apply a Newton
step to the modified KKT condition.
And guess what that, Newton's, it's the
Newton's step for
the problem we just look at.
So, okay, everybody, got this?
So that's it.
Okay, and you can get some other
interpretations.
You don't need to know any of these
things, but
they're just kind of cool to help
understand what it is.
Here's one, so let's forget the equality
constraints.
Let's suppose you're minimizing you're
minimizing f0 subject fi less than zero.
That's the log barrier, so let's center.
You can think of it this way.
I like to think of it as tf0, that's the
potential of a force field,
and the force field is minus t times the
gradient, right?
So it's, it's actually a potential.
And then minus log minus fi.
That's the barrier term associated fiI
less than zero.
That's, that's actually the potential of
this force field.
This force field which is one over fi,
times gradient of fi, right?
And then the optimality condition for
minimizing this is that, and this is all
the forces balance, right?
So, and, I mean, it's dumb.
It's saying like, look, let's minimize,
you know,
this potential plus these potentials.
And each of these is a logarithmic
potential that says you're one constraint,
okay?
So, it's like a force field
interpretation.
And, for linear program, you get something
even cooler.
A very simple interpretation.
The objective is just something like that,
tc,
and if you like, you could think of it
like this.
I have a constant force field in the
direction minus c.
It's like gravity, except it's, the
magnitude is t and I can turn it up.
So I can turn gravity up and up and up.
And it's a constant forcefield.
It just points in the direction minus c
and
I have the ability to turn up gravity,
okay?
Now, the other planes, the ai, those
things, the, it turns out, that the,
this is the thing whose, that's the force
field associated with the logarithmic
barrier associated with just ai transpose
x minus b is less than 0.
Or ai transpose x is less than b, right?
That's the force field.
It's a beautiful force field.
It ports, it always points away from the
plane, and
it's actually a beautiful thing.
It's with exactly an inverse distance
magnitude, right?
So for example, if that's a linear
inequality this says,
please stay on this side of the linear
inequality.
It says that the force field here will
point away from this this thing and,
and the magnitude will be inversely
proportional to how close you are.
Okay, so as you move closer, you get a
very strong repulsive force, right?
So, it means like you've sprayed these
planes with some repulsive stuff.
I don't know, you have to find any, I
don't know.
Actually, I don't think there's anything
in physics that does this, but
you can pretend like there is, right?
So, by the way, it's not correct that you
spray it with charges.
There's no physical thing that will
actually make the analogy, right?
So, at least that I know of, so, that's
that.
And now you can actually visualize what
the force field is.
It's very simple.
For example, at this point, you're
actually being acted on by five.
Five things, right?
Five forces.
But the, the force field is pretty much in
that direction because,
because you're right up under the shadow
of a very strong one.
And so that's dominating, right?
And, so, what happens now is the analytic
center is when you've got all
these repulsive fields all around you.
And you retreat to the center where all
those forces balance, okay?
And now they all, they all balance, I
mean, that's, that's this, this point.
I mean, actually,
here it's not the Alexander that we've
turned t up a little bit,
iit's t equals one, right?
And so this minus c, when you make this
thing bigger, right?
You move to a new equilibrium point, okay?
So, this doesn't do anything, it's,
it's just a way to think of all these
steps, right?
Otherwise it's just too fast, you know, so
I,
I mean it's actually not a bad way to
think about what these things do, right?
So, okay, now we get to the Barrier
method.
So, oh, and let me say it, let me give a
little bit of preempt.
'Kay, so, simply choosing a big, a big t,
a big enough t, and minimizing using
Newton's method.
That's called, it actually isn't called,
but I decided to call it that, the UMT.
That's unconstrained minimization
technique.
And I'll tell you why I decided to call it
that.
It's because it's a weird, retro,
historical reference, okay?
So that's the unconstrained minimization
technique,
weirdly, it actually works fine.
So, it's actually an awfully good way.
If you're solving LPs, but to some
relatively low accuracy.
So, t doesn't have to be gigantic.
It's an excellent method.
You write Newton method and you go at it.
It just works, right?
Every, everybody, so, it just works,
right?
And it just always, you know you get the
minimum, you get, you get the duality gap.
Yet returns primal point, dual point,
everything and
the gap is exactly m over t.
And if you wanted that to be 1e minus 3 or
what 1.01, right?
Depending on your application, that's
exactly what it will be.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
It works pretty well.
now, it doesn't if you ask for high
accuracy or something like that.
Then it doesn't, it doesn't work.
Hey, okay, it works, it just takes 10,000
iterations if you implement it
in infinite precision arithmetic, right?
So, okay, so there's actually a, a method
and it's a general idea, and
so, the other name for the Barrier method,
by the way, from the 60s is SUMT, SUMT.
That's Sequential Unconstrained
Minimization Technique.
Beautiful name, right?
Because it says exactly what it is.
Well, except, we added the equality
constraints.
But for all practical purposes, those
aren't, you know,
so equality constraints don't hurt you.
They're the unconstrained referred to no
win equality constraints.
Everybody got that?
So that's a beautiful thing, there's a
book written on this like 1969.
Sequential unconstrained mineralization
technique, okay?
So, and if you, if you just fix t and
solve it once, that's now, I decided to
call it OOMPT.
Okay, so alright, so the sequential
method,
that's the barrier method, and it works
like this.
So you, you start with some, some point
that's feasible, here and
what you're going to do is the following
at some positive t.
Now, it's primary a mu this is a very
simple method and
you can do the following..
You're going to compute by minimizing this
thing
subject to a equals b then you're going to
update.
That's going to be your nu value of x, and
then you're
going to quit if m over t which is exactly
the gap is less than epsilon, right?
And then you would return by the way both
x and the and the dual end points, right?
Because, that's what you should return.
If you write a solver you should return
the duo points as well.
Okay, and you increase t.
Now the key here is that you use Newton's
method
to minimize this starting from the last
point.
That's the key.
Okay, so that, that's, that's the key
here, right?
And there's a name for this.
And this beautiful pictures for this.
Like, so for example, another way, another
name for
methods like this, this method in fact, a
method like this.
Another name for this beautiful name is
Path Following Method for optimization.
Absolutely beautiful, because, you know,
here's, here's the central path,
right, going in to your solution, right?
And a path following method says your
here, that's a certain value of t.
Let's take mu equals, you know, 1.1, okay?
Then, what happens is you, starting from
this point, you apply Newton's method and
you bump around for a bit and then you end
up there.
And, and this is, this is x star of t, and
this is x star of mu t, right?
That's the new point.
And you can see what you're doing.
You're sort of following this path, right?
So, and, there's a, actually there's a
name for these methods and
it's actually a, is a very good thing to
know about these the, these methods.
so, actually there's a beautiful, so the
name for a, let me just,
this something, this something again, you
don't need to know this.
But it's actually a very good thing for
you to know if you do any kind of math or
anything like that.
Here's a general family of methods for
solving a hard problem, right?
And it's called a Homotopy method, okay?
And the way it works is very simple.And
the way it works is very simple.
You have a hard, something you want to
solve,
like a set of equations, or for that
matter, an optimization problem.
But you have a set of equations you want
to solve, and they're hard to solve.
So what you do is you introduce a,
a parameter into the equations, that it's
a knob that you turn, okay?
And it has to be continuous or, or you
know,
as you turn the knob the, the equations
deform continuously.
And now the traditional ranges of these
values for the knob, or zero and one.
And so the idea is when the knob is all
the way up at one,
you got the problem you wanted to solve.
That's the traditional parameter value.
When it's zero, the idea is it starts with
a simple problem.
Everybody following this, right?
And then the idea, now the,
now the method I'll describe a Homotopy
method is very simple.
Here's what you do.
You set your knob to zero you know the
solution already.
Then you set the knob to 0.05, okay?
Well, the problem is now close to an easy
one, and you knew the solution for
the easy one.
So you use something like a Newton method
to try to find it.
By the way, what would you do if you, if
Newton method failed to find that point?
Yeah you'd back off.
Instead of .05 you'd go to .025 right?
Now in this, in this particular case you
don't have to because no
matter how you set this thing it's
going to work.
Although it might take too many Newton
steps, so
you might do something like, I'll set at
.05.
If I don't converge, in 15 steps, screw
it, I'm going to back off.
It means I, I, it means I stepped too
aggressively along the path.
Everybody following this?
Okay, so, then you're 0.05 and you said,
now you said theta equals 0.1 and
you apply Newton method again and
hopefully you get there.
Everybody following this?
And so, and there's, and
there's a beautiful book, I think the sub
title of the book on this is pathways to,
oh something like Homotopy methods.
Oh something like Homotopy methods.
The subtitle is, Pathways to Solutions.
I mean, come on, that's like, too cool,
right?
This is a Homotopy method, right?
It's when, but there's a difference
between a general Homotopy method.
And the general Homotopy method, when you
increase that parameter,
you're actually not sure you can actually
solve the problem.
And during the general Homotopy method
goes like this.
If, you know, if not solve problem right
then it says back off back off the
parameter increase.
Everybody understand that one line?
Okay, so that's the general homotopy, here
you can't fail, right?
Because we can set t equals to nine.
And at least in theory we can tell.
Now there's a practical idea of failure
that might be that it takes more than 10
or 20 Newton steps, right?
So, I just mention that.
Okay, so here it's so it's extremely
simple.
That's the idea.
Now mu, that's, that's the amount by which
you increase, oh, sorry, the, the typical
Homotopy method, the traditional parameter
range is zero to one.
Zero's your easy problem, one is done,
okay?
So, our, our parameter range is like zero
infinity, okay, or
one infinity, something like that.
Okay, so that's but so what, that's,
that's a difference but
I thought, I thought I'd mention it,
right?
Okay, so now what we do here.
Is, you're going to increase t, which is
actually a measure of inverse gap.
You're going to increase t by a factor of
mu.
Now, if you really sort of follow the idea
of, you know, a Homotopy method
following the central path towards the
solution, you know, pathway to solution.
If you really kind of follow that image,
you would think of mu as being 1.05,
right?
That, you'd, you'd increase mu 5%, you
know,
start, and you'd hope for a couple of
Newton steps, and it's all over, right?
That, that, would be, and there's actually
names for methods like that,
those are called Short Step Path Following
Methods.
Okay?
So you Google that, you'll find, 50
papers, okay?
There are long step one's,
is where you're much more aggressive in
updating the parameter.
And the choice of that mu, which is how
much you update the parameter value.
that, that's sort of like how aggressively
you update, there's a trade off.
If you make mu tiny, then presumably,
every time you're solving a new problem,
it's basically the same as the problem you
just solved.
You're within the range of quadratic
convergency due one step.
And in fact there are methods based on
that,
they're called, those are the short step
path following methods.
And they chose mu so
small that you're always in the range of
quadratic convergence, right?
So that, so literally you do one newton
step, increase mu,
one instep, increase mu.
So that's, these are short step methods.
Long step methods don't do that, right?
So, and it turns out actually that a,
as a practical matter different values of
mu are actually better, 10,
20, 30, I mean actually fairly aggressive
ones, even 100 or something, okay?
Okay, so, you're going to, if you're
going to stop.
At at duality gap epsilon.
Your duality gap,
when you finish centering, is always
exactly m over t, right?
If t has been increased by mu each time,
you just take the log, you know,
base mu or whatever it is.
And that tells you, you know exactly the
number of outer iterations to
achieve duality gap plus an epsilon is
this, right?
So, it's kind of a beautiful thing.
You can see that is mu is one point oh
five,
that's a small thing in the bottom, right?
And you take a lot of iterations.
If mu is a hundred, it's a lot fewer outer
iterations, right?
Because actually, every time you do an
outer iteration,
outer iteration is a centering.
So, every time you do a centering,
your duality gap goes down exactly by a
factor of mu.
So if mu is 100, that says, you start with
a duality gap of, you know, 100.
Next step it's one, then it's 0.01, 20
minus 4, 20 minus 6, okay?
That kind of thing, right?
On the other hand, with mu is 100, you,
you got some serious, you got some serious
Newton heavy lifting to do, right?
Because you're starting from one problem
but
it's not that close to the next problem.
And so you, who knows how many Newton
steps you're going to have.
And in fact, what happens in a general
Homotopy method,
which is what you don't want to happen, is
the following.
As you approach the target, the problems
get harder.
This is what screws you.
And this is, by the way,
why it doesn't work to just go sand
something off in any way you like.
So that's, that's it.That's what happens.
If you go ahead, I've just got this great
idea, I don't want to talk to you about,
you don't have to know anything.
Let me have your problem, I'll just sand
these things off.
I have a parameter that controls how much
sandpaper I use.
Well actually it's the grid of the
sandpaper, right?
So I start with 80, I go to 120, I go to
400, I go to 800, you know,
this kind of thing.
I guess they don't make grid finder, they
probably do make grid for
like lacquers and things like that, that
go up to the thousands, right?
But okay, but then, you know the problem,
the downfall of a completely general
Homotopy method is very simple.
It's that as you increase,
as you get closer to the solution, the
problems get harder and harder.
So, you're increasing mu, let's go from
zero to one.
You know, let, let's take a parameter
theta going from zero to one.
That's the traditional range.
You know, I go from zero to 0.1, no
problem, 0.2, 0.3.
Now I start getting to 0.9, and instead of
two Newton steps, it's now taking 20.
And now I go to 0.92, because I've had to
back off, and
it's taking 100 Newton steps, and you can
see this is not going well.
So that's the downfall of why
disconstructing a general purpose
homotopy fails.
Okay, we're going to see something amazing
happens here.
And it's very specific to the log barrier
and so on.
Okay, so this is the number, total number
of,
of, of of outer steps you're going to do,
obviously.
And then, you're going to multiply this by
the number of
Newton steps required to solve the
centering problem here.
When t is mu times the previous t starting
from the solution when it was t, okay?
Now if you use the classical analysis,
something bad happens, right?
We go back to the classical, classical
Kantorovich analysis of Newton's method,
you will actually find that these problems
are getting harder.
Well, okay, they wouldn't assert that,
because they understood well that they
were simply producing an upper bound on
the number of steps which is valid.
I guess they would, they would say it, the
correct way to
say it is the complexity in that, the
upper bound, is growing, right?
So what happens is, when t gets very big
here, L gets big.
The Lipschitz constant, we, and we know
that because, you know,
what your'e really doing is you're
replacing something that looks like this.
With something that's curve, you know,
looks like that.
L is going to get really big, and the
prediction is,
is that as you increase t, sure you start,
the problems get harder and harder.
And like, first you're doing ten Newton
steps, then 50,
then 100, and then it all falls apart.
Everybody following this?
Okay, so that's the classical analysis.
But let's, let's take a pause and let's
just run the method and
see what it looks like.
So here's the method, here's an inequality
form LP and what's crazy about it,
so this is you know 50 variables, right?
And here it is and I have to explain
exactly what these are.
This shows duality gap and these are like
little staircase plots.
And what I, what I have,
what you have to understand is, I'm
counting Newton iterations here.
And so, the width of a tread is the number
of Newton steps required, right?
So, I don't know, let's look at this one,
this one is, that's 20.
That's, that's, like, I don't know, eight
Newton steps, right?
These things, this is from mu equals, 50,
and that's from u equals 150, okay?
Now the height of one of these stairs is,
when you finish centering you just
reduce the duality gap always exactly by
mu, by a factor of mu.
So when a log duality gap plot, you go by
fixed amount.
So, the height of the stairs in each case
is exactly the same as log mu.
Well, it's mu on a log plot.
Everybody' got this?
Okay, so, now, you can see, mu equals 2.
By the way, we'll see that if you're doing
complexity theory, right?
So, you want to prove that it's a
polynomial type method,
it will suggest taking like mu equals
1.01.
What do you, what would it look like if it
was 1.01 here?
Well first of all it would be one Newton
step for sure every time, right?
And it would be a, this would be like a
little staircase going like that, right?
And it would go, you know, it would work,
okay?
And, you know, but, so what's weird here,
so now you can see everything.
Here's mu equals 2, and you can see that
the, the treads are short.
Meaning you're not taking, you're taking
two, three Newton steps.
I don't know, you crank this up to 50 and
150 and you're taking like eight
Newton steps, but you're making a big
progress in gap, right?
So, alright, now here's what's weird.
Let's just focus on this guy, like right
here.
You just reduced the duality gap by a
factor of 10 to the 8th.
Okay, for all practical purposes you just
solved that LP.
That is an LP with 50 variables, okay?
With 100 constraints.
That's a polyhedron that has got a
absolute gigantic number of
vertices, right?
R50 is a big place, okay?
This says you just solved the LP in 30
steps, okay?
Now that's ridiculous I just want to point
that out.
That means you're in 50 dimensional space.
You actually stopped and asked for
directions 30 times and
said excuse me which way should I go?
And the answer came back from some Newton
thing or
something like that which is like go in
that direction, right?
That's what you did, 30 steps later you
found your way
to one of the who knows how many vertices
this is but the answer's a lot.
You found you're very close to the
vicinity of the optimal.
Everyone following this?
So, that's, that would be like in our
three, asking for directions, like, twice.
Or one and a ha, I mean, you're asking for
directions in a substantially fewer
number, than the dimension.
I, everybody realize how ridiculous this
is, right?
That's a number 50.
Here's what's cool.
Guess what these plots look like if you do
this with 50,000 variables?
>> The same.
>> They look exactly the same, they're the
same, okay?
They look exactly like this.
And it's the same thing.
It's weird.
Now, this is like a plot of the number of
iterations you need as you vary mu.
And something pretty weird happens.
If you make mu too small over here, sure
you are going to take a lot of steps.
By the way, if we continue this, this
starts going up like that, okay?
But this is very cool, because what's
happening across this range of mu.
This is super good news because mu is an
algorithm parameter, right?
And it's super good news,
because it means the good performance
persists across a wide range.
Now, what, what's happening it's very
interesting, as you vary mu, as you
increase mu, what's going to happen is the
threads get, they are getting wider.
But the stairs are getting taller, because
you get more, you get,
you get more duality gap, reduction, every
time you center.
But it takes you more Newton steps.
Miraculously you multiply these two
effects out, and it's constant.
Can everybody, see this?
And that's just a ridiculous number, I
mean, 30, 30 steps.
These are in fact the numbers, that you
have been seeing, for a whole quarter.
If you pay attention, you probably don't,
but if you paid attention to
the things like what's reported when
[INAUDIBLE] and STPT3 run.
Is you can now actually understand many,
most of the columns of what's being
printed out.
I don't know if you've noticed, but if you
get a super duper easy problem it's,
10, 10 iterations, usually, it's 25.
It can be 30 and if you give it some weird
things,
some SOCP right on the boundary in it, you
know, whatever, it can take 40.
I don't know if you've been watching but
that's, that's what this is, right?
By the way, a bunch of the other entries
being printed out you should
also understand, because things like
primal residual, dual residual and
things like that.
So, okay, everybody.
So this is actually pretty cool stuff.
All right, so, here's a GP.
Guess what?
Looks the same, okay?
The same.
This is with log sum x,
bunch of log sum x.
That's a, that's a geometric program.
Here's a bunch of LPs.
I think this is the problem you're
going to solve, and
this is what it looks like.
This is for each one, you get about,
you get a hundred instances for each
problem size, and you solve it.
So this here, is a problem I
guess with a thousand constraints and two
thousand variables.
Okay and you can see by the way in all
these simulations the maximum number of
iterations was something like 30, that was
it, 31, that's it, okay?
Everybody.
This is kind of the scaling.
By the way, this scaling law continues.
Oh, and I should tell you how this works.
The theory, we'll get to it in a minute.
The theory says this thing scales like the
square root.
That's the best bound known to date.
It says that as you get bigger and bigger
the problem goes like square root.
That's enough by the way for
our polynomial time complexity theorists
to be happy or something, right?
So that's fine.
This is the scaling and I'll tell you a
little, let me just tell you
a little bit about, about this and we'll,
were going to quit here for today.
But I want, I want to say a little bit
about it.
You see these pictures?
Guess what?
The pictures look the same, if these are
anything LPs QPs actually we'll see later,
we'll extend this to do semi [UNKNOWN]
program, things like that, SDPs, SOCPs.
It doesn't matter if its a problem from
signal processing, from control,
from finance, from machine learning, they
all look the same.
And, I was going to say something about
this,
this thing, this thing, this empirical
thing continues.
Because I have a friend, in Lazgo,
who solved an LP in exactly this form with
I think it was
something like a billion variables on some
gigantic, ridiculous, gigantic machine.
One of these IBM Blue Jean things or
whatever, right?
'Kay?
I just, go ahead I said what method do you
use?
He said just standard, standard method.
And I said how many iterations does it
take?
And the number?
>> [INAUDIBLE].
>> Very close, it's 24.
The, this is the amateur,
what you're seeing here is the amateur
implementation that's you know.
By the way all of these implementations
you can find on, I mean,
on the book website, you can find art
code.
But, so the pedagogical amateur
implementation gets 30,
the really cool ones get 21, 24.
So, just 24 steps, it was identical,
right?
Now, I should ask something about this,
this is the number of steps.
But the number of, at the time for a step,
is not constant.
You know, duh?
Because a step is actually solving a least
squares problem.
Everyone agreed because it's solving a
Newton system.
What's a Newton system?
It's solving a least squared, it's
minimizing a convex quadratic.
That's, there's another name for
that, it's called solving a least squares
problem.
Everybody following this?
Right?
So, the difference between this guy who
solved a billion variable problem and us
solving a hundred variable problem.
You know, that's like over here somewhere,
is considerable.
I, I solve my hundred variable problem in
100, 100 microseconds and,
oh, each iteration for him by the way took
something like 90 minutes, okay?
And the lights in Glasgow dimmed while it
was running, okay?
And the downstream river was, like, was,
like, really hot or something like that.
But the point was it was just 24 of those,
so 24 times 90 minutes, right?
So, but actually, this is actually super
duper interesting,
because what it says is the following.
It's kind of weird.
It makes full circle with the whole course
back to least squares, right?
So, when you come into this class you know
about least squares.
I mean everybody knows about least
squares.
And you shouldn't make fun of least
squares,
because like all sorts of crap is made to
run really well with least squares.
All sorts of image processing, like pretty
much all of actual statistics that's used,
I mean, right?
All of control, all sorts of stuff in
these squares.
I mean, you throw in regularization, some
other tricks.
You fiddle with the weights.
You can make a lot of stuff happen and
then, basically 20th century engineering
was done with least squares okay, period.
And a lot now too.
Everybody on board with this?
And then you say, why do you take this
class.
And you go, well, you know, that, that's,
that traces back to, to, Gauss.
We're going to learn that you can do kind
of the same stuff but
now have inequality, the constraint and
you can really say what you want.
Everybody, following?
I mean, that's kind of what the class is
all about, right?
Here's a joke, at the end of the class,
someone says okay, fine, I, I believe it,
I can do monotone regression now.
I can solve all sort of sick, sick things
in you know,
crazy machine learning thing, with I don't
know, all sort of weird hinge losses, I.
You know, in new signal processing, in
compressed sensing, all these crazy stuff,
I do finance with like three halves power
transaction cost model.
All these crazy stuff and someone goes,
woah, that's cool.
How do you solve it?
And do you know what he says?
The answer is you solve 20 least squares
problems.
Everybody got that?
So what this says is, if you, if you're
solving, you know?
The classical, you know, older
mathematical engineer is sitting there.
You, what are you doing?
LQR, I don't know, Kalman filter.
And then, what are you doing?
Well, I'm adjusting some things, like
covariance matrices or weights or costs or
something like that.
They're tweaking it to make it work,
right?
So then they'd say well what are you
doing?
And you go, I'm doing convex optimization.
I don't have to say these are between 0
and 1 or I don't have to tweak things to
make it between 0 and 1, I can just say I
want these variables between 0 and 1.
Everybody following the story?
Okay, and they go, huh, how do you do
that?
And I go, by solving 20 at least squares
problems.
>> Uh-huh.
>> So, it's kind of embarrassing that
they're so close.
Now so far we've assumed that you've
started with a point that was feasible,
and we're going to fix that now.
And we're going to fix it first in the
absolutely classical way.
This is from 1948 or something like that.
So the question is, how do you define
feasible point if you don't know one?
And, lot's of answers.
Here's one way.
Is, what we want to do is find a point, x,
that satisfies the inequalities, and
Ax equals b.
And the truth is, if we really want to
initiate a barrier method,
these inequalities have to be strict,
right?
So, not, it's not good enough to do this,
because the log barrier domain is these
things strict.
Or another way to say it is, if you're
using a Barrier method, slate or
better hold.
The slate or constraint qualification
You better have a point that's strictly
feasible.
So here's your basic one 1948 goes like
this.
You introduce a nu variable s and you
minimize over x and s,
s subject to fi of x less than s, and Ax
equals b and that's it, okay?
And I mean if and, and if you look at this
you'll realize immediately this is
nothing but the epigraph formulation for
minimizing the max it, it your minimizing
max fi, right?
That's what this says.
Okay, so what happens is clear, is clear.
If you solve this prob, oh, let's discuss
it.
For this problem, you have,
you, e can easily get a strictly feasible
point, right?
So, what you do is you pick any x in the
domain of fi, right?
You need, oh, you can actually relax the
Ax equals b or
whatever, or something like that.
But, did, you can handle that as well.
Let's, let's even just skip the equality
constraint for now, right?
But, you simply take a point x.
Then, what you do is you choose s to be
say, the max of fiI of x plus 1.
And, now every one of these inequality
holds with at least a gap
of one in there, okay?
So that gives you a strictly feasible
point.
So you solve this method, you solve this
problem using, say, a Barrier method.
And what will happen is this, if the
optimal s is positive you're done, right?
Because you now will have a certificate,
proving that there is no point that
satisfies fi, a of x less than zero.
In effect the optimality conditions here,
you can reconstruct a dual certificate and
actually a theorem of the alternatives, an
alternative certificate, right?
So that's the case.
Otherwise, it, you can terminate the
minute s is negative, right?
Because if s is negative, you break here
and
you've computed a point that's feasible,
that's strictly feasible.
And then you go, you switch to the Barrier
method, okay?
So, this is completely it's classical,
okay?
There's variations on it,
in fact, I think on your current
assignment where you're implementing one.
There's even a more sophisticated
variation where
you take into account the equality
constraint, so.
Okay, here's a very interesting
alternative.
These are called phase one methods.
I, I guess I should mention that, that the
idea is this phase one and phase two.
In phase one, you determine a feasible
point and then in phase two
you then find an optimal point starting
from a feasible point, right?
So those are called phase one phase two
methods.
Actually most modern methods use a
different thing which combines both of
them at once.
So here's another variation.
Instead of minimizing the maximum of the
functions in phase one,
you minimize the sum of the violations.
So if you take a look at this problem
here.
S is, should be interpreted this way, Si
is something like a violation in f.
it's, it's, it's how much extra slack you
have to add to that inequality to allow it
to be true, or something like that, right?
So, here you're minimizing one of the sum
of the S's and
this is clearly, this is exactly
equivalent to this.
You are minimizing, here, sum of fi of x,
plus, it's exactly that.
So the sum of the positive part, by now,
you should have a guess as to what that's
going to do.
Because in your head, you should see this.
And, I guess if you're in machine learning
you call that hinge laws, or something.
But whatever it is, it, it should mean
something to you.
What you would expect, and this is exactly
correct.
Is that, when you solve this problem, well
if,
if there's a feasible point they'll, you
know you'll get every point here.
But if it's infeasible something very
interesting happens.
You might get a few points up here, or
another way to say it is you have a
sparse, you have sparse violations, right?
So that's what this, this will give you
sparse violations, that's the idea.
So here's a quick example.
We have a set of a hundred linear equal,
inequalities, 50 variables here, right?
So it's infeasible.
So there's no point that satisfies all
hundred inequalities.
If you applied the standard phase one
method, this is the margin here, right?
So if you're above zero, that means
you're, you've satisfied the inequality.
Well what you've done, in the,
in the original, in the basic phase one,
the mini max phase one.
What you do is push all of them this way
and the result is congratulations.
You didn't satisfy, you didn't push the
margins,
all the margins positive, there is no
point with that.
But what's happened is of course all the,
all the margins have piled up on the,
on the line where you're pushing, right?
And so that ended up being, you know,
minus point two.
So the point is, here you've got 50 out of
your 100 linear inequalities are violated.
And actually, there's a couple down here,
so
it's probably more than half are violated,
something like that.
Well, I guess it's here, yeah, 51, okay?
So 51 inequalities are violated.
When you do the sum, the sum of
inequalities,
like the sum of violations method, you get
something very interesting.
And you can sort of see what happens.
So, by the way, how should we,
what this says is that many of them,
right, are, are satisfied, right?
There's a big bump right there,
that's a whole bunch of things that ended
up right there, it was just as easy.
And you have, you know,
you have a hand full out here that are the
ones you cannot satisfy and so on.
Now, this does not, compute the point that
violates the fewest inequalities, right?
It, it doesn't do that.
It's a heuristic for that but you can see
what it does.
Everybody got this?
So, an by the way,
how would you interpret, what would you
say about that inequality right there?
It's an easy to satisfy inequality.
So, not only is it easy to satisfy, it's
easy to satisfy with a bunch of margin.
It doesn't really cost anything, so, it's
done, okay?
By the way, there is no incentive
whatsoever for
a margin to move to the right, none what
so ever.
Because the slope of the hinge loss is 0,
once you've satisfied it, right?
So, you know, you could put a small slope
on that if you cared, right So,
okay, this is quite, this has actually got
a ton of uses.
I mean, for example, in engineering
design.
If you throw together a problem with a
whole bunch of inequalities,
a whole bunch of specifications, and it's
infeasible.
It doesn't really help you to get a phase
one
solution that violates like all of your
100 inequalities by some small amount.
It's actually quite interesting to get one
that satisfies like almost all
the constraints but a few.
So, it hand-selects a few.
And it kind of guides you and tells you
which of the constraints you're
going to have to give up on, or it
suggests which ones you could give up on.
Okay, so, there's a,
a very interesting thing occurs, when
you're doing phase one and
it has to do with the, the complexity
analysis of it.
And, in fact, this is the Achilles' heel
of the complexity in analysis of
all these interior point methods so if, if
you do real complexity analysis.
This is an you want to look and see kind
of where the fraud is
in complexity analysis of of interior
point methods.
Look for a constant that tells you how
feasible the problem is right,
because basically it, it's a bit,
it's a bit fishy.Uh, so, but let me
explain what the idea is.
Here, what you do is you construct a
family of linear inequalities like this.
Now, the, the fact is if you have a bunch
of linear inequalities and
you run a phase I method.
Actually two interesting things happen if
the inequalities have a giant feasible set
it'll take like ten steps and you'll have
a feasible point and you'll stop.
So if the feasible set is gigantic you'll
terminate very quickly because it's just
tons of feasible points.
You'll find one quickly, okay?
Now the flip side also occurs,
it's completely symmetric and it goes like
this.
If the inequalities are wildly infeasible,
right, which, by the way,
would mean what in terms of the dual or
alternative problem?
To be feasible and it's feasible set would
be, big, right?
So to be wildly infeasible, right?
Means that the dual inequalities are not
only feasible, but
have like a giant feasible set, okay?
Right?
What that means is there's tons of
certificates proving those things are
infeasible.
Everybody following this?
This is all complete hand waiving, but
it's actually good to know, okay?
So in that case also, phase one terminates
very quickly because it
terminates when it produces a certificate
of in-feasibility.
So again eight, ten iterations, 20, you
know if, if it's a challenging one.
Everybody following this?
So it, but write if you now make a
parameter.
That takes you, that perturbs the problem
and
makes it go from feasible to infeasible,
right?
And you tune that parameter right at the
phase transition
between feasible and infeasible.
That's where it actually gets hard to
solve, right?
And this is actually intrinsic.
I mean there's nothing you can do about
this, right?
This, this is, it, it's sort of obvious
intuitively, obvious and so on.
So, so what happens,
turns out is it's extremely difficult to
create a problem that will actually
be hard for a phase one to determine
feasibility or infeasibility, right?
You just generate, anything we come up
with in practice will be totally,
it'll work just fine.
It'll be 10, 20 steps, it'll be all over,
right?
It, it, period.
Actually, there are some pathologist, but
that's a different story.
It's a pathology and that's your fault
anyway or something like that.
If you're using barrier, the general
pathology is that you don't,
later is not satisfied, and that will do
the trick, right?
But using other methods that don't care
about slater you get you get
the same thing like this.
So what happens so the only way to do this
is actually to very carefully construct it
and you can see what's happening here,
right?
The number of steps is taking you, that's
25 or 30 or something like that.
It's a bit high but you know, it doesn't
matter.
This is infeasible, and then this is
feasible.
And if you zoom in,
right as you transition between them you
get something like this, right?
So, now, let's think about what these
mean, right?
This is saying well it's now taking 80
steps, here, to work this out.
That's because this problem is infeasible.
But it's infeasible in like the seventh
digit, right?
This problem, is feasible in the seventh
And so, you know, in, in some sense this
is of
no interest whatsoever in any practical
application, right?
If your problem, is, feasible in the
seventh digit, you, you've got a problem.
You have a serious practical problem.
I mean it's not going to work, basically.
Whatever, whatever you think you're
going to use it for,
it's not going to work, right?
And the same for infeasibility, right?
So, but this is just to show you what
happens here.
So let's do the complexity analysis via
self-concordance, right?
And, so the assumptions are that the, well
the sublevel sets are bounded.
In fact that follows from
self-concordance, in fact.
no, not quite, if, if you have a bounded
feasible set.
And we'll assume that tf0 plus phi is self
concordant.
And sometimes you assume this, for
example, for t bigger than one, right?
This, actually, we're going to increase t,
do it,
if it's true for any value of t and above,
it'll be, it'll be true.
For example, that 0's in concordant, self
concordant.
This is true for t bigger than or equal to
one, right?
If phi is self concordant and f0 is.
Now this would hold for
things like linear programs, QPs, QCQPs
geometric programs, things like that.
Now there are some cases where it isn't.
Here's one, here's a maximum entropy
problem, right?
And it's not, it's not self concordant.
But it turns out it's really easy to make
it self concordant and
actually when you think about it you'll
realize it was even the right thing to do.
One of the problems is,
there is an implicit constraint here that
xi is bigger or equal to zero.
That's the domain of the entropy function
here, okay?
And it turns out,
all you have to do is add that, and you're
back in self concordance land, right?
The, the reason is,
to, to the function here, remember,
negative entropy is not self concordant.
But negative entrop, entropy plus t times
the, minus sum log xi.
That is self-concordance, right?
So, when you add this constraint, this
thing is self-concordance, right?
So, sorry, tf0 plus phi is
self-concordance for this reformulation.
And, in fact, what it means is that xi
equals 0 is a problem here, right?
And what this says is you better make it
explicit,
because that's actually not a barrier for
it.
That's not a function that goes to
infinity as x goes to zero, right?
So, this says go ahead and make it, call
it out explicitly,
instead of implicitly, and actually then
the formulation works.
Okay, oh, and I should say before we even
start the complexity analysis,
I should start with a general comment.
The Barrier method works extremely well,
even when f0 and
tf0 plus phi are not self concordant,
right?
So, work perfectly well.
But if you really want to understand why,
eh, I mean, if you want to understand why,
it has to do with self concordance and
things like that.
So, okay, so
I'll go over the idea of this actually,
it's a, it, it's a bit complicated.
So I'll say just a few things about it and
then this, this is something that you'll
want to go figure out for yourself.
So what happens is we, we know the number
of outer steps.
That's just basically log one over
epsilon, right?
Because you, you divide the duality gap by
a factor mu every outer one.
So the question is how many Newton steps
does it take?
And the answer's very simple.
You are going to minimize mu tf0 of x,
right, plus phi of x.
We're going to minimize this,
starting from the minimizer of tf0 of x
plus phi of x.
That's what we're going to do, right?
Because, we're, we've minimized this.
That's x star of t, right?
And then we're going to increment t by
multiplying it by mu, and
then we're going to minimize this
function.
So starting from the minimizer of this
function,
we're going to find the minimizer of that.
And Newton's the complexity analysis of
Newton's method via
self concordance tells you that the number
of steps is less than or equal to this.
It's a constant times the starting value
of this function, that's this here,
minus, well, if you put a plus there,
that's minus the final value.
So x is the current point,
x is the minimizer of this x plus is the
minimizer of this.
It's for the new value of t, which is mute
times the old t, okay?
So, it says, you simply say it's the
starting val,
function value, minus the final one,
and then multiplied by a constant, and
then plus c, where c is 6, right?
Or log, log1 over epsilon, I mean,
whichever, right?
So that's what it is.
Okay, so we have to bound this.
Now, we already know what's going to come
to our rescue here.
Because it looks like a weird circular
thing that's completely useless,
because it says, it says, how many Newton
steps does it take?
And it says, oh, no problem.
It's your function value minus your final
function value.
And you say, well, how do you find the
final function value,
you say, use Newton's method.
But then, if you run Newton's method you'd
know how many steps it is and all silly.
And, of course, what's going to come to
your rescue is duality, right?
Of course, right?
So, I'll, I'll go over a little bit of
this.
It's probably a bit too complicated for,
to do in lecture so, it's it's the kind of
thing you have to work out on your own.
And I'll just say a couple of things here,
so here when x is the minimizer of this.
And we define, if you remember lambda i to
be 1 over t times minus fi of x, right?
And these are dual feas, these are dual
feasible points, right?
And in fact they're the ones that give you
duality gap exactly m over t, okay?
So now we simply go through and make
various substitutions, and I'll say
a little bit about each one but won't go
into to, to many horrible details here.
So this says for
example that you can represent the, you
can take phi of x here, right?
And write it, you can write phi of x here,
which is the minus sum log minus fi.
And you can write that as minus sum log
minus fi,
actually has the form 1 over ti lambda i.
And if your listening end of it and if I
said it right, which is not clear
then the minus' go away and that's like
sum log ti lambda i, right?
That you shove into this, right?
This thing is, that's minus, minus sum log
minus fi of x plus, and you put those in,
and you get this thing, like that.
The mu is pushed in and then taken out
here, right?
Because the mu is just, you just take the
mu out, you get m log mu, and
that, that accounts for it, okay?
By the way, we've already used duality.
This is where we, this is where, if you
wonder where the duality came in, come in.
It comes in right there, when we did this.
Okay, so in the next step, you simply use
the fact that, you know, log
log x is here is less than or equal to x
minus 1.
So we do this here, this is log that, we
write that out here.
And now, a pattern starts emerging.
You see, mu t, f0 of x plus, minus mu t
times sum lambda ifi of x plus.
And you say, oh, hey, that is the dual
function evaluated at, that's the dual
function, evaluated, or, sorry, that's the
Lagrangian, evaluated at x plus, right?
So, okay, so, then, and
there has to be less than or equal to, the
dual function, the dual function there.
Because that is the minimum of this over
all x.
And in fact it is minimized by x.
So you get something like this, here, and
now you're very close,
because f0 of x minus g of lambda v,
lambda nu, sorry.
This thing, that is exactly the duality
gap, it's exactly m over t.
The t goes away, and
you end up with a very, very simple
expression like that, right?
Now mu is bigger than 1, and if you plot
this function for mu bigger than 1,
it looks like this, right?
So here's, here's mu equals 1, and, what
it is, it starts quadratic.
And then it kind of ends up going up kind
of linearly.
I mean it's a little sublinear, because of
the log, right?
But basically it's linear.
But it looks like that, okay?
Actually here's the really cool thing
about it.
When it finishes, something really weird
happened.
Everything went away.
It has nothing whatsoever to do with the
dimension.
The number of inequalities comes in as m
up here.
So it's very simple.
It's just proportional to m and mu.
That's your parameter.
And notice that this does, this predicts
some, we're, actually, in some ways,
we're already done, right?
because what this says now, is it says
that the number,
the complexity of implementing t by a
fixed factor mu.
And then using Newton's method to
minimize,
doesn't get harder as t gets bigger, that
already says this.
Everything is there.
It has nothing to do with t, nothing,
everything went away.
And it even tells you more.
It tells you that for
example if mu were kept small, this number
would be very small, right?
It would be like, you know, one, and
there's names for those methods.
You can choose mu, so that in fact one
newton step will suffice, right?
That would be even less aggressive.
I don't know if you remember our,
our examples where we had things that look
like this, here, right?
So something like that, mu equals two.
That's pretty aggressive.
But if you had mu equals like 1.05,
it would just be one Newton step per, per
iteration, right?
It'd take you a long time.
But it would be one Newton step per
iteration and
that's actually predicted exactly by this
by this right here, right?
So and then it says as mu gets bigger you
pay approximately linearly, okay?
So now you're ready for the final
assembly, because that's our
incredibly simple and by the way notice
completely explicit bound.
It's not one of these nonsense Western
bounds, right?
That has all sorts of constants you don't
know, you don't, you know,
you'd never be able to know or anything
like, you could never evaluate.
And it just makes you feel good, because
oh, but you see it's a polynomial or
something, and then that's good.
Everybody know what I'm talking about.
So, this is completely explicit.
It's just, it's a number right there, I
mean, one over gamma's 11.
If you do the fancy analysis, it's more if
you don't, c is 6, just 6, period, right?
Five, six, okay?
This Is the number of outer steps.
That's the upper bound on the number of
Newton steps required to do,
to actually carry out the centering.
And you get really cool stuff.
This thing starts when mu is near one.
This thing is like quadratic.
Then it accelerates to linear, that's this
term.
This term is really cool, it has a 1 over
log mu in it.
So as mu gets close to one, this thing
gets big.
And of course, this thing getting big
makes perfect sense.
That says you're going to do a lot of
outer iterations, but
each one is going to be super duper cheap,
right?
So, okay, so you multiple the two together
and
you get a function that looks like this.
So that's, that's and this is,
I'm evaluating, I'm using, our bound,
which is pretty poor.
I think it's one over gamma's 365 or
something like that.
And this is for like 100 inequalities and
stuff like that, but
the point is that is actually kind of
gives you, it tells you something.
It says for example, that you should use
mu equals 1.02, there you go.
You should increase, you should increase
the homotopy parameter by 2% each step,
each time.
And this says you'll absolutely do, for
sure, less than 10,000 Newton steps, okay?
Right?
Total, right?
Now, we know, I mean the im,
empirically you're going to do 20, maybe
30 or 40, right?
So, something's off here.
By the way, if you replot, this, using not
the upper bound, but,
in fact, the typical values.
I don't know if you remember that, but you
can just change this value of gamma.
I think you change it to, like 1, or
something like that.
It turns out if you do that,
you actually start getting predictions
that are completely reasonable.
You get, you should set mu equals 50 or
100 or something like that.
Of course, it depends on m, and all that
kind of stuff.
So, so it actually does predict
everything.
But, most importantly, it just gives you a
bound,
it doesn't depend on anything that you
don't know.
You know everything in this bound.
Now, the numbers are big, but, you know,
it's a bound, okay?
Now if you go back here, and you look at
this thing, this thing, and
you ask yourself the question, I'll
minimize m, right?
I mean, of course, m is fixed.
Your initial gap, that's m over t,
0 of epsilon, that's, that's something
that's, that, that's known.
So, for a fixed M and
fixed, you know, other than the Newton
parameters, fixed fixed gamma and c.
And what you do now is you optimize over
mu.
And here's what you get approximately.
It says that mu should be one plus one
over square root m, right?
Now in practice you would never do this,
right?
You'd have mu equals a hundred or
something like that, and in fact I'll
later I'll tell you in fact what you know
how this is really done.
Someone already hinted at it earlier.
Mu is actually ada, I mean t is actually
adap, mu is adapted every step, right?
But roughly, so this says if you do that
and if you work out what happens,
it turns out that the total number of
steps is, it's o of square root m, right?
So, this is, and this is sort of the
crowning achievement right of
the complexity analysis of interior point
methods.
And this is for the Barrier method, but
it's true for every other interior point
method.
It's just o of square root m, right?
Where as, as a practical matter, it's
observed that it's actually O of one and
much more specifically it's like 20 to 80,
is what the number is, okay?
okay, so that's the, that's sort of the,
the crowing achievement of the complexity
analysis.
okay, now what's interesting is that this
number of
course is multiplied by the cost of a, of
a New, of a Newton step.
But a Newton step is a least square
problem.
So you have to solve a least squares
problem every step.
So it's actually quite interesting, it
basically says.
So the bottom line is if someone says give
me the executive summary on interior point
methods, you'd say, oh no problem.
Again, this is a practical matter it'd be
something like this.
You'd say it can solve a convex problem
with constraints.
It'll take about some, a few tens of
iterations, each iteration is
solving a least squares problem, that
inherits its structure from your problem.
Everybody get that?
So, that's, that's the executive summary.
What's bizarre is, that's also true for
a lot of other optimization methods that
we won't look at in this course, right?
So a lot of other methods, like operator
splitting, and other things.
Same, same story, right?
It's also kind of interesting 'cause it
puts it all in perspective, right?
It says that, after a century or
more of people using least squares and
twiddling weights to make things happen.
You, it says basically, that's what an
interior point method is doing.
It's solving 20 least squares problems.
But then it solves an LPE,
or some complicated other fitting problem
you have.
And it did exactly what you wanted, right?
So, it's an, I think it's a very
interesting, observation.
Okay, so
our last topic is that to generalize
interior point methods
to what's going to generalize to
generalize inequalities, right?
And you could have guessed that everything
was setup to do this, right?
There's actually only one thing we have to
do I will what that is in a minute.
So everything is set up to, to have kind
of very powerful notation.
So that the notation suggests what you
should do.
And there's only one thing we'll, we'll
really have to do.
So here's a generalized problem and
the difference here is that these
functions return vectors.
And then those, those vectors are not just
less then zero.
They're, well, they're less than zero with
respect to a cone, Ki, right?
Now if the cone is like the non-negative
orthon this is kind of a fancy way to have
ordinary inequality, so it's not
interesting.
It is very interesting when Ki is
something like for
example a positive semidefinite code,
right?
Because then this, I mean really that's
the most
significant example of a generalized
convex problem, right?
It's something like semidefinite
programming.
Alright, so, alright.
So we have to reinvent everything to work
in this case.
Actually, it's going to be shockingly
easy, right?
There's only one, one real thing we have
to do.
Okay, so, the main thing we have to do is
to work out what the log is, right?
Because, in fact, what we, I mean, what we
want to do is, we want to write down tf0
of x plus sum minus log, minus fi of x,
right?
That's, and then we want to say minimize
that,
we're going to call that x star of t.
And when you minimize that then t times
equal,
whoop, then we want to say t times equals
mu, okay?
And that's how, in fact we want to run the
exact same algorithm we had before.
The only one minor problem here, is that
this makes no sense, right?
So you, you have the logarithm of a
vector, okay?
So that's the only thing we have to do is
generalize the log to vectors.
Now, by the way, you can almost guess what
this is going to be.
Like, what do you imagine is the
generalization of
log to positive semidefinite matrices.
I mean, you get three guesses and the
first two don't count.
>> Log debt.
>> Yeah, of course it's log debt, so it's
going to turn out to be log debt so
that wasn't so hard.
Now by the way for the second-order cone,
it's, it's less obvious what it is.
But yeah, it's going to turn out to be our
friend log debt, right?
And that's going to be good because that's
self concordant and
all sorts of other stuff so.
So if you were just looking at
semi-definite programming,
it would be obvious what You know, what it
would be, it's log debt.
So let's, let, let, let's take a look at
what you, what you need to do.
Okay so you have a idea of a generalized
logarithm.
And the generalized logarithm for a cone,
it's something like this.
It says that the domain is the interior of
the cone.
I mean that's the same as the domain of
log, is r plus plus, right?
It's positive numbers.
But the domain of log debt capital X is
positive, is S plus,
is S n sub plus plus, right?
Set of positive definite matrices, right?
So the same.
And, let's see, this says, well, it's
concave, right?
So we're going to require it to be
concave, like log, right?
We'll say a little bit more about that in
a minute.
That's the idea.
So it has to, the domain is exactly the
interior of the cone, just like log.
Okay, and then here's the interesting one,
along any line it has to be the log.
So it has the look, if you restrict to a
line, it looks like a log.
That is actually exactly what happens for
a log of debt, right?
If you restrict it to a line there's a
line going through the origin,
it actually looks like the log.
Its exactly the log so okay, so it has to
have the fol,
the following form, if you scale it its an
additive term.
But there's a coefficient in front called
theta, right?
That's actually going to play a big role.
It's called the degree of the degree of
the logarithm.
And we'll see, what, it's going to be
obvious things.
So, here's the non-negative orthant.
Just to make sure this all make sense.
And here, we take the logarithm.
On the non-negative orthant, is the sum of
the logs.
I mean, this is kind of dumb, but fine.
And then, you check that if I, if I scale
a vector, right?
What happens?
If I scale a vector I scale every
component.
And so what happens is, basically what,
what comes out,
is theta, if I scale by s, what comes out
is n log s.
Because each of these contributes a that,
well, you add something,
which is log s, and then you get n times
it.
So the degree is n, by the way,
there's a beautiful interpretation of what
degree is.
It actually, it has to do with the
geometry of the set and its the maximum,
its something like the maximum number of
scalar constraints that are active.
We're not going to look into this here,
but and that's true for
the nonnegative orthant.
When you get down to the point 0, you've
got like n planes coming in and
that's why theta is n.
Okay, for the positive semidefinite cone,
we take log det and, sure enough,
everything works there.
The theta is n, that's, that's a
surprising theta
because the dimension of the positive
definite cone is n, n plus 1 over 2.
So, if you really call that n, I mean, if
you call that n, then,
basically it says theta is square root n.
For second order of cone, this is the, the
log, the logarithm for
a second order cone.
It's actually interesting.
It's this, it's actually the log of, and
then,
you simply form this quadratic formula.
What's a bit shocking about this and would
kind of make you nervous,
it takes you a while to get used to this,
a bit more sophisticated is the following.
This is a quadratic form, that's a
quadratic form.
What's the signature of the quadratic
form?
Is it positive semi def, negative semi
def, what is it?
Convex, concave?
You should be able to see it, just look
right at it.
It's diagonal, and what, what's the
diagonal matrix look like?
It's got a bunch of minus ones, and how
about the last entry?
It's plus one.
So, this is a quadratic form, but it's not
concave.
It's not convex, okay?
So, this doesn't, it, eh, everyone see
what I'm saying here?
So, you have to get used to this this is
right?
so, an the lo, the log of that is actually
concave, okay?
So, this is the,
this is one of those small subtleties,
it's, but it's actually worth knowing.
This is it, its not this is not obvious
here.
And by the way that definitely does not
come from one of your composition rules
right cos your, cos the argument to log
here is neither convex nor concave, right?
So this comes from the structure of this
particular thing.
Okay, so, that, and actually if you look
at it,
it's actually really cool what it
represents.
It, that represents the margin in the
second order cone, right?
Because second order cone says that the
sum of these thins is less than that.
And so this is the margin, it's how, in
fact,
probably it's close to a distance to how
far you are from the boundary if
this is the second order cone, going up
like this.
This is probably something like the
distance.
I mean, you might normalize it or
something like that.
But that's what it is, okay?
Everybody got this?
So that, that's the idea.
And the log of that is concave and
satisfies this.
And its degree is two, period.
Okay, okay, so
here are some properties, and these are
things, some of these are easy.
Most of them are actually pretty easy to
show.
First is, the generalized logarithm is
actually monotone, right?
So monotone, if you remember, means that
if one thing is bigger than another.
Then the function value of the first is
bigger than the function value of
the second.
It's mon, log is obviously monotone,
right?
So, but, in fact, to express that in terms
of derivative, it's that
the gradient should be non-negative in the
dual inequality, right?
So just to, that's what it is so this says
it's monotone.
And what this says is that y transposed
times the,
the gradient is just theta, it's constant,
right?
And that follows from this log thing and
the homogene, that homogenated property.
So for nonnegative orthant the gradient is
that, it's monotone here.
And I mean, this is, this is always
positive here.
In the dual inequality, which is the same
as R plus to the n.
and, and you get exactly that.
Y transpose this is just n.
For a positive semidefinite cone, the
gradient is,
I mean with some conventions about how you
represent the gradient of a matrix.
The gradient is the inverse, right?
Well, actually that's kind of the analogue
of of log.
Deriv log is one over, so for log det it
should,
by aesthetics, be something like one over,
so it's the inverse.
You have to be very careful as to what
exactly you mean by this stuff.
So that's what it is.
So the gradient of log det is the inverse.
The inner product, right?
Of y and the gradient, well the inner
product of two matrices,
the natural inner product, is trace of the
product.
And guess what?
Trace of y times the inverse is n, right,
which is theta, okay?
So, for the second order cone the gradient
looks like, that, that's the gradient.
And so, that's, that's the gradient.
And in fact if you work out y transpose
times the gradient of y you get two, okay?
So this is the, the idea.
These, these are the main logarithms we're
going to use.
There are actually some exotic, other
logarithms, for
other sets, that people use.
And it's, it's although they give better
complexity results in some cases,
it's not at all clear that they have any
use in practice.
I mean, and they give any advantage at
all.
Okay, now we can continue this, the
analogy.
So we're going to first talk about the
logarithmic barrier for
a set of generalized inequalities.
It's the same thing, you simply form minus
sum log minus i.
And by the way [COUGH], if these cones
were all the same.
Or we could even write this as log sum i.
That would be very cool overloaded
notation, right?
Very involved notation, right?
Because if you, in fact, you could even
write just log there.
So, it would look exactly the same as for
the scale, as for
the scalar inequality case, right?
And then it would be overloaded, meaning
log.
Has a different meaning, depending on the
type of it's argument.
It's a scalar, it's your old friend log.
And, if it's something in a cone, it
refers unambiguously to some logarithmic,
some generalized logarithm for that cone,
right?
So, for example, log of a matrix would
then be interpreted as log debt.
So, anyway, that's what this, that's just
a barrier function.
It's convex.
Why is it convex?
Well, again you needed all those
properties.
You use the following.
These things are concave, and they're
increasing.
That's convex, so this thing here is
actually by the composition rule,
that's actually going to be concave.
Sum is concave, minus turns it to convex,
okay?
They're just the same as before.
It's the same reason minus some log minus
fi is convex an x, okay?
So the central path is then simply this.
It is the set of minimizers of tf0 plus
phi of x subject to a, Ax equals b.
That's the central path.
So it's identical, right?
It's the same thing.
Oh, and, properly generalizes right?
That if, if all the, if these were all
simply r plus,
then this would reduce to what we have
already seen.
Okay, well then, let's, everything else
just works, right?
So if you write down what it means to
minimize this thing.
Well, that's simple.
It says that the gradient of this, plus nu
times here a plus
a transpose nu is zero, and Ax equals b,
those are the KKt conditions.
And so you get something like that.
Now I called it w naught nu, okay?
So this is the condition, it's a bit
harder you stare at it for
awhile and you get something pretty cool
here.
What you realize, you divide by t and then
what you
realize is that you take lambda i star,
and that's going to be this thing.
But remember, we have the following
property.
The gradient of the generalized logarithm
is dual positive, right?
That's the same as saying for
a log, right, it's derivative is, is dual
positive.
But that's silly because the dual of our
plus is our plus, right?
So you, so here we're using the fact that
it's dual positive here, okay?
And then, what this says is that if you
minimize, if you center here,
then basically, it says that you minimize
this Lagrangian here.
Where lambda star is this thing, nu start
is that,
that's identical to the other case.
And you work out the duality gap, and you
get the same,
you end up taking the gradient of this.
Transpose this thing and you know what you
get?
You get the sum of the thetas.
So, it's just, and notice, the
calculation's identical and you get this.
What's really cool about this is, so, this
is the analogue of m over t,
that you've seen up til now, for the
scalar inequality case.
And, in fact, the scalar inequality case
is a, is a simple case.
You just say, [COUGH] that you're, you
have a problem.
You have fi less than zero, but that's a
scalar.
Then you'd say, well the generalized
logarithm uses the logarithm and
it has degree one.
And so you'd sum up one m times and you
get m over t.
So, what it says is that this plays the
role of the, what was m over t, and
in fact it's really cool.
It says sum of theta you, you can even
think of that as something like as
the effective number of scaler
constraints.
That's an excellent way to think of what
theta means, okay?
So so from now on in LMI, roughly
speaking, counts as n scaler inequalities.
A second order cone counts as two, right?
A scalar inequality is one.
Everybody see this?
So, you can, actually then, take a
problem, a cone problem, and
say this has 237 effective scalar
inequalities.
That's simply the number here that plays
the role of what's just m, if for
example, all the inequalities were
scalared, okay?
Everybody, this one's kind of, its
actually cool.
Okay, so we get two semidefinite program.
So here, I mean this is the most important
case, so here is one in inequality form.
We're going to minimize c transpose x
subject to f of x is less than or
equal to zero.
The logarithmic barrier is log det of
minus f of x inverse, right?
So, the inverse is the same as putting a
minus in front of log det here.
The central path is it, to get x star of
t,
you minimize t times the objective plus,
this thing,
and if you take the gradient of that, you
get here tci minus.
This is the partial derivative in respect
to xi, and this thing is well,
the gradient of this like minus f of x
inverse, right?
And then you would, if you wanted to know
what is like partial f partial xi.
This is very rough, but that's fi.
And so you'd put trace fi times this, and
you get this, this, this inequality.
This equality here, right?
So that, that's the optimality condition.
You get a dual feasible point, because
this thing, here, if I multiple
by minus one over t, that's dual feasible,
and I get a point z that satisfies that.
This is the inequality form STP, and the
dual is the equality form here.
And I, I, if I'd simply minimized this
function using like Newton method.
I get now a dual feasible point.
And the duality gap is, it's really cool.
You just work out what it is.
That's the, the dual objective, primal
objective.
You subtract them, that gives you the
duality gap.
That turns out to be, using this formula
here, p over t,
where p is the size of the LMI, right?
So, that's it.
So, I mean these are you know it's kind of
this, this stuff has been,
I guess it's been well known for maybe 15
years now, 20 or something like that.
But 20 years ago not that many people knew
about this kind of stuff and
a lot of people didn't.
So now we have the Barrier method.
Here's a hint.It's identical, so it's
exactly the same, there's only one change.
What's happening is different, the only
difference is this used to be m and
now it's some theta i, that's all it is;
the sum of the orders.
Otherwise it's absolutely identical to the
other Barrier method.
I mean, of course it was set-up that way,
right?
So that it will work out.
It didn't just happen.
And that's it.
And the number of outer iterations is
the same except that instead of m, you
have, of course, the sum i over theta i.
And, actually, all this, all the
complexity analysis holds immediately,
the, it all just works, it's, it's all
exactly the same, right?
So you have polynomial time complexity for
solving SDPs and things like that.
Okay, so, let's look at some examples now
when you look at
these your first impression is that it's
the wrong figure that's been included.
Because it looks exactly like the other
one, right?
So but it's, it's not, I mean it's not.
I mean they are, they, these things all do
look the same, right?
So I guess that's good.So it means it's,
it's exactly the same.
These plots look the same, this looks the
same.
By the way this would also up here start
going up, like that, right?
So they look the same, as for example LP.
So, actually it's a very nice set of
generalizations and
overloadings of meeting and things like
that.
Because, it's not just that the code,
if it was written nicely would look
identical.
It's more than that, actually the way it
all works would be the same.
In fact, even the empirical the way it
would work
empirically would look the same.
So let's just take a look at one of these.
Here is a semidefinite program with 100
variables and, and
a single LMI constraint in, in with 100 by
100 matrices, right?
So if you want to picture something like
that, it, your bounding some covariance or
something matrix or something like that
with a 100 variables or something.
It's not a simple problem.
It's one that 25 years ago absolutely no
one would have any idea it
could be solved by any method, right?
Let alone by something like 20 steps of
some quite simple method that 's probably
like only 50 lines or something like that.
So it's, it's quite a complicated problem.
And here, you can see that you're actually
these with this
very simple Barrier method you're solving
with things like 20, 30 steps, right?
So real methods would do it in 20 or 18 or
something like that.
Each step is solving in Newton system Any
guesses, just for fun?
Just to see, what the complexity of a,
the computational complexity of a Newton
step is here?
because that's n to the fourth.
That's still pretty good, though, right?
For a semidefinite program.
It's n to the fourth.
It turns out that,
it's actually not solving the Newton
system which is order n cubed.
Its actually assembling the heshion in the
general case cos n of the fourth.
So, that, that's actually what the
computation complexity is.
That's still quite good right?
because, it could have been like the dual
has whatever 5000 variables that
would be end of the sixth or something.
So you would have n squared variables and
then you apply Newton's method there you
get end of the sixth, alright?
So okay, so anyway, so
these are, this is all, like it's very
impressive that this stuff works.
So here's a family of SDPs, it's like the
family of LPs and for
each of these you solve, that's actually a
very specific SDP.
But for each of these, you solve 100
random instances,
actually it's not at all clear what
happened out here the 1000.
But I guess it suggest that it, it's being
reported honestly.
But probably that's some numerical issue
or something like that.
But it;'d be nicer if it just looked like,
like it did for the LPs and
kind of just go like this right?
That, that would be better, right?
So, okay.
So, it's the same sort of thing.
I, I should say that SDP is still kind of
a an op that its no one has I,
it's not completely nailed yet, how to
solve SDP's.
If there are plenty of sort of SDP solvers
there, also just the special ones for
different structures and things like that.
People solve very big ones.
For example, people who work on
comdutorial optimization,
and need to do SDP bounds.
They solve big ones.
But there has not emerged what you have
in, for things like LP and
SOCP, which are simply, kind of the best
methods that just work.
This has not emerged, so it's something
people have been looking at for
maybe 20 years now.
And it'd be really good if someone were
to,
like, figure out good, universal methods.
So, that was a hint or a suggestion.
A plea?
One of, one of those.
So, okay, so the last thing I want to talk
about today our
Primal-dual interior-point methods, right?
So, in fact the Barrier method is not
really used.
Actually it is in a few weird places,
right?
And in fact it's even simpler.
Barrier method with a fixed value of t is
used in a few real-time things right?
Where you don't need high, high
resolution.
And you just use Newton's method to solve
something like that.
But generally speaking people don't do
this, what they really do is don't even
distinguish between inner and outer
iterations.
It's equivalent to changing, in another
way of saying it is to change t every step
of, every, for every, you do every one is
a Newton step.
And you change t every single time.
Instead of we you know we go like eight
steps satisfy a conversion criterion then
it's you know t times equals mu.
And in fact the way real ones work is they
do a little bit of work to
update t every single step right?
So that's one way, and they also but
however,
each step always, nothing but solving a
set of linearized KKT.
So the equations look like basically
identical.
And they use infeasible start Infeasible
Start Newton type things.
So you start, you don't have a phase one
and phase two.
So these are kind of the standard,
standard methods.
But the cost per iteration is identical to
the barrier method, and thinks like that.
So they're not, they would have kind of
some minor advantages, but
not, not, not huge, huge big advantages.