So the next topic is duality.
It's a whole world.
It's an absolutely beautiful subject, it's
you can think of it in many, many,
different ways.
it's, one way to way to think of it is
it's a way to,
it's an organized way to form highly
nontrivial bounds.
On optimization problems.
And we'll see that that's one of its
beauties.
Even for hard problems, not necessarily
convex.
We'll also see that it, it's a, it's a,
it's for convex optimization problems is
a beautiful theory that will lead to
things like,
optimality conditions, that give you that
in a few, handful of cases, you can solve,
but always will give you insight into how
a convex optimization problem works, or
what the solution's going to look like.
And finally, we'll see that it, it, you
can interpret the,
some results from duality, as giving you a
sensitivity of the optimization problem
to perturbation and sensitivity analysis
of various things.
We'll look at a bunch of examples, and
we'll con-, extend this to generalized
inequalities.
That'll be the last thing.
That will do in, in this section.
I should say something else about it, it's
it's all, it's all,
it's, I mean of course a lot of it is just
theory and it's absolutly beutiful and
it's, a lot of the theory works even when
the problems involved are not
convex the differences when they're not
convex you can't actually Do it in
a sense because you're actually asked to
minimize various things.
And roughly speaking you can't do that
unless the problem,
the functions involved are convex.
So what's very interesting about duality
is that it becomes,
although it's interesting theoretically
always, it actually becomes.
Actionable in the case of convex
optimization.
So it'll, it's actually, you can do it,
you get numbers and
they have beautiful interpretations and so
on.
So, that's the idea.
Beautiful subject.
Alright, so we'll start.
And for a while I should say, we're just
going to be defining various things and
going very slowly but you'll see actually
even after just a few pages we're going to
end up with something that's actually
highly nontrivial and interesting.
So, let's start.
So I'm going to start with a standard form
problem and
I'm going to not assume it's convex now.
So, I minimize an objective subject to
inequality constraints and
equality constraints.
And I'm going to form a Lagrangian and the
Lagrangian is this.
I'm going to form, I"m going to add to the
objective a sum of the lambda is
are going to be non negative numbers here.
I'll, I'll get to that in a minute.
Multiples of the object, of the constraint
functions here and
I'm going to add some other numbers.
These are going to be unconstrained new
i's.
I'm going to, that's going to multiply.
H i of x you should think as a residual.
It's the amount.
If it's 0, that perfect, that means you've
satisfied that constraint.
Otherwise, it's a residual.
So that's the idea.
That's the Lagrangian, and it's a function
of both x and these things.
One way, nice way to interpret the lambda
and nu Vectors.
Is if, you like, you could think of them
as prices, right.
So, for example, F0 of X lets assume
that's in dollars, F1 of X,
well, I don't know what it is but its in
some units.
And Lambda 1 is the price in dollars per
that unit.
So.
If this were zero eh, lambda 1 f1 would be
zero, and
there'd be no payment either way.
But notice also that is f is positive, it
would cost you.
So, it costs you to have positive f.
Now, in the original semantics, the cost
of having positive f1 is very simple.
It's plus infinity.
So in this, with, with this Largrangian
here, the cost is actually, its linear.
It's not something that goes from 0 to
infinite.
Okay.
And these are called dual variables for
reasons that will become clear later or
they're called Lagrange Multipliers.
And we'll call them lambda for the
inequalities nu for the equalities.
Okay, so this is simply the Lagrange unit.
Now the Lagrange dual function is this,
it says it's a function only of lambda and
nu.
And it says you should minimize Over x,
the lagrangian of x lambda nu.
And, if you like to think of it this way,
it's the infimum, of, of,
well that's the lagrangian.
And one interpretation of it is very nice,
it's this.
You could say that's the optimal cost with
the prices given by lambda i and new i.
Right?
So if, and
some people make a big story about it.
We'll see this later, but, you know, they
think of
they think of this as sort of a market
solution or something like that.
That instead of strictly enforcing fi less
than 0,
instead you simply set a price lambda i.
And instead of saying oh, you know, h i of
x should be 0,
I'll just put a price new i.
And then this says that you should
minimize x over this.
And so this is the optimal cost under the
prices or
Lagrange multiplier vectors, you know,
lambda and new.
Okay, very important fact about g.
That's this.
It is concave, even if the original
problem is non-convex.
And let's see why.
Here's the Lagrangian here, and as a
function of Lambda and Nu,
it is affine, period, for any x it's
affine.
Okay, now the enfemum over any family of
affine functions is concave.
So That, right?
So, now of course it can be minus infinity
for some lambda and nu.
Okay?
That's, that's, it's an [UNKNOWN].
Of course it can be unbounded.
Okay.
Now here's something that's going to be
kind of obvious.
It's going to lead to really interesting
results though.
It's this, suppose I told you that the,
that the Lagrange multipliers associated
with inequality constraints are
non-negative.
Then the claim is, the dual function
evaluated at Lambda and Nu,
is a lower bound on P star.
That's the optimal value of the original
problem.
Okay.
Well, look at the proof.
It's embarrassingly simple, it just says
this,
it says suppose X tilde is any feasible
point.
And let's assume that the Lagrange
multipliers associated with
the inequality constraints are non
negative that's here.
Then it says the following f 0 of x that,
that's bigger than this and I'll explain
why in a minute.
And this thing i mean by definition if you
minimize over x if that's smaller than
this value but that's g and this one here
this one follows from the most
embarrassingly simple thing it says the
following,it says take cap zero of x and
if these are non-negative If x is
feasable, these are less than or
equal to zero, and now we're going to use
the deep mathemetical result.
That the product of a non-negative number
and a non-positive is non-positive.
We'll use another deep result that says,
the sum of,
in this case non-positive numbers is
non-positive.
So this whole thing here is less than or
equal to zero.
Now, it doesn't matter what the new i's
are,
because if x is feasible, these are all
zero.
And the product of zero and any number is
So this whole term is zero.
And that says that whatever this is, when
x, for any x L of,
if x is feasible, then L of x lambda nu is
less than f 0 of x.
For any feasible.
And that by [INAUDIBLE] over x, I get
this.
Okay?
So, what this says is actually really
interesting.
It says this dual function, whatever it is
You can think of it as
providing a parametrized lower bound on
the optimal value of the problem.
Right?
And
the parama, it's parametrized by lamda and
new.
Now, they can all be crappy lower bound
for example, you can plug in lamda and
new in G of lamda new could be minus
infinite that's the universal lower bound.
In other words, I don't have to know
anything about your problem to
say minus infinity is the lower bound.
It's the completely and utterly
uninformative lower bound.
So, you get lower bounds nd they're
parameterized by lambda and nu.
By, by the way, that alone is quite
interesting.
By the way, one thing that you're, you'll
be tempted to do immediately is this.
If I have a lower bound, it's opt, it's
paramatized by some parameters.
You should have the urge to change those
parameters so as to maximize the lower
bound because as you maximized the lower
bound it becomes better right?
If I tell you here's a lower bound that's
minus 12,
if I can get another lower bound that's
minus 10.5, that's better.
So you should want to maximize the lower
bound.
That's quite interesting cause guess what
that function is concave.
Maximizing the lower bound is going to be
a convex optimization problem right.
So that's very interesting.
Okay let's look at some examples.
Let's solve, let's minimize x transpose x
subject to ax equals b.
Well, the Lagrangian is we take the
objective, and
to that we add nu transpose times Ax minus
b.
That's the residual.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to minimize that over x.
That's easy enough.
It's you can work out what the sol, I
mean, you just take the gradient and
set it equal to 0, and you get that.
And you plug that in to this lagrangian
here and you get the following.
You get that.
It is a negative it's a concave quadratic
function.
That's what it is.
Okay.
I mean by the way it had to be concave
because the dual function is always
concave but here we see it explisitly and
that says the following.
[COUGH] This says, if you picked, if you
want to solve this problem,
this says it's the least, it's the least
norm squared solution of ax equals b.
That says if you picked any value of, any
vector at all, any vector, and
you evaluate this quadratic function here
That number is bigger than is le,
is a lower bound than the optimal value
here.
Okay?
Now, that's not so useful here because we
can solve this problem exactly.
Well, that's not entirely true I'll give
an example.
When x has size let's say 100 million this
could actually be a challenge to solve and
you might use some kind of by using some
kind of integrate method,
in the integrate method after some number
of iterations it have an x and if you
are lucky it will have ax equals b, and
you could look at the value of this and
supposedly you find that is 7.1 lets just
say ok,now enough to be able to identify
a new evaluate this number, and find out
that the value of that, if that number
evaluates to 7.0, you are super lucky.
Because now you've decide, you've shown,
you have an x that achieves enough, an
objective value 7.1.
But your new is a certificate proving that
the best X has to be,
has to have a value of this worse than 7.0
And
that says you're pretty close to optimum
and you can quit with confidence.
Right.
You can quit saying that,
at worst you're 0.1 optimal.
Sub optimal.
We'll talk about these ideas later but
I'm just saying this has practical
applications like.
Immediately.
By the way you could ask a reasonable
question.
How would you choose this new?
Great question of course it's a lower
bound no matter what new you pick but,
if you pick a crappy new you're going to
get a crappy lower bound.
So, we're going to answer those questions
as, as we move on.
But, for now it's just a lower bound
depends on a new Any number you,
any vector nu you plug in and evaluate
that you get a lower value.
Let's look at LP.
I want to minimize c transpose x, subject
x equals b and x non negative, so
here's the Lagrangian.
It's the objective, plus I take...
The, here I take a, a new transpose,
that's the dual vector times a x minus b.
And here I'm going to write this x less
than, or
x bigger than equal to zero as this thing.
Minus x is less than 0.
And so I get minus lambda transpose x.
That's the Lagrange multiplier term.
And so I get this, and You look at that
Lagrangian and its affine, in x.
Well of course it was going to be a, its
going to be affine because every
function involved in a linear program is a
affine is an affine objective,
affine inequality constraints and all you
do in lagrang,
following a lagrangian is you form a
waited linear combination of.
the adjective in the constrains,so you
gets to know is alpine and
now we rest is minimize alpine function
well that's actually quiet easy to do
right,if you minimize an alpine function
,basically for most cases you just get
minus infinity if this vector here is non
zero i can make this thing small as i
like go in the direction negative And
multiply by a big number.
I can make, I, I get this is unbounded
below.
So if I take the infimum of this affine
function, I get minus infinity,
almost always.
Except if this, this thing here, is 0.
If that's 0, L is quite boring.
It's constant.
It's minus b transpose nu.
So I get a weird function g.
It looks like this.
It's minus b transpose nu, if this holds.
Otherwise it's minus infinity.
So, what it says is,
I have a parameterized lower bound on the
optimal value of the cell b.
It's parameterized by a vector nu, and
lambda.
Now, If, the fol, if Mu and Lambda don't
satisfy this equality constraint, then
my lower bound is minus infinity which a
completely uninformative lower bound.
But if they satisfy this constraint, I can
announce minus B transpose new,
is a lower bound.
On this, on this, LP.
Right?
So, for example, if I could find, if I
were lucky enough to find a nu and
a lambda that satisfies this, and minus b
transpose nu equals c transpose x,
I would be done, and I would absolutely
know it.
I'd know it, because I have a point that's
feasible.
Achieves a certain objective value.
And I have a lower bound showing that that
objective value is optimal, right?
So, I'm getting ahead of myself but this
is, this is the,
this is where we're going with all of
this, the practical applications.
So what does this mean, to say there
exists a lambda for
which A transpose nu minus lambda plus c
is zero.
That's the same as saying a transpose new
plus c is bigger than equal to 0.
because you just take the negative of that
to be lambda.
Sorry, that's equal to lambda.
And so what it says is this.
It says that if you have this l p here,
and it says that if you find a vector new,
That satisfies a transpose nu plus c is
bigger than equal to 0.
Now, at the moment, we don't know how to
find such a vector.
We have no idea.
We're going to see later how to find such
a vector.
But right now, we're, we, we don't concern
ourselves with how we find it.
If you find a vector nu for which a
transpose nu plus c is
bigger than equal to 0, then this number,
minus b transpose nu, is a lower bound.
On the outcome value of that standard form
LP, okay?
So that's the idea and, you know, if, if
this is a real duality,
a really Lagrange duality, you know, it's
not hard to show.
You can show this directly although,
if you didn't know about Lagrangian, you
might not have guessed such a thing.
Okay.
Let's look at equality constrained norm
minimization.
We already looked at one that was kind of
like this but
not quite because we squared it.
So let's minimize norm x, norm is a
generic norm subject to ax equals b.
Well, the duel function is the infimum of
the norm of x
minus new transpose ax minus b, that's
this here.
And here, we're going to infamize this
over x.
Now here, that's the norm minus a linear
function.
Well the norm minus a linear function, we
have to see if that's, you know,
we have to minimize over x.
That's a homogeneous function, so the only
possible things that can happen is
you either get zero Or you get minus
infinity when I minimize.
And in fact, I get zero if and only if the
dual norm [COUGH] of a transpose new is
less than or equal to one, so that, that's
this term.
Okay?
alright, so
now I have a beautiful lower bound
property.
It says if you want to do general norm
minimization with equality constraints,
it says the following, if you're solving
that problem or
whatever you care about, it says if you
can find a vector new for
which a transpose new in dual norm is less
than one That tells you that b
transposed new is a lower bound on the
optimal value here, okay.
So, so I think you can see here where what
we're doing is we're generating
parameterized lower bounds on the optimal
value Of an optimization problem.
I mean, that's kind of what this is.
We have not yet said anything about how do
you optimize that parameter, you know,
anything else like that.
We, you know, how tight is lower bound.
We're going to get to all these things,
but for the moment, that's the correct way
to think of this, what we've done of
Lagrange duality so far.
Okay.
Now, our last example of this is actually
one where it's quite interesting.
It's a nonconvex problem, so let's take a
look at that.
Here it is.
You'll recall that the partitioning, part
two of the partitioning problem is I
have n items and I'm going to partition
them into two groups.
Right?
And I'm going to encode the partitioning
by taking a vector x On our end.
And the entries are really going to be
plus 1 or minus 1.
Plus 1 means one group, minus 1 means the
other, right?
So, a plus minus 1 vector corresponds to a
partitioning of these x into two groups.
And I have a matrix w that tells you how
irritating it is for x i and
x j to be in the same partition.
And that's given by w i j.
And so, this is so W i j, I guess you
could say is, that's, that's how much,
you know, let's say person i hates person
j, let's say, dislikes.
Let's not use hate.
Dislikes person j.
That, that would be for a constraint, so
dislikes.
And so this says and then if they're in
the same.
partition, right?
Then, you know, this is of course sum
xixjwij.
And if they're in the same partition then
they're both either plus 1 or
minus 1, [COUGH], and you add wij.
If they're in different partitions xi and
xj,
the product is minus 1, and you actually
subtract them, wij, right?
So, so this says something like,
you know Partition into two groups in the
most harmonious way.
Okay.
Now, that problem you may, you may know,
we've already seen it.
That's actually m p hard.
So that is as hard as many other
combinatorial optimizational problems.
No one knows how to solve this thing,
exactly.
And quickly.
So it's a complicated problem.
By the way, there are many, many methods
to solve to solve this approximately and
in fact, we're going to see some,
momentarily.
And it's a prac, it's a problem that comes
up all the time.
Right, so for example okay, we, we'll move
on.
so, that's a nonconvex function because
these constraints are not
remotely convex, right, that's a quadratic
equality constraint.
By the way this relaxation That's gone
vex.
And that's a very famous relaxation of
this problem, and
I think we've seen it before.
however, what we're going to do now is
we're going to take this,
by the way there's also no reason to leave
the w well it's symmetric because
there's no reason to believe it's positive
semi-definite.
Okay, so here's what we're going to do.
We're going to take, we're simply going to
follow the rules.
You take f zero and to that you add sum of
new i times, these are h i, of x,
and that's these quadratics.
And if you look at what this is, it's a
quadratic plus a Constant, constant n x.
Well it's a quadratic how do you minimize
a quadratic?
It's very simple minimal of a quadratic is
either minus infinity if
it's got a negative [INAUDIBLE] value or
it's 0 if it's positive semi definite.
So what you get is the dual function is
either minus infinity or
If this matrix is positive semi-definite,
the best x you can do,
I mean the x that minimizes this, is x
equals zero.
And then you just get this thing left
over.
You get that.
And that happens if that's true.
And that says, we have the following
statement.
If you can find A new, such that w plus
diag of new is bigger than equal to zero,
then minus one transposed new is a lower
bound on p star.
Okay?
That's incredible.
It's quite sophisticated.
It says that, by the way, that's an LMI in
new.
That's a linear matrix inequality.
It says that if this matrix inequality
holds Then you get a lower bound, okay.
It's quite interesting.
For example, here's one, you take nu is
minus lambda min of w times all of ones,
and you get a very famous bound for this
problem which is
this: the optimal value is bigger than
equal to n time lambda min of w, okay.
And I'm going to show you another way to
derive that.
Another way to derive this inequality,
very famous inequality,
by the way it's also, it suggests a method
for approximately solving this problem,
which is actually called [UNKNOWN] well in
this case it's spectral partition, but
let me say a little,
let me derive this another method that's
maybe simpler than [UNKNOWN] 's duality.
It goes like this...
You want to solve this problem.
If you cannot it's, I mean it's too hard.
So you look at it, and you say, you know
what though, if x i squared is 1,
I'll tell you one thing I know for sure.
Some x i squared is n.
Okay, because each of the numbers is 1.
Okay?
And that says so These n inequalities
imply that inequality.
Okay?
That's one way to say it.
Or, if you like to think geometrically,
these inequalities say that xi sits on a
hyper, the vertex.
It's on the vertex of a hypercube.
So, there's a cube in rn with entry, the,
the extreme, the vertices there are
Boolean vectors, right?
That's the hypercube.
Then, interestingly, this is the sphere
that covers the hyper cube, okay.
So, so you can think of it as a
relaxation.
It says that if you're in the hyper, if
you're on the vertex of a hyper cube,
you're in the sphere.
But you know what?
I know how to minimize a quadric, an
arbitrary.
Quadratic fun, form.
x transposed, Wx, subject to this.
Because it, it's simple.
That's, that's one of these non-convex
problems we can actually solve.
If I say, what's the minimum of a
quadratic form,
subject to the norm being 1, (no period)
The answer is, it's lamdamin ??
of w.
And you take x,
by the way, to be an igan vector,
associated with the minimum igan value.
And so, here, the sum of the square, the
norm squared, is n, so
that scales everything up by n and you get
this bound.
You get the same bound.
It's a beautiful bound.
By the way, it also suggests.
A good idea for x.
Know, tell you what it is right now.
You compute the minimum,
the eigenvector of W associated with its
minimum eigenvalue.
That's the first step.
And you get, and let's call that vector V.
Then you simply take Xi is the sine of (no
period) v.
Done.
Right?
That does quite well.
When you think of this as a partioning
probelem, that's called,
this is called spectral partitioning in
this case.
Well, that's one name for it,
although that name is used to refer to
something similar but not the same, but
that's the idea.
So the point here, let me sum up what the
point of this is.
This is a hard problem right?
If w is 1000 by 1000, I, I don't know if I
give you 1000 by 1000 sparse w and
I say solve the two way partitioning
problem.
It's not, it's not unreasonable to say the
following, you can't solve that problem,
you can't tell me what the global minimum
is.
Okay.
What this says is, the following, it says
you can get a lower bound, you have
to exhibit a vector new, check that this
matrix here is a positive semi definite.
If it is, minus 1 transpose nu is a lower
bound of an optimal value.
Now in this case, this is exceedingly
valuable, exceedingly valuable.
Because for example you could do spectral
partitioning.
You could start with this one.
And you could observe that it gets good
results.
By the way, after you do this, you could
do something like a greedy heuristic.
i would do it once you find bit
vector,Boolean vector all this x's
are plus and minus 1 here why would you
not do the following i
would cycle through x and for the each x i
,i would flip it and
see it if it gets better Most of the time,
it doesn't.
But if it ever gets better, I take it, and
that's my new X.
And I keep running through my data until
this stops.
And then, when I stop, I think that's
called something like, 1 opt,
in combinatorial optimization.
What that means is, I can't change one of
my variables and
improve the objective, okay?
So that's one opt.
It just means it's a kind of local
optimality, it doesn't mean.
You're at the optimal point.
So the point is then method I just
mentioned spectral partitioning followed
by a local optimization.
a greedy local optimatization.
I can implement that for a matrix w which
is 50,000 by 50,000.
Actually I can scale it as big as you want
and people do.
And you will get exceedingly good
partitions Okay.
The question will be, how do you know it's
good?
And the answer might be, although like I
haven't said yet how you would find it,
you do the following.
You would exhibit a new, demonstrate the W
plus diag of new is big and equal to zero,
and if that's true you can simply assert
That the optimal value of this problem,
whatever it may be, which no one knows,
it's bigger than this, and if that number
is close to this number that you got by
your heuristic method it's your lucky day,
because now you know that although your
method was heuristic, on that problem
instance you were lucky and you actually
solved the problem either exactly or
to some precision, alright, so that's the
idea...
Okay yeah [COUGH] in general there's a
strong
connection between the Lagrange dual and
the idea of a conjugate.
So, let's see how that works.
If you minimize f0 subject to Ax less than
b,
linear equality and inequality
constraints.
You formula Lagrangian, but because all
the constraints are,
involve linear functions, you're adding a
linear function to an objective,
to a function, and you're minimizing.
But, we have a name for that.
That's called the conjugate function,
right.
Because the conjugate function.
Minimizes rough, it minimizes f of x minus
a linear function of x, right.
I mean okay it maximizes y transpose x
minus fx, it's the same thing, so that's
the conjugate, and what that says is
there's just a little formula for the...
The dual function of a linear of a problem
with linear equality constraints is
very simple formula it's just this minus f
0 star of minus A transpose new minus C
transpose new and then with this linear
part.
Now, you have to be very careful turning
this around with all the minus signs and
so on but this is probably correct.
And if it's not, then it's close, but one
minus sign or
something off, but that's it.
so, don't recommend this because it's
better, I mean, I personally,
I derive dual functions by hand every time
because it's good exercise, and
it's just as hard to use some forumla like
this one.
But let's do one.
Let's do entropy maximization.
So here I want to minimize negative
entropy subject to some equality and
inequality constraints.
Well, that's a,
the, the dual, the conjugate of that is
actually some exponentials.
That's beautiful because it'll it'll allow
me to get the conjugate like immediately.
And so the original problem I had to solve
is linearly constrained with
inequalities and equalities entropy
maximization.
I can get a a dual function and it's going
to involve exponentials.
That's quite interesting.
We get to what's called the dual problem.
Now we've been hinting at this for a while
and it kind of makes sense.
If you think of g of lambda and nu as a
lower bound on p star, right?
If, if it looks like, if that's your
interest and
interpretation of what the dual function
is [UNKNOWN] new parameters.
Then, then you're interested in getting a
lower bound p star than obviously you'd be
interested in getting the best lower
bound.
So, that's the so called Lagrange dual
problem.
It says maximize this lower bound g of
land and
new, subject to the land is bigger than
zero and
you need that constraint there because
otherwise that's not a lower bound.
Okay?
So and you can interpret this problem this
way.
It's, it's finding the best lower bound
based on Lagrange duality.
And by the way, there's no reason for you
to believe at the moment, that it's good.
I mean, but it's just the best lower bound
you can find by the Lagrange duality.
we are going to call optimal value of this
d star and
we obviously have p star bigger than or
equal to d star right so
we will see more about these two numbers
shortly ,ok,lot of times people will do
little bit of transformation for example
If you have an LP, you form its dual, and
its dual is really this, it's maximize g
of lambda new,
subject to lambda bigger than or equal to
zero.
But [UNKNOWN] the g is most of the time
minus infinity.
So if you make those implicit constraints
explicit,
you get something that looks like that,
right.
And so, although it's not quite right to
say, this is,
people would say, this is the Lagrange
dual of that problem.
ok,by the way we can interpret it
beautiful way someone says what does that
mean and you could say i can tell you what
it means it says if
you find a point new is feasible for this
problem it says this objective value is
lower bound on what the optimal problem
That's what that says.
It's quite interesting, right?
Then they say well what is this
optimization problem,
you say oh it's simple That says, pleas
find the best lower bound on this,
on this problem obtained by this method
which is Lagrange duality.
Now, you always have d star is less than p
star, always.
Oh, notice that in principle, d star is
computable.
d star is computable because you're
maximizing a concave function.
Now You can't always maximize a concave
function.
You have to be able to evaluate it and
things like that, and so
I want to be careful and not assert that
it always works.
But in many cases, you can.
Okay, now what this allows you to do is
you can find nontrivial lower bounds for
hard, difficult problems.
So for example, Let's go back to that two
way partitioning problem.
It says, if I solve this problem, that's a
semi-definite program.
That gives you a lower bound for the two
way partioning problem, okay.
And you will, it will not be equal to p
star.
But you'll get a number d star.
Which is less that P star and it's a
really,
it's often a very good lower bound not
always but it's often quite good.
We'll maybe say more about that later.
Now strong duality says, what happens when
D star is P star, what does that mean?
What that says is.
That the lower bound on p star, obtained
by the Lagrange duality, is tight.
It says you have a parametrized lower
bound, but if you adjust the parameters
just right, the lower bound goes right up
to the, to the actual optimum value.
Okay?
And, in fact, by the way, people call p
star minus d star the duality gap.
We'll, we'll, we'll see more about this
later, but that's called the duality gap.
And so strong duality says there is no
duality gap.
Okay?
Now, by the way, for
a non-convex problem like this There's a,
there's a gap.
there's, there's a duality gap.
In this one, there is.
There had to be.
If there was no gap in this problem, then
this would constitute a proof that p
equals np, not that that's impossible, but
it just doesn't happen to
be the case at this moment or when this
was first observed.
Okay, now,
in general, you don't have, there's no
reason to believe that d* is p*.
I mean that, there's no reason to believe
that.
But for convex problems, it usually holds.
Not always, right?
And de, you have to add extra conditions
to the problem (no period) To [COUGH] make
sure, you get d* equals p*, and these are
called constrain qualifications.
That's a, that's a historical term people
use.
And you add those.
You say, if the original problem is convex
and
blah, blah, blah, blah, then D star equals
P star.
Okay, so the sledgehammer of,
of the, of constraint qualifications is
Slater's constraint.
It's the only one we're going to look at,
but we'll look at a minor variation on it.
I mean there's entire courses, whole
semester long courses that do nothing but
look at constraint qualifications.
The whole course is a big glorified study
of when do you get p star equals d star?
And that's very interesting mathematics.
But the sledgehammer is Slater's
constraint and it's real simple.
It says this.
It says that if you take this convex, if
that problem is convex and
if there exists a strictly feasible point.
That merely means there's an x that
satisfies x equals b and
these, these inequalities hold strictly,
right?
If there is such a point that's slate,
that's as Slater's constraint
qualification holds.
And in that case, p star equals d star
period.
Okay?
Now it, supply, it suggests other things
as well, but, okay.
And by the way, there's tons of other
types of constraint qualifications.
They depend on things being affine,
non-affine, various things being bounded.
It goes on and on and on.
But that's, that's the idea.
and i should say there is a variation on
this and its actually useful and
it says the following,it that for you can
exempt for
linear inequalities from the requirement
of this later So in other words, if, if
you're the only inequalities that have to
hold strictly are the nonlinear ones.
And that's like a Slater, that's a, a
sharpened Slater's condition.
And that one is quite useful.
Let's look at inequality form LP.
There's the primal.
There's the dual.
There's the dual problem right here.
And okay, now the question is whether or
not the,
if I solve this problem, do I get the same
objective value as solving this one.
And Slater's condition says the following,
it says there should be a strictly
Feasible point here.
There should be an x with Ax still the
strictly less than b, okay.
Now in fact you can say more here.
The strengthened Slater's inequality says
all these inequalities are linear.
Therefore they are exempted from the
strictness requirement, and And
from the strengthened version, right?
From the strengthened latest condition the
only thing you have to satisfy is that.
And that says, that's the same as saying
the problem is feasible.
So the strengthened Slater's condition
says for
this inequality form LP if it is feasible
Then p star equals d star.
Okay.
Now it turns out, you get p star equals d
star even in cases where something is
infeasible around bound it, but
it can turn out for an inequality lp
there's one pathology and
you can actually have p star as plus
infinity and d star as minus infinity.
That can occur...
But all of these other ones cannot, right?
So, okay, so that's the that's, that's,
that's duality theory, the summary level
for LP.
Let's look at QP.
Let's minimize this quadratic function.
Let's make it strictly convex.
That's to make something, that's to make
minimizing Lagrangian easy.
[INAUDIBLE] linear inequalities.
here, we form the Lagrangian, that's this
thing.
So I take this, affine function, and I
rewrite it.
I augmented the objective with that and
I minimized, that's a quadratic function,
and
I get, I can work out exactly what it is,
I just set the derivative equal to zero,
I get 2px plus lan and I solve it and I
get that, which is a concave quadratic.
So the dual problem looks like that, ok?
Now Slater's condition says The basic
letter says you have to
have something that's a polyhedron.
This says there has to be a point in the
interior of the polyhedron.
Strength, if I strengthen this from the
strong version of Slater's condition,
it's simply this.
It says it has to be feasible.
So, that says that it's feasible, you get
p star equals d star.
But in fact, in this case, it's always the
case.
You always get p star equals d star, by
the way,
including the case when these two numbers
are plus or minus infinity, okay.
So in other words, the following is true.
If the optimal value of this is plus
infinity, right.
that would occur if for example it will
not occur for example it occurs if and
only if Ax<=b is infeasible that set of a
linear inequalities that is only if and
only if optimize this problem that's
interesting so that says this dual
problem is unbounded above when this
primal problem is infeasible and
that is super cool what is i mean to say
the dual problem is unbounded above it
says that you can make the dual objective
as large as you like but
the dual objective is always a lower bound
on the optimal wire i
can make it as large as i like you have to
have historicals So, it's got to be and
in this case you get perfect strong
duality all
the time.
Okay I'm going to mention one more.
I'm not going to go into the details.
This is handled in one of the appendices
in the book in much more detail.
This is an advanced topic.
But it's an, an interesting one so I'll
just talk About it.
You can have strong duality, p star equals
d star,
in cases where the problem is not convex.
So this can actually occur.
Now, if the dual problem is solvable,
which generally it is right, then It,
it, it says the original problem can
actually be solved.
That means it's all very rough, but
the original problem can be solved by
convex optimization.
It's tractable.
That's very interesting.
And, by the way, the general case there is
the following.
Any optimization problem involving exactly
two quadratic functions, so
minimize a quadratic function subject to
quadratic inequality or
something like that Every such problem can
be solved exactly, okay?
And, convex or not.
That's a, I mean there's many ways, what,
there's many ways to understand why
that's true, but [COUGH] one is to
understand the following.
It says that, for all such problems, the
dual problem is actually an SDP.
And you can prove using, in fact, you have
to use the structure of the problem.
You know, some algebraic geometry.
Something like that.
That basically says there's zero duality
gap.
And I should say a little bit about this,
what the connection is to things that
we've seen.
You know, if you think about what are all
the problems that people can
actually solve?
Right.
Well, a huge number of them are convex but
some are not, and
there's some real obvious ones just
glaring out there.
I mean here's one.
If I walk up to you and I say, oh I say,
how do you solve this problem.
Like, you know, maximize x, x transpose P
x subject to say norm x 2 equals 1.
How do you solve that?
Well we know the answer.
I mean you take the largest Eigen value of
P and
x is the Eigen vector associated with
that.
Fine.
This thing is not close to i mean that's
not convex right ,p could be anything ,if
p is negative semi-definite or something
then this is a convex problem but
other than that this works always p can be
positive definite ,it doesn't make any
difference at all And that equality
constraint sure is not convex, right?
yeah, I mean you can relax it to this, and
it becomes convex, right?
But, in general, that's not convex, right?
So, and this is, of course, this is the
basis of all sorts of things.
This is the basis of PCA,
principal component analysis, singular
value decomposition.
These are used everywhere.
All the time.
All sorts of cool stuff.
Okay?
And these are nonconvex problems.
So, if someone asks you, what are you
doing offsetting convex optimization.
Why?
Because a lot of problems are convex.
If they say, are all problems convex?
You say, absolutely not.
And, and
ones that are widely used that are not
convex, examples would be PCA and SVD.
But, what this says is There's at least a
weird technical argument you can
make where you'd argue that PCA and
SDP can't arc, they're solvable because
they're convex.
I mean I don't believe that, that's weird,
but there is a connection.
You can solve them using convex
optimization and it's this.
Let's look at,
return to this specific example, which is
a special case of this by the way.
sort of ,so the dual function here is to
you take the adjective and to that you add
this inequality with a lambda and you get
that ,you get a quadratic function,but you
can minimize a quadratic function right if
its negative i's minus infinity or
otherwise workout what this is and you end
up With a dual problem that looks like
this and it's actually easiest to write it
as an SDP.
It's cleaner.
It says maximize minus t minus lambda
subject to this lmi.
Okay?
Now, that is an SDP.
We can solve this thing.
Here's what's interesting.
The gap, the optimal value of this problem
is actually always exactly equal to
the optimal value of that one.
This one is a non-convex problem.
This one is convex, and tractable, right?
And that says we have a way to solve this
problem.
Now, you know, in some special cases you
already knew that.
I mean you, you know, you don't And
obviously when we teach people linear
algebra and you learn about things like
PCA the first time,
you don't tell students at that point
about things like you know,
SDP duality and things like that, you just
say look we can compute the,
you know, the [UNKNOWN] vectors or
something, that's the solution.
But it is interesting that there is this
connection.
Okay I think we're going to do,
one last thing we're going to do is get a
geometric interpretation of what p
star is, of what d star, and in fact what
a duality gap looks like.
So here's what it is.
We're going to do it for a super duper
simple problem...
With one objective f 0 one constraint f 1
of x is less than 0.
And we're going to write down this in the
following plane this is going to be
the constraint function that is f 1 right.
This axis is going to be f 0.
And so your goal g is going to be the set
of all possible pairs of values of f 1,
f 0 and So your job is to focus only on
ones where the, the first component is
less than equal to 0 and among them find
the lowest value there.
So in other words, we should take this
picture,
we should focus only on the left because
these are feasible points.
And then among those points that gives you
this little thing that goes down like
this, a little nose-like thing.
And then it says, go as, go as low as you
can here.
And the answer is you go right down there,
and then that's p star.
Okay?
Now you see what p star is.
That's what it is.
All right.
So, I mean here's a, here's for example a
point that has a lower value of f zero.
But it's infeasible because this means,
the fact that it's to the right says it's,
f 1 is positive and therefore it's
infeasible, okay, so
this is the picture, this picture right
here,
this little point here is going to show,
is going to be p star.
Okay.
Now let's look at legrange duality,
because on the same plot we can actually
look...
At the lagrange dual problem and see what
happens.
So on the, the lagrange dual says take a
what you do is, you take lamda one and
you take inner product of lamda one with
this vector and minimize it and
the minimum value of that, that's exactly,
that's exactly is g of lamda and so
what it says is you take uh, [COUGH] you
take a vector like this who's normal,
whose slope is in this case because you're
multiplying lambda one,
that's the first thing.
The slope is exactly lamda, negatve lamda
and we minimize it.
Okay?
And so what that says is, I set the slope.
In the slope, then, we find the, in this
whole set here, we find the closest point.
So if lambda is big enough, you get this
value, and as you crank it up,
you would get things like up, up here.
Right?
And you could see that this thing, this
is, this would go like this turn.
It would actually at one point it's
supported at 2 points there and
then it would keep rotating that way and
it turns out in that picture where that
intersects this axis here that's d star
exactly.
Okay?
And so that says for example if I take
lambda that's totally inappropriate like
this one here that's going to lambda, this
continues down there and way down here.
They, they cross and that crossing value,
that's a lower bound on p star.
Well in, indeed it is.
It's a really crappy one.
As I take lambda and change it so I move
like this,
that lower bound gets better and better
and better until right when I'm here.
Right.
I now, I now hit this part and when I keep
rotating, which is changing lambda.
In this case, I am turning lambda down.
I keep rotating and now my, my,
this, the dual objective value, g of
lambda, goes down now.
And it reached its maximum right when it
was touching its [INAUDIBLE] destart and
so now you can see exactly what duality
gap is, right.
The duality gap is exactly the following,
its the gap between this thing that
whenever this whenever horizontally here
and then the best.
A line that was tangent to this set g, and
what you get there is this point,
and this gives you the duality gap as this
distance here.
And, in fact, this picture is enough to
tell you almost everything.
So you can see Its not true that G convex
when F0 and F1 are convex,
what is true is the lower, the lower left
facing face of G, that's convex.
So you can see here, the reason we got a
duality gap here.
Is clear, is because we were able to sort
of hide the solution inside a dent in
this G.
If G is convex or at least its lower left
face is convex, you can't hide,
there's always a supporting hyper plane,
it goes there.
So, that's this picture once you
understand it all, it explains.
Pretty much why, for
convex optimization problems you
generically have zero duality gap.
The, the truth is you can also understand
Slater's condition using this
graph as well.
Okay, so how do you do that next step?
That's simple.
What you do, is we replace that g with its
epigraph.
And what we do is we simply replace
things, it's sort of,
it's these values plus everything up and
to the right.
Now, that set is convex if f one and f
zero are convex, that set is convex.
Okay?
And nothing changes if you do this.
And then, strong duality Basically, is the
following.
It says, if at this point there is a
non-vertical supporting hyperplane,
then strong duality holds.
And Slater's condition says the following:
it says A is convex.
And it also says, it says that not only A
is convex but
it says the very important part.
Which is this, which is that A penetrates
over to the left and,
therefore, at this point, here, it has a
non-vertical supporting hyperplane which
looks like that and, sure enough, that
slope is the optimal Lagrange multiplier,
lambda star and then, in this case, you
get p star equals t star.
So, that's the picture for, that's what
happens when you apply
that's the analysis that even explains the
geometry of the Slater condition.
The next topic is this idea of
complimentary slackness.
And so we'll start assuming the following.
Assume x star is primal optimal.
And we have dual optimal variables, lambda
star, nu star.
And what that means is That f0 of x* -
that is the objective attained by x* - is
equal to g of lambda*, nu*.
And that's the lower bound that you get
from LaGrange duality from (no
period) The, dual variables, lambda star,
and nu star.
And of course, we assume that x star is
primal feasible, lambda star and
nu star have to be dual feasible.
And of course if we have this equality,
that's the end of the story.
We know for sure.
x star is optimal for the primal problem
and
we also know by the way that lambda star
and nu star optimal for the dual problem.
Okay, so now assuming that you have a
primal dual pair.
I'll call it a pair because it's a pair of
a primal variable and
a set of dual variables.
If I have a primal dual pair, let's see
what it means.
Well This dual, function value it that's
by definition.
That's the emphemom over X of this thing.
Well the emphemom over X is certainly less
than if I plug in any particular value of
X, so I'm going to plug in X Star, my
primal optimum point.
I say that this thing is, of course, less
than that.
And in fact, you get equality here if and
only if x* also minimizes the legrontian.
??
We'll come back to that in a bit.
So, right now I'll just say that's less
than or
equal to that, but now we're going to
observe the following.
We're going to observe that.
'x star' is feasible therefore the 'fi's
are less than or equal to zero.
The 'lamda i' is, 'lamda i' is feasible
too.
So 'lamda i' star has been bigger than or
equal to zero and therefore each of these
numbers is less than or equal to zero.
The sum is less than or equal to zero.
This thing is less than or equal to zero
and this term here is zero Why?
Because if x is feasible, h i of x star is
0 and
therefore, this is just 0 and just goes
away.
And we see that this is f 0 of x star plus
something less or equal to 0,
and that's less or equal to that.
And now we have a chain.
And we see that in fact, these must have
been equalities here.
These must have been inequalities, okay,
so
they're inequalities now we go back and
see what it means.
Well it can mean, the only plea, it means
actually two things, and
we get some interesting things.
The first is, it says x star minimizes the
lagrangian...
okay that says if the Lagrangian evaluated
with dual variables the optimal ones
right so that says if we have dual optima
lambda * new * then any optimal x
minimizes the Lagrangian has to be because
the argument i used here was that x
is optimal and lambda * and new * is
optimal Okay.
That's the first one.
And that's what would give you equality
here.
Now, to get equality here, this term must
be zero.
But if the sum of terms that are less than
or equal to zero, if the sum of things
less than or equal to zero is zero, every
single one is less, is equal to zero.
And, in that case, you get something very
interesting.
It says that the individual products
lambda i star and f i star of x,
f i of x star, those are zero.
And that's called complementary slackness,
that's the name for that condition.
And, there's several ways to say it.
But it basically says that you have the
inequality,
you have several inequalities, you have
two inequalities here.
You have lambda i.
Bigger and equal to zero and you have fi
of x less than zero.
And to say that one of these inequalities
is slack is the same as saying that it
holds strictly.
And so what it says is that if one of
these holds,
if one of these holds with some slack, the
other must hold without slack.
You can't have slack on both.
That's basically what this is saying.
In fact the product has to be 0.
So another way to say it is, if the
optimal Lagrange multiplier is positive,
strictly positive, then that constraint
absolutely must be tight.
That's what it says.
Okay?
Conversely, if a constraint, I mean, well,
it's not conversely, it's kind of the same
statement.
It says if, if a constraint is slack,if
there is an optimal point where the i
th constraint is slack that what this less
than equal to 0 restrictly less than 0
means that says,the associative optimal
branch multiply must be 0
ok,now the meaning by all the things is
actually quiet An interesting statement,
because this holds for any optimal x and
any optimal lambda and nu, and
what that says is, if, if, I mean if it's
just a unique optimal x star and
a unique optimal [UNKNOWN] star nu star it
just says these things hold, but
other than that it holds actually for
any optimal x...
Any optimal lambda star new star.
So okay.
So this leads us straight to something
called the the KKT conditions.
It's an interesting story behind this,
Kuhn and
Tucker published worked out these
conditions.
Um,and then Several years later, I mean a
substantially long time later, and in fact
you can look in old books and find these
referred to as the Kuhn-Tucker conditions.
And they, at some point somebody did some
well was poking around somewhere and
found out that Karush had written a
masters thesis at University of Chicago,
completely unpublished, with essentially
the same ideas in it.
And Kuhn and Tucker were nice enough to
append,
actually to prepend [UNKNOWN] name to the
results.
So it's now the KKT conditions.
Okay, so here I have a problem with
differentiable fi, and hi.
'Kay?
So, and it says here, here, here are the,
here are the Karun, the KKT,
the Karush-Kuhn-Tucker conditions.
First of all, primal feasibility.
That's the, you have to satisfy, x
satisfies inequalities and
x satisfies the equality constraints.
Okay?
Dual constraints, dual inequality
constraints I should say.
Lambda has to bigger than or equal to
zero.
Complementary slackness that says that
here,
whenever lambda i is positive, f i is
zero.
That's one way to say it.
You could say it the other way around.
You could say that whenever fi is
negative, you must have lambda i zero.
And the fourth condition is that the
gradient of the Lagrangian with respect to
x vanishes, right?
So that is the gradient with respect to q,
x Of L,
and that's given by the gradient of f0
plus sum lambda i
gradient fi of x plus sum of this nu i
times the gradient hi of x equals 0.
Okay?
So, these conditions all together,
that's called the KKT conditions, and what
we saw on the previous slide here is
the following: that if f, if, if the fi,
if the problem is convex and X landa and
new are optimal, which really means x is
primal optimal, landa new is dual optimal.
If that's the case, then these four
conditions hold, right?
This holds.
The idea, this holds because we saw here
that whenever this holds when you
have zero duality gap.
X star must minimize the lagrangian here.
This is a convex function.
Right?
And if f, if f zero f i and
h i are differentiable, the idea that x
zero star minimizes this says that if i
plug in x zero star here and take the
gradient, I better get zero.
Right?
So that, that recovers this condition.
So, what that says is for a convex
optimization problem,
if x lambda nu are optimal, KKT conditions
hold.
Now the converse is also true.
You have to be kind of careful about this,
but the converse says this.
If I have three points, x tilde, lambda
tilde, nu tilde, and
they satisfy the KKT conditions, and it's
a convex problem Then they're optimal.
And you have to go back and check various
things.
From complementary slackness, you can show
the following,
that f zero of x tilde is l of x tilde
lambda tilde new tilde.
>> That's easy because, well the only
difference here are the sum lambda i
tilde times fi of Fi of x tilde but
that product is zero, that's by our
assumption of complementary slackness.
And the other one holds too because of
primal feasibility of
the equality constraints.
So you get this.
From the fourth condition, that says that
that,
it says that the gradient of the
Lagrangian evaluated with dual variables,
lambda tilde and nu tilde, the gradient
with respect to x vanishes at x tilde, but
it's a convex function, the Lagrangian
with respect to x,
and if its gradient is zero, you must have
minimized it.
So, that tells us that x tilde minimizes
that, and that tells you that If x
tilde minimizes it, then this thing is
equal to g, the lower bound.
And we are now done, because we've shown
that g of lambda tilde,
which is a lower bound on the optimal
value, is equal to f zero of x tilde,
where x tilde's primal feasible, and
that's the end of the story.
X, x, x tilde is primal optimal.
And by the way lambda tilde and v tilde
are dual opt.
>> Optimal.
So, okay, so that is the argument for
this.
So roughly speaking, you can say that
Slater's condition sorry the KKT
conditions are the necessary and
sufficient conditions for
optimality for a convex optimism problem
with equality and inequality constraints.
So now it assumes that the fi, the
objective and
the constraint functions are all
differentiable.
Right?
And it's a nice extension of the standard
optimality condition for an unconstrained
problem which is the gradient as zero.
Right?
So that's the idea.
Okay.
Now, in a few cases The KKT conditions
allow you to solve a problem.
Now they're not the most interesting
problems.
And there's other ways we can think of
them.
But they do give you I mean they do come
up.
And they're interesting to look at.
So, here's an example.
This one comes up in, for example,
wireless communications.
What you've got is you want to minimize
the sum.
Log XI plus Alpha I or Alpha I or a bunch
of positive constants that you're given.
And the Xs have to be bigger or equal to 0
and they have to sum to 1.
Right, this is, this is the,
they get summed to any other number, this
is good enough.
And so that's the question, right.
So how do you, how do you solve this.
Oh, by the way, if you're curious what
these things are.
X could be the power in a channel.
And you want to allocate the power across
a bunch of channels.
And the alpha has to do with the signal to
noise, the signal sorry, the noise level.
In that channel, right, and this says how
do you optimize the maximum,
how do you get the maximum bit rate by
allocating power to different channels.
Okay.
Alright.
Well let's write, let's just write down
the KKT conditions.
Write down the KKT conditions, you need a
lambda and a [UNKNOWN],
there's a lambda associated with the
inequality constraints and a [UNKNOWN],
a single scaler [UNKNOWN] associated with
this single constraint here...
Okay, so, x is optimal, if and only if
it's not a negative.
It's [UNKNOWN] one.
That's primal feasibility.
And there exists a vector landed in our
end, which is now negative.
Right?
And a single number new and they have to
have the following property.
This is simply writing down the partial
derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to,this is simply the partial
Lagrangian with respect to x and
you get the following condition,we get the
condition here this is
complementary slackness and that is the
gradient of Lagrangian respect to
x is zero now we stare at these thing and
we can work various things out Let's see,
if I told you that if for example, well we
can work out, the conditions actually
just depend on this one, right.
If xi is zero, here, then we get one over
alpha i plus lambda i equals new.
And so we can work out what lambda i is,
and if lambda i would be
new minus one over alpha i So that, that,
that gives you alpha i.
Sorry that gives you lambda i.
Okay.
On the other hand when x is positive you
have to have lambda 0 and for those if
lambda is 0, again we can get what x is,
x is one over from this equation, x is one
over nu minus alpha i.
And the only thing that we haven't
satisfied yet, is this condition here.
oh, and we can work out what these two
conditions are because it's going to
depend on whether nu is less than one over
alpha or bigger than one over alpha.
That's the conditions under which you end
up with something.
That satisfies this with alpha being
bigger than or
equal you know with, using the fact that
the alphas are positive.
Okay, so what that says is, if you work
out what these values are,
it says we're going to determine nu from
one transpose x,
but if x has either this value or this
value it's e-, it's this.
It's the max of 0 and 1 over new minus
aplha i.
And we simply have the some of those as
equal to 1.
Okay, now, you'd notice a couple of things
here.
We're going to adjust new to make this
true.
Now, that can be done y, because if I
increase Nu,
this goes down therefore, everything here
goes down.
So the sum is monotone decreasing.
If Nu is, you know, gigantic I get if Nu
is extremely large, right,
then this is max of 0, then this is just.
Zero, this le-, left-hand had zero, so
you're way under one.
On the other hand, if nu is tiny, then one
over lambda, nu,
one over nu is a very big number.
You subtract alpha i and this is a very
big number, and you're way over one.
So you can simply use bisection, it's
monotone.
Okay, and there's a beautiful
interpretation which give the name of
this method water-filling and the idea is
something like this.
You draw a profile of the alphas.
So, these are, these are the alphas,
right?
This is i, that's i equals one, two,
three, that doesn't matter of course.
And then what happens is,
it's says that you choose a value, new,
that's right here.
You write 1 over nu here and then you
imagine that you take this thing and
you flood it to this level.
Okay?
So you, you flood it to this level and
what you do is you,
is this, this amount here That is actually
x i.
All right?
So, and the, and the idea is you take a
total unit of one amount of water and
you dump it on this thing, and
when it all settles out, the sum of all
these will be one.
And that's exactly what we have here.
And the depth will be the correct value of
x i.
So you can see here that for example X3 is
zero, right?
So are these two, whatever they are.
They're zero, and that's the idea, okay?
So this so, it's water filling.
If you've taken a class on information
theory, you have definitely seen this.
Now the last topic,
in duality that we're going to look at in
standard duality before we look at
other variations on it is this idea of
perturbation and sensitivity analysis.
This is extremely useful.
It's also a very good way to think of it
and it is, has huge practical use.
So let's see what it is.
We start with the, an unperturbed problem.
That's this one.
Okay?
And it's dual.
There's the dual.
So the unperturbed problem says here is
some constraints, inequality constraints.
Here's equality constraints.
And what we're going to do now is we're
going to perturb the problem.
And let me explain what that means.
We are going to change the right hand side
Here from zero to ui,
here and in the quality constraints from
zero to vi.
Okay?
Now when you do this.
I mean, these are just constants.
They go there and you can figure out
exactly how they affect the dual function.
You get a new dual that's that.
That's the new dual problem, okay?
So.
And
what we're going to do is we're going to
let p star of u,v, that's going to
be the optimal value of this perturbed
problem as a function of u and v.
Okay, so that's the idea.
Now, we'll be able to show pretty quickly
that's a convex problem,
it's a convex function of u and v.
And what, what we want to do is get some
information about p star u and v.
And first, before we do that,
let me say a little bit about the
interpretation of what it means.
here, if, let's concentrate not on the vi,
which is actually hard to interpret, but
let's look at the conc-, let's concentrate
on what ui means here.
If ui Here is equal to, let's say, 0.1.
The question is, what does that mean?
Well, if let's take it u1 is 0.1.
If u1 is 0.1, it means precisely the
following.
It is, your first,
your original constraint was f1 of x had
to be less than or equal to zero.
F1 of x, is basically,
the idea is that 0 is right when you've
reached some resource.
And what it says, that if you perturb it
by making that point 1,
it says you've given about point 1 more
units, well,
you've given point 1 more units of
resource.
To the 1st, whatever the 1st constraint
handles, right, so
you have more resources or you could say
its a relaxation because the feasible set
is bigger, but whatever happens, I
gaurantee you, this thing goes down.
Right, because I give you its a circuit
design problem and the 1st constrain
express the power constraint and I tell
you I'm going to give you 0.1 more power.
You better come up with a better design.
Not a better design, but certainly you can
come up,
you can, you shouldn't come up with a
worse design, right?
So, that's what that is.
So you would say that when ui is positive,
you would say something like,
I have loosened the ith inequality, ith
constraint.
On the other hand, if ui is negative, you
have tightened the ith inequality.
That's what that means.
Tightening it means You've restricted the
resources, and so one.
Now, by the way, if I tighten this
problem, if I tighten the constraint,
there's no reason to believe that this
thing cannot go to plus infinity.
I can tight, I can tighten the constraint,
and the whole problem becomes unfeasible,
and this number, p* of u, v will then be
plus infinity.
Okay?
So alright, so what we're interested in
then and one, one way to interpret what
p star is p star tells you how the optimal
value changes when you tighten or
loosen the inequality constraints and you
can interpret v i as a shift.
In inequality constraints.
So that's what that is.
Okay.
Now, as a result here it's actually quite
easy to work out.
You just simply apply weak duality to the
perturbed problem.
And you get the following.
P star of u and v.
That's the optimal value of the perturbed
problem.
It's at least as big as P star of 0 0.
That is the unperturbed problem.
Minus u transpose lambda star, minus v
transpose lambda star.
And this holds for any lambda star new
star [INAUDIBLE] dual optimal, for
the unperturbed problem.
Okay?
Now this is an inequality.
It says, in fact, it's a, it says that
when you
Perturbed the problem your results will be
at least this bad.
It's a bound on how good they could be,
because this says if this were able to go
down a lot that would be good.
And what this says is it puts a lower
bound on it.
That's what it does.
There's no upper bound on this.
You can perturb This, by the slightest
amount, and
you can have p star equals plus infinity,
and so there's no upper bound here.
It's just that.
Okay.
So, let's see what it means, and
you have to be very careful because it's
asymmetrical.
Or I should say, this is a global result.
It's simply You think about it as being
interesting when U and
V are small, those are perturbations to
the problem, but
in fact, these are, these can be gross
perturbations.
I can add U equals 7, UI equals 7,
I can do all sorts of things and these
inequalities hold.
So lets see what they mean.
Well, first of all, it says the following.
If Lambda I star is large.
Then it says it says that if you tighten a
constraint,
let's forget the equality constraints.
But let's tighten a constraint.
That means if you tighten like, it means u
i goes less than or equal to 0.
And this is minus a negative number.
Times a positive number, in fact, a large
positive number, and a,
a pretty good well, here, if, if I tighten
it.
It says, and then it says this thing will
be worse, this, this will go up, right?
This'll be positive, this'll go up, and in
fact, it'll go up a lot.
So for example, if I tell you that lambda
* is 100.
Let's say, lambda1* (no period) And
I've tightened the constraint by a mere
point one.
Then what it says is the optimal value of
the new problem absolutely must
go up by at least ten the op that's the
optimal class must go up by ten.
It can go up by much more.
It can go up to infinity, for example,
if by tightening that first constraint,
that rendered the problem infeasible.
Okay, on the other hand, if lambda i is
small here it,
it says that P star does not decrease that
much if you loosen the constraint,
right, so that says if this is a small
number, here, then it says,
if U even if U is big and positive it
guarantees that
the optimal costs can't go down much.
Right.
By the way,
the converse assertions you cannot say
here.
You can't conclude.
Okay.
And these are, this is, you'd make the
same conclusions for
these things for the inequalities, right,
I won't go through that because actually
the inequalities are probably more
important to understand...
Okay.
Now, we can also get a local sensitivity
result, and
this is extremely useful in practice.
Let's see what this does.
So let's assume that the optimal value is
differentiable at zero zero.
Now by the way,
there's many cases where it's not so this
is not just a mathematical pathology.
This can occur in real problems, right?
And, let's see what it, then it turns out
that we can say what lambda i star and
nu i star are exactly.
They are the partial derivative of the
optimal cause with respect to u i
with a negative sign, and the same for nu
i star, and
that's the, the, it's partial p star,
partial v i.
And that's also with a minus sign.
Okay?
Now how do you know that?
Well, that's easy enough we simply
subtract these two things divide by t and
this thing is, this, I, I let t goes, get
less, go to zero, being positive right.
This says This number here is always,
actually always, bigger than that number,
and they're, or its limit is.
And here, if I let t go up, this number
here is always less than lambda i*
therefore, so is this limit, and
therefore, the limit is equal.
These are just equal to minus lambda*.
And the picture would look something like
this: here's a single constraint f (no
period) 1 is less, f1 of x is less than or
equal to u.
That's the perturbed version.
And this gives you p 0 star, right?
So that is, that's p star of 0.
That's the original optimal value.
Now, you can see now that as you move, as
you, as you loosen the constraint or
tighten it If you loosen it, of course,
the objective goes down.
By the way, that requires you to
re-optimize right there.
Everything here is with the idea that if
you change the constraints,
you solve the problem again.
It doesn't mean you get the same answer.
If you tighten the problem, the optimal
value of p goes up.
And it is smooth here and differentiable.
You can see here, the [UNKNOWN] multiplier
is, let's say 3,
right, because it's the negative slope of
that line, right.
And what the global result here says,
what this global result says is it gives
you the following inequality.
It simply says that this curve, P star of
U is convex.
That's what it says, and
it says that, in fact, the 1 given by the
legrange multiplier is here.
Is it tangent?
That's essentially what it says.
And you can see how it could be, for
example your landa star's about three I'm
just guessing from the picture here.
If I, this p star could go up to plus
infinity just like that right?
And then I could,
what I could do is say well I'm going to
tighten that constraint a little bit.
Right?
And in fact, the value of p star there,
it could be plus infinity means the
problem is infeasible right?
And it's also true that this could go like
that, and that means lambda star is three.
I would loosen it considerably, sort of
expecting the optimal cost to go down, but
it doesn't go down that much.
Okay, so this the, this is the idea.
Now what's now I'm going to say something
about the practical import of this.
What we're going to see later is the
following.
When you solve a convex optimization
problem,
typically at absolutely zero cost you will
get a set of optimal Lagrange multipliers.
>> [INAUDIBLE] Dual variance.
It, that's, it's automatically returned
with most methods, and things like that.
And that's actually unbelievably useful in
practice, 'because what happens is it
means that you have a bunch of constraints
or we can, we can, by the way,
check our complementary slackness
condition with this right now.
For example If I have a optimal point, and
f one of x star is minus one, that means,
the first constraint wasn't active.
And now imagine that I perturb the right
hand side.
Instead of zero, I'd plug in minus 0.1 or
plus 0.1.
It won't make Any difference and
that tells you partial p star, partial p
one is zero.
What that says exactly what complimentary
slack says.
It says that if the first [UNKNOWN] is
slack,
the first optimal dual variable absolutely
must be zero okay?
So that's, that's quite highly consistent
with this.
Back to this, practical use.
So the practical use goes something like
this.
You have a big problem, you solve it and
there's a whole bunch of constraints.
Let's suppose they're inequality
constraints.
And you look at them.
Some are slack, some are tight.
'Kay?
So the slack ones, we know what it means.
What it means is that Those inequalities,
we impose them in the problem but
we didn't need to in a sense because they
didn't affect the optimal value, okay.
By the way, that does not mean you wasted
your time.
Because had you, you didn't know ahead of
time before you solved the problem that
they were going to be slack.
Okay.
But now you look at all the ones that are
slack.
And you ask yourself something like what
would happen if I tightened or
loosened each one?
And the answer can be can range.
From the following.
If I tighten it a small amount, the
problem will simply become infeasible.
That's the extreme case.
On the other hand, I could loosen an
inequality considerably, expecting
the alpha value to go down and it won't go
down very much, might not go down at all.
That could happen.
Okay.
So
those 2 things can happen, but for small
pertibations, these things tell you.
How the optimal value changes, right, and
[COUGH], it allows you to actually, it's a
beautiful interpretation.
it allows you to say that the Lagrange
multipliers tell you how
tight a constraint is.
So for example, if I, I could solve a
problem.
Let, let's say I'm doing circuit design
and I want to satisfy something and
Minimize some objective, and what I'm
going to do is,
I have two constraints, a power limit, and
I have an area limit.
And when I come back, both of them are
tight.
That's it.
So out of a 50 milliwatt budget,
your design comes back using all 50
milliwatts, it's hardly suprising.
You had a 1 millemeter squared.
Area constraint.
You come back using one square millimeter.
Okay?
Again, hardly surprising.
You were given these resources, you use
them.
And the question then is what this answers
for
you automatically is questions like this.
What if I were to increase or decrease the
area or the power budget?
Right, so, and in fact what might happens
is that [UNKNOWN] 1 star is 0.01 and
lambda 2 star, right, this is power and
this is [UNKNOWN] and
lambda 2 star is 100.
Yeah it's extreme, but let's suppose that
came back, right.
Let's see what it says.
What it says is that...
>> This says, now remember that the power
and area constraints are both tight.
They're both tight.
They're, they're, you know, you gave 50
milliwatts you used 50 milliwatts,
you gave a square millimeter, a square
millimeter is what you used.
So they're both tight.
But what this says is that in some sense
the power,
the power constraint is less tight.
Because this says I, it probably says that
I could decrease the amount of Power.
I allocate to it, and we could get just
about the same objective, right?
And also a negative result says this, if I
increase, I suppose I say,
you know what, I want better performance.
I'm going to double the amount of power
you get from 50 to 100 milowatts.
Surely if I give you twice the power, you
can get a better design.
And what this tells you is you cannot.
Now, this tells you that what's really
killing you in this problem is area.
And so this says, this tells you for sure,
if I were to have the area I gave you,
like I said, nope, I'm sorry, we can't do
it, the economics doesn't work,
you can't have a whole square millimeter,
I'm going to give you half.
This is going to guarantee you that the
objective is absolutely guaranteed to
get a, do a lot worse.
So that would be it.
Now, you could also say, oh because it's
so
tight it says that if I give you more area
you should do better.
That's actually only a local result.
It's not global.
So, for example you'd expect it and it
might happen but again we don't know.
It's a local result so.
Okay.
So, the recap of that is that these
optimal Lagrange multipliers,
which come for free when you solve a
problem typically.
Actually give you a very nice and
indeed quantitative measure of how tight
the constraints are with 0, lambda i star,
you know, if lambda i star is 0, meaning
somehow it's not, it's not tight right and
lambda very big meaning it's a very tight
constraint very constraining.
What we're going to look at first is the
idea of duality and reformulations.
Alright so
here, let's, let me draw a picture here to
show you how this might work.
Let's take a problem, p, like this that's
a primal problem And
then, let's form some equivalent problem
like this.
So this, this this bi-directional arrow
basically says that P
prime is some problem equivalent to P.
Now you've seen lots of equivalent
problems, for example,
you can eliminate variables, you can add
new variables, you could give an objective
as non negative, you might square it or
something like that, minimizing the.
Square is the same as minimizing the thing
as long as its a negative.
Is lots of things, there are lots of ways
to produce equivalent problems, right.
Okay, now, duality, through duality we can
make it dual.
So there's the primal problem and there's
the dual.
And of course we can do that down here,
right?
So this is D prime, right?
So, that's our original problem.
This is our reformulation, right?
And this reformulation could be simple.
I mean it could be also very
sophisticated.
Right?
Okay.
Now, when you see a picture like this,
then if you're,
if you have any training in math or just
sort of minimal aesthetics You
have an overwhelming urge to do the
following, to draw an arrow like this.
Right?
When you do this is just, you don't need
to know this, but it's not bad to know.
This is called a commutative diagram.
It says that basically, you can get,
that you could say that this dual can be
found, you know, two ways.
It's either the, the dual of the primal Or
you could go this way.
You could reformulate the primal, from
the, the dual of the reformulation and
then somehow that's related to this one,
you know, something like that.
Now of course in some dense D and
D prime are related because they're
related this way.
Right?
So, so this is very general, very vague
idea of, of what you'd like to happen.
Okay, so the now I'll tell you the bad new
is that this is completely Wrong.
This doesn't happen.
This is, this is not accurate.
And there's in general no such thing.
Now it turns out that's actually very good
news, and
we're going to see why in a minute.
So it turns out that if you take a
problem, it's in fact,
at first it sounds strange.
If you take a problem, actually just form
a very simple Form a,
a very simple variation on the problem.
It's a equivalent.
Right?
You, you add a variable,you make
the epigraph version i mean just something
that's totally obvious.
Right?
Or you just do something simple.
Then it turns out these duals can be
wildly different.
We're going to see examples of that soon.
They can be wildly different.
And at first, that's too bad, right?
Because you want, you wanted to idea of a
dual to be intrinsic.
It's not really.
It depends very much on the description of
the problem.
and, but we'll see actually that it's a
very good thing.
Right?
Because it opens up the ability,
given a problem, here, of forming many
many different kinds of duals.
And, the method is very simple.
You take the original problem.
You then transform it, often, as we'll
see, in a very trivial way, and
then form a dual of that transformation
and
you get something completely different
then if you had done the dual here.
This one, for
example, we'll see cases where this one is
actually useful and informative.
Where this one is completely trivial and
completely uninformative.
So, this is the big picture idea that
we're going to look at.
Okay.
so, let's let's look at a, a case.
This is an extreme case, but it,
it proves this, it kind of, it illustrates
this point.
So here, suppose you want to minimize F0
of ax plus b,
right, well, there are no constraints, so
what's the Lagrangian?
Well the Lagrangian is the function.
That's the, that's the Lagrangian.
Because it's, there are no constraints so
we don't even have to, we have no dual
variables, right.
That's the Lagrangian and
now you're asked to minimize the
Lagrangian over the primal variables...
That would give you the dual function.
All right.
So, you minimize that, and you get the
minimum here.
It's called p star.
Okay?
So, the dual function for this is simply p
star.
Now, good news is, we have zero duality
gap, right?
Because the, if I ask you to maximize the
constant p star over, well, no variables,
'cuz there are no dual variables That's
easy to do the answer is p *.
And then you say hey look at that, that's
fantastic that's the, that's the minimum,
that's the primal optimal object, that's
the primal optimal objective.
So, so now you can see it, but it's
completely useless right.
Okay now what we're going to do is this
we're going to simply take this
problem and rewrite it this way.
Okay?
So, the only thing we've done here is you
introduced a new variable, y.
And a bunch of equal, this second
constraint, it just says y is ax plus b,
yeah ax plus b.
I mean, the equivalence of this problem
and
this problem are, is completely
transparent, right.
It's just totally obvious.
It's so simple, it's ridiculous.
And then you say well And this is if you
like, that's P,
this is P prime in the picture I drew
before.
And now you say, let's find P prime star,
which would be, I guess, B prime, right.
So lets find that.
So lets take this thing and form the dual,
well the dual turns out to be this and,
I'm not going to go into the details but
by now you shouldn't be surprised that
something like this would happen, you can
write it explicitly.
Its maximize B transpose Nu minus.
The conjugate here of, of f, of the
objective of nu,
subject a transpose nu equals 0, okay, so
this one here, is in fact,
first of all, it's not, the duel of this
one is absolutely silly, right,
it's silly the constant, which is the
optimal value, um...
This one is actually useful informative it
is
not hard to imagine applications of this,
right?
When you're solving some gigantic problem
and you just want to stop in criterion or
something like that, so the point is you
look at your algorithm and if at
any point You can find something that's in
the null space of A transposed new,
you simply evaluate this number and
that's absolutely guaranteed to be a lower
bound on the optimal value here alright?
So, so this is a case where A,
where dualization And trivial
transformation.
They definitely don't commute right in, in
this case.
They, they do not commute.
You, you get, if you transform it and
then form a dual, you get something that
is actually useful, interesting,
informative, if you don't transform you
get something that is completely silly.
okay, now here, I mean, we can work out
the, the, the dual function here.
You simply form the [UNKNOWN] which is
this thing and
then you minimize over x is what happens.
Right?
And you minimize over sorry x and y is a
new introduced variable,
if you minimize over x this thing is
either minus infinity or it's 0.
If it's minus infinity, if ,if a transpose
new is non 0 right,
if a transpose new is 0 Then this term
drops out, and
then you'll recognixe this as related to
the conjugate function of f0, right?
So, again, that's just a calculation, and
you can check on it, and
all that sort of stuff.
Okay, so, this is a good example,
where (no period) A transformation before
you apply before you compute a,
determine a Lagrange dual makes a hu, a
world of difference, right?
So, by the way, what this means is that
while people talk a lot of times and
they say, here's a problem, and then
informally you'd say the dual is this.
And it turns out that's really not quite
right.
that, that's loose speech, and often,
well, it can mean this, I mean,
technically when you say the dual is this,
it means you follow the script perfectly.
You simply, you form the Libron gene, you
minimize over the you
minimize over the primal variables to get
a dual function, and
you maximize that subject to lamda bigger
than equal to 0.
Those are the Lagrange multipliers
associated with
the inequality constraints.
Right?
That, in some sense,
that you just turn the crank on Lagrange
duality, that's the dual.
but people are informal and they will
allow you to do little bit of
transformation before you perform the dual
and
sometimes a little bit of transformation
after you form the dual and
this is then a static thing we will often
be in the situatuion where someone will
say here is the primal and here is the
dual And
what they really meant to say, maybe, was
here's the primal and here's a dual.
Right?
And so, that, by the way you'll notice
that sometimes when you hear
people attach a name to a dual.
So they'll say here's a quadratic program,
and here is the Franke-Wolfe dual.
Or here is the, you know, whatever it is,
such and such dual.
Right?
So that, that's your hint.
That, that they're being a little bit
loose with the idea of a dual.
So, okay.
Alright, let's look at a couple of others.
Let's take a norm approximation problem.
So you want to minimize the norm of Ax
minus b.
And again we'll introduce an equality
constraint.
so, we'll write this as minimize the norm
of y.
Subject to y equals Ax minus b, where y
and x are now the variables.
By the way, I mean, this, this is,
we're going to see this again when we
actually solve these problems.
That you know if you were confronted with
this problem,
you might have an overwhelming urge
immediately to get rid of y.
Right?
Because, it's silly.
Why is x minus b, why, why not just plug
that in the top, and I mean, you have a,
this problem has fewer variables, you
know, all this kinds of stuff.
So you might be tempted to do that.
And in fact, you're training your pencil
and
paper 19th century kind of silly
mathematics education you've had.
Up until probably recently possibly until
now.
But probably, certainly most undergraduate
courses are like that.
You know, you would of course do that
because, you know, in the pencil and
paper world or the chalkboard world you
know, that's simpler than that.
It turns out though that's often not the
case when you're actually either solving
the problem, we're going to talk about
that in the last third of the course.
Or in fact even here when you're actually
doing things like forming duels and
things like that.
If you're actually better off, sometimes
working at a problem that appears by
19th century asthetic to be more complex.
You may be better off.
We'll see why that is later.
Okay, so let's, This thing.
I mean minimizing a function subject to a
quality constraint is
just a completely uniform dual.
And it's in term, it comes up in terms of
the you can work it
out in completely generally in terms of
the conjugate of the function.
And we'll get to that.
But the conjugate of a norm,
is in fact, indicator function of the dual
norm [UNKNOWN].
And some of these things by the way will
start, should start lodging in your mind.
I mean that you should start building maps
of things, and if,
if not the exact details.
Then at least just patterns.
you, you should know these patterns.
So that when you see a, a max in one, you
should expect in the dual to see
something like a probability distribution,
or something that sums to one.
Right?
So when you see a norm in one.
You should expect to see a dual norm
constraint in the other.
When you see a norm squared in one,
you should expect to see a norm, dual norm
squared in the other.
So, you don't have to [INAUDIBLE] same if
you see an equality constraint in
one with A, you should expect something
involving a transpose in the dual.
So, these are just general patterns You
could always just calculate,
in fact you should probably do that just
to be sure you got it right.
But these are patterns you should start,
I, I, I don't memorise them but
you should at least start picking up on
these high level patterns.
By the way if you do that,
what's kind of cool is you'll start seeing
them in every other course you take.
Right?
They won't call it the conjucate,
they won't call it the dual, it'll have
another name.
But you'll look at it and say, I've seen
that, I know what that is right?
That, that's the dual and you'll see it in
you know,
in your statistic classes, certainly in
economics and, and in lots of classes.
So okay.
>> So here let's just work out the The
dual and so
here what you would do is you would you,
you minimize the objective here.
Plus this is,
you put an equality constraint, a new
transpose times an equality constraint and
that's, that's all of this thing here,
right, written out.
And now we are asked to minimize over x
and y, x is easy, right?
And we keep using this very simple idea.
that you know this Lagrangian here is an
alphine function of x and
as silly as it sounds it is useful to know
how to minimize an alphine function ,very
easy actually,here is the answer minus
infinity right and
less the linear part of the alphine
function Vanishes, right.
So, so no problem here.
This says unless this vector, sorry, I
meant to, do these, right.
Unless A transpose new is zero,
the minimum over x of this thing is minus
infinity.
Right?
So, alright.
So, and then, if,
assuming A transpose new is zero, then
that term just goes away, right?
So that tells you that you get something
like this.
If A transpose new is zero, then you have
the norm of y plus new transpose here.
Times, and I guess you could write this as
y plus b or something like that.
Whatever it is.
and, oh sorry, this one can just cut, this
side, that's just a constant, and
that can come out here.
And you end up with something like this.
And whenever you see the [UNKNOWN] of a
convex function plus a linear term,
you can rewrite that as a conjugate,
right.
Or in this case, we can work it out
directly.
A norm here is a, is homogeneous, so if
you multiply something by three.
It the value is,
you know, three times the, its, the value
is by a factor of three.
Its homogeneous, so is this, and so what
happens here is,
if, here, Nu is big enough in the dual
norm so that you can make this thing.
any number if it is negative then i can
make it minus infinity by
homogenating right and so
it tells you that by this thing here which
is actually related to conjugate of
the norm is simply the indicator function
of dual norm unit wall,right so
we are going to end up with this And so
the dual of norm approximation problem is
this, is you maximize here b transpose new
subject to A transpose new equals zero and
new star less than or equal to one, right?
And so this, that, we're making various
assertions here.
What we're saying is something like this.
For this problem, if you find any vector
by any means,
any vector new in the null space of A
transpose Whose dual norm is less than 1.
Then b transpose nyu is a lower bound on
the [INAUDIBLE] of that problem.
Period, right because that's, that's
assertion number 1.
Assertion number 2 is our actually is a
value of nyu here for
which its actually equal to the lower
bound, right and
in fact by carefully analyzing what would
happen here you can actually recover.
What, partly, you can recover what the
optimal x is,
if I gave you the optimal mean.
So this is, this is the, this is the idea.
Another variation on this is dealing with
implicit constraint.
So that works this way: is that you can.
And oh, there's a name for this sometimes
eh.
Some people call this partial, a partial
LeGrangian and partial dualization.
so what that says is this,here is my
original problem and
it doesn't really matter what it is it's a
kind of little linear problem it
says minimize c transpose x subject
Ax=b,linear quality constraints and
the constrain that x is in the box so all
the interests of x are between plus and
minus 1 well if i simply form the dual,i
will get what it looks this,okay fine,no
problem,that's it,but there is an other
way to do this ,what you do is ,what we
will do is we take these constraints these
are explicit constraints what we will do
is we will put them implicitly in the
adjective,so i will take this problem and
i will transform into this problem,they
are diffrent problems and
it is extemely important to understand
These are different problems but they are
equivalent.
In this problem, the only, there's only
one quality constraint and
the objective is either, c transpose x
plus infinity but
I've added in this thing here, and so it's
very important to understand that,
you know, as objects say, you don't have
equals equal here.
Right?
This one, this problem, if you ask how
many constraints do you have,
the answers two.
Right?
If I say how many constraints you have
here, the answers one.
If I ask here is, if I say you know
problem dot objective dot is linear,
it's true here and it's absolutely false
here.
Everybody see what I'm talking about?
But they're clearly, completely
equivalent.
In the sense that, you know, an optimal
point here is an optimal point here, and
vice versa.
Okay?
So, it's actually quite important to be
very clear in
your mind about equivalences, verses,
being the same.
Right so, okay, so these two I mean it's
just really dumb, it's just a dumb way to
and the only way you would know any
difference would be something like this.
If I were to throw, if I, if I had this
problem and I said problem not eval and
I threw in an x which was outside the box.
Here.
I, it would retur, what would be returned
would be something like an error token.
And it would say something like
infeasible, right?
And it would violate this constraint,
right?
Here, if I give you, if I give you an x
that satisfies a x equals b,
but some x's are bigger than 1 or -1,
right?
And what would happen in this case is I
get a new, I get a new thing,
I get something back that says it would be
an error just as well.
but it wouldn't be the error your
infeasible in fact I get what would come
back would be a token telling me, oh thank
you, x is feasible.
That's the good news, bad news is it's out
of the domain of the objective or
another way to say it is the objective
values plus infinity.
And if you're minimizing that's about as
bad as it can get.
So everybody, fo, following this.
Right, so it's important to understand
these are different.
They're different but also when you learn,
you know, when you're kind of in
a situation where people are doing, you
know, street fighting type stuff.
You don't even think about this, right?
You just quietly do this, or, so.
oh, so if you take this problem, and
then you form the dual function here, you
actually have a different,
you don't even have a dual variable
associated with these inequalities.
Right?
So you just get this.
The dual function is this but, now this
thing if you like I put it there,but you
really should be an indicator function
over here.
Right?
Should be an indicator function of the,
the box.
Right?
Like that.
So here it asks you to do this, but
minimizing a linear function an ad-fine
function [UNKNOWN] trivial we know how to
solve that and you actually get this.
Right?
And so
the dual problem after, after this Minor
reformulation is this.
It says that the dual problem of this is
that.
It says maximize this thing and everything
works, right?
Now, fact is if you stare at this long
enough you'll realize that this is
the same as that.
so, you know, in this case you do have the
communitive diagram.
The, the p DP prime and P prime, you
actually get a communicative,
a simple communicative diagram, right, but
it doesn't always happen.
Okay.
So by the way this,
this thing here is called a partial
legrangian, and, or
another way people would say what would
happen is you say I
start with this problem and I'm going to,
I'm going to form, I'm going to dualize...
Keeping the inequalities implicit.
So that, that would be how people would
say this.
There, there'd be various descriptions for
it.
That's if people are being clear, right?
Okay.
Next topic is generalized inequalities.
So, so far everything in duality has
happened with
ordinary scalar inequalities.
So, constraint functions return numbers.
If the number is negative, it's feasible,
if it's positive, infeasible.
But now we'll look at problems with
generalized inequalities.
Right?
So here these are potentially
vector-valued and the constraint is that
that vector has to be negative, or
less than or equal to 0 but with respect
to some cone.
And the, the obvious nontrivial case is
the positive semidefinite cone.
Right?
So that can be a matrix inequality.
Okay.
And it turns out all the notation is set
up perfectly.
This is how you know you have good
notation,
is that everything looks exactly the same.
You make a few minimal changes, and it's
actually correct.
Right?
So, here what you do is these,
the left and right hand side of that
constraint is a vector, it's an Rk.
KI and so what we'll do is the Lagrange,
the associated Lagrange multiplier dual
layer is a vector, okay, and the
Lagrangian is the obvious thing.
It's this.
It's the completely obvious inequality,
that you would have.
By the way if this was a vector equality,
I mean, that would be fine, you could put
a transpose right here and, and it would
look exactly the same, so that's it...
Again, it, it reduces in the case whether
scalar to just what we had before but
here it's a vector.
Okay, so and the dual function is
absolutely identical, so it's great, so
it means if you kind of wrote the you
know,
abstract enough software whatever your
Your same thing that would work in the pr,
in the scalar case would just work
absolutely transparently in this case.
Right?
So that, that's good.
Okay, now the lower bound property,
there's one subtlety.
The lower bound property for general dual
is this.
If lambda is now negative Then g gives you
a lower bound on the primal problem.
So, these are vectors now, the lambdas.
And it turns out that the correct,
the correct way in which they're
non-negative is in the dual cone.
Now, first of all, you could have guessed
that for many reasons.
First of all you should've guessed it on
aesthetic grounds.
And here are the, here are the aesthetic
grounds.
You're taking the inner product of two
things.
One is supposed to be negative in one
inequality, in one cone.
Then it actually sort of makes sense, and
if you do sort of the very abstract
mathematics and keep track of like row and
column vectors and dual spaces and things
like that Then you would be led,
it'd have to be that these thing are in
the dual cone.
Of course then you can just check because
either these things are going to work out
or they're not.
So turns out, that's the subtlety.
Now for the scalar case, the dual cone of
r plus is r plus.
So we don't see any difference right.
We just say if the inequality holds.
Then if you have a non negative Lagrange
multipliers, you know,
that's how that works.
Okay, and to see how this works it,
the proof is essentially the same, except
that you wouldn't have a transpose there.
It's, it's quite the same.
It says to take any x that's feasible and
then let's form this Lagrangian like that.
Well these are zero, so this term just
goes away.
That's totally irrelevant.
>> Okay, and now we look at, well we look
at this.
What ever this is, if what ever this is
for any [INAUDIBLE] this is
bigger than the dual condition there
right, because the dual function is
the minimum of the [INAUDIBLE], so this is
bigger than that, that's g.
And over here if you look at this, the key
point is that you can,
you want to conclude that all of those
numbers are less than or equal to 0.
And that's correct because the fact that x
i is feasible says that f i
of x [UNKNOWN] is less than or equal to 0
in the k i cone.
The inner product of that with a
non-negative in the dual cone,
that's what gives you that that's less
than or equal to zero.
So each of these are less than or equal to
zero.
Right?
So
that's the, that's the, that's the key
here.
So, so it just works.
Okay.
So, everything is the same.
Including, by the way, its [UNKNOWN],
condition, and things like that.
Generalize [UNKNOWN], it's all the same.
Okay, so the most important example of
that is Like SDP, so
semi definite program.
Semi definite program that looks like
this, this is an inequality form.
An inequality form you minimize a linear
function subject to what's called a linear
matrix inequality that says that a, a, a
linear sum, a weighted sum of a bunch of
symmetric matrices should be less than or
equal to another matrix, right.
And that's in the matrix sense, this
inequality.
So, that's a, that's a semidefinite
program.
This is an MLI here.
And so here, we introduce, we're going to
form the dual.
We, so, we have to form we have to have a,
a Lagrange multiplier you know something
like a lambda.
But it's a matrix because here let the,
let the right hand arguments are matrix's.
Right?
So it's going to be a matrix,
we'll call it Z.
It's a symmetric matrix.
And the Lagrange is this, it's C transpose
X,
plus and then the it;s going to be the
inner product of Z.
And the part that is negative, which is
this thing minus G.
Now, the inner product of two symmetric
matrices is the trace of
the product, right?
I mean, that's just, that, that's the
inner product of the two
matrices considered as vectors in rn
squared, right?
It's just the standard inner product.
So, I get this, like that, and
now we do the same thing As usual, we
minimize over x, right.
This is an affine function of x, so
nothing could be easier, right.
If you minimize an affine function of x,
the answer is minus infinity.
Unless the linear part of that affine
function vanishes, right.
So let's look at the linear part, or
you know I could do this with respect each
x i.
Let's minimize over x one this expression.
Well, I get c1 x1 here.
And I get trace z x1f1, but I can take the
x1 out.
And so what I would get is c1 x1 plus, and
then trace zf1.
That's a number times x1, and
then plus a whole bunch of crap that
doesn't depend on x1.
Right?
That's what this Lagrangian looks like,
okay?
I minimize over x1.
That's completely trivial.
The only, the only option is that this
plus this has to be zero.
Period, okay?
And that's true for any x1, it's true for
x2, it's true for x3 and so
what I get is this.
And I, all of these go away and what I'm
left with is trace minus trace zg.
And so I get this.
The dual function is minus trace jz
provided these quality
constraints hold here.
Otherwise it's minus infinity and I get
the following dual, and
it looks like that.
It says that, and this is already a bit
loose, but
it says the dual of this SDP is this, and
actually quite, it's kind of cool...
This is an inequality form SDP, right?
Because it is minimizable when your
functions of origin is LMI.
Sure enough you get an SDP over here,
which is in equality form, right?
So in other words that the, the constraint
is that you variable that's not
negative and then equality constraints.
And these are patterns that should start
looking familiar [INAUDIBLE] linear
programming, right?
If you have an inequality form linear
program, The dual is a linear
program where the variable is a non
negative quality constraints and
vice versa, I might add.
So these things should start looking the
same to you, you should see patterns here.
And you know, by the way, people sometimes
make little tables and cards and
things like that, you carry in your
wallet, that you know says,
here's the primal and here's the dual.
I mean that's fine.
But I think it's enough to just sort of
recognize the patterns.
And then, of course, in any given
particular case, you better be prepared to
work it out carefully and make sure it's
actually true.
So, okay. So that's it. So that's the
dual.
And you know this is not obvious.
I mean, the assertion is not obvious here.
that, that this is the dual of that.
And if you expand that out into what
you're really saying It's,
it's not an obvious thing at all.
These are things that maybe 25 years ago
would have been things that
basically the vast majority of people
wouldn't know.
So, it'd be a shocking thing to study this
problem 25 years ago People would say,
you know, you can't, you shouldn't do
that, that's hard to do,
you can't do that and then, and then say
well here's a duel and
you'd say what do you mean by that, and
you'd say, well, if anything feasible for
here that gives you a lower bound on that
and it's tight and so on and so forth.
People, it would've been it would've
looked pretty complicated.