Now, we're going to start in on convex
functions.
Well, first of all, the definition is very
simple.
It's this.
It says that a function is convex if its
domain is convex, and also if it satisfies
this inequality.
Now, this inequality says that if I take a
mixture of two points, so theta's
between 0 and 1, if I take any mixture of
two points x and y convex combination.
I form theta x plus 1 minus theta y.
I evaluate f there, that's less than or
equal to the same convex combination of
the values of f, right.
Evaluate at the end-points.
Or another way to say it geometrically is
if you have the graph of f,
that's, that's this thing.
That's the graph of f.
It says that the chord, some people call
it that, that's a very old term for
the line segment in the graph space that
goes from x, f of x to y, f of y.
It says that the chord, and this chord is
parametrized this point right here.
It says that f y is below, the graph of f
y is below its chord.
So that, that, that would be the very old
way to talk about convexity.
A function is concave if minus f is
convex.
And it's called strictly convex.
If it is a convex function.
And if this inequality here holds
strictly,
as long as theta is not zero or 1.
Well, of course, a theta zero one it
cannot hold strictly.
Right?
But when, for
theta in between, it holds strictly.
Right.
So that says that it's,
there's actually a gap between the
function and this chord.
The function graph and, and the chord.
Okay.
So let's look at some examples.
Well, we'll look first at just functions
on R just to make it simple.
You, by the way, you could just plot these
at truly or
virtually and just look in, you know, use
your.
Use your eyeball to look at these things.
The important point here is convexity
means non-negative curvature.
It means it curves up.
Okay.
So affine.
Well, an affine function, the graph looks
like that.
I mean, it's got zero curviture.
So these are, these are of course convex.
Oh, and by the way,.
Affine is right where you get an equals
there, right.
So affine say's you get equals here for
all theta.
Not just theta between 0 and 1.
Okay?
So in
some sense affine functions are right on
the boundary of convexity.
So, okay.
Exponential, well these look either like
that or like that, right?
This is if a is positive.
That is if a is negative, these are
convex.
The curvature is positive.
Powers well this again you can figure this
out.
If alpha is bigger than one, this is on
our plus, so if it's bigger than one
that would be a power, that's like to the
1.1 or something or 1.5.
The square, you know what that looks like.
The cube.
These things get, actually more and more
convex.
They curve more, they have more and more
curvature.
But it's also true for alpha less than
zero.
So for example 1 over x is going to be
also convex.
Right?
That looks like this.
Right? Oh. And we should be careful here.
Because when I say one over X, I have to
say that the domain.
If this is F, I have to say the domain is
R plus, plus.
Alright, because.
So there's a distinction between sort of
informal kind of
high school Algebra writing 1 over x.
Right.
And what you really mean.
So when, usually when we say one over x,
and we'll see this for several other
functions, we mean a different function,
we mean one that's not defined for x
negative.
Whereas of course one over x is quite well
defined for x negative.
So, okay.
What can you say about one over x for x
negative.
Convex, concave?
>> Concave.
>> It's concave, so, okay.
Powers of absolute value, I mean again
these are kind of obvious.
Negative entropy, that's something that
looks like this.
It's got infinitely sharp there and then
goes up like that, okay?
And it's convex.
Alright.
concave, well affine, because they're
both.
In fact, affine is another way to say
you're both convex and concave.
Powers between zero and one, square root
for example, is is going to be concave.
And the log is a, is a, is an, these are
very obvious concave functions.
By the way, the picture here is something
like this: You're going to build up
a family of basic functions that you know
to be convex and concave.
Most will be kind of obvious, like this.
Some will be less obvious.
And then you're going to, we're going to
work out a calculus of convex functions so
you'll be able to combine them in various
ways and things like that.
And actually, just a couple of these
things and you'll be quite you'll actually
be quite effective at sort of detecting
convexity or establishing convexity.
So, okay.
Let's look at some functions on Rn.
here, a general affine function, that's
box convex and and concave norm.
So any norm is convex, okay?
So, any norm is convex.
So that's things like the one norm, the
two norm, infinity norm, you know?
Three norm, doesn't matter.
Any other norm is convex.
And then we can look at examples on
matrices.
So here's a add find function.
The general inter product on m by n
matrices.
Is simply trace a transpose x so
this when you see this, this here by the
was some people even write it this way.
Right you can write it that way or other
people write it this way.
Its basically the generic standard inner
product so
when you see trace a transpose x or a
transpose b.
It's the inner product of a and b, right?
So that's what it, I mean, here, here's
another method you might write this as,
is I find this a bit weird, but okay.
Something like that.
I mean, this is kind of mixing weird
notation, but that's it, okay?
So, alright, so
an affine function of matrices is trace
something and then plus a constant.
Here's one.
The maximum singular value.
So, well, it's a norm.
So of course all norms are convex so
maximum singular value is.
Right?
So, by the way,
that's not a simple function.
The, the maximum singular value.
Right?
It's, it's quite complicated.
For example, to actually evaluate it,
I mean, in principle you would form a
characteristic polynomial.
You'd factor that.
You'd look at its roots, and you'd take
the largest Among all the roots,
you take the largest one, and then you
take the square root of that or something.
So this is not a simple function.
So, and yet we know it's convex.
Okay.
So
this is, this is one of the tricks you
need to know about.
It's this.
If you have a convex function,
from R on n into R.
And sorry.
If you have a function then you can
restrict it to a line.
Now a line is given by x plus tv,
x is something, you know, you might call
that the base point.
You might call v the direction of the
line.
And t is a parameter.
Right, so T as in R and it tells you where
you are on the line.
Oh and I should say V has to be non zero.
It doesn't give you a line.
So x plus t v.
This is the free parameter representation
of a line where x plus t
is a parameter that's real.
Okay, so this says evaluate f at the point
on the line parameterized by t, right?
And I'm going to define that to be g of t
So that's a function from r to r.
Right?
And so, here's what, here's, here's what
the result is.
And this is not too hard.
But it says the following.
A function is convex if and only if.
When it's restricted to all lines, it's
convex.
Okay?
Now, in principle, this is quite useful.
Because, oh, let, let me ask this.
How do you, how do you determine if a
function from r to r is convex..
Yeah.
You plot it,
and, and you looked with your eyeball.
Does it curve up or down?
Or both right and if it curves up then you
say well its convex.
OK, by the way what you do then is you
back off an dyou go to some other fancy
method like you differentiate it twice and
prove some inequality.
And then you destroy evidence that you
actually plotted it but
the correct thing to do is to plot it.
Okay, so that, that, that's how you use
this.
Okay?
So alright, what this says is in principal
you can detect if a function is convex,
a function of RN by simply taking all
lines.
Now of course, you can not really do that,
but
this does tell you, this gives you a
perfectly good method for
checking if a function is convex and I
will tell you what it is.
So here's what it is.
First, you might try some analytical
tools.
You know, you might differentiate
something twice, but
after the formulas grow to the size of a
page you might quit, or
something like that.
Then what you do is this.
You write a simple little program to
generate random lines.
Right?
Then do effectively do the same as plot.
Just evaluate the function at a hundred
points along the line.
And check the inequality, just to check
that it always curves up.
Right?
By the way, if it,
if you ever find a point where it doesn't,
you're done.
Because you,
you've produced two points where the
inequality defining convexity is violated.
In which case, the you are done and
it's absolutely no one's business how you
found this point.
Everyone realize?
So what you do now is you go to lunch.
>> Is everyone following, is everyone
following this?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
You go to lunch.
And you come back after lunch.
If in fact it is terminated, and bounded
by two points, then you walk down
the hall to your colleague who asked
whether the function is convex.
You go, obviously not.
>> [LAUGH] And they say why.
And you say, well look at this point here.
And you, you, you give x and y and
the convex combination, which violates the
inequality, and you go, I,
I don't even really know why you would
think that was convex in the first place.
>> [LAUGH] Everyone see what I'm saying?
And then they'd say, well, how the hell
did you come up with these things?
And you'd say, I don't know, it seems kind
of obvious to me.
I don't...
>> [LAUGH] So, okay.
Does this, everyone following this?
Okay, now that's the def, the,
the other outcome is that actually it
hasn't been violated.
Now, you don't know for sure it's convex.
But you went out for lunch and you fired
this up, depends on maybe you used
a cluster, maybe, maybe you fired up
something on EC2, I don't know.
But, a fair number of points may have been
checked by now.
Now you don't know if it's convex or not.
Okay.
So now I can actually tell you several
ways to move forward.
The first is, you then try to prove it's
convex.
That, that would be, that's the simplest
way.
And if you do prove it,
you destroy all evidence that you ever
tried to establish it empirically.
Everybody understand this?
Okay, so then, now the other thing is you
can still get credit for
it even if you can't prove it's convex.
You go to the next conference.
And you say, well, I think the log and the
detection probability.
It seems to be like it's gotta be concave.
Is that, and you just drop that around.
You say it obvious places, and things like
that.
And then the next year, some smart young
researcher will prove it.
>> [LAUGH].
>> And if you're really lucky,
they'll have attached your name to it, and
call it the such and such conjecture.
Everyone following this?
>> And then people would say, how did you
know?
It, it the proof is very complicated
there's all sort of algebraic geomerty and
all sorts of other stuff how could you
have possibly known it was concave and
then you look straight at them and you say
intuition.
[LAUGH] Is everyone following this?
Okay, so these are advanced methods for
establishing convexity [LAUGH].
Well we'll talk more about these as the
course goes on, okay?
Alright so let's do one, like that.
By the way if you do these things just
don't tell anyone where you learned them,
[LAUGH] so, because I'll deny it.
So okay so let's look, let's look at an
example.
Here's a very famous one it's kind of one
of the first functions that's not
obviously convex.
It's log of a determinate.
Right?
Well, that's not.
By the way, these two thing, these two
symbols go together.
It depends on what courses you've taken.
But, for example, you would recognize this
as related to the entropy of
a Gaussian random variable, where x is the
co-variance.
I mean.
So you
probably have seen log determinants
sitting next to each other before maybe.
Okay.
Maybe you have.
Maybe you haven't.
But the idea is there,
there are a lot of areas where they fit
very comfortable together.
And it turns out log determinant of a
matrix is concave.
For a positive definite matrix.
Just a fact.
I mean, later, this will be completely
obvious.
We'll get to it.
By the way, it would be kind of a pain in
the ass to show this via a direct proof.
Although if you've taken information
theory.
and, and.
For some reason think that, that's simpler
than sort of basic inequalities.
Then you'd say oh that follows because
entropies some mixture something and
you say something and some theorem from,
from information theory would tell us
immediately that this concave.
Okay, its a mixture of Gaussian I don't
know what it is anyway, okay?
So let's check this though.
So how do you check it?
Well, what we'll do is we'll form an
arbitrary line.
So, what does a line in matrix space look
like?
In symmetric matrix space.
Well, it looks like this.
It's got a base point, X, and it's got a
direction, V.
Now, X we can assume without a loss of
generality is positive-definite.
because this line has to intersect the
non, the positive-definite dom,
it has to right, otherwise there's nothing
to show, right?
So it has to intersect right so
we might as well say it intersects when t
equals 0, right?
So we can assume without lost generality
that x is positive.
And then v is merely symmetric, so x plus
t v is really a line.
And if you want to, you can think of it as
a line of potential covariance matrices.
So that's what it is.
So it is parametarized by t.
Now, for an interval of t, for some values
of t,
it is possible there is an interval where
that thing is positive definite.
But there is, it is possible if you make t
big enough one way or the other.
It is possible.
In fact that, that matrix will become not
positive definite.
So there may be an interval of little t.
Over which, X plus tV is positive
definite.
So this, the, is there, positive definite
matrices?
There's a line and it may intersect it at,
now you can have weird things where it
intersects at, at only one point.
It's a half open interval but you know,
but that would happen for example.
If v is positive-semidefinite, the
direction.
Okay so let's, now let's look at this on a
line.
Well on a line, this thing is log det.
I'm going to, I'm going to expand, I'm
going to write this as,
I'm going to do this, I can/g, there's
several ways to do it, but
I can write, I can pull out x one half.
On either side of this thing, and
write this, i plus t is x minus half v, x
minus half, and x one half.
So, certainly, this, this matrix is surely
the same as that, here.
Right?
And now I take the determinant of that.
It's the triple product of the
determinants, you get, and log is the sum,
so I get log det, I get one half log det x
plus one half log det x,
that's this one, this one, and this one.
Okay.
That's a constant and doesn't interest me
as far as convexity is concerned.
Now we look at this thing.
So what it says is something like this.
Without loss of generality,
I can concentrate on the case where my
base point is the identity.
Okay, but
log of det of i plus something, we know
the eigenvalues of this matrix right?
The eigenvalues of that matrix are exactly
1 plus t lambda i where lambda i
are the eigenvalues of this matrix, right?
So and in fact the that tells you that the
log determinant is the sum of log plus t
lambda i.
and, guess what?
This function is concave and you can just
check that again.
My claim is that for
a variable for something with one
variable, you can just check, right?
That log of 1 plus t lambda depends on the
sign of lambda i,
which can be positive or negative.
But either way this thing is concave,
because log of something affine is
concave, right?
So, that's it.
So we're, we're done.
By the way, these lambda i's they might
look mysterious here, but
if you know, if you had an advanced course
on linear algebra or maybe you took
a mechanics course, these are actually the
generalized eigenvalues of the pair, x v.
Right, so if you've, if you've, if you
trained in these areas, you,
this, this does not look mysterious at
all.
OK.
So, there we go.
By the way, this has been known about a
hundred years,
the fact that the log determinant is is
concave.
OK, now there's a one, one other thing
we're going to cover is this.
It turns out when you're dealing with
convex or concave functions,
there's a very nice way that you can
actually pull in the idea of the domain,
and, and define things over.
A bigger extended have extended values.
So what you could do is you take a normal
function F, which has domain F.
And has value when you're in the domain F,
F of x,
at if x is in the domain, if the value.
So, and for an ordinary function.
If I call f outside the domain.
what, I mean, well, what I should get.
Is, what should be returned to me, an
exception should be thrown.
And the exception thrown should be
something, should be a token like OOD,
which means out of domain.
Which means I have no intention of, of, of
evaluating f out there.
Because, you're not, it's not in the valid
domain.
Right, so that, that's, so you should get
something like that.
But you can actually modify things and do
the following.
What you do is f tilde is the
extended-value extension.
What you do is, it's the same as whenever
x is in the domain, it's just f.
But when you're outside the domain, you
assign the value plus infinity.
And it'll turn out, everything's going to
work,
included, including like inequalities and
various things.
It's all just going to work automatically.
Right?
So in some sense it's not a whole lot
different, right?
And if you think of a return value of plus
infinity as an exception then well okay.
Then whether or not you get the exception
OD, for out of domain, or
plus infinity, I guess doesn't matter
much.
But what's nice about it is If you think
of it,
not as an exception, but as an extended
value, all sorts of inequalities and
things like that will just work, right.
So this is the extended value extension.
And it simplifies notation, right, so for
example this holds now for any x and y.
And you can sort of just check.
And there's a couple of rules.
There are a few things that are not
well-defined,
in extended arithmetic, obviously.
Well, zero times infinity is not
well-defined.
But all, everything else is,
the inequalities, everything, everything's
well defined here, and, and just works.
Okay, so this is the extended value
extension.
This will also come up a bunch of times.
Okay, now we get to sort of first order
conditions for convexity.
Well, the, if F's differentiable that
means its domain is open.
And it has a gradient.
These partial derivatives exist at point
okay.
By the way this constructor here which is
a parenthesis with a middle.
It's more compact.
Right so this is a column factor that
actually looks like this right?
Like that.
That's the same is that and
the first order condition is actually
really interesting.
It's one of the most important tings.
It's actually the one thing which kind of
tells you everything.
It's this.
This function here, that is the that is
the first ordered tailored function of F.
At the point x.
Right?
So the y is the variable here.
That's an affine function of y, this what
I've, what I've ident, this thing.
It's an affine function of y.
It's the first-order Taylor expansion of f
at x.
Okay?
So if this is f, right?
Here is This first ordered tailored.
That's this function.
Here is this function y okay.
Here's what calculus tells you is the
following.
This function is really close to F if you
are close to x.
It means that you are close to x this
function is close squared.
The f.
That's what calculus tells you.
Right, that that's the whole thing.
What this says instead the assertion here
is a global inequality.
It basically says the function is bigger
everywhere, globally.
Than the first-order tailor series
expansion, right.
And so this is your first hint that what
you are seeing is not calculus.
It's some weird, sick, global, and
asymetric thing.
We have a different animal here.
The first thing is it is a inequality,
right,
that's the first difference with calculus.
Calculus is just, you know, above, below,
you only have the concept of close.
And it's symmetric.
You can be above, below, you're close.
Right?
And it's weird and local and asymptotic.
This, there are no conditions here.
This is just, it's it's a global
inequality.
Just looks like that.
Okay?
So, that's it.
So,
this is actually very important, actually.
This is also going to come up later in the
class you're going to be
doing convex optimization.
You'll be doing, you'll be solving, I
don't know,
some problem with a thousand variables, I
don't know.
And you'll be And someone will come along
and say what are you doing?
I'm solving this problem.
And you'd say here's the solution, and
they'd say oh,
well how do you know that's the solution?
You go oh no it is.
I mean that's, no one can do better.
But R 1000 is a giant place, right,
there's a lot, that's a huge thing.
You can't possibly go to lunch and check
other points and come back later and say.
I checked a million points.
You know, and our one thousand, that's
like zero.
Okay, so you know nothing.
That is all I'm saying.
So someone can reasonably say, how do you
know?
How could you possibly assert that this is
the best, that no one can do any better?
In such, in such a giant place?
And the answer will be this inequality
here.
That's it, that's the whole, the whole
thing is constructed on the basis of
global asymmetric, well asymmetric in an
inequality, that's what it is.
Okay, second order conditions.
Well if a function is twice differentiable
that means it's, it's got,
all these partial derivatives exist and
they're That's denoted the Hessian.
So, sometimes written this way, right?
of, of the function at that point.
And what it says is the following.
If, if f.
It says that f is convex, if and only if
its second derivative is non negative.
Now that's a matrix.
So that means positive semi definite,
okay?
So that's the, that's the condition.
Now, it turns out there's a weird
asymmetry here.
If a function, if the second derivative or
hessian is positive definite, that's not
enough to guarantee.
sorry.
That guarantees straight convexity, but
the other way around is actually false.
You can be strictly convex without having
the hessian, positive, for
all points in the domain.
Okay?
So, I mean, and there are things you can
say about that, but that's good enough.
So that's it.
So that's another way to say it is, again
The second order expansion.
When you get that second, that second
term, that second term is in fact the,
the matrix is positive-semidefinite.
Okay so let's look at some examples.
Let's knock off all quadratic functions.
Here's a quadratic function.
Without loss of generality we can assume
that p here is
positive-semidefinite symmetric, sorry
symmetric.
Right, because, and otherwise you get the
same quadratic form.
The gradient of this function is PX plus
Q, right?
And the heshin is P.
Okay?
So that's the, that, that's the heshin.
And it's really simple.
The quadratic function is convex if and
only if its quadratic part.
Is positive semi-definite.
Okay.
So here's an example.
Is the score subjective?
So let's take F of X is AX minus B norm
squared.
Well the gradient, is, and you can put a
one half there, you know, for aesthetics.
I mean, it doesn't make any difference.
And people often do, for aesthetics.
The aesthetics is the following.
That you don't get this 2, and you don't
get this 2.
Right so, well the gradient is a transpose
ax minus b.
And the hessian is simply its constant its
a transpose a.
But that's always positive semi-definite
so you're done.
OK, and here is I think probably the
simplest function well we've already seen
log that, that wasn't obvious but this is
sort of a really simple function.
And its the first one most people don't
know.
Is convex.
Its really simple function its x squared
over y.
And its a function of two variables x and
y and
the domain is y has to be positive OK.
And here's a plot of it so there, there,
there's the plot.
By the way you've seen that plot actually
twice before I claim.
Weirdly.
The first is I, you saw it when we
plotted,
when I gave you a plot of the positive
semidefinite cone in 2 variables.
Right, and I think that I mumbled
something incoherently about
somebody telling me once it looks like the
front of a ship.
Okay?
I also said that if you took that thing
and rotated it,
it's actually the same as the Lorentz
cone, it the cone.
Right, so that's a lot of mileage from one
stupid cone, right.
It's come up three times, but the point is
it's the graph of x squared over y is,
is this thing.
And it turns out now, you, you can verify
many things, but
you just work out what the, the Hessian
is.
I mean, this is kind of high school
calculus.
So you work out what the Hessian is, and
sure enough the Hessian has this form.
It's rank one, but it's positive
semi-definite, 'kay?
And you get that, so
that tells you, and in fact it even tells
you a lot, the fact that it's rank one.
The fact that it's rank one tells you that
at any point on that surface it's
sort of curving in one direction, but not
the other.
Alright, so that's what it says.
In one direction, it's flat.
In the other direction, it's got positive
curvature.
So x squared over y is convex.
By the way, we're going to see lots of.
Implications of this.
Right, this is going to come up in like
robust statistics, and
all sorts of other things.
It's going to come up a lot.
You'll see.
OK, here's one.
It's log sum exp, and
what it is is you take the log of the sum
of a bunch of exponentials.
And before we get into it.
I want to give you a rough idea of what
this function is because it's going to
play a big role and the bunch of stuff we,
you probably have seen before, will see
again if you've taken the right courses
anyway and will see also in this course.
So here's what log-sum-exp is.
So, first of all it's the power combining
formula in Electro engineering.
In decibals right so again so this I'm
going to go into dialect so
those of you not in electrical engineering
I apologize formally but thats okay so
I'll go into dialect.
So if I tell you that you have a bunch of
signals coming in you know one at
plus five dbm one at minus twelve one at
this or what something.
And I say what's the total power.
Incident there.
What you would do is -- each of these are
decibels, for the rest of
you who don't speak this dialect -- is a
log of a power level, right?
So, so if you want to convert these to
powers, you form an exp.
I mean, there are some, y'know, factors in
there, but I don't care about them.
So you form an exp.
Then you add the powers.
Now we're at the sum exp.
We're up to here, right.
And then the log reconverts back to
decimals.
Okay, so, so my claim is that everyone at
ee knows this it's the db
combining formula.
So don't, don't pretend like you haven't
seen it, you have seen it if you're in ee.
The second thing is this is a smooth
approximation of a maximum.
Okay and in fact another name for this
function is soft max okay?
So that 's that.
You may have seen in maybe machine
learning course It's a soft.
Is that what it's called in a machines
learning class.
Okay good.
And the intuition is really simple.
It's this.
If I got a bunch of exponentials,
the exponential is going to actually
accentuate.
Large numbers.
Like, if one or two numbers are much
bigger than the others.
Their exp, their exps are much bigger than
the exponentials of the others, right?
You add 'em up, and the big ones dominate.
You take the log.
And you get something.
So it's like a soft approximation of the
max, right?
So that's another name for the soft max.
And it's also normalizing function in
statistical mechanics for something.
And it comes up in lots of other things
too.
But maybe not quite with this notation.
Okay.
So this is convex.
and, again, the way to show that is to
work out the proof.
And then to write it this way.
Now, unfortunately, the proof was either
going to be shorter or a bit longer.
It's going to, it's, it's not totally
simple.
Because this one is positive semi
definite, clearly.
Unfortunately, that said, that goes the
wrong way.
It's minus, right?
So you actually have to do some work to
show this is positive semi definite.
And to do that.
You really have to show that this thing
here is, is positive semi-definite.
So you form something like v transpose
times the Hessian times v,
and you argue that that thing is bigger
than or equal to zero for all v.
And you might do that this way.
You might use Cauchy-Schwarz right, so
Cauchy-Schwarz would tell you this
inequality.
Right, that, that would be the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality applied.
2 square root, well, to square root zk and
square zk vk, right?
The, the two vectors, you plug
Cauchy-Schwarz and
you get exactly this, right?
And that tells you up here that this thing
is bigger or equal to 0.
So, so.
And, by the way,
I'm not going to go into, you're not
suppose to be getting this in real time.
You have to go out to quiet place.
Check that you believe all these things
and so on.
So, okay.
Geometric mean.
So the nth root of the product of a bunch
of positive numbers.
Well, or, or none negative for that
matter.
That's concave.
And it's the same kind of thing.
In fact, it turns out that the, you know?
For a function like that, and for many
functions like this, it turns out.
That the Hessian is non-negative diagonal
minus rank one.
That's what this is, and you get the same,
same type of argument holds.
Okay, so what's the connection between
convex sets and convex functions?
And that's this, it's through a simple
thing called the epigraph,.
So we'll encounter a whole bunch of
things.
One relating sets and functions.
So here's one.
If I have a function, then it's alpha
sublevel set,
is this, it's the set of points in the
domain.
Although, of course if you used extended
value that happens automatically.
Where f is less than alpha.
Okay that is the sub level set.
By the way this will have all sorts of
practical meanings when we get into this.
If F is an objective that you want to
minimize than the alpha sub level set
are the set of points designs or
choices whatever the x represents, which
are at least as good as alpha.
The alpha good, alpha good or better
points.
Right?
So, and
if you have a convex function the sublevel
sets are convex, 'kay?
So, the set of points better than
something if you're trying to minimize it,
that's convex, 'kay.
The converse is false.
You can have convex sublevel sets and
you're not a convex function,
in fact those functions have a name, and
we'll get to them.
later.
The real, the, the closest connection,
the correct connection is through
something called the epigraph.
So epi means sort of above.
And, graph means of course, you know,
something that's, that's drawn or in
mathematics it's the pairs, points comma
values in our N plus 1 in graph space.
People can Rn plus 1.
And so the epigraph of a function is the
set of all pairs x t where f of x
is less than or equal to t, right?
So the normal graph is equals to t because
you just get the surface of the function.
The epigraph is everything above it right
so
its this shaded thing here its the
epigraph.
OK, and there's the connection very
simple.
So a function f is convex if and only if.
Its epigraph is a convex set and that's,
that's the connection.
So the real connection between convex
functions and
convex sets is through the epigraph,
right?
And in fact we'll see all sorts of cool
things.
You know various things about convex
sets,.
Those will all translate to various rules
about convex functions.
And we'll, we'll look at, you know?
We'll look at a couple of those, and all
that kind of stuff.
And so, in fact, what it will really mean
is that moving, after a while,
when you start, when you start
internalizing all these.
You'll have different ways to say the same
thing.
One will be a w statement about sets.
There'll be a statement about functions.
And the connection will be through the
epigraph.
Okay.
So, Jensen's inequality.
It's about a hundred years old.
Now maybe, actually a little bit more.
Actually the inequality was around
earlier.
You know, obviously, for, for, for very
specific things.
And it was was Jensen who kind of looked
at it and said Hey you know what.
Everyone keeps making the same, keeps
talking about the same inequality, and
here's here's what it is that they're all
saying.
He just collected the name for it.
OK.
Basic inequality says this.
If f is convex and you have theta between
zero and one, you have that.
Now and in fact that's the definition of
convexity.
So I don't know, anyway that.
That's called Jensen's Inequality.
OK, now it turns out Jensen's inequality
you can generalize various ways.
Number one to finite sms right so if I
have a if I have a set of points x
one through x k theta one through theta k
theta i non negative add up to one f
of sum theta i xi is less than equal to
sum theta ix of f of xi.
Okay?
So that's, that's it.
Then you can, you can extend it to
infinite sums, integrals, and
finally you go all the way and it's just
expectations.
So the right way to say it is this.
If you have a random variable Z, it takes
values from the domain of F.
Right.
By the way, if it doesn't take values, if
it, if there's a positive probability it
takes values outside the domain of f, then
there's really not much to say here.
But, so it takes, it's values are in the
domain of f,
almost surely, then the following is true.
F of the expected value is less than the
expected value of f of x.
That, that's it.
And guess what.
This very basic inequality here, is
exactly this.
This is the most general form of the
inequality.
And this is a special case of that for a
very specific distribution of z.
I mean, it's really dumb, it's atomic.
It's a distribution that assign, has the
value of x with a probability theta, and
probability y with probability of.
Has the value y with a probability of one
minus.
Data.
Then this is a special case of that.
So, so this is, so this is another way to
talk about convexity.
It's, function is convex if it doesn't
commute with expectation that's affine,
right, but what it does is expectation
Always, I means there's lots of ways to
say this but, well when you commute them
you get an inequality, right so
actually one way to say this is, and this
is weird and
this is a little bit dialect but,
dithering increases the value of function.
Ok, that, that.
The dithering is to add noise to some zero
[INAUDIBLE] noise intentionally.
Ok, so now let's talk about some of these
operations that preserve convexity.
so.
What you'll have, what you, what you will
be doing establishing convexity of
functions, and sets, for that matter.
and, so.
How do you do this?
Well, one is just, every n-, every now and
then, although quite rarely.
The best thing to do is just roll up your
sleeves.
Fill at x y,
take a theta between 0 and 1 and just jump
in and then establish an inequality.
That's actually extremely rarely.
It's that the right thing to do, right?
Sometimes.
Or you can restrict to a line and verify
it.
That's another option.
Now, for twice differentiable functions,
you can differentiate twice.
And, if the function is simple enough, you
know, go ahead.
If it's not simple and,
in fact, it takes very little before this
method is completely unworkable.
Just because the notation proliferates and
you get horrible expressions and
you write it down and it's half a page of
Stuff, and someone says what's that?
And you go partial squared F, partial XI,
partial XJ.
And then, and then they say what do you
have to do now?
And you go, prove that that,
half page of formula represents a positive
semi affine matrix, right?
And this is not fun, so,.
Now, the way.
The, sort of, I think a more modern way to
do this.
Is certainly a, a way that is more useful.
And it's the way you will do it in this
course, mostly, is the following.
Is, you'll actually do this,
constructively by a calculus.
And what that means is, you'll, you'll
know a bunch of convex and
concave functions.
You've already seen a bunch.
You know, norms, and, you know?
Square root log entropy.
Geometric mean all sorts of things like
this, right?
You'll have those, you'll have, in that,
that by the way that list of atoms will
grow, as you learn more of them.
And then you'll have some operations that
preserve convexity.
Right so some of them are going to be some
are going to be totally obvious and
stupid like the sum of two convex
functions is convex.
Well duh two times a convex function is
convex fine right.
Minus three times a convex function is
concave OK fine.
Others are going to be way less obvious OK
so we'll, we'll get to those and
it turns out that you don't have to know a
whole lot of these things before you put
them all togeterh and they're actually
quite powerful at establishing convesity.
Parking capital or something like that.
And that, that, that's going to be the
thing.
Or if you like thinking of it from a
computer science point of view,
your proofs or verifications of convexity
are going to look like this.
Your going to have expressions and trees.
The leaves are going to be things you know
are convex or concave.
That's going to happen.
And, all of the internal nodes in that
expression tree are going to be
expressions whose convexity or
concavity you can tag by one of these
calculus rules.
So if you understood that, great.
If you didn't, you will, because, you'll,
we're going to force you to.
Alright.
So let's start with the obvious ones.
I mean, positive weighted sum and
composition with an affine function.
So,.
Non negative multiple, these are kind of
obvious.
By the way these things do have to be
shown, right.
So somebody should show them, or you
should show them, or something.
I'm certainly not going to do it here.
sum.
Right.
So if you add 2 convex functions it's
convex.
I mean, it's kind of obvious.
Composition with an affine function.
If you pre-compose.
A convex function with an affine function,
the result is convex.
Right?
Same for concave.
Let's look at some.
Here's one.
Log barrier for linear inequalities.
So, here's a function.
It's the sum of minus log, b i minus a i
transpose x.
The domain is this open polyhedron.
It's the set of points where it's the
interior of this, right?
So it, it doesn't include the boundary, is
what the domain of f is.
And in there, we can even, we can even
interpret these terms.
This, that's the margin in the ithenic
volume.
If you require BI to be bigger than AI
transpose X,
strictly bigger, that's the margin, a
positive number.
You take the log of that.
Well, okay that's, that's, if the margin
is small,
that's a very large negative number.
And the minus sign converts it that way.
This is a, so true that this is a convex
function,
called a logarithmic barrier function for
this polyhedron.
And we're going to see a lot of that later
in the class.
And you can guess kind of why it's called
a logarithmic barrier because if
you were to visualize that function on a
polyhedron, this function,
it goes to plus infinity on the
boundaries, right?
As you move towards the boundary, one of
your margin,
at least one of your margin gets really
small.
One term in here.
One term in here goes to zero; the log
goes to minus infinity, and
the minus makes it go to plus infinity.
So it's like a barrier.
If you think of it like in physics,
a potential function, it's an infinite
potential well.
Okay?
That's what this is.
Alright, you can have the norm of an
affine function, right,
because that's an affine function composed
with a norm which is convex.
I mean, this is kind of obvious, but,
we'll quickly get to ones that are not.
So, pointwise maximum.
So if you have a bunch of convex
functions,
then their pointwise maximum is convex.
I mean, this is kind of obvious.
I'm just going to draw a picture.
Here's one function.
Here's another.
Here's the pointwise maximum, is this
function here.
That's the pointwise maximum, and it's
convex.
I mean, the picture is clear.
It's two lines of a proof, if you can
stretch it to two lines.
You know.
It's, it's not hard to show.
Actually this is very interesting and this
tells you that you are you
are not in the calculus mode anymore
here's why this is one of
the most most basic constructors of convex
functions is through point wise maximum.
And what's completely clear even this
little example I
just drew is it does not preserve
differentiability.
Right max of even differentiable functions
is generally not diffrentiable OK
you get points and in fact that's kind of
a theme for the whole course.
It turns out differentiability doesn't
play a huge role in convexity.
There is certainly complex optimization,
it doesn't play a big role.
So and again, these are just things that
we're, you're going to just,
this'll be clear, but
this is kind of your first hint that this
is not going to be like a calculus class.
So, here are some quick examples.
Piecewise-linear function so that maximum,
I have a bunch of affine functions.
Then piecewise-linear functions just, the
max,
a maximum of them, that's convex
immediately, right.
So, by the way that's a very specific form
of of a piecewise-linear function, right,
because normally when people talk about
piecewise-linear functions.
They talk, you know, you, you specify the
dom, the, the little regions, and
then on that region, you say it has this
value and this value and so on.
This one kind of does all that implicitly.
It just says it's the maximum of a bunch
of functions, right?
Here's an affine function, here's that,
you know?
That is the maximum.
The function, it looks like this.
That is the, that's a piecewise-linear
convex function, right.
And it's just the maximum of a bunch of
affine functions.
Here's one that's less obvious.
How about this?
The sum of the r largest components of a
vector, 'kay?
So the sum of the five largest components.
That's kind of a complicated thing, right?
If anything, you should be getting a
combinatorial feel for it.
This is convex, and the argument is really
quick.
Let's talk about different ways you might
show this.
Okay, let's talk about differentiating.
If you, let's talk about it.
So what's the derivative?
What the gradient of the function which is
the sum of the five largest entries in
a vector?
Wherever the five largest elements are
bigger than.
There's a gap between the fifth and sixth
element in the vector.
That function is actually just alfine.
And what is the gradient there?
It's a vector with a 1 in each component
if you're among the top five, and
0 otherwise.
Right?
So that's fine.
It's got a gradient.
And you could try to show that gradient
inequality or
something like that, ignoring the fact
that, in fact, the gradient doesn't exist.
When there's a tie between the fifth and
sixth elements in this function.
And a hessian out of the, it's just zero
everywhere,
except on these points where it doesn't
exist, and all that kind of stuff.
So it gets weird.
Okay.
So that doesn't work.
But it's actually very easy to say what it
is.
It's a maximum over, n choose r linear
functions.
Because what I do is this.
I simply say.
I take all vectors, which consist of r1s
and n minus r0s.
And then, of which there's n choose r.
Right, so I take all those vectors, and
I take the linear function, which is that
vector in a product with x.
That's the sum of a particular, actually
each one of those.
In our products is the sum of five
particular elements.
I'm going to take r equals five.
So, it's the sum of five particular
elements in that vector.
Right?
And now I take the maximum of all of
those.
Right?
That will give me the sum of
the five largest.
Okay?
So there's a two line proof,
one line that the sum of the three largest
entries in a vector is, Is convex.
OK?
So that's it.
By the way, this doesn't give you a good
way to calculate it this way.
But still.
OK.
Well this idea extends actually to
infinite sums, and it's the same way if
you go back to the epigraphs.
It's the same way, it says that
intersection of an arbitrary number.
A convex sets as convex.
So, here, pointwise supremum,
is you can have the supremum over an
arbitrary set of functions.
Right, ar, arbitrary set of convex
functions.
So the idea is this, if you have a
function, F of X and Y.
Y actually can be completely abstract.
It does not have to be a vector in our n,
right?
It can be indexed by sup things or strings
or weird, I don't know, anything, right?
It doesn't ma, matter.
It says that if this function is convex in
x for each y,
then the supremum of this Of these
functions is convex in x.
And we can look at some simple examples.
Here's one.
The support function of a set is this.
Here's a set here, here's a set.
It doesn't have to be convex right?
Like that, that's C.
And the support function says, here's a
vector y.
You actually form the largest inner
product, and so
that would tell you Well, I didn't draw it
right, but it looks something like that.
Here, I'll, I'll bend my set to touch it
there.
Okay?
So this would give you, it tells you how
far you can go in the direction y.
And it's as a function of y.
That is a convex function of x.
'Kay?
And so let's see, why is that?
Why would you say that?
Well What kind of function of x is y
transpose x?
It's linear, okay?
So it's linear.
Therefore, it's convex.
Because, convex promotes to linear, right?
I'm sorry.
Linear promotes to convex, okay?
So, the, and then it's a supreme over
them, so that's convex.
Here's another one for fun.
Is the maximum eigenvalue of a symmetric
matrix right?
That's one way to write that is this, it's
the supremum of Y transposed capital X y.
Subject to norm Y equals 1.
Okay?
That, that,
the answer is the maxim eigenvalue of X.
Right?
That's almost the definition, okay?
So, then the question is.
How do you, how we do know that's a convex
function?
By the way, we already talked about it.
It's a quite con-, complicated function,
right?
It involves writing out the, you know?
The characteristic value of x.
Factoring it, taking the largest, you
know?
All this kind of stuff.
So let's see.
What kind of function of capital x is y
transpose x.
Why?
It's linear and that's right.
Actually this is a very good, this is the
first time you've seen this.
There are going to be lots of times when
someone walks up to you and
you see Y transposed X Y.
The quadratic part of your brain is
already, sort of actit-, activated.
Right?
It's Y transposed X Y.
It's quadratic.
Right so but here you have to be you have
to think very straight because
someonee says y is given x is the variable
and that thing is linear right.
So this is kind of the idea and then we
take a supremum of this over all possible
y and you get something that's convex.
Its the composition of functions so here's
the idea I have a function,.
H.
And I have a function g and I compose
them.
So I take h of g of x.
I'm going to call that f.
And the basic rule is very simple.
It turns out that a convex increasing
function of a convex function is convex.
Okay, so that's, that's the, that's,
that's the basic composition rule.
Convex increasing.
Now there's some details here and they're,
they are actually important.
They are not little sort of analytical.
Things that only a mathematician would
worry about.
They are quite real, and they have all
sorts of consequences.
The first is this.
the, the outer function, here.
The one that you apply.
The increasing or non decreasing re-,
restriction there is actually on its,.
It, its conve-.
It's, it's.
Extended value extension.
Right, so, so here h tilde is the extended
valued extension of h.
OK and so, what this says, I mean we can
look at some examples.
So here's a function, let's take.
H of x equals x squared with dom h equals
r plus.
Okay?
Now, in fact, you would normally say,
that function is non-decreasing, it's
increasing.
Okay?
It, it is increasing.
If you take any two points on its domain,
which is non,
non-negative numbers One is bigger than
the other then.
It's, it's bigger because the square makes
things bigger.
Okay?
Period.
So that's an increasing function.
That's not good here.
That won't work here because h tilde looks
like this,
h tilde, I'm just going to draw it kind of
Is a diagram.
It kind of goes up here to plus infinity.
Okay, and so the point is, that is not,
that is not an increasing function.
Well, in fact you can see it goes from
plus infinity down to zero.
And in fact,
if I compose This function here with
something like x minus 1 squared.
The, actually, the conclusion is wrong.
You get a function that is not convex.
Okay?
So, these are detail-, these are details.
But they're actually important ones.
I don't expect you to get it here.
You should, you know?
You should be read-, you'll read this part
of the chapter.
And you'll do homework exercises and
things like that.
Then it'll become clear.
But the, the zeroth level one that you
should remember is
convex increasing function of a convex
function is convex.
OK, so and then there's variations on
that.
A, you have a function is convex if the
inner function is concave but h is.
Instead if non decreasing, non increasing.
So it's basically a decreasing function
okay, informally.
So that's the idea.
Now how do you prove this?
You can actually prove this directly and
it's actually quite simple.
And in fact it's even clearer,
because a basic proof of this there's one
in the book.
Basically does not requi-, it doesn't.
It makes no assumptions whatsoever about h
and g.
They don't have to be differentiable.
Nothing, right?
But an instructive proof is actually to do
one,
assuming that these are scalar fun-, that
x is scalar.
And that these function are differentiable
twice, right?
So, in that case, you just take the train
rule.
And you work out what the second
derivative of F is.
Right?
Because essentially,
convexity is a statement about the second
derivative.
Right?
I mean, when a function is convex or, or
sorry, when a function is smooth.
So here, you simply work out what the
second derivative here and
you get this expression here.
And so This,
this composition theorem here is actually
going to turn out to be very simple.
It's a case where trivially you can assert
the sign of the second derivative.
OK?
So let's look at it.
If you look at the first term, you see
that there's a h prime prime.
So let's look at this theorem that says
that a convex increasing function of
a convex function is convex.
Well here, h prime prime, this thing, is
bigger than or
equal to zero.That's what it means to be
convex.
This is squared, and so it's totally
relevant, it's not negative.
Right?
Then this thing here, that's the
assumption.
It's of a convex function.
So this is, this is going to be non
negative.
And then this here.
Now you can see where the monotonicity
requirement comes in.
The monotonicity requirement comes in
because it gets multiplied by h
prime, right?
So, another way to say it is something
like this, and this'll be very rough.
But, this composition theorem tells you
when you can deduce the sign of the second
derivative, using, well, calculus and then
a very elementary signed arithmetic.
Signed arithmetic is very simple, right?
It means you multiply two things that are
non-negative,
you get something non-negative.
You add non-negative things, they're
non-negative.
You add a ne, you multiply a negative and
a positive thing, you get something
negative.
That's like signed arithmetic, okay?
So it says It says that basically from
calculus and
signed arithmetic, you can conclude the
sign of the second derivative.
If it's positive, you got a convex
function.
If it's negative, you got a concave.
Everyone following this?
OK, so, but I, the interesting, the funny
part is actually the, the proof that
holds completely generally, right, not for
differentiable, is actually easier.
Then it's, well, at least mathematically
it's easier.
All right.
So what are some examples?
It says that the exponential of a convex
function is convex, okay?
And the inverse of a,
of a function is convex if the function is
concave and positive, right?
So one over a concave function is going to
be.
Concave, sorry, convex.
Right?
So, okay, alright, now there's a vector
version of this, right?
When a function takes multiple arguments
and
actually This is incredibly important,.
We can argue that the one thing on this
page you're going to use,
probably every day for the rest of the
quarter.
Not, maybe not today, tomorrow.
But starting, like next week, I promise
you.
You will use this every single day.
So, we're going to arrange the homework
load to ensure that you'll be
using this everyday.
So this is it.
Here it is.
It's this, it says, so all I'm saying is,
this, this is, this is going to be
a big part of your life is going to be,
actually just this one composition term.
It's this, it says suppose you have a
function.
So G of X, has, is is R k value, right.
So, I have a function h, of k, k
arguments.
G1 through gk.
And I want to con, conclude convexity of
that thing.
Well, a simple one is, is this, is if the
enclosing function h is convex.
And then there's a rule.
And it say's that for each argument, that,
I mean these are the two simple versions.
But then I'll give you a completely
general version.
The simple version is this.
Is that if each of these arguments is
convex right?
And H is increasing in each argument.
Okay.
And in fact it's h tilde, the extended bag
extension, but
let's, that's, that's the idea.
So, in fact, it's the natural extension,
right?
So what it says is, is this right, each of
these right here, h is,
is you, you analyze the monotonicity with
respect to each argument.
And if it's increasing in every argument,
then you can take a convex.
Function at each point.
Actually, you can mix and match these.
So, let me explain that, and in fact, let
me give you a very general one.
It goes something like this.
F is convex if, and this is only
sufficient,
it is absolutely not necessary, it's, if
the following is true.
For each i, right?
And I'll, I'll give you a more general
version, and we'll have an exercise on
this, so don't worry about it, but I just
thought I'd say it now.
One of the following occurs.
first, if, if, gi is affine, then you,
there are no,
absolutely no monotonicity requirements
on, on the enclosing function h.
Right?
That's the first one, right?
Or gi is convex and h h,
sorry, is increasing in Arg i.
Okay?
I'm, I'm writing this informally, but you
know what I mean.
Or gi is concave and h is decreasing in
arg i.
Okay?
So that's it.
So, now one of the reasons that you need
to know this is because this is
the basis of for example, cvx.
Which you'll be using starting next week.
Okay, which is a software system for
doing convex optimization, convex
analysis, things like that.
And it's all based on these basic rules of
convex analysis, right.
Although, they're basic but you get a lot
of them.
So this is, this is the, the idea.
There details here like the monotonicity
has to be with respect to
the extended value extensions, so you have
to take the domain into account.
So, there's a generalization of the
others.
actually, here's a very interesting fact
all the other rules you've seen so
far, almost all of them This includes
them, right.
When you teach this stuff to humans, you
say things like look it's good to
know that the sum of convex functions is
convex, right.
That follows actually from this directly.
because all I do is I take h, the outer
function to be the sum.
It's kind of a silly, right, it takes two
arguments and it adds them, right.
So that's a convex function.
I mean.
Sure, right.
It's convex, oh and guess what, it's
monotone increasing in each argument.
Therefore, the sum of two convex functions
is convex.
Now that's kind of pedantic, right,
because it's a,
you're using a sledgehammer to show
something that's quite obvious.
Everyone following this?
But my point is.
Then in fact this is kind of the only
thing you need to know actually is
just this one thing.
There's max we looked at that we said that
we observed at the max of a pointwise max
of a bunch of convex functions is convex.
Well guess what all you do is you take
this theorm you take h is the max.
That's a convex function by itself it is
increasing in each argument.
I guess not in its, its non-decreasing.
Oh.
You have to distinguish between
informal speech and then when you're
writing.
So when I'm talking, it's informal speech,
and
I say "increasing" to mean non-decreasing.
Okay.
So, so it -- so -- so
this also tells me that the maximum of a
bunch of convex functions is maximum,
point-wise maximum.
So you, you actually get a lot out of this
one A, one composition here.
So let's look at an example.
You have something like this.
well, let's see.
The sum of the log of bunch of concave
functions, is going to be concave.
Right?
And that would follow from
something like this.
Here's one.
Log sum X of GI.
Of x.
If the GIs are convex.
Log sum x g, i.
That's convex.
By the way, you should be getting a little
bit of,.
L, let's first, let's talk about that a
little bit.
And I'll just say a little bit about it.
Log sum exp you should think of as a soft
max.
It's an analytic or smooth approximation
of the max function.
But the max of a bunch of convex functions
is met, is convex.
So, you know?
Intuition suggests that log sum exp would
be convex.
So.
Immediately, we get a, this is consistent
just by intuition, right.
And then, now there's all sorts of things
we could do here to parse this and
establish convexity.
I'll show you one that doesn't work first.
The first one is to, is to simply parse it
from the inside and go out.
Here's one.
What can you say if GI is convex what can
you say about X GI.
It's convex.
because that's the most basic thing there
is, right.
It's convex increasing function of
[UNKNOWN].
Okay, how about the sum?
You can label that.
It's convex.
Okay.
How about the log of a convex function.
Right.
There, in fact, it's false.
There's no rule, that's, you can have the
log of a convex function, it's nothing.
It could be.
That, you could, that could be concave, it
could be convex, it can be anything.
There is no rule that says the log of a
convex function is anything.
because there, it just, just isn't one.
Everybody see that?
So that failed completely.
What is the correct parsing of this?
What you do is you make h the log sum x
function.
The log sum x function is clearly, it's
what's convex.
And it is increasing in each argument.
By the way, there, it really is
increasing, so I'm okay.
That's informal and formal.
It's [INAUDIBLE], and therefore, log sum x
of a bunch of convex functions is convex.
Everybody.
Got that?
So, actually,
a lot of this will become much clearer as
you get into actually doing these things.
But, what this says is, proving convexity
of something it's not as,
you just don't write the first parse tree
that comes down.
Because it might be wrong.
The first parsing might, well sorry, not
that it's wrong,
it won't work using these rules.
Okay?
Okay.
So minimu-, this is a very, minimization
is a very general construction.
Oh and I should contrast this with
maximization.
You remember the following.
That if I had a function F of 2 variables
here if this was,
if this function is convex in X for
each Y Then, the following, is, this is
just y in any set, right?
This function is convex in x, right?
So, there's absolutely no requirement that
the function be convex in x and
y and, in fact, y here doesn't even have
to be a vector.
It could be some any other kind of, it
could be some weird combinatorial thing.
It could be over parse trees or, it
doesn't really matter.
It could be Anything.
Right?
So
the sepremum of an arbitrary family of
convex functions is convex.
What's interesting is, infemum, the
minimum,
of a convex function, sometimes yields a
convex function, but
it's in very specific cases, and the
conditions are stronger.
It's this.
If you have a function that is, it has to
be jointly convex and X M Y.
So it's convex and both X M Y.
And if you a convex set then the infimum
is
sometimes called the partial minimization
of F.
Right?
Cause I have a function F of several,
well 2 blocks of variables X M Y.
And I'm going to minimize it over one
block.
And that will leave a function of the
remaining variable.
Has everybody got this?
That's called partial minimization, is
another name for this operation.
Partial minimization.
And partial minimization, here preserves
convexing.
So if you do partial minimization, you get
a convex one.
This is actually extremely important.
This is kind of the basis of a lot of
things like.
Dynamic programming or something like
that.
It says that you can minimize over some
things, and
look at this as a function of what's left.
And then you can minimize over some more
things.
And some more.
And some more.And some more.
And that would give you dynamic
programming in the right circumstances.
Right?
So that, that's the idea.
This is actually, this is actually quite
important.
OK.
So this is called partial minimization.
And it, it comes up in a whole bunch of
things.
You'll see some of it later.
Surely.
Oh, by the way in terms of epigraphs this
is embarrass-, look here,
it looks very complicated.
Like, oh my god you're minimizing this
thing and you know it's complicated.
It turns out in terms of epigraphs, this
is nothing but projections.
Projections of an epigraph onto, the
first, like you know, whatever it is,
end components.
It's nothing more.
You can check that, right?
Okay, so here's a, here's a very famous
example.
Let's take a quadratic function.
So that, that's it.
But we're going to block the variable into
2, the argument to 2, 2 parts.
X and Y, right?
So, here's a general.
That's, that's a general convex quadratic
function of 2 sets of variables,
quadratic form x and y.
And what it is, and it is jointly convex
in x and y,
that means its block matrix is positive
semidefinite.
For simplicity we'll assume c is positive
definite.
You, you actually don't need to, but
that's okay.
And now, if we minimize over y, you can do
that [UNKNOWN] you just set
the gradient equal to zero and various
other things, and what you'll get is a,
you, the result is actually a quadratic
form.
Over x.
And the matrix there is this thing, it's a
minus b c inverse b transpose.
You probabily have seen this matrix
before.
If not, get used to it because you will
see it in pretty much any class you take,
any good class.
If you don't see it then I'm suspicious.
Of, of the class.
Right so, for example This is the matrix
that comes up, in example for
circuits analysis, and mechanical,
mechanical engineering.
Everything is this, right, analysis of
structures in, probability.
This is conditioning.
This is the covariant, this is the
conditional covariance.
This is, what, this is how you condition.
Right?
So and it's actually a nice thing to
remember in your head as
a big high level thing is this,
is quadratic functions actually are
preserved under partial minimization.
That's actually extremely important,
right?
It says that if you, if you take a,
a quadratic function, convex quadratic
function.
And you minimize over some variables.
Then the result is a quadratic form,
convex quadratic form in the remaining
variables, and,
in fact, specifically, it's the Schur
complement.
This matrix is called the Schur
So, okay.
And we'll have a, we'll certainly have an
exercise on that, and
you're going to encounter the Schur
complement, like, throughout the class,
and, for that matter, throughout And every
other class you take, I hope.
Another not-obvious not-obvious operation
that
preserves convexity is perspective
mapping.
So perspective mapping is this, and you'll
remember,
you'll remember that perspective the
projective mapping for convex sets, right?
That was something that took [UNKNOWN], it
took X and
divided by the last component or
something.
And it basically, it's a, it's what it
looks like when you see
a three-dimensional object when you put
that onto an image plane, right.
So, this is the perspective of a function
is this.
You have a function from Rn to R.
The perspective is a function on the graph
space, so it actually takes two arguments.
One in Rn and one in R.
In fact r plus or
actually r plus, plus so positive argument
and its this tf of x over t.
So that, that is the perspective of a, of
a function, and it is the set the domain
is the set of points where t is positive
and x over t is in the domain of f.
And it turns out this is jointly convex in
x and t.
Okay?
So that's, that's, and by the way,
very simple if you want to know what this
is look like in terms of epic graphs, this
is you have the projective transformation
on the epic graph, and so that's.
That's what it does, gives you this.
So let's look at some examples.
Oh, here's one.
well, let's see.
F of x equals x transpose x.
That's the sum of the squares.
That's convex.
In fact, in some ways, that's your
canonical smooth convex function, right?
That graph is a bowl.
That couldn't get simpler than that.
So if you calculate the perspective of
that, its this.
You'd take, well, basically, you'd take.
T, and then x over t transpose, x over t.
And when all the smoke clears you get the
sum of the squares divided by t.
And that's convex.
Right?
So now you remember we showed x
squared over y.
Was convex when y is positive before, and
its got various names like you
know quadratic over linear I don't know
there's lots of names for that function.
But we did it by calculating a hessian and
that's fine it doesn't kill you to
calculate a hessian.
But here it says that this file was
instantly from the perspective,
mapping right,.
Here's one.
The negative logarithm in convex.
So if I calculate what its perspective is.
It's simply t log x over t.
And that is this thing.
And it says that's the relative
[INAUDIBLE].
And it says that that is going to be
convex, on.
On our, on-on, jointy in t and x, right?
So a lot of things will come out, it takes
an innocent function where convexity is
obvious or concavity like log, and you
apply something like this and
all of a sudden things like [UNKNOWN]
diverergence comes out.
Functions that look like it would be kind
of a pain in the ass to prove are convex,
and they just pop right out from this
rule.
Okay?
So they also often have interesting
meanings in that field.
So if you're in a field and you work out
the perspective of a function, right,
it often has some interesting meaning in
that field.
So, okay.
The conjugate.
So this is also something that's going to
come up like crazy in chapter 5 and
this may have come up in other classes
you've seen especially if
you took economics except it wasn't stated
this clearly.
Unless you took a graduate course.
If you took an undergraduate course you
saw this but they went on and on and
it wasn't clear, but anyway.
So the conjugate of a function is this,
and
again, all of this is sort of without
context, so.
Starting next week.
Beginning of next week you'll start seeing
you'll,
you'll actually start seeing applications
and stuff like that.
But for now all of this is without
context.
So here's the conjugate.
The conjugate, of a function is this: it's
denoted f star here.
And I mean that's kind of standard right,
because there's a whole bunch of
mathematical terms that you use and they
kind of evoke the same thing.
Dual Conjugate.
Can you think of many others?
Ii kind of think.
What they all suggest.
Things that if you do them.
twice you get back to where you started or
something like that, if certain things
happen.
it's one of them.
Transposed would be another word like
that.
Here it is.
It's the supremum, or
the maximum, of y transpose x minus f of
x.
Right, so that's, that's what it is.
Right?
So and, you know, the, there are a lot,
you can give lots of interpretations to
this beautiful interpretations, in fact.
Right?
Like let's see, you could do something
like this.
Your minimum,
this could be something Like this f of x
is cost if x is a set of vectors its
a vector that tells you how much of the
say the commodities that you own.
Right f of x tells you your cost.
I guess economists make it they look at
minus f of x that's your utility.
Right.
So, we look at f of x.
F of x is your cost.
And that's, that's how much it irritates
you to own that amount.
I mean, if it's negative, I suppose that
means you're happy or something like that.
But anyway, so that's f of x.
Then y here has the interpretation of
prices.
So y is a price vector.
And then what you're seeing is the
following.
It says, if the prices were y,
how much would you, of each of these
things would you?
How much would you purchase?
And the answer is, you would take your f
of x,
that's how irritated you are, and maybe I
got the sign wrong slightly, or
something, here maybe minus y is the price
vector.
But I would take f of x, and to that I
would add how much I have to pay for it.
And then I would, I'd minimize that.
And that would give me the, the least, the
amount that I should buy so that the sum
of how irritated I am plus how much I had
to pay for the good is minimized.
Right?
And so that's, that's where things like
this come up.
And it comes up in lots of other fields
too.
And we'll see things like this so.
OK.
So the picture is something like this.
Here's your function, and then what it
says is for,
to evaluate the conjugate what you do is
you, you take a slope like y.
So we're going to evaluate it at y and we
take a slope like that, x y.
And then it say we take,
we're going to maximize the difference
between this thing and f of x.
Right?
And so
that means you move This way, until you
just touch here.
And then in fact if you simply move over
here,
that gives you the height of this is the
negative conjugate here.
So, so in fact, in this case, for this
example we could
even do things, like I could ask you
questions about.
What happens if I increase y?
So for example, let me do this.
For this example here if I were to, y is
maybe about 1, here.
And I would like to know, if I make y 2,
what happens to the con,
what, what is the con, what does the
negative conjugate function do?
Just visually?
>> What happens?
>> It goes down.
>> It goes down, yup.
The negative conjugate goes down.
So what happens is the slope is now two
and
your point of tangency might be like here.
And it might go down right down to there.
Right?
And then that would be, so the negative
conjugate went down or
the conjugate went up.
The idea is you can visualize it.
Here's what's kind of cool.
It turns out that the conjugate of any
function is convex period, any.
Looks like a deep mathematical fact or
something like that.
It's extremely easy to show.
Let's show it.
What kind of function of y.
Is that expression.
What is it?
It's affine.
Right.
I heard someone say linear, that's cool,
because we're among friends here, but
it's affine.
Okay?
No, I mean, you know what I mean, right?
So, it's affine.
okay, so affine, an affine function is,
and
this is critical, because we're going to
promote it to something.
Convex.
So, I can also promote it to concave, by
the way.
That's what it mean to be [INAUDIBLE],
'cause you're both.
I'll promote it to convex.
This says, take the supremum parameterized
by x of a family of convex functions.
In fact, they're [INAUDIBLE].
Well, the supremum of any family.
Of convex functions as convex, so this is
convex, period.
Right?
So, okay, so that, that's the the
conjugate.
Okay.
Some examples, you can work these out.
I mean, it's a bit silly right now, but I
mean, you should look, go,
go through this once, but then later
we'll, this will also Be just as
completely central part of the course, so
if you take the negative logarhtm you
would have to for example calculate what
this and you'd work out what that was.
I mean it turns out if y is bigger or
equal to zero the answer is when you take
the supremum its plus infinity.
If y is negative though you can work out
what this is.
You can work out what the optimal x what
the optimal x is and so on and so
forth you get that expression.
Here's an interesting one.
Take convex quadratic.
So, that's one half ex transpose q x.
And then you calculate the supreme of
this.
Well, this is easy to do, you just set the
gradient equal to zero.
Because that's, everything's got, got the
right curvature.
And it turns out The answer is this.
So the conjugate of a quadratic form is
the quadratic form with
the inverse matrix, right.
So there's, and we'll see there's lots of
intersting things going on here.
So now what we're going to do is we're
going to talk about two three, sorry,
three extensions of convexity.
Right, so there's actually, like, tons.
Like, 20 or 30 different extensions, and
they have all sorts of names like
quasi-convex, pseudo-convex, you know,
quasipseudo-convex, generalized convex.
Generalized, quasi, pseudoconvex and so
on.
And, and often in these books somewhere
around page 500 there's usually a diagram.
So, now we get a very clear picture.
And there's going to be like 20 different
things and
you'll say now we see that a pseudoconvex,
Schur-convex,
quasiconvex function is also such-and-such
convex.
Anyway, so, alright, so
Some of these extensions are useful.
others, maybe not so much.
so, done a bunch of triage here.
And come down to a handful that are
actually useful, like three, okay?
And they're, they're fairly natural.
But we'll, these are things that are
going to come up all the time.
So, quasi convex is one.
And a function is quasi convex.
what that means is this it says that the
sublevel sets are convex that,
that's all it means.
Oh another name for this is uni-modal.
So in probability it would be referred to
as unimodal and
maybe some other fields too.
Right so and, and for example for a scalar
function it just means the following.
It says that if I slice the function at
any level and I look at the sublevel sets.
Well, in R, I get an interval.
But it could be half.
You know?
Like, for example, when I slice at beta.
I should get, I get a half, infinite
interval.
I mean I get a, well, yeah.
F, an infinite interval right?
Everybody got this?
And it's not hard to figure out what the
condition for quasi convexity is in R.
It's basically that it is monotone
decreasing up to some point.
And then, well, monotone non-increasing,
and
then monotone non-decreasing to the right
of it.
That's it.
And that, by the way that justifies this
ideal of unimodal, right?
That it can't have 2 bumps, right?
That's what it can't have.
Okay.
So,
that's a quasi-convex function,
quasi-concave is the negative.
And quasi-linear is both.
Okay?
So let's look at some examples.
Well the square root of the absolute value
of x.
That's a function that looks like this.
Right?
And that is definitely not convex, and
it's definitely not concave.
But it's quasiconvex.
Right?
Because sublevel sets if
you draw a level here is just an interval.
So you're okay.
Here's one, the ceiling.
So that's, that's the integer part, right?
Or the, into the next, the integer that's,
that's bigger than the given function.
That, that's pretty weird.
Because that thing is integer valued,
right?
And you don't have very many integer
valued convex functions.
We have a couple, but they're really
silly.
Right, mostly they're constant, right, and
not interesting, right.
But that says you can be, the ceiling of a
function is, is quasilinear.
You'll see some more interesting examples
in certainly in the book and
in homeworks and in things like that.
Log x is quasilinear.
So it's both, a monotone function is both
quasiconcave and quasiconvex.
Here's one, x1 x2.
That's a product.
That's definitely not convex.
It's not concave.
In fact, it's hessian, right?
That's a quadratic form, right.
And the hessian, the hessian is just this
right?
It's like that.
And matrices like that, clearly, it
clearly has split eigen values.
Right?
It's got a positive one and
a negative one.
And that tells you, kind of, like where if
you're looking at a function closely.
Well globally.
Cause it's actually a quadratic form.
It says that in one direction, it goes
like that, and
in another direction, it curves up.
It's a saddle point.
Everywhere.
Right.
That's the curvature.
So that thing is for sure not convex, not
concave.
But it is quasi-concave.
And to test that, you'd say what is the --
what are the points that look like this,
right, x1, x2 is bigger Than t.
That's the hypo yeah this is not the
hypograph,
sorry this is the super-level set, not the
sub-level set.
Oh, and of course we have to have x i
positive.
Right?
That set looks like this.
That's all these things.
That's all this stuff over here.
Alright, and for any t that's going to be
convex.
Okay?
So that's it.
There's a lot of other ones, a very famous
one is linear-fractional, so
a ratio of two affine functions.
Notice it's called linear-fractional, but
that's already ingrained in the in, in, in
standard mathematical speech, so, anyway,
linear-fractional functions Are quasi.
They are going to be actually quasilinear.
Right?
Because if
you ask what are the points where f is
bigger than sum value t.
Right?
Or less than sum value t.
All you do is you take the denominator,
put it on the other side.
And you get a linear inequality.
So you get a half space.
Everybody got that?
So I just said that, but that's, you'd,
you'd want to check on that.
Okay.
here, let's look at one that's real.
So is internal rate of return.
So here, a vector x represents a cash
flow.
And it's, the sign is it's if, if it's a,
if it's cash coming in, it's positive.
Okay?
So that's, it's a cash flow, right?
So, and then lots of things would look
like you could write out all sorts of
financial instruments.
As non-, I guess they're non contingent
[INAUDIBLE].
So you could write them out as a cash flow
vector, right?
Right?
Like, if I, if I lend something to someone
else.
Then what happens is my x zero is
negative.
And then all my X1s, X1, X2,
up to Xn, would be principal plus interest
payment, right.
An interest only thing would look like I
have X0 if I,
if I borrow interest only, X0 is positive.
I then have,.
You know?
Negative things.
'Cuz I'm, I'm paying the interest.
And then on the last step, the last one, I
would pay off the principal, right?
So something like that, right?
And you can do all of these things, right?
An amortized loan.
All these kind of things, right?
Okay.
Set a cash flow, it's a vector.
So we're going to assume x zero is
negative.
That means.
We're going to make an investment.
That's, that's, that's cash weak, so on
the zero thing, we're going to invest.
And you can turn it around too, it doesn't
matter.
But we're going to invest.
In amount x zero.
And, you should interpret x one, x two, x
three.
Those are payments to us.
I mean, if they're positive.
We hope they are.
Right.
By the way, they might not be there.
There might be further investments.
But if they're positive, the idea is that,
those are, we make an investment of x0 and
then x1, x2, x3, up to xn.
That's money that comes back in.
Okay.
Well if you have an interest rate r And
you discount these cash flows.
Then this'd be the present value,
right, it's just the sum of 1 plus r to
the minus i, xi.
Right, because the i is indexing periods
in the future and
you discount each one by the interest
rate.
Okay, so, that's the so called present
value and
it's a function of the cash flow vector
and the rate Interest rate.
Now the internal rate of return, of a cash
flow vector or
investment sequence here, is this.
It's the smallest, by the way it's not
said this way because people are not
clear about these things and it's usually
wrong and all that kind of stuff, but
in fact this is the correct, this is the
correct way to say it.
They say this: it's the interest rate
which makes the present value 0.
Okay?
So that, that's, that's the idea, right?
So, that's silly.
Because if this thing, this thing here
could actually be zero for
multiple values of r.
In which case, it's the smallest one,
right?
So it's the smallest interest rate which
makes the present value zero, right?
And so the idea is something like this.
If you make a good investment, it means.
X0, you don't put in, your initial
investment is not very much and
lots of stuff comes back to you.
And it comes back to you so fast that even
when you, when you...
It takes a lot of discounting to make it
look like the net present value is zero.
So that's the idea.
Okay, so this is the internal rate of
return.
That's really quite complicated as a
function if you think about it Right,
in fact if you really, the only way you'd
be able to do this would be to do
something like even compute you well you
take x and you might do somehting where
you try some internal rate of return and,
and, and look at and you vary it.
Or calculate the internal rate of return
over 100 values or something like that.
That would give you the internal rate of
return to some accuracy right.
You'd find where its slightly negative and
one where its slightly positive and OK.
It's a complicated function.
But it turns out it's quasiconcave.
So, quasiconcave says this.
It says the internal rate of return of a
cash flow sequence, right,
exceeds some number r, say, 10%, right?
That's true, if and only if the following
is true.
For all, for all, discount factors up to
That 10% value, right?
The net present values is positive, right,
so that's the, that's the idea, okay?
That, that, that would give it to you.
This as a function of x, what is that
actually, geometrically?
>> This inequality for a fixed value of r,
what does that look like?
In, in cash flow space?
>> Polyhedron.
>> It's what?
For a fixed value of r?
>> [INAUDIBLE] No, it's, it's a
polyhedron, I agree, but
it's, it's sim, much simpler.
What is it?
>> Halfspace.
Yeah.
It's an open halfspace.
Okay?
So that's an open halfspace.
And then this say's you have to take the
intersection of o,
of an infinite number of open half spa,
half spaces and
you get, in fact in that, turns out the
answer's closed.
But that's irrelevant.
So you take the int-, intersection of the
infinite number of half spaces.
And then that's actually going to be your
super level set.
And that basically is saying The
interpretation of this is beautiful.
It says these are the cash flow sequences
which have an internal,
intenral rate of return exceeding let's
say 10%.
Right, it's not all of them of course.
There's a whole bunch of crappy cash flow
sequences, there's good ones.
But the boys, it says that the super level
set.
Is convex.
Right?
And that means this thing is
quasi-concave.
Now I, I'm moving fast.
There's no way you could get all of this
right here.
So the idea more or less here is just to
get kind of the idea and the flavor of it.
Okay.
So let's look at some properties of
quasiconvex functions.
The first is, you have a modified Jensen
inequality.
In stead of saying that f, if you evaluate
it at a mixture of points,
is less than the corresponding mixture of
f values, instead of that,
this says you just write max.
And so the picture is, is kind of cool.
It's this, right?
Here's a, here's a generic quasiconvex
function.
Like that.
And what it, so
convexity, let me take some points where
it's definitely not convex.
There.
Okay?
So if I take those two points, that's X,
right?
That's Y.
And let me just take the midpoint, that's
A equals a half.
And we can see that by Jenson's
inequality, we're not doing well here.
It's, it's not, it's violated.
Right, OK.
However, what this says is that if I draw,
it says that instead of lying, you don't
have to lie.
The function doesn't have to be below the
cord connecting these two points on
the graph.
It has to be below this box,
which is kind of goes from whatever the
taller of one of them is and then down.
Right, so it has to sit under there.
That's a, that's a quasiconvex function.
There's first order conditions and
I think we'll, we'll come back to this
later in the course, but
it's basically something like this.
It says that, it says that if f of y is
less than f of x then the gradient of f
of x transpose y minus x is less than
zero.
So these, these might be the sublevel sets
of a quaziconvex function.
And it says that if If that is the
gradient, right?
Then it says that all points that are, had
a lower value of F,
lie in this half space, okay?
So, there are some things you have to
worry about.
Things like this.
Sums of quasi functions are not quasi
convex.
And extreme, I'll just draw the, I'll draw
the picture.
And that's the end of the story.
So here's the picture.
There, there's a quasiconvex function.
And here's another one.
Okay?
And now add them together in your head
please and
you will see a non-quasiconvex function.
Right.
Or maybe clearer, a non-unimodal function.
Right, because you'll see something that's
got two bumps.
You, you draw your sublevel set right at
the right thing.
You get two intervals or whatever you like
as the sublevel set and it's all over.
Okay?
So.
Okay.
Next generalization.
This is going to be two out of our three,
is log concave.
Actually the, the quasi-convex stuff is
actually fairly straight.
Forward.
It just introduces some notation for
some stuff that's obvious, will solve a
lot of problems that are quasi convex, and
things like that.
We'll get to that later.
Log convexity, and by the way, for
some weird reason, it comes up what's
interesting always is log concavity.
This is not a simple extension.
It, it, there are some things here that
are not obvious at all.
It's, It's kind of, it appears to be quite
deep.
So, a function is log-concave if its log
is concave.
I mean that's just.
That's what it means, very simple.
And what that means is this.
Another way to say that is this.
It says that, it says that if you evaluate
f at a mixture of two points x and y.
The f-, if it were concave, it would be
bigger than the mixture of the f values.
But here what it says is, it's bigger than
the geometric mixture.
Geo, weighted geometric mean, however you
want to call that.
Okay?
So that's what it says.
And you take the log of this, and that,
that's what it means to be concave.
Okay, so it's log-convex if log, if the
log of the function is convex, and
if the function's obviously positive.
So, examples would be powers.
But this is actually where it really comes
up.
And we'll see this later in great detail.
It turns out, tons of common probability
densities, are log concave.
Right so that, that's going to be
completely, I mean, tons, that, it takes
you a while to even think of a named
distribution that is not log concave.
You can, I mean especially if you're in
statistics, but
Generally speaking, there, all the ones
you bump into, they are all log concave.
And it's going to have huge implications
later in the class when we do statistical
methods and estimation and things like
that.
And they're going to be good.
The consequences.
So here's one.
Here is the density, of a normal, random
variable.
With, you know mean X bar and co-variant
sigma.
Okay?
And
if I take the log of that density, what do
I get?
Well I get a constant that's not relevant
minus a, minus a convex quadratic.
So it's a concave quadratic.
Okay, so that's an example.
By the way, a uniform distribution, on a
convex set.
Right, so any uniform distri, uniform
distribution on any convex set.
Has a log concave density, right?
Because the, here's, let's talk about what
that is.
If I have a uniform distribution on a, on
a set c.
Then the density is a constant on c.
And then off of c, the density is zero.
You take logs.
It says the log of the dens-, the log
density is a constant.
It's a log of the original constant,
right, on c.
And then it goes to minus infinity.
And you visualize that in your head and
you realize that's concave.
Okay?
And
in fact that's really the extended value
of extension.
Right?
So, so, that's another one.
And here's one.
This is much less obvious.
The cumulative distribution function, of a
Gaussian.
Okay?
So that's, that is log concave.
Right, so that, that's something.
That looks like this, right?
It goes like that, like that.
And so that.
So something like, things with, like these
[INAUDIBLE] shapes.
These, many of these.
Well, actually, the cumulative density of
any,.
Well, log concave density is, is log
concave.
But we'll get to that, right?
So, [INAUDIBLE] when you look at that,
that does not look.
Concave, right?
So what you have to do is you look at that
thing.
And you take the log in your head, right?
And when you take the log in your head,
here's what happens.
You know, that's, like, a half, right?
That's one.
And this is going down to zero.
And so what the log does is over here.
It, it takes that part of the curve and
bends it down.
And what you get is a quadratic.
OK, so you just get a quadratic,
sorry you get something that approaches a
quadratic I'm sorry in this case OK.
So this would give you some something like
that OK.
Now let's look at osme properties of these
well the first is, if you have a,
I mean one condition is this you, you can
say that a,
a twice differentiable f with convex I
mean its log concave if and only if.
This inequality holds and we can rewrite
this another way.
We can write it this way.
I'll just erase this part.
If this inequality,
now concave would be if the right hand
side of this expression were zero.
Right?
If that was the zero matrix, that would be
a concave function.
It says, it says the Hessian function is
negative semidefinite.
Here though, you allow the Hessian to be
less than or equal to a rank one matrix.
Right?
So you have to
know a few things with what I'm about to
say, but I'll say it anyway.
That says you can have one eigenvalue of
the [INAUDIBLE] can be positive.
And you can still be log concave, okay?
Okay.
Now, how do I know that.
Well, if a matrix is less than a rank one
matrix.
.Then, in fact, all its eigenvalues but
one.
Are, are less or equal to 0.
Okay?
So, and this is just to
give you some flavor at this.
So, it says that more is allowed.
And in fact we already saw that earlier,
right?
So, here is an example where clearly here,
the second derivative is positive, but
if you take that log, and it ends up being
negative.
OK, here's one.
Let's see.
Product of log-concave functions is log,
that's trivial because if you take the
product of two functions and
take the log, this basically says that the
sum of two concave functions is concave.
So this is easy.
The sum of log-concave functions, that's
not always log-concave.
So in probability that means that a
mixture distribution with
log-concave distributions is not
necessarily log-concave.
That's totally obvious, right?
Because look, here's a galsion, here's
another galsion.
You take the sum or the average to get the
mixture distribution and
it, it's definitely not log-concave.
Okay?
And then here's a very interesting one.
Integration.
If you have a function that takes two, two
var-.
Two block, I block the argument into two
things.
And I integrate over one of a set of
variables.
So, I, so this is like partial
minimization.
But this is partial integration.
Okay.
If I do that the result is log concave.
So the, the, if I integrate out over, and
it, you know, by the way, this would be,
this would actually, this is part of
conditioning or something like that.
In, in, a dense, if you'd like to think of
it that way.
And what that says is this thing is logged
concave.
The integral is logged concave.
We'll look at that.
By the way.
For that fact,
I'm [INAUDIBLE], I am unaware of an
elementary derivation of this.
So, here's some consequences.
It turns out that, because of the
integral.
[INAUDIBLE] it turns out the convolution
is log concave.
Is preserved from, that's very interesting
for
probability densities, 'cuz this says the
following.
It says that if I have two.
Random variables, each with a log-concave
probability distribution.
Then the sum of those random variables
also, whose density is the convolution,
it says that sums of, it says random, if
you take sums of random variables with
log-concave distributions, you get a
log-concave distributions preserved.
Right?
Here's one.
This is a very interesting one.
This is alone just has huge applications.
It's this If you have a convex set.
And I have a random variable with a log
concave pdf, then the following is true.
I make a function which is this.
This is actually called the yield function
option like in manufacturing.
It's the probability.
So I have a set that looks like this.
Here's my set c.
And what I do is I, to evaluate my
function, I take x and
then to that I add this random variable.
Okay, so I, it doesn't matter lets make it
galcion or,
it doesn't really matter, it's some
galcion and it's spread around here, so
Let it, you know, it would, I'll try to
draw it.
I don't know how to draw a distribution,
but it looks something like that, right?
There's a little volcano that kind of goes
up, and you, and then what, the point is
now, you look at that as a, what you do is
you take the total probability in the set.
Right?
And then you move that target point, x.
You can think of it that way.
And it changes with the yield, right?
So the application of this is pretty
simple: C is a set of values of
some parameters that are acceptable,
right?
So it's you -- you build a chip or
something like that,
and it means that the final thing actually
does clock at this rate and last this long
or something li- -- it doesn't ma- -- it's
some manufacturing problem.
Everybody got it?
Then y is just the, the variations in
manufacture.
Just uncontrolled, right?
Critical dimensions, things like that it,
your ability to control the process, and
things like that.
I mean, that, you're pushing everything to
the absolute limit, so
it's not like you can, yeah.
If, if the distribution is super tight,
then you're not doing high-end
manufacturing.
Right.
You could be
pushing this way harder, right?
So, you push it and it looks like that.
Then, the problem of choosing x is the
target point that you set your machines,
your manufacturing machines to do.
You say please target this.
And you know, look, if you target it out
here,
that's like really dumb [LAUGH], right?
Because basically, most of the time, the
thing, comes, it doesn't work at all.
By the way, every now and then, it works.
Right?
Because every now and then, a random
manufacturing fluctuation will come up
with that point and you'll have one
working device.
Everybody following this, right?
So, that, that point,
this point here would not be a
particularly good choice yield wise.
Okay?
And so then, obvious question is how do
you What target point would you choose to
maximize the yield, right?
And it takes very little imagination to
realize actually how much,
how actually, how much this would actually
mean in certain contexts right.
I mean it's incredibly important, right.
And so the idea's there, do you want to,
it's going to be somewhere in the,
what this says is that function, the log
of that yield function.
Is actually concave.
That says we'll be able to maximize it,
right?
So it's, that's going to be a convex
optimization problem.
That means we can effectively solve that
problem, right?
So, so just this little thing already has
like serious implications.
So how do you show something like that?
Well, you just set it up for this integral
thing.
And so the way you do it is this.
You write this thing, the thing that we're
interested in, as the following.
As it's an integral of two things, the
product of two things.
Actually and, these things are the
following.
So p is, are that's the density of y.
And g is this weird function, that's like
one or zero.
Right?
Both of those functions are log concave.
Right, p by assumption.
G is because g is, actually, it's silly.
It's log zero on, on, on c, and then it's
minus infinity outside c,
that's a con, it's silly, but it's a
convex fun, a concave function.
Right?
Product of two log-concave Integral over
some of the variables in this case just y
that's log concave and
this is what you have so that's the idea.
OK, so I think we already talked about
this, this is the idea.
And this says that the yield the log of
the yield function is, is concave.
So and by the way we don't know that yet
but
we'll see later that means that basically
we can effectively.
Maximizing, right?
So, by the way a lot of weird things
happen this way.
Where there's an asymmetry between what
you want to do with something and
there's a, and there's also a asymmetry in
what you can and cannot do.
This is a perfect example.
Right?
You take a yield function, there's a
strong asymmetry here.
You want to maximize it.
You don't want to minimize it.
Well, you can turn everything around and
mini, that'll be you want to, the set C
will be some terrible outcome and
you want to maximize, you want to avoid
it, but, anyway.
And it turns out, it's concave, that's
something we can maximize.
If it were convex, we cannot.
So, okay.
And our final, generalization X functions
is,
to generalize it to the idea of, vector
values.
Right? So here are the ideas. I'll take a
function which takes, you know,
as usual a vector argument.
But it returns a vector argument, not a
scaler argument.
So I
take a A vector argument.
And you define a function to be K-convex
if the domain is convex and
if this Jenson inequality holds.
But it holds with respect to this concave.
Okay?
Now this mostly only comes up in a couple
of, you know, in, in a couple of ways.
I mean a couple of these are are come up
much more often than other things.
And so one for example, if this is, if
this is matrix inequalities, and
these are symmetric matrices, and that's
matrix inequality, then this,
a function that is K-convex with respect
to the positive semi-definite cone,
that's called matrix convex.
So, that's.
So here, for example, if I've a mapping
from m by m symmetric matrices, into m
by m symmetric matrices, and the mapping
is the following, you square the matrix.
That's it.
Then, the claim is that is convex, matrix
convex.
Okay?
And.
What you have to check is this.
You want to check here, whether or not you
have to check whether z
transpose X squared z is convex with
respect to capital X, right.
For each Z.
That's what you have to check.
And, that is true because you write it
this way.
And now this expression, capital x times
little z, is actually linear in capital x,
and then you have a norm.
Squared, that's convex.
Okay?
So this, so this expression is convex in
capital x, okay?
By the way, it kind of suggests that,
right?
I mean, you know, if x squared is your
canonical convex function,
little x squared Then Y wouldn't capital x
squared become x as well.
I mean you have to be very careful with
these things because some
things are wrong.
For example x, you don't get a whole lot
more.
I mean that's convex and capital as well.
And the x of a matrix, symmetric matrix is
actually not a matrix convex so,
there's some weird stuff happens.
I mean seriously weird stuff so but In
this case it didn't happen.
Okay, now this is true for any z, and that
tells you that I removed the z's and
I changed this inequality to a matrix
inequality,
because that's what it means for matrix
inequality to hold, right.
It says that if you take the one quadratic
form and
another, this quadratic form is always
less than this one.
That, that's always true, then it means
that this matrix is less or
equal to this one in the matrix sense, and
so you get, you get a statement that looks
like, like that, okay, so that, that's it,
and this is sophisticated statement.