Part one of the course was basically well,
all the analysis and the mathematics
behind convex optimization.
Right?
So convex analysis, the basics there.
The most important thing there you need to
know are things like convexity of
a whole bunch of atoms.
And a lot of, and a lot of these
composition rules, and
other rules, these are good to know about.
Right?
Then there was a section on
the anatomy of the anatomy of optimization
problems, and some of them had names.
Right?
Like, you have linear programs and
second-order com programs, and geometric
programs, and things like that.
Right?
In some sense, those names matter less and
less.
You should know that already, because with
things like CVX a lot of
the transformation of a problem that has
no name into some problem that has a name.
It can be automated or is part, at least
partially automated.
Still you need to know the name so
that, I don't know you can talk to other
people, but that's the idea.
And then of course there's duality, so
when duality is sort of a big field by
itself.
And it's, it's really nothing but an
organized way to come up
with lower bounds for problems, period,
that, that's what it is.
In fact it's quite a trivial way,
in some sense, to come up with them but
it's an organized way.
And what is shocking is that in for
convex problems, it's generally speaking,
not always, but that,
these are little minor details without
with a with a constraint qualification.
It's sharp, right?
So that these lower bounds are actually
sharp but
then we'll see lots of advantage, we'll
see lots of uses.
You will see, by the way, if you look, if
you take other courses,
you'll see examples where people use
duality all the time.
They wont even say it.
Right?
I mean, you take a wireless course and
there you're trying to figure out how to
do,
you know, assign powers to channels or
whatever.
And they'll call it something else like
water filling or something.
But now that you know the secret, you'll
just look at it and say, oh.
That's that, that's called duality, right?
Or you take a information theory course,
they're telling you about how to
allocate bits to something, and you look
at it and you go, that's duality.
So, okay.
Duality also has, there's a lot of
aesthetics in duality where it's useful to
recognize that problems that can at first
look very different.
Or actually intimately related, right?
So and this will come up when we look at
applications a lot.
so, for example, it'll be weird things
like, again, if, if you're in
statistics or if you have taken some
advanced machine learning courses,
you would know things like this.
But you get weird things where You know
duality of certain you get maximum
liklihood estimation problems.
The duals are things that look like
maximum entropy or
Colback-Liberg divergents type things
right.
And so I by the way if you don't know what
I'm talking about that's fine.
I'm being very obscure now, but I just,
I want to just point that this is going to
permeate lots of things you've seen.
And actually in various areas it's
completely well known.
I mean people know these things, okay.
So now we're going to start another
section of the course.
It's the middle section and honestly this
is the payoff.
So I mean the truth is you've already seen
enough.
You're already being paid right now.
I mean, homework is now fun.
It's useful and so on.
Well, that's my opinion.
You're the one doing it.
But I still say it's fun, and it's useful,
and stuff like that.
This is really the payoff for the course.
Right?
That what we're going to do is for
the next couple of weeks.
We're just going to look at various
application areas, you know, one by one.
And we'll look at some topics, some will
be obvious our first,
our first topic here is going to be
totally obvious.
Actually some will be less obvious.
I mean we'll look at some weird
geometrical ones,
some ones in statistics and stuff like
that, and they'll be,
they won't be totally obvious.
Actually watch out because some of the
most useful material is in
the totally obvious stuff.
Like the stuff we're about to do.
Is shockingly elementary and unbelievably
useful.
So so this is it.
This is also,
by the way the material that's not in any
traditional course on this material.
Right, because the traditional course
segues immediately from
convex analysis to basically deadly,
boring, long,
complicated proofs of complexity of
algorythms.
Right, so, this is the part that's
missing, so.
OK, so we're going to start in,
by the way these problems have been
categorized into gross areas.
This is approximation and fitting, but
we're going to see that this'll overlap of
course with things like statistics.
I mean obv- duh, a lot of statistics is
basically fitting models,
which is in some sense approximating data.
So we'll see connections between these
things right, you shouldn't be
surprised also I should add that in the
lectures here we're just going to cover
some of the high level stuff there's a lot
more material in the book and
you should absolutely read it, well, put
it, let me put it another way we
will hold you absolutely responsible for
everything in the book so We'll exercise
a reasonable fraction, a reasonable
fraction of it, through the homework.
Not all, because it's just too much, but
we will work with, our working assumption
is that you will have read all of it, so.
OK, so, we'll start with just this very
general idea of approximation and fitting.
And we'll start with norm approximation
and
then something which is a vague dual of
it, lease norm problems.
And then something that combines kind of
both regularized approximation and
then we'll look at robust approximation.
And this is sort of this is relatively
new.
This is stuff from the last of couple
years, or Last decade or
something like that, so okay.
So norm approximation.
Well, I mean in simplest case it's just
this.
We minimize the norm of ax minus b, right?
And you have your data is a matrix a,.
Usually with M bigger than N.
So it's taller than.
It, it's a, it's a tall matrix.
A skinny matrix.
and, and the norm.
This is just any old norm on our end.
Right.
So, when you instantiate or
specify the norm, it becomes a specific
problem.
Right.
It becomes, you know, regression or
some least squares, that kind of thing.
Okay, and, now when we are doing this if x
star is the minimum of this, and
I should warn you right now the minimum
does not have to be unique.
You know that of course for the two norm,
if a is per rank its unique, right, but
in fact you know, for other norms it's
absolutely false.
So do one norm minimization many norm
minimization It's incredibly common that
there are multiple optimizers.
[COUGH] So here, this just, this notation,
it doesn, I don't mean,
I don't mean to suggest that there's a
unique one, because there need not be.
Okay.
So what's an interpretation, well there's
lots of interpretations.
The first one is geometric.
Basically what it says is.
Vectors of the form Ax, or x varies,
sweeps out the range of A.
Right, so that's a subspace.
Then it says, then it says you have a
fixed vector b, and so the question, and
then you have the, the distance as
measured by the norm between b and Ax.
And so, basically what you're saying is.
Please, this basically says the optimal
value of this thing is literally,
it is literally the distance of b to the
range of a.
So solving this problem is the same as
saying find me
the distance under the norm, norm here, of
b to the range of a.
So that, that's what you're doing.
So that's what it is.
And if, and you say find a, a point
closest to this right?
And here I didn't put v so it's not
technically wrong.
If I had put any article in here it would
have been A and
then it would have been correct so.
Okay now another fit ano, another way this
comes up is in estimation.
So in estimation it goes like this.
It says, I, I, I want to estimate some
parameters x.
Okay?
And what I have is I
have linear measurements of x.
That's y equals a x, but they're corrupted
with noise.
And that's the, so I add v.
Right?
And so now, if I asked you to guess x,
interestingly, implicitly, you're guessing
v.
That's really what you're doing.
Because when you guess x, then y minus Ax
is v.
Right, and so the problem of guessing X is
the same as guessing V,
and we'll see that this is exactly the
statistical interpretation as well.
Right?
So you're basically guessing that, and so
what we're doing is something like this.
We're intuitively here.
We'll do it quite differently when we do
statistics, but
here we're saying intuitively.
That among possible v's, smaller is more
plausible.
Smaller v in norm is more plausible than
larger v.
Alright?
So that's the implicit assumption here.
And in that case, you would say that
solving this problem would
give you something like the most plausible
value of x.
Right?
Because it's the one where the implicit,
when you are implicitly guessing v, it is
smallest, as measured by the norm, right?
So that, tells you about pla-
plausibility.
It's, it's the least implausible or
something.
Okay.
Another one is optimal design.
So here, x is a set of design perameters.
That, that you can fiddle with.
These can be a force profile for a
vehicle.
It could be all.
It could be all sorts of things.
Right?
Then you have a linear process.
So, X causes the results, AX, and you have
a target, which is B,
that you want to hit.
If you can hit it, fantastic, but if you
can't.
You have to get you have to compromise and
simply get close and
then how do you determine what your
happiness level is or
really we should say your irritation level
right.
So how irritated will you be if you want b
little b.
And get a x.
And we'll measure that by a norm.
So the norm encodes your irritation level.
And then it says, and the best design is,
is obtained by solving this problem here.
Because it gets you closest to what you
want, measured by your irritation.
And we're measuring irritation by a norm.
Everybody got this?
So these I mean Don't over interpret what
I'm saying,
because what I'm saying is completely
trivial.
So, if you think for a second 'Oh, I
better go think about this' or
something, you're over interpretting it.
And that's going to continue by the way
for
a few more things I'm going to say about
this, so.
It really is this simple.
Okay.
okay.
Now, let's instantiate some specific
examples.
If you take the 2-norm, you get least
squares, right?
And what is the analytical solution of it?
I mean, you know, if, if A, if A is full
rank,
you know, it's a just a least square, so
it's A transpose A inverse A transpose B.
Right, so that's your least squares
solution.
Oh, and in that case I should say that the
project has lots of names.
It's called regression in statistics.
I guess it's called least-squares fitting
everywhere else.
Okay, so that's the so there's probably
some other names in specific fields for
this, but I can't remember what they are
right now.
Okay, but interestingly.
We can do other things.
If you take an infinite norm,
then it's called, it's actually got lots
of name actually.
If you minimize the norm of AX minus B
infinite,
it's called Chebyshev approximation is one
name.
Another name is mini max, mini max
fitting.
Right?
And It's actually quite interesting, what
minimax fitting is.
And it has it's uses.
It basically says I want to fit a model,
but
what I care about is the absolute maximum
error.
Not the, well, not the sum of the squares.
I care about the absolute maximum.
Right?
And that would be minimax fitting.
It's got lots of applications.
Interestingly, least squares is used by
zillions of applications.
Right?
It's the basis.
It's the workhorse of giant fields.
Pretty much it's the workhorse in
statistics.
Right?
I mean, pretty much, right?
I mean, all the advanced stuff people do,
that's coming on line a bit, but.
Bottom line is most people are doing
regressions, right?
And if you're snickering,
making fun of how unsophisticated people
are in statistics, don't.
Because for example, control is the same
way.
All of control.
You know, I mean there are some advanced
control methods, that's fine.
Are they working?
Yes, they're working.
But the bottom line is that most control
is kind of least,
is variations on least squares.
Signal processing, image processing,
again, don't make fun of them,
it's mostly least squares.
Are there more advanced methods coming
online?
Absolutely, right, but mostly, it's done
by least squares.
So, interestingly, what you find is, this
is, is discussed almost not at all.
In any standard curriculum.
Bottom line is that the modern, the modern
viewpoint in my opinion, is,
that turns out we're going to find out
later computationally,
this is no harder than that.
Shocking isn't it?
It's absolutely no harder.
Right?
But no one knows it, because everyone in
this room has been exposed to this,
probably in multiple contexts.
Right?
In some class on [UNKNOWN] series,
on some class on linear algebra, probably
in other classes, you've seen this.
And probably no one has seen this I'm
guessing.
So, okay.
So, anyway, back to the main thread here.
That this, of course you can solve this
problem as a linear program.
Now, that may or may not be relevant, but
because may times, in automatic system
will do this for you.
But, nevertheless, it can be written as an
LP.
What there is not, is there is not a
formula like that, and
that's why we don't teach it, in some of
the more traditional courses.
Alright, so, okay.
Here's another very interesting one.
It also has a very long history.
If the sum of absolute value sum of
absolute residuals approximation,
you use norm one.
That says minimize this.
That's extremely interesting.
Again, no formula, you can solve it as an
LP.
We'll find out later, the computational
effort, of solving this, and this.
It's basically the same.
It's the same.
There's no difference.
Right?
I mean, is that,
there's an aesthetic difference if you're
locked in the 19th century aesthetic.
There's a big aesthetic difference, but,
computationally, none.
This is really interesting this one.
It's an example, of what we're going to
see later is a robust Estimator.
The properties are shocking and it's
actually things like that are form
the basis of actually a lot of modern
statistics and a lot, machine learning and
a lot of other things so we'll, we'll,
we'll see that.
So it's quite different and you know these
are not new.
Well the fact that this is Chebyshev and
I'm not sure, I'm sure there's a Russian
name we can attach to this.
And it would be traced to the 30's and
40's.
In fact, at Moscow State University, I'll
check with my friends and
find out, what the correct name is, but
there is shirley one.
and, so these are not new things.
It just kind of languished in obsurity,
until the last decade, now,
they're the height of fashion, of course.
Depending, in various fields.
Okay.
So now, we're going to look at, sort of
the generalization of norm.
minimization.
What we'll do is this.
We're going to, just to make the notation
easier,
we're going to introduce a x minus b.
We're going to call that the residual.
Assign a name to it, r.
Okay?
And then what you'll want to do is
essentially you want all the entries of
r small.
In fact, if you get all the entries of r
zero, that'd be ideal, right?
Because you'd have I don't know,
it'd mean you got exactly what you wanted,
Ax equals b.
Right?
So, but let's, assuming that's not the
case,
you're going to have to compromise, and
you can't have all the residuals zero.
Right?
So what we'll do is we'll penalize values
of r by function phi.
That's just a function from r to r.
Okay?
That's just, that's it.
And so, we're going to minimize the sum of
the penalties.
You know, you could divide by M and get
the average penalty.
I mean, it wouldn't make, it wouldn't
change the problem, but
give you a better interpretation or
something.
OK?
So, now you can choose phi and
please don't over-interpret what I'm
going to say because
you're going to want to but it really is
as trivial as I'm saying.
So here it is.
You use phi to shape how irritated you are
with the residual of a certain size,
that's it, okay?
So for example if you take phi is the
square function then that tells you
something like this.
If a residual is why, I'll ask you.
If phi is the square function this is li
squares.
And, and that implicitly says that if a
residual is small, how irritated are you?
Yeah, very little.
Everyone got that?
So the very means it's small, it's small
squared.
Okay.
Now, in least squares, if a residual is
big, how much does it irritate you?
[COUGH] Very much, thank you.
Very much.
And the very is not casual, right?
It's not, so.
All right.
So, I mean, and that's kind of the idea
behind these squares.
Right?
That, that, that, you know,
if a residual is small and you're like you
know, fine.
If it's big, not cool.
Right?
So, all right.
And just, don't over interpret this.
Right?
By the way,
we'll have multiple other interpretations
when we do statistics about densities and
all sorts of crazy stuff.
Maximum likelihood.
But for now Take everything sophisticated
out of your mind, and
we're just doing this way.
Now if I take phi as the absolute, I get
L1.
Let's talk about that.
If I take in L1, an absolute value
penalty, then if a residual is small,
how much does it irritate you?
Let's compare.
How.
If you.
If you compare that to the square, how
much does it irritate you?
More.
Much more.
Right?
So, in least squares,
a small residual that irritates you very
little.
I'm going to try and say it correctly.
And, but an L1 norm, right?
And here at, in the absolute value, it
says you're irritated a little bit, but
relatively speaking, that's a lot.
I mean, compared to squares, right?
How about this: with absolute value,
if you've got a big residual, how
irritating is that in the least squares?
Very.
And in absolute value?
It's irritating, without the very.
Everybody got this?
Okay, I mean look this, this, I know this
is,
sounds, it really is this dumb, you'll,
you'll, it really is trust, trust me.
But this is unbelievably useful right?
Because I think that what has not been
recognized Until relatively recently and
is not by any means fully recognized now
is the following fact.
That (?) is the one case where you get
some silly 19th century formula, right.
But all the other things we're talking
about you can solve just as easily.
Right, and so people haven't looked at
them, so, all right.
So let's look at some things.
Well we just talked about the quadratic in
detail.
here, let's do something else.
Here's dead zone linear.
That's this function right here.
Look at this it's, it's, it's linear.
And then it's got a dead, what's, we will
call it dead zone, in the middle.
So between plus and minus 0.25.
Someone, you should articulate,
what does that mean about how you care
about residuals?
Aye, and this case is very specific.
If it's less than some threshold, it
doesn't irritate you at all.
And, and in particular, that goes two
ways.
It means that a residual of point, of,
of 0.001 is absolutely no better than a
residual of 0.25 here.
None.
Right?
By the way, there's plenty of applications
of this and it doesn't, it doesn't,
you know you can think, they're going to
to come you like pretty quickly.
You make, if you have like a, an analog
digital converter and you,
you'd make a measurement then you know,
being off by something less than your LSB,
your least significant bit.
It's not better, I mean, it's, you're not
better, it's just,
all you know is this value, signal value
is, in some interval.
You don't know anything else.
Okay.
And the fact that it's linear, once you go
outside the dead zone.
Let's talk about how much you care about
large residuals.
So you'd say look, who likes large
residuals?
No one.
I don't like large residuals.
But you don't go nuts about it as with a
quadratic.
That would be the explanation.
Everybody got this?
By the way, we're anthropomorphizing all
of these, but
what we're going to find out is this does
exactly what you want.
So okay.
So.
Here's another weird one.
Here's log barrier with a, with a, limit
a.
So there's just an expression here.
It doesn't matter what it is.
Well, I can tell you what it is.
It matches the quadratic almost perfectly
over plus, minus, you know.
Over a, over a pretty big range.
It matches the quadratic very closey.
But then what happens, it excellerates and
goes up to plus infinity.
Someone explain that to me.
It means, I am, I do not even want to
discuss the possibility of residual more
that plus or minus one.
I won't allow it, right.
But for smaller residuals, it's just like
Lee's Squares, okay?
So, these are the idea.
Now, the whole point of this is that then
you would craft your own.
Your on penalty function.
And let's just try one.
So as I'm doing least squares fitting or
aggression.
So I, I just want to minimize, I want ax
to equal b.
But suppose I said that, I care about,
take the residual r, and then over fit.
Let's say that being above is okay.
I don't want to be below.
I, I really on, I, I'm, I care four times
as much about being below.
So you could interview me and you could
say, tell me about the residuals and
the model and the data that you want to
fit, and I'd say, well I want it to fit.
And some, then someone would ask,
well what about, how do you care about big
residuals?
And you'd say I don't like them.
I don't, of course I don't like them.
You say, but, I mean, will you go way out
of your way?
To not have biggers.
And you go, no, if we have to have some
big ones we'll have some big ones, 'kay?
Everybody, you should get, you should, we
just, we just nailed, by the way,
the asymptotics of the, of the penalty
function.
And then you'd say, well tell me about
under and over fitting.
Is it symmetric?
You know what under and over fitting is?
It means you look at an entry of b, and
you look at a, an entry of a x,
and you compare the numbers.
Right?
If you say I don't care I mean above
below, doesn't matter to me.
But suppose you said no actually there's
asymmetry there.
It's much worse to under estimate so if AX
is less than B, that's bad.
Right.
How bad.
You know, got a reasonable factor or
something.
You know.
It's five times worse.
By the way, there's a bigger picture here
which actually fits with all of
optimization.
That the idea is, not to focus on the
algorithm, that produces x.
What you do is your tools are, is the
problem.
You formulate phi, and
the optimization will carry out your
wishes to the extent that it can.
Right, so that's the idea.
So you should express your wishes in
fitting.
By setting a penalty function or
something like that, then let optimization
sort out the details.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
And these are totally obvious things, but
believe me, they have not been in,
they have not been internalized by the
vast majority of people doing kind of
mathematically sophisticated things.
So let's look at it.
Here's an example.
Very simple.
We just generate a random data problem
with 100 measurements,
30 parameters that we want to esitmate.
These are, and then we'll, we just solve
various problems.
We'll do one.
We'll do an L1 norm.
We'll do, least squares of regression.
We'll do a dead zone linear, and we'll do
this this, this.
Analytic center or what, what did I call
it?
I forget what I just called it.
Log barrier.
Okay. Yeah. Log barrier.
So we'll do log barrier.
By the way the name of the point is the
analytic center.
We'll get to that later, but.
Okay.
So and what's plotted here.
Let me explain what's plotted.
This function here.
So each of these.
That, that's one norm two norm.
Well square.
Right.
Dead zone linear log barrier.
And you see the actual function plotted on
some scale here.
so, this function tells you kind of your
irritation at having a residual of
that level, okay?
And then what's shown in here is the
histogram of
residuals that you get, right?
So you get different Xs in each case,
right?
And you get different histograms.
We'll start with least squares because
this would be the most,
this is kind of the starting point for
everything.
Here they are well its kind of nice you
get a bunch of get a bunch that are at
here you have a few that are big not so
big you know and but
there all bunched in here okay let's look
at the L1 case you get something bizzare.
And it is completely explained intuitively
by what we talked about.
The first you see that catches you eye is
that's a different scale.
You got this giant pile of x;s, sorry of
residuals that are flat zero.
And by the way, it's not that their small,
their actually zero.
Okay so I will give an intuitive
explanation for
this the incentive to drive a residual to
0 holds up until it's 0.
So if you're if a residual is at this
value there is
still a strong incentive to reduce it
okay, now that's completely false for
quadratic because the smaller a residual
becomes The less incentive there is.
An incentive is just a slope of this
thing.
It tells you, it says; you know, how much
would you,
how much benefit would i get in reducing
the objective?
But to make that residual slightly smaller
and
the answer in these squares is you have a
diminishing residual benefit, right.
Here it holds up, to the very end.
Okay and the result is, a whole bunch of
them become 0.
By the way, for those of you, who've take
machine learning class,
the statistics class, whole bunch of
classes, you will recognize this.
You should already have heard about
things, like L1 and sparsity and
things like that.
We're going to see.
You're going to have in your head, burned
a connection between.
L 1 in sparsity where things are actually
0.
And in fact it turns out not l 1 it's just
the point it turns out that
the point is here.
So the one we looked at before our,
our asymmetric one we'd have the same
property all right.
But the other interesting thing is this is
look at that there is a residual up
here which is like 1.8.
And you didn't get that in the L2, one,
right?
Because 1 point 8 is a big residual and in
this square, you care about that a lot.
One point 8, squared.
Right?
And so, again i'm anthropomorphising, but
in these squares, pushing these down here.
Was a good tradeoff in terms that these
things split and moved all around here and
so on, in that sort so,
I mean this is just all anti amorphization
of all of this, but this is the idea.
Okay?
Here's dead zone linear.
And you see something very, very
interesting.
That if your residual is between plus, and
minus, and half.
We don't carry at all.
One half, a re, a residual of one half is,
in terms of the rotation, no better, no
worse, than 0.
That dead zone, dead zone linear says,
there's an incentive to reduce a residual.
The incentive entirely disappears once a
residual's hit one half, right?
And in fact, that's what's happened,
right?
So these are sort of residuals that, well,
you know, why not?
But they weren't, they weren't forced to
be between there, right?
They just happened this way.
And here, is the log barrier.
And sure enough, as required, they've all
been crushed down here.
So now let's,
let me introduce some really cool stuff
you can make cool Frankenstein like.
We can, we can cut up penalties and resew
them together and
make you know, things that I guess don't
come up, obviously.
Here's a The very famous one is the Huber
penalty function.
The Huber penalty function is this.
It's quadratic up to a threshold,
whereupon it, it transitions to linear.
And so this is the Huber function here
with threshold m.
Actually it's a very important function,
and
you know, for, I would say 80% of where
people use these squares right now.
My guess is that in 80% of those cases,
the application would be improved, the
performance in whatever the application,
would be improved if it was replaced with
a Hubert.
And no one knows that.
Alright so, I mean people know that.
People do advanced statistics, they always
do this kind of stuff.
Right, but in lots and lots of other
areas.
They don't know that.
So that's the Huber function, and first
let's just talk through what it means.
So the Huber function says something like
this.
If you are below the threshold,
if a residual is below the threshold, it's
identical to least squares.
Basically says it's least squares, but
if you go over the threshold, it's
radically different from least squares.
And what can you say about a Huber penalty
as opposed to least squares.
It looks like an l1.
And it is a penalty that it, it's more
relaxed.
So you would say something.
You could just guess this.
You would say that if you do Huber.
Approximation, let's say.
You'll end up with something like this.
Compared to lee squares, it will be,
it's going to be lee, if everything, if
all the residuals are in the threshold,
in below the threshold, it's just lee,
it's exactly the same as lee squares.
But what it'll do is it's going to be much
more relaxed about
having a couple Of outliers.
[COUGH] So it will actually allow a couple
of outliers.
It's not going to like it, but
it's not going to go insane like least
squares will, and it won't.
It won't actually ruin everything else or
won't increase all sorts of other things
to try to to improve one.
Okay.
So
it turns out this is a robust estimator.
We'll see lots of.
We'll see lots of this in the future, but
it's a robust estimator.
It works unbelievably well.
And so let me show you the kind of thing
it works on.
So, here's a, here's a picture [COUGH]
with, you know, 42 points, okay?
So, 40 points are obviously scattered on
that line, you know, on the line, and
these are two.
You know obvious outliers, okay, so, and
we just made the data.
This is just plotted so
you can see it, you know, obviously for
fitting data in two dimensions.
You don't need any fancy combi-, you use
your eyeball to do it, so
that's not what this is for.
Okay, but this is just to illustrate what
happened.
Okay, so there is your data, if you do the
least squares fit,
you get this dash line here, everybody see
that?
And the discussion is extremely simple.
It's basically, look, that is so big that
when you square it, it's gigantic.
It's extremely irritating and least
squares will actually bend the fit to
reduce that big number which you're
squaring, and
it will take a hit on all those other
numbers.
Everybody.
Got that?
And by the way, in your head, you can take
these two things and
you can move them this way.
You can make them much worse.
I can make the least, I can make the least
square thing, actually flip over and
have the wrong slope.
Okay?
Now, by the way, if you think, I mean of
course in our plotting a silly data with
like one vari, ih, ih, It's goofy, right?
But the point is this.
You get this same thing when you are
fitting things like things in
dimension in, in high, very high
dimension,
like dimension 100 [COUGH] at which point
by the way your eyeball is no good.
Just for the record.
Right?
[LAUGH] So and it's at.
So, so the Huber fit is that.
Is the dark line here, right.
And it's false to say that it's
unaffected, that it's actually false,
because I can also show you a fit where I
remove these two, right.
And then, and that black line would move
very slightly, OK.
So, and and, and, would then fit those
things perfectly.
By the way, that's also a standard two
step procedure in that wire.
Your first use something like a Huber or
Robust estimator.
To guess which are the outliers, remove
them and refit.
So, that's, that there's a whole, I mean a
whole lot of stuff on this.
So this is this is this.
By the way, these, this thing works so
well for a lot of sort of practical data.
You know, people blabber on and on about
things like big data and stuff like that.
So, things like these, these robust
estimators are absolutely critical in,
in a situation like that, right?
Because when you have a billion pieces of
data, and,
you know, a thousand of them are complete
and
utter nonsense, there's outliers that can
render Lee squares utterly useless.
And these things will just power through
it.
in, actually in Shocking ways where you
can a problem,
we'll have some more word problems on
this, but it'll be shocking.
You take something, you add in outliers at
the 10, 10% of the data will be outliers.
20, 30, I mean, there's usually a
threshold point where it fails.
But you can get just absolutely, and it.
A lot of times, you have to double check,
that what you're looking at is the right
thing.
You think, you've maybe used the true
parameter, not the estimated one.
These things work so well.
So, well and
this is something that you know, that's
implicit in a lot of modern statistics.
It's implicit in a lot of gene learning
and things like that.
So, but it's a very good thing for,
in my opinion, everyone should know about
this, these kind of things.
So we'll look now at something likes like
the dual of the approximation problems and
non-approximation problem and that's at
least norm problem and
the basic idea is, is this here you have a
quality constraint so
in this case a is not generically tall its
generically wide So, A is a wide matrix,
and this says that I have something like M
equality constraints on X.
Presumably not enough to completely
constrain x.
I mean then it's a silly problem.
It has one feasible point.
And then among the x's that satisfy ax
equals b we're going to choose the one
that has minimum norm and you've probably
seen this in some class if
you took 263 this was the least norm
problem it was the two norm there.
So what's the interpretation of this, and
of course I should say something here when
I say equals argmin.
If this norm is strictly convex, and that
would be the case for
example, for two norms, then it's unique
of course.
But it can easily be not unique.
Right?
So we should say something like well,
one notation would be x star is in ard
min.
Because one, one and, one,
notational convention is that argmin
returns the set of minimizers.
So by x star equals argmin, we just mean
it's a minimizer.
So the geometric interpretation is this.
We have an affine set that's generically
given by the set of x,
such that a equals b.
So we have this affine set, and what we
want to do is find the point.
Closest to zero in that set right.
And a simple completly elementary
variation on this is where we
project a point in a non zero point on to
that set.
So that's the idea.
Its a projection of zero onto the affine
set.
Estimation is this.
The idea in the estimation interpretation
is something like this.
We interpret B equals AX to mean that we
have M perfect linear measurements.
So there, there's, there's no noise.
Nothing, they're perfect.
And then, but we have N parameters to
estimate, and
we have more parameters than we have
measurements.
Right?
So, I have 150 parameters to estimate,
I have 50 measurements or 100 measurement,
something like that.
And that leaves me basically 50 unknown
dimensions or something like that.
So ax equals b in that case.
We interpret as the set of parameter
values that are consistent with
the perfect measurements, right?
So this, if you were to put a comment
here,
you would say something like consistent
with measurements like, like this, right?
And, and then the assumption is the
measurements are perfect.
Right?
So that would be that.
And then the interpretation of minimizing
the norm is
you then choose most plausible.
Choose the most plausible point.
Right?
And here implicit is the following idea.
That the larger X is the less plausible it
is.
Right.
So that's the idea.
In other words, you're in some situation
where there many parameter values
consistent with the measurements, so
nobody, anybody who chooses X with AX B
can not say to another person who chooses
another X to satisfy A, they're wrong.
What, what one can do then is just talk
about which is more plausible or
something like that.
And so the idea is that the norm is here
used as a surrogate for
I should say implausibility.
Cause the larger the norm the less
plausible it is.
And by the way, we'll connect this
possibly even later today,
we'll connect this to a statistical
interpretation.
Another one is design.
So here, you think of x as a bunch of
design variables,
these are inputs for example.
This could be forces that you apply to a
vehicle or something like that right.
It could be voltages or current drives
that you're going to send to a motor or,
or current drives that you're going to
send to an antennae.
Right something like that.
Then ax gives you something like the
result right?
So this, this gives you the result so
and it might be something like this that
you choose 150 forces to apply.
Maybe at different times different
accuators.
But actually all you care about are maybe
six or eight things at the end.
For example the position and momentum at
some final target time.
Something like that, right?
In which case Ax gives you the result.
Of the action X.
Then B, is actually your desired action.
So, any X that satisfies A equals B, is
valid.
It says, find me a set of forces,
that will take my spacecraft, move it over
to here, 12 seconds later and
arrive here, you know, with this position
and momenteum.
Right?
So, that would be, lots of X's do that.
And here what you're doing is you're
saying please find me an efficient one.
One that minimizes a norm.
Could be two norm.
Could be one norm.
One norm would be closer to fuel usage in
a lot of cases.
Something like that.
It could be infinity norm.
It could be anything, in fact.
Okay so this is just interpretations of
the problem minimizing the norm
of a of x subject to ax equals b,
equalities, right?
Oh I should say that one nice thing about
our approach to these, which is to
simply look at these and simply say,
that's a convex problem, period.
Right?
One nice thing is, you can mix and
match, if all of sudden somebody comes
back and
says, oh dear, I need to add some
constraints, here.
Like for example, the X's have to between
plus and minus 1.
It's not a big deal for us, we just add
these constraints.
Right?
So, okay.
I'm not showing them here, just for
simplicity.
Okay.
Let's look at some specific examples of
least norm problems.
Here's one.
Most famous one is you take the two norm,
and
in fact, what you really minimized is not
the norm but the two norms squared.
The, not the two norm, but the two norms
squared.
And this is the same, because minimizing
two norm squared and two norm is the same.
Has the same solution.
And this, the optimality conditions, you
work them out.
The KKT conditions are linear.
They're a set of linear equations.
So you can solve them exactly, and there's
a formula for it.
If A is full rank and all that kind of
stuff, and you've seen that in 263 or
some other linear algebra course.
Right?
So and that's why this is, this is,
of course, extremely widely used.
Right because it.
Fits fits, it's fits everything, right?
Looks like it's simple, fits the 19th
century, you know, formula model and
all that kind of stuff.
Okay now you can do other things, which is
actually quite interesting.
You can do things like this.
You can actually take the L1 norm, and
this is a very interesting problem.
This says minimize the norm of x1, subject
to ax equals b.
Okay, and this is something actually
that's quite in Vogue right now and
has been for maybe 5, maybe 10 years now.
It has no analytical solution, in general.
Well, except for very silly cases.
Has no analytical solution.
So, it's got various names.
This one's Basis Pursuit.
And let me ask you, in view of the
discussion we had last time.
The last time, we talked about a penalty
function, and how the shape of the fenal-,
penalty function has an influence on the
distribution of residuals.
That discussion transposes perfectly to
this situation.
Right, so here, the idea is that if you
have a penalty function,
here the penalty is embarrassingly simple,
it's the absolute value.
But what it does is, that's going to shape
the distribution of Xs,
what I would like to know from you,
is what do you image this solutions of the
basis pursuit problem look like.
What you would expect and turns out,
in fact, to be true, is that when you
solve this problem, most of the x's are 0.
Okay?
And, I mean there's various ways,
you will observe this as a, as an
empirical observation and
in fact, you can prove various things
about that and so on and so forth.
so, in fact, this is a heuristic for
getting a sparse solution of Ax equals b.
Right?
So okay, and this is going to be a theme.
It's going to kind of follow us through
the rest of the course and so on.
So, okay.
And we'll see a lot about this.
Okay so well, we've already been talking
about this but
the least penalty problem says that you,
you choose a penalty function phi, here.
And then you minimize the sum of the
penalties subject to a, x over b,
and then you would, you would choose.
Phi, to shape to get an x that you'd like,
right?
And by the way, this is, there's,
something quite interesting about it,
because it has something to do with how,
people don't talk about it a lot but
there's the question of, sort of, the
entire design flow.
How do you use, like convex optimization,
this kind of thing?
And in fact there's this big trend across
many fields to move away from
something that's a direct solution, that
says oh,
you know I want a sparse solution, so
here's what you should do with the data.
Towards one, where you put one level of
indirection in between.
And what you do is you form an
optimization problem.
And what the user does, is mess with the
optimization problem and
then you let some numerical method, work
out the actual solution.
Right?
So, this is a big trend, across many, many
fields, right?
Like, for example, it's like control
signal processing, even statistics.
You move away from this idea of.
Here's how you, here's what you to do the
data.
And instead, what the designer of a method
is really doing is
actualy designing an optimizaton problem.
He changed perimeters here and there.
Somethings to smooth, there's some,
if somethings not smooth enough, you add a
little regulization and you crank that up.
But, your not You as the user are not
actually figuring out exactly how to
transform your data into your estimate or
something.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So this is the, so
this is a very big, it's a big picture
observation, but it's, it's happened.
It's prevalent.
Okay.
Well, the parent of these two problems,
least norm and then norm approximation.
Is is just regularized approximating and
in fact there's even a more general parent
and the the basic idea is to
regularization is its kind of ubiquitous
across lots of fields and it
its basic the correct way that I think to
think of it is its a bicriterian problem.
And it basically says I care about two
norms, each of which I would like small.
Right?
So the norms are.
This is the most traditional setting.
The first one is something like AX minus
B.
That can have lots of interpretations
depending on if you're doing
a statistical model or, or data fitting.
This is your misfit.
X is your model, Ax-b norm is the measure
of how well your model agrees with
the data you have obvserved.
That's that's that's so that's something
like misfit.
Or fit.
Norm x, is basically how big are your how
big are your model parameters, and we'll
talk in a minute about why would it would
be that you would want small parameters.
And actually there's some very good
reasons why you
would want small parameters.
Well, like many good ideas, it can be
justified from like,
five different completely different points
of view.
So let's look at some of them.
So the idea here essentially you're
saying, you know what?
What I want is I want a good fit.
I want Ax to be about b.
But I want to do it efficiently.
I want x to be small.
So this is the essential idea.
Right.
Oh, and again, these ideas are all very
simple so
if you're not following, don't
over-interpret what I'm saying.
What I'm saying is so simple that there
are no subtleties here, none.
So when would this come up?
Well, an estimation, it might be something
like this.
You'd say, well I happen to know, what I'm
observing is y equals Ax, so Ax minus y or
Ax minus v, Ax minus v if v is what I
measured is v, and so
this is something like the norm of that,
this thing, and you know that's small.
But I had prior knowledge that x is small,
right?
So that's what this term does for me.
Right?
So that's what that says.
You can have optimal design.
You could say actually I don't insist that
ax = b.
I will give up on ax = b.
I will simply get close enough.
Close enough?
Well there's applied criteria here in
problems.
So you have a whole pretail-optimal curve,
and
you would determine where to operate on
that curve once you see the curve.
Then you'll look at it and say, okay fine,
I, I don't need to, dot, I mean if I'm,
if I'm within three millimeters, that's
actually fine.
Especially if that allows me to use,
you know, one quarter the fuel I might've
used otherwise, right?
Something like that.
Okay so there, the idea is you're willing
You don't even, you,
you know, you're willing to not have a x
equals b.
You're, you'll get up a little bit on
that.
And hopefully you'll take as a benefit for
not doing that exactly a small inefficient
small x, right?
So that's the idea.
Another interpretation is this.
Is a robust approximation.
And this is something we're going to talk
about later.
This is quite a modern interpretation, and
it's extremely important.
And the idea is something like this.
You really just want to fit a model, so
you really want norm x minus b to be
small.
That's really what you want.
Problem is, you don't quite know A.
Right?
This is extremely typical. Right? That the
As are measured or
something like that, you don't quite know
what they are.
And by the way, it's, this can happen in a
design setting,
it can happen in an estimation setting.
Right?
In a design setting, someone, you say, you
know what I do know, I know the moment of
inert-, you know, I the moment of inertia,
I know the mass of the vehicle, the CGI,
I know all these things pretty well, but
actually only about 1%.
No better than that.
And what that says is, if I apply a bunch
of control surface deviations to
an aircraft, and I ask where will it be in
22 seconds?
The answer is actually technically, you
don't know, right?
Because, I don't know there's plenty of
air.
And you know, and
I mean, hopefully you have a pretty good
idea of where it's going to be right?
Because otherwise, your, your in deep
trouble.
But the point is that there's really like
a,
a cloud of where it might be, depending on
what you do.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
It should be a tight cloud, one hopes,
right, but
the fact of the matter is you don't know
exactly, what's going to happen.
Right?
So, this is, that's the idea.
Okay, so then you say, well, what's
interesting about this,
is how much is your X effected by changes
in A and that we can even work out.
I mean this is going to be an intuitive
one.
We'll look at this more carefully later.
But so what you do is you think of "A" as
being sort of the nominal one, and
delta is a matrix, presumably small, which
is basically your error in "A".
So this is, this is what you have, right?
So for an aircraft, this is the nominal
model.
That assumes that your estimate of the
mass moment of inertia, you know,
blah blah blah, all these things, are
perfect.
Right?
They're, they're double precision perfect.
This is basically a very, these are
variations due to the fact that you know,
these things are manufactured, things vary
by 1%,
you know all sorts of things happen.
Right?
That's what the delta is here.
And if you look at this equation, we're
going to work this out but
it's very, very simple, what you get is Ax
minus b and then plus delta x.
And what you see very clearly is the
following, is that these,
the errors in A multiply x.
And so, for example, suppose I chose x to
be zero.
How much would that be affected by model
errors, by the delta?
Not at all.
Right, and you can see immediately.
I mean, this is very intuitive.
The basic idea is.
Oh, by the way these are sometimes called
multiplicative errors.
That's a.
That's a name you will hear, and
it makes perfect sense,
because it's an error in A which then
multiplies your choice X.
So it's a multiplicative error, and for
a multiplicative error, it's, it's, it is
in your in.
If you want to be least, less sensitive to
a multiplicative error.
Then here's what you want.
You want x to be small the thing that
everybody see this.
And so this is why a small x would be
preferable.
right?
That it,
it would be that it would be less
sensitive to errors in a.
That was a long description.
I, it's not, it's not supposed to be
fancier that what I just said, but
that's the idea.
And I can give you yet another
interpretation of it.
I mean, in some sense all these
interpretations come around to
the same thing.
Another one is this.
You have y equals you have a model like
this estimation.
You have y equals ax plus v.
But the truth is, you really have
something like this, right?
You really have a non-linear model.
However, near, you do,
near where you're looking right now, y
equals a x plus v works.
That's provided x is small.
OK, so the idea there is this,
this sort of tells you your nominal error
based on your say linearized model.
This says please have x small, because the
smaller x is,
the more accurate, the more I trust.
My linearized model, right?
And if fact, in that case, the term that
constrains X, either via regularization or
as an additive term in regularization, or
as a constraint.
If it's a constraint, it's called a Trust
Region Constraint,
which is a beautiful term, because it
basically says please estimate X.
I want norm AX minus B small, but
I want norm X small, and someone says why
do you want norm X small?
Do you care, and you go, actually no,
I don't care at all how big the parameter
is.
The problem is I have to add that there
because if X gets bigger,
my model AX is no longer accurate.
Everybody.
Getting this?
It's pretty straight forward.
Okay.
Alright.
Let's look at some simple cases.
I mean so, how do you solve it by criteria
and problem?
You sclarize.
Right, this is the simplest method.
So, you take the norm of Ax minus B plus
gamma norm x.
And for us that's a convex problem, no big
deal, we solve it, okay?
So that's fine.
And, and gamma is a positive parameter.
You sweep it from zero to infinity.
And at the two extremes you would get you
could get the extreme points by
solving a constrained problem or something
like that.
Okay.
And so
this traces out the, the trade off curve.
a, a very And the very traditional method
is to square the two.
You get the same trade off curve and by
the way that's something you
want to check right that in fact the the
curve of solutions here parameterized by
delta identical to the curve of solutions
brown tries by gamma here.
Right?
So, in fact you can even work out how
delta and gamma are related.
Right? [COUGH]. And it's not totally
straightforward and
it has to do with the particular problem.
But these are 2 parameterizations.
Okay.
so, if these are 2 norms, and
the reason generally one square's a norm,
I mean there's several reasons, but
the most tradition one is when you square
a 2 norm,
you get a quadratic function, which is
nice and
smooth, and you know the derivative is
linear, and you, you know, and then.
Then all your, you have a formula for the
answer right?
Okay.
So,
most famous there is is taken off
regularization.
Oh, and I should say in statistics it's
called Ridge Regression,
is the name in Statistics.
There's maybe another one.
But it's called Ridge Regression.
And this just turns into a single least
squared.
I mean you can solve this analytically of
coarse, it's Two norms, right, so, and
the solution, you can either make it,
stack it and make a big (?) problem, or
you just get, sort of an analytical
solution like that, OK.
Now, the horrible reason to use this, the,
the, the one that, that, I don't like
at all, and is in fact probably the most
Common use of regularization is
someone says, "What are you doing?", you
say, "I'm adding regularization." Why?
And you would say, "because without it, I
was getting numerical,
my solver was sending complaints to me."
Right, so, everybody see that.
If you add Delta here, this just, now
works perfectly.
It has to work perfectly.
You can never get a complaint.
It says, inverse condition number big or
you know, numerical.
It's not going to happen.
Can't get something singular working
position.
So let's look at an example and this
example actually it's, it's very simple.
But it's, it's going to be an example of,
it's meant to illustrate exactly what I
talked about earlier.
This idea of a design flow, right.
How do you use these things, right?
And this will be one from, you know,
control, if you like.
This could just as well be statistics, it
could just as well be,
you know anything else.
It could be image processing, video
process, it can be anything.
And you can construct a similar story.
Right?
It could be finance.
So, let's look at this.
Here's the idea.
I have a convolution system, so so I have
I apply an input.
u, scalar input over various time
intervals.
It could be a force I apply to something.
It doesn't matter what it is, right?
And something I call the output is a
convolution of the input with some
convolution kernel, or in EE dialect,
that's called an impulse response.
But that's dialect, the standard term in
convolution kernel.
Kay?
So and in mixed company you should always
say convolution.
Okay.
So the input design problem is choose this
input u so that y does something you want.
And this is just going to be a very simple
example to
show what a typical design flow looks
like.
Here it is.
What I want to do is I'm given a desired
trajectory, and I want to track it.
That's it.
So, and, and I, I want to make.
I, I have to give a measure for
mistracking, and so
I'm going to call that J track, and if,
if you can't think of anything, if nothing
immediately comes to mind.
Then you should just use the squares, just
as through historical, and
to follow in a historical tradition, and
what, I mean it's not a bad thing, right?
I mean.
By the way, if I were to make this the sum
of the absolute values it's,
it would change the result and you can
even kind of guess what would.
Happen when you, when you do that, right.
If I were to make this the Infinity norm,
right, that you would call that something
like mini max tracking error.
You might give a name like that, and
you would get different results as well,
right.
So, but here we just take the squares and
make it simple.
OK, Now, at the same time, I want you not
so big.
Right?
So I'm going to
introduce an objective called the, the
magnitude, J mag.
And these are, oh by the way, if you look
at these, they're quadratic forms.
Right?
So, so far.
because that, they're, they're square,
they're squares, the sums of squares.
And I'll take an input vary, this just
tells you how.
well, you shouldn't say smooth, how wiggly
the signal is, or something like that.
And it's going to be the sum of the
difference,
of the first differences, here.
Right?
and, and now I can ask some questions,
like when would J track be 0, which is its
minimum possible value?
It means you have, your y is equal to y
desired, and you, yes, and a good name for
that is you might, you might say that you
interpolate The desired thing.
Or you might say you achieve perfect
tracking,
meaning that the output absolutely tracks
what it is that you required.
OK, so that would be that.
When would the input magnitude objective
term be zero?
When u equals zero, okay?
So, in which case, by the way,
your tracking error would simply be some
wide desired squared, right?
Because your output would be zero at that
point.
Okay, and how about input variation?
When would that be zero?
Constant, exactly.
So, if you were to crank up.
The coefficient on input variation, very
high.
You would expect to see inputs that were
constant right?
And at the same time, they're attempting
to track and things like that, okay?
And you could go on and on.
For example you could have a second finite
difference which would be something like
a smoothness measure and that would be
something like UT plus 1 minus 2 UT.
Plus UT minus one.
That's.
I, I don't know if you recognize that but
it's the all.
It's the famous, you know, minus one two
one, in a tridiagonal matrix or something.
It's a second difference.
Right?
And then.
And
that would give you something smooth, and
when would that be zero by the way?
Linear.
Exactly.
So if you, you look like that or that.
That would be zero.
Right.
So.
Okay, great.
So, what we'll do is we'll just make this
a regularized least squares problem.
We'll take the tracking error plus delta
times the derivative error plus ETA
times the magnitude error.
And I mean this is a least squares
problem, right?
So I mean you, we just solve it, right?
This is the idea.
We get a least squares problem.
And then the idea now is that delta and
eta are knobs that you will fiddle with to
get something that you like right?
And you could, you could do this in a
formal way and
actually do ten values of each I mean its
a trivial problem.
You can do ten values of each.
And then just make a, a big ten by ten
matrix, and
actually plot all these things, look at
'em, whatever you like.
You could have two big knobs in front of
you that labeled, you know, delta and
ada are two sliders or whatever on some
user interface.
And, and you could fiddle with them and
see what you like, right?
So that's the idea.
Okay.
So.
Quick example.
Here, here is some, here are, three per
retail optimal solutions, right?
So the first one has delta equals zero and
that means we have, we,
we're putting zero penalty on the
uh,variation in u.
Right?
So, fine.
We're and we're putting a small weight on
the sides of u.
That's eta, small.
And here's the input and the output.
And two things are plotted in the output
you can't see,
there's a dashed curve here, which shows
you the desired one.
The desired one is just this kind of
square wave thing,
that was dialect that goes like, that
jumps up and then jumps down.
Right?
Like that.
So that, that's the desired one.
And you can see if you look at this that
we're tracking quite well.
Well you can see there's little errors
right at the transitions and so on.
And this is the input that does the trick,
over here right, so that's the input.
And you can see the input gets its high as
you know, almost five positive and
it jerks down to like minus oh, I don't
know, seven and a half or eight there.
Okay, so that's, that's it.
And you can also see that the input Is
quite wiggly, right?
So, fine.
That is just one point down the trade-off
curve, right?
Then you'd say, well, in the second, in
the middle,
what we're going to do is we're still
going to have no derivative error but
we're going to crank up eta and we expect.
So that means we're going to add more
penalty.
To, the size.
And so what we expect is the size of u to
come down.
And by the way we're going to pay for
that, in tracking error.
Right?
So, and
indeed if you look on the right, you can
see here, you know, the tracking error
probably is mostly accumulated around
these end points and it's pretty small.
Here you can see, there's some pretty.
You can actually see some pretty
substantial tracking error.
Here.
Everybody got this?
The difference is, look at this, instead
we've, we've basically halved the input.
Right?
So with half the input, you know, and so
if this good enough for you, great.
I mean this is kind of the idea.
Right?
And finally, in the, in the last one what
we are going to do is we are going to.
Add we're going to now turn on a bunch of
smoothing regularization and,
again, you pay for it in terms of
tracking.
Maybe this is good enough for you, maybe
not, and now, but
you can see immediately what happens.
Things like these, which rack up a big
bill in the derivative.
Cost function.
Now we're smoothed out, and you get
something like this.
Okay, so anyway this is, so this is not
supposed to be complicated.
This is not complicated.
It is simple, but the idea is this is what
you do.
And you would typically sit there and turn
knobs, and see what you like.
Right?
And this could be any applicationary.
This could be image processing,
where you turn a knob and you go, no no
no, it got too smoothed.
And then you crank it down the other way.
And now some of the noise comes back.
And then, you turn another knob and, this
is how this goes.
So let's look at another area, it's it's
also very simple bicriterion problem,
it's signal reconstructions, quite
straightforward.
It's this.
What I have is I have, I'm given a
corrupted signal.
That's x you know corrupted okay.
And what I would like to do is to come up
with xhat which is supposed to be
an estimate of this corrupt of well its an
estimate of the signal before it
was corrupted okay?
And that's what I'm going to do and so I
at.
I want x to be close to x corrupted, but
I don't want it to be equal to it because
it's been corrupted.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to
have a second function here,
which is known as, it's got lots of names.
It's a regularize, it's a regularization
function, or
sometimes people call it a smoothing
regularizer.
Okay, and so that's this function phi of
x, x hat.
And the idea is that by looking at a
trade-off between these,
I'm going to do some, it's a, this is,
this is a principled way to do smoothing
or something like that to smooth a signal.
Alright, and the model is something like
this.
You have some unknown signal.
You observe a corrupted version and then
you're going to solve this problem.
And examples would be something like this
you know.
So simple quadratic smoothing would be you
simply take the differences squared like
we did in the previous example.
the, some of the absolute values, that's
called the total variation regularizer.
Right?
So that's, that's completely standard so
that, that's actually a standard term.
Let's look at an example.
I, simple example, right?
So here's some signal, it's 4,000, you
know, time samples, or
whatever you like here.
This is the original signal, and this is
the corrupted one, and
I mean this one's kind of goofy because,
you know, take in the signal.
You've added some, and you can see that
the,
the difference between the signal and, and
the, the corruption you can see
that the corruption is very like high
frequency or something like that again.
So that's.
So it's kind of obvious, right?
So here what you do now is we simply use a
quadratic smoother and
what you would get would be things like
this.
So this is with a little bit of smoothing.
This is what you'd reconstruct.
This would be substantially more and even
more still.
Right?
So, that's the idea.
And, you know, you might say, that's a
little bit too much, and
then that's just about right.
Now, unfortunately, for smoothing problems
like this,
there really aren't any particularly good
ways to choose.
You.
The level of smoothing you do except maybe
aesthetically.
I mean, you have to have some side
information.
Right?
Or you could have some cases where you
actually knew what the exact signal was.
Right?
So that.
Then, then you could actually do
reasonable things like cross validation.
Here's one, [COUGH] and this is much more
modern.
By the way, total variation reconstruction
this is very,
this is introduced maybe only in the
1990s.
So this is pretty, relatively recent.
And it's, it's actually quite interesting
and
quite stunning, in fact I've tried to get
some audio recordings of this.
I mean I haven't tried that hard and I
should because they're amazing.
I put em on course website or
something like that or if, anyway but I'll
explain that in a minute.
So here's a picture.
What I have is, here's the original
signal.
Eh, it's got a smooth components but
these, these kind of jumps every so often.
I mean this is all just made up.
Right, so this is just to illustrate, what
happens, right?
So here we have this signal.
And so you'd, and then we add this high
frequency noise to it, like that.
So that's the corrupted state, right?
Now, one of the problems here is that you
don't have this
frequency scale separation, right?
Because the original signal has these
jumps.
And a jump.
Again, if you know about Fourier analysis
and
all that kind of stuff roughly is going to
contain a lot of high frequencies.
So you don't have the spectral separation
of the underlying signal and
the noise here.
And the result is if you do quadratic
smoothing,
which in fact is a linear operation.
It's just a low pass filter, frankly, is
what it is.
And what you get is this.
If you do some low pass filtering, well
sure, this gets, this gets moved out.
That gets attenuated.
But you can see as you crank it up to
smooth out more,
you can see exactly what's happening here.
That a transition that in fact was a
single value.
Has now, widened, and
now it's taking place over, ooh that's a
lot, you know, 50 or something, right?
So, a transition that was,
that, that went in like one time sample,
is now happening over 50.
Right?
So, by the way if this were audio This
would bake, make something sound very
muffled if that was a, if this was the
attack caused by a drum, right?
Someone hits a snare drum.
You will get something that looks like
that.
And if you smooth it, like this, and
instead of the attack, you know rising and
with tin samples, you know 48 kilohertz,
or
something like that instead of 10 samples
that goes at a thousand and
It just, it sounds like a thud, it doesn't
sound like a drum anymore.
Okay?
So, alright.
But let's do total variation de-noising.
Right?
So, total variation de-noising does this.
Actually, we can see a lot of things here
that you would predict.
So, the first is this.
This is where you have put a lot of total
variation de-noising.
In.
And you're beginning to see something
pretty cool.
When you crank up something which is
basically the L1 norm of the difference,
of x hat, t plus 1 and x hat t.
Again You should start now and
by the end of the course it should be
completely engrained and second nature but
you want to make connections between
things like L1 and sparcity, right?
that's the very simplified model but it
should really be kinks and
sparcity, right?
So let's look at L1 and
sparcity When someone says please minimize
you know Well, it's part of it right?
If they say please minimize this, right?
What you would expect is that if the
coefficient in front of this is
high enough right, that a whole lot of
these numbers will be zero.
And that says if you do total variation.
Denoising.
You should expect a [NOISE] piecewise
constant signal,
because a piecewise constant signal is.
That's what is means.
This is like a derivative.
This first difference, and
if you have sparse derivative, [NOISE] it
means you're piecewise constant.
Everybody got that?
By the way, if this were the second
difference, and I put an L1 norm.
And I minimized.
What would you expect to see?
Piece-wise linear, exactly.
ANd if I took the third difference, what
would you get?
Piecewise quadratic, and by the way those
would be splines just for the record.
You get splines.
Okay?
So this is sort of the idea.
Now here what's happened is you are
tracking this.
Right?
But what's happened is your regularization
is so
high that things like that just got
constant.
Right?
You've, you've lost the fact that this is
varying here.
Right.
Oh, I should add also kind of a cool
thing.
If you do this on images.
It's a gray scale or color stuff.
You get very cool stuff things start
looking cartoonish, right.
Because, you have a whole bunch of,
you have, you have whole regions where it
was one color or one shade or
their was some gradient, it's just like
now replaced flat.
So, I think you can even imagine what this
looks like, right?
>> Mm-hmm.
>> So, right, this is for that.
So, if you do tele variation
Regularization on an image.
What happens is, as you, at, at first you
have a million pixels.
You're probably going to have a million
grayscale values, right?
I mean there'd be no reason for any of
them to repeat, right?
If they do, it's an accident.
You turn up total variation regulization
on an image, and
they'll jump down dramatically.
And after awhile you'll only have a
thousand and then you keep turning it and
at some point you'll like ten gray levels,
right.
And, by the way, it will still be
completely recognizable as the,
as the image you wanted, right?
But, anyway, so, I'm just saying, these
things apply to everything, right.
You'll, you'll see these all over the
place.
So, here you can see, this is where we
might probably have not enough.
Total variation regularization because you
can see there's also squigglies there, and
this is kind of the proverbial just
enough.
Right?
Something like that.
Finally, there's a big thing.
We, we, we'll look at this idea of robust
approximation.
So here, and we've already seen a little
bit of this hints at it.
Right?
So the idea is.
You want to minimize let's say norm AX
minus B,
but the problem is you don't know A.
Now, I should add this issue is universal
in actually in all optimization problems.
Right that, that you have data in an
optimization problem, and,
you know, we can talk a little bit about
some generic things to say about data.
You know, when data, when values that are
zero, one, minus one.
Sometimes 2 minus 2, one half, things like
that.
Those are probably really those numbers,
right?
Because it may be some, coefficient that
makes sense.
Like you're basically saying, you know,
this thing's equal to that.
And that would reveal itself as a one and
a minus one.
And those really, really probably are ze,
one and minus one.
Any other constant other than the ones I
just named, and maybe a handful of others.
Generically speaking, they have a
provenance.
And you can trace it back.
And they trace back to models of things or
measurements or experts or
econometric models or mechanics or physics
models or something like that, right.
And in fact, if you trace them all the way
back you'd say,
oh you know that came from a finite
element calculation and blah, blah, blah.
And by the way.
That means that those numbers are suspect,
right?
I mean, they could be accurate to three
significant figures, maybe five, right?
Maybe one, right?
Or in economics the signs is suspect,
right?
[LAUGH] Or something like that, I mean you
just don't You know, right?
There's places where it's dominated.
I mean, you know, there's extremes here,
right?
So, alright, so, the point is,
in all these cases, you have, there is
error in the data, right?
And there are ways to handle it simply.
Simple methods that we've seen one
already.
Regularization is essentially a method to
choose Xs
that are not extremely vulnerable to
changes in a.
For example, that's a very simple example
of a robust optimization problem, but
there are plenty others, right?
By the way, how is parameter.
>> Variation handled in real life.
So what do you think is by far the most
prevalent method for
handling the fact that your parameters are
not known?
In real, now in real life I'm talking
about when people actually solve things.
>> Ignore it.
>> What?
Ignore it thank you.
That is absolutely correct.
That is by far the prevalent method.
Now.
That's okay, in my opinion,
provided you do one thing, which is, which
then takes, makes this okay.
What would that one thing be to do.
It's the least that you could do.
So you just solved a problem, you assumed
that all your data was accurate,
they are double precision numbers.
You got them from, you know, Bob or
whatever, some other intern.
It doesn't matter.
You got the model, and you did it.
What should you do now?
Generate a new A, with the entries changed
by a plausible amount.
Everybody got this?
Right?
And you just simply test the, the X you
found before.
With the new A.
And if things are way off now then you
know that you
cannot ignore safely robustness.
Everybody got this I mean its incredibly
simple but its unbelievebly importing its
actually shocking to me how many people
don't do this.
Right, so.
But
it's, this is just completely standard.
If you come up and say, oh,
wow, I've got a fantastic, a fantastic
four sequence to land an airplane.
You gotta see this.
It's just, it's unbelievable.
Yeah, it's like no.
People don't even notice it, when they're,
oh yeah, and you say, okay fine.
Here it is.
You absolutely have to go back.
And change the model change the total mass
move the center of gravity and
resimulate the same thing with these
changed parameters.
And you have to do ten hundred of these
after which by the way you know absolutly
nothing I might add technically.
But I mean from a.
Strict point of view, right?
But at least you've done the common sense
check.
Everybody got this, right?
If you, if you come and say, I've got a
trading strategy, it's unbelievable.
[LAUGH] And they go, really?
And you go, oh my God you should see what
it did last year, unbelievable.
Then you'd say well did you try it on the
year before?
The main method, traditional method used
for handling uncertainty in data is to
ignore it, and I'd say that's actually a
perfectly respectable option,
provided you do a posterior analysis of
the effect of the variations.
Then it's totally legit.
Assuming the posterior analysis reveals
that it works fine.
Okay.
Now the next step is to have a heuristic
that kind of is a heuristic for
making sure that things don't get too
wacky when the parameters change.
That'd be like regularization, absolutely
fine.
Again, you'd do a posterior analysis to
understand if it works.
And the new thing, this has been coming
up.
Maybe in the last, could be 20 years, but,
and
it was done by a handful of esoteric, you
know, work by academics.
It's now coming on mainli, main,
mainstream, it's this.
You simply take into account,
the uncertainty directly in the problem
statement.
Umk, and so that, these are called robe,
that's roboz optimization.
And this is a special case.
Okay, now were jumping back to the
specific.
That was the background, were jumping back
to the specific problem were looking at.
So you have to have a model for how A
varies.
Right?
And in one it's to, it's stochastic.
You would say A is random and you would
describe it's distribution.
And the distribution could even be finite.
Like, you just say it's got 25 values with
these probabilities, right?
By the way, that's an extremely reasonable
thing to do because what you do is,
if you track the providence of a and it
came from other measurements in data,
then what you do is you'd go back to
someone there,
it's like cross validation or something if
you know what that is.
But you'd go back and you'd say, here's a
model for my chemical process.
And you'd go great how'd you get it?
And you'd go from data, I fit it from
data.
And you go, you know what?
Fit me, a separate model for every day of
the week.
I'd like to, I'd like you to fit a model
for your chemical process for
Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday, Saturday, Sunday, right?
So you get seven models now.
Right?
By the way, if you look at these, A, so
now you have A Monday and A Tuesday, A.
By the way, if they are all completely
different, you should just turn around and
go away, because basically, you're hosed.
There's nothing you can do.
There's nothing intelligent, there's not a
place for us to be doing anything, right?
Basically means it's.
There's no consistency and it doesn't make
any sense.
Okay, fine.
So hopefully all the entries of A Monday,
Tuesday, Wednesday, they're close.
In a worst case in a worst case robust
fitting or
approximation problem, you'd do this.
You would say I'm not going to use a
statistic model, instead what I'm going to
do is I'm simply going to, I'm going to
have a set of values of a and
I'm going to judge my fit by the worse
case, right?
And by the way there's everything in
between these two, right?
So these are just two and, and this
incredible you know,
complete nonsense silly relegous words
between people who You know.
I mean, and, and it makes no sense out of
a context.
Right.
In, in any particular context,
it makes tons of sense as to discuss what
would be a reasonable robustness model but
it outside of a context-free, it makes no
sense whatsoever.
Right.
Mostly what you do.
Oh, and this.
Oh,
this is sometimes called a minimax minimax
fitting.
This that doesn't have a name.
Yeah it does.
It's called stochastic optimization.
But okay.
So that's the idea.
now, to sol, solving these problems is
tractable only in special cases.
I mean in, in a lotta cases it's not
tractable at all.
But some are.
Here's, here's a super duper simple
example.
We have a matrix, which has a one
parameter variation.
It has the form a 0 plus u a 1.
And U varies between, let's say 1 and
minus 1.
Something like that, right?
So, basically in matrix space, you have a
little line segment, right, and
you hope it's not a giant one, right?
But it's a little line segment and
of course, in a more realistic one, it's
varying in a ball, I don't know.
But this has a line segment, that's it,
right?
Okay.
And you can actually easily imagine where
the dominant variation is one line, right?
Cause it could be some process that you
run, and
in fact to first order it's mostly
affected by say ambient temperature.
And so the ambient temperature goes from
you know 10 C to 35.
And that changes the model.
Right?
And I mean things like this happen all
the time.
Alright.
So,
what you do here is in this case you can
solve all these problems.
All of em.
And so, here are, this shows you a couple
of the solutions.
So x nom, simply ignores it entirely,
minimizes this.
And then what you do is, you take this x
and
I calculate the norm here as a function of
u and that's plotted here.
So, this is x nom, and the nominal point
is right here and
look at that, of course by definition it
has to get the lowest value.
This is the nominal value Sure enough, it
does.
Gets the lowest value.
It's right there.
But then you see as u changes, you start
paying for it right?
By rising cost.
Okay, so here's sto,
the ex stochastic, that minimizes the
average, over the interval minus 1, 1.
So over here to here, that gives you this
one here.
' Sorry.
This one here.
this, this one here.
This is x stochastic, right?
And you can see that it, you pay for it in
nominal performance, right?
because at the ver, you get a, at the
very, the stochastic one dips not as well.
So the nominal performance is a little bit
worse.
But now as u varies out to be 0.7 minus
0.8.
You're actually doing much better.
Okay?
So everybody, I mean this is kind of
clear, but that's, that's the idea.
And the final one shows worst case.
And that's this last one.
It's very flat.
You've paid for the cost in nominal cost.
You do much worse than if it's nominal.
But if you look at the mini max over minus
1, 1 you do very well, right.
So this is to illustrate.
Very simple thing.
Okay,.
So we can also handle I mean some.
As an example of another thing that has an
analytical solution would be
stochastic robust least squares.
So let's work that out, this is absolutely
traditional.
It's kind of cool actually.
And it relates to something we were
talking about earlier.
It's this.
Suppose your matrix A, has the form A bar,
a nominal one, plus U,
where U is random, zero mean, and has
expected value, U transposed U is P.
Okay?
So we want to minimize the expected value
of the square of the two norm of
this thing.
And the, of course the expectations over
the distributions of U.
Here, right?
So, you just work that out.
I mean, you expand this thing the ter-,
the cross terms, like here, the-,
there's, when you expand quadratic,
[COUGH] there's a cross term,
which is x transpose, u transpose, a bar x
minus b.
You take the expected value over u, u has
zero mean.
Those go away.
So the cross terms drop out in the
expectation here, right?
Leaving you with the nominal cost, plus
this thing, and you get that, and
it's super cool.
You recognize that immediately.
That's regularization.
It's quadratic regularization.
And in fact, it's even cooler, it
basically says, if you do Tikhonov.
Regularization like this, which you can
claim to be doing,
is you're actually minimizing this, which
is super cool.
And you say, you're minimizing this thing
where, instead of thinking of the matrix
a as fixed, you're actually taking into
account that every entry varies.
They're all independent and have a
variance which is,
I don't know, something like delta over n.
I mean, you can figure out what it is.
Right everybody got this so its actually
super cool.
So if you do taken off regularization or,
or, or ridge regression.
I guess if you're in statistics you do
ridge regression and
you don't have to justify it to anybody.
But if, if you're in a field where they
don't have a special name for
taking off regularization and they ask
what are you doing.
You could say, oh, I'm doing robust
squares.
I'm taking into account minor variations
in the A's.
Everybody got it?
Now we can do some worst case ones.
I'm not going to go into the details here,
because they're quite hairy.
This is quite near, this is something
that's 15-20 years old.
So, let's do the case where the matrix A
actually is at,
lies in an ellipsoid of matrices.
Again, completely reasonable.
And what we really want to minimize is the
worst case so
its going to be a weird thing if you like
its a game or something like that or
it, it, its like the basically you, you
commit to x first and then your
opponent will then choose the worst
possible a That's what this is, right?
So this is something like that.
And there turns out something like this
you can solve exactly.
Right?
So if you work it out, and
again I'm not going to go through any of
the details because they're quite hairy,
and since it doesn't really.
Matter I mean you should go back over and
check it.
It turns out that here when, one,
when the opponent is calculating what's
the worst thing I should do?
They've committed to x and I'm going to
find the x, you end up solving this
problem, and that is a non-convex problem
if I ever saw one, right?
Because the objective, because you're
maximizing a quadratic, right?
A convex quadratic, right?
Now you haven't seen this yet, maybe you
did or something but it's maybe time for
you to know this, so I'm going to say it,
this is an excuse to let you know.
There are some generic, non-convex
problems that can be solved, okay?
And the simplest one has a very simple and
short description length.
Any optimization problem involving 2
quadratics can be solved globally.
Okay?
Everybody got that?
That's in the appendix of the book.
You should read it, or remember what I
just said, okay?
Because it actually comes up in a whole
bunch of different applications, right?
So, and, and that's convexity, not
convexity.
And you know lot, by the way, you know
this already.
If I walked up to you and I said oh, you
know, please help me solve, you know,
this problem A is symmetric you know,
right.
Something like that.
I said please maximize this thing, right?
How do you maximize that, subject to that?
Well, that, that sure is no convex
optimization problem right, because this
thing is not concave, unless A is negative
definite, negative semi-definite, right?
There's no way, that's never a convex
constraint.
Right?
That's a sphere.
So,
that's a hideously, [COUGH] non-complex
problem.
But everyone here, know the answer.
Knows this can be solved.
This is basically an item value problem.
Right?
The answer is the largest igon vector,
corresponding.
It's the largest Igonvalue, blah, blah,
blah.
Everybody got that?
So, [COUGH], alright.
This fits the thing I'm saying here.
That is an optimization problem, and it
involves exactly 2 quadratic functions.
The general statement is this.
Any optimization problem with exactly 2
quadratic functions can be solved exactly.
And so, what that says is you know someone
says what are you doing,
I'm taking class on convex optimization.
Oh is it interesting?
I, I don't know, and then they,, then you
say well, are all problems convex?
You go oh no, no, no.
The someone says, name the widely used,
useful problem, that's not convex.
The first thing you shouldn't mention, I
would hope,
would be things like singular value
decomposition PCA eigenvalues.
Okay?
We know what this is?
This says those are convex.
Sorry so I mean its kind of weird and
obscure right.
But, and the reason by the way is that the
duals of
these problems have zero duality gap so.
Anyway, right.
So this, that was just my weird little
aside, but this is an advanced thing,
this is not a simple thing, but it's an
extremely good thing to know.
Alright, so, if you include these, you'd
be very hard pressed to find problems,
any problem you can solve that is not
convex if you include these, so, and
that is an open challenge so, so okay.
So, this one, actually can be solved by
solving its dual, which is this SDP.
Doesn't matter, the fact is a zero duality
gap.
[COUGH] Right?
so, okay, now it's fine, because you want
to minimize over choice x,
this thing, but this thing has just been
expressed as a minimization function.
Right, and therefore you minimize both at
the same time.
You solve this sdp and you solve,
you actually solve exactly this robust
least squarest problem, right?
>> Here, what this is, is the following.
Is we have a, I mean this is a very simple
thing we actually have.
It's a two dimensional ellipsoid.
I guess you might even call it an ellipse
or something like that of A matrices.
You commit to X, and then we find the.
We'll find like the worst.
In fact, what we'll actually plot here is
a histogram of the residuals.
Right?
Now here we'll take U uniformly
distributed on the unit disk.
Okay?
And we'll take several values of x.
The first is, suppose you just completely
ignore uncertainty, and
you solve the least-risk problem
minimized, A0 x minus B.
That's the nominal problem.
You minimize that, and you get this
distribution of residuates.
Right?
So, they're all over the place.
And, you know, some of the residuals are
four and five.
By the way,
how would you describe what happened in
this situation over here on the left?
Dumb luck, that's exactly what it is.
Right?
You committed to an x,
and in fact, there are a's that make the
residuals smaller than you thought it
was going to be.
Okay, so that's just dumb luck.
But you pay for it over here.
Okay.
Now you turn on Tikhonov regularization.
And you can even imagine.
I mean, one can even make a cartoon of
this, right?
You can imagine turning off the Tikhonov
regularization knob.
When it's zero, you get this distribution.
Kay?
As I turn it up,
what happens is that distribution will end
up looking like this.
So this is sort of the best looking one,
the Tikhonov regularization one, and
you can see it does exactly what it was
supposed to do.
Right?
Taking off regularization as something
like a heuristic, for, it's a heuristic
for giving you a robust solution, and
you can see, and here robustness we're
going to make it very vague.
You get a tighter distribution of
residuals, okay?
In fact, the expected value of this
distribution is smaller than this one.
I mean, I'm not going to work it out
because it's too simple here.
But you can see it simply, from a
robustance point of view,
a better solution, okay?
So this shows you exactly what people have
known for, I don't know, 50, 100 years.
That you had, you had regularization.
And one interpretation of regularization
is to make your solution more robust to
variation here.
Okay.
Now, the exact Robust lead squares,
the one that minimizes the worst-case
residual over this, over this ellipsoid of
matrices, is the one you obtain by solving
this this SDP here.
Right, so you solve that SDP there, and
you get the following distribution of
residuals right here.
And this is, right there, that is, that's
the number.
Right?
That, that is the optimal,
that's the globally optimal number for the
best you can do.
Right?
And so this is kind of the idea, and I
think these distributions sort of explain,
everything, right, about what you're, what
you're trying to do here, and
what robust optimization does.
Right?
So this is the kind of, thi-, this is,
this the idea.
Notice that when you I mean we can
anthropomorphize this a little bit, but
one thing interesting to notice is that
all of, all of these, everything over here
in either the Tikhonov regular rise or the
nominal solution,
all of those are cases where by dumb luck
you did better than the robustly squares.
Right, so, and what's interesting though,
when you typically push the worst case
regial down usually an effect is
that actually the best case actually goes
the other way.
Right, and, I mean this is sort of natural
but
again, what I'm saying now is extremly
vague.
These would not be arguments you would be
allowed to make.
In public but it's just something to point
out.