Today we'll, we'll do an overview lecture.
Just about sort of the big picture.
And we'll start with the, I'll talk about
a couple things.
I'll talk about just sort of, what is
optimization?
It'll be very informal, so anything you're
not supposed to be following, you're
certainly not supposed to be following
every detail of what I say today.
Because everything we're going to talk
about today,
we're going to talk about later in
disgusting detail.
I mean, we're going to go through it, it's
going to be much longer.
So, if, if you're not following something,
that's fine.
In fact, it's not even clear, it's what we
say is complete.
okay, so talk about optimization.
I'll move on to least squares and linear
programming and
these are really the most famous And the
most widely used
optimization problems widely applied
optimization problems that there are.
By the way, they're both convex
optimization problems.
I'll then say just a little tiny bit about
the common parent and
the common parent of them is convex
optimization.
We'll look at an example, and then I'll,
I'll have some general comments about
what, you know, what, what are we going to
cover in the course?
What are the goals?
What's the style, all that kind of stuff.
I'll say a little bit about nonlinear
optimization.
That's something we're not going to talk
about much in the class.
But just be, as it's weird not to say
something about it before launching into
in, into the class.
And then I'll, I'll,
I'll finish up this overview with a little
bit of a history of convex optimization.
Okay, mathematical optimization.
Well an optimization problem.
Now the the notation is this, is, is, you
say you minimize a, a function.
An objective function, subject to some
constraints like that.
By the way, there's many other notations
for this.
In particular, the notation from the
Soviet Union.
Where there was a long tradition of work
on optimization is this.
You write a problem this way, and this is
now in, in the US you know, from,
from various people who were trained say
at Moscow State, State University.
Is you write you write f0 arrow min and
then st doesn't mean such that,
it means in this case subject to, and then
you'd fi of x is less than bi.
Okay, something like this, so you'll see
other notations for it.
One other thing I should say is although
minimize and
subject to as English words, obviously.
I, I don't consider them that way here.
They are actually names of attributes and
sort of,
you can think of this as an object, right?
It's an optimization problem.
Object minimize is an attribute which is
the sense, it could also be maximized of
course, f0 of x is an objective fi of x
are called constraint functions.
Okay, now, so that's, that's an
optimization problem and
we'll talk about it in much greater detail
later.
so, here so these, you have, you have a x
here,
that's called the optimization variable.
There's a lot of other names for it.
Another one is decision variable, which is
a great name because it,
it sort of tells you it's something you
have to decide on.
You have a choice of different things.
Then f0 is the objective function.
F0 of x basically tells you actually how
much that choice irritates,
irritates because you're minimizing f0.
And so, if f0 of x is large, that means
you're very irritated, and
the smaller it is, the better, okay?
And then the constraint functions have a
different semantics.
All that matters with a constraint
function,
is that fi of x should be less or equal to
bi.
Often, some of these, not al, but not
always,
these have interpretations like resource
resources or something like that.
So, fi of x is, when you choose x fi's how
much of the ith resource you use, and
this constraint states that your budget is
bi, okay?
Now, a solution is simply a point x which
satisfies the constraints, and
among all those that satisfy, all the
vectors that satisfy the constraints,
is one that minimizes f0, right?
And you can call that an optimal point.
You can also call it a solution.
To be honest with you, optimal solution,
that term is redundant.
It's technically correct.
Stylistically a better statement would be
something like, optimal x star or
solution x star.
Let's look at some examples.
So the, the first one, is portfolio
optimization.
So, here the variables could be the
amounts, you have x1 through xn, and
these could be the amounts you invest in
different assets, right?
So, and by the way, these amounts could be
number of shares, they could be
dollar values, or they could be fraction
of a total torp, portfolio, right?
So, so there's lots of, they could
represent different things.
also, by the way, negative could be used
to represent a short position, right?
These are assets you borrow but have the
obligation to pay back later, and
that's essentially the same as owning a
negative number of them.
Okay, so these are the variables, right?
And so you would talk about a vector x
then,
in this context as like a portfolio vector
or a portfolio allocation vector, right?
So, that would mean how do you allocate
your budget across a portfolio?
Something like that.
Well the constraints would be things like
this.
Well, you'd have a budget for example of,
everyone I'd like a portfolio which is 10
to the 9, 10 to the 9, 10 to the 9, 10 to
the 9.
Everyone would.
And it wouldn't matter I guess this can't
be fraction but
if they were in any other amount that'd be
fine.
But of course, there's the constraint that
it has to that the total has to be,
less than your budget.
There might be maximum, minimum investment
per asset,
very common is that the, it's required,
that the x's be none negative, right?
That means that you can't have short
positions, right?
That you can't have you can't own a
negative number of shares.
That's actually required legally in a
bunch of situations like for
example mutual funds in the US.
You can't have you're not,
you're just not allowed to own a negative
number of shares.
Hedge funds, that's false.
You're allowed to, okay.
You might have some,
another very important one would be like a
minimum return, right?
So, you'd say, and that's of course
expected return, right?
So, if there's a minimum guaranteed
return,
that's called an arbitrage that, that,
that well that, that's the,
that the religious basis on which modern
western eco, economics is based.
On the idea there is no such thing as
arbitrage.
Actually a lot of people at hedge funds
will, will, will snicker and
say, oh yeah, sure.
[LAUGH] So okay, and then the objective
might be so,
you might say, I want 5% expected return,
minimum, okay?
And the objective might be to minimize the
total risk in the portfolio, Right?
And, and there're many ways to give risk.
It could be the variance of the return
over some period.
It could be something more sophisticated
like you want to make sure that
the probability of a loss of a certain
level is less than some number.
Lots of different ways to give these.
By the way, we'll end up looking at, at
many of them.
Okay, so here what portfolio optimization
does, is it chooses the best
portfolio that satisfies all the
constraints and minimizes your risks.
Okay, next one is device sizing.
SoI guess that's form conceptual to and
virtual to physical, right?
So, here the variables are the device with
with some link.
So, all of you have lots of electronics on
you right now.
every, all of it was at some point
designed by someone.
And in particular, all, every device had
the, the widths and
lengths of all the devices were, were
chosen, right?
The lengths are often,
in digital circuits are often chosen to
have the minimum possible value for
that technology.
Actually not always, but usually.
So that's, that's chosen and, and the
basic and strength there is,
you can make a big, wide device.
it, they will be like like a wide gate.
A wide transistor and it will be really
fast.
That's the good part.
The bad part is there will be,
it will consume a lot of power and it will
consume a lot of area, okay?
So, I mean this is just roughly, the idea.
Okay, now the constraints are, things like
manufacturing limits, right?
Because, when you design the circuit you
send a big old file,
over to Taiwan where upon it gets sent to,
uh, [COUGH] where upon it gets sent to
Pudong, for manufacture.
And, this is this giant file that
describes in the standard language
basically the post script of, circuits,
it, it, it explains, it,
it says this is my physical circuit.
Please manufacture it.
Right?
So, but whenever, when you manufacture it,
at a certain fabrication facility or
fab, there, they'll have limits, right?
This length can't be bigger than,
can't be smaller than 22 nanometers,
something like that, right?
So that's, that's how that works, okay?
Or, can't be larger, and there's actually
very complex rules, but
the basic ones are minimum and maximum.
Things like that.
This is very important.
You have timing requirements.
So, timing requirements is that,
well, it basically says, your circuit has
to work, okay?
It has to work at whatever clock speed it
needs to work at.
So, if it's going to clock at 1.5
gigahertz, or a gigahertz, or
something like that, then it says in maybe
80% of a nanosecond once this, once the,
once the clock flips.
And the signals start running through the
various gates and things like that,
you have to have stable values with with
some margin before the next clock tick.
Which will come one nanosecond later
gigahertz, right?
And so, there if you make minimum size,
all the devices minimum size,
the good news is your chip will be very
small and will consume very little power.
That would be great.
And the only minor problem is it won't
work because it,
it won't, it, it certainly won't clock at
the speed you want and
it may not even clock at a much lower
speed.
But in any case it's not that interesting
if it clocks at 150 megahertz, right?
As opposed to whatever, to whatever it's
supposed to.
So, these are timing requirements.
And of course you might have a maximum
area, right?
So, total area, you might say, it has to
be no more.
than two square millimeters period, and
that drives a lot, a lot of economics of
chip design and
stuff like that is based on area for you
know, obvious reasons, right?
Okay, and the objective might be among all
designs that satisfy the timing
requirements, everything else, might be
minimize power consumption.
And that would be a good thing to do for
many reasons but for portable devices it's
it has an immediate and obvious good
effect if you have low power.
Because it means long battery life or
something like that, so that's great.
Okay, so now, that, that's your second
example in here.
If you apply optimization to this, which
is basically what is,
in fact, done, what happens.
is, among all designs that meet all the
constraints you find one that has
minimum power, right?
So, that's, that's kind of the idea.
Okay.
And the third is actually from a different
category.
It's data fitting.
Right?
So, it's got lots of other names.
It's also called for example statistics.
Another name for it is machine learning
and we'll see lots of others.
Estimation.
Okay, so these are all names for kind of
the same thing, but the idea, and
we'll see lots of examples of these by the
way, but the idea is something like this.
Here the variables that you're deciding
on,
note that the variables up here are things
that kind of translate into actions.
Right?
So, for
example, up here in the portfolio one, x3
is the amount of asset three to buy.
That would translate, well in the the old
days, into a phone call to tell someone to
buy three shares of something or whatever,
or you know?
Some number of shares or something.
And nowadays, it ends up with a fixed
protocol packet that goes to
some trading computer and then executes a
trade for you, okay?
So, that's it's in other words when you
optimize,
the result of the optimization is, there's
an action, okay?
And the same is here, same is true here
for device sizing, right?
You finish the optimization and the result
is, this gigantic file, that describes
physically your chip and that gets sent
off to TSMC or wherever it's going, right?
So, that's how that works, it gets sent to
a fab to be made.
Okay, so these are, these are actions.
In data fittings, it's quite interesting,
the variables represent model parameters.
And they actually, they, they don't
correspond to any action whatsoever.
There's no action, right?
So, the variables are model parameters and
the constraints so,
in other words you have a family of models
to describe some data, right?
I mean, well, that's, that's what
statistics is, right?
And then your constraints might be things
like prior information.
For example, some of those parameters
might be non-negative and
you know it, right?
And, and you won't even entertain a model
that,
you won't even look at the idea of a model
where those numbers are negative.
And other parts, part of the parameters
might be, for
example, a co-variance matrix, right?
So, and they're,
no one would ever even entertain a method
that estimates co-variances and
occasionally comes back with a matrix
that's not positive, semi-definite, right?
This just doesn't make any sense.
Okay and the objective well, there's a
couple so this is simplified.
But the main objective is actually just it
could be
something like measure a misfit against
your data, right?
So, and we'll see lots and
lots of examples right, for classification
in regression type problems and
just general estimation, where you want to
estimate some parameters.
You have some measurements and then the
question is from the measurements,
how should you estimate the parameters?
By the way, it has lots of other names
classically in,
in kind of older approaches to this.
It's sometimes called inversion.
Estimation even has kind of an older sound
to it, sounds like it's from the 60s or
something like that, right?
But the modern method, it's a set up an
optimization problem and solve it, right?
You set up, you say what you want to
minimize and
then you do it if the problem is solvable.
We'll get to that, okay?
So, and this, we'll see a bunch of cases
like this.
What's very interesting about this example
though,
is that here the variables are not
actions, they're parameters in a model.
Okay, so how do you solve an optimization
problem?
Well, I should say, oh, I should mention,
there are the childish ones that you
were subjected to when you were taught
calculus, right?
So, this is kind of this 19th century
view, right?
Yeah [INAUDIBLE] it kind of works.
That's like you set some derivatives equal
to zero and there's like 21
problems like that you can actually solve
and you know fine, whatever okay?
So, there are these cases, right?
And we shouldn't deny that, that these
cases exist, but it's not
particularly interesting in my opinion in,
in current in the current situation.
Okay, so most of them are basically very
difficult to solve.
And in fact, probably I could go further
than that and
say they are impossible to solve in some
ways, if, if by solve you mean solve.
And you what you can do is you can change
what you mean by solve, right?
To mean for example not solve um, [LAUGH]
well, we'll, I'll get to that.
We'll talk about that a bit later.
Right?
So, so in fact,
now the fact is a lot of people use, some
general optimizations all the time, right?
Generally there's, but there has to be a
compromise you know, in all cases.
The most, the most usual compromise is to
not always find the solution.
So, that's, that's local optimization or
something like that and
it means you simply run an algorithm that
does something and may or
may not produce a point that's feasible.
And has an objective value that's lower
than [COUGH], I don't know, it might have
been, or often you compare it to a
starting point or something like that.
And that's, that's fine.
And that's quite useful now if you do
insist on actually solving the problem,
like actually finding the, the global
minimum.
Then what happens is, these problem can
have very long computation times, right?
And there are other cases where that is
used not anywhere near as many.
Okay, but there are exceptions and
the exceptions they are very famous
classes of problems where that,
there are exceptions, and the most famous
one by far is least squares.
So, in least squares problem,
that's a optimization problem we'll talk
about it shortly.
You solve the problem.
You don't, there's nothing about, you
know,
sometimes it works, it often works, it
really works well.
It just works, always, period, okay?
So, so that's least squares problems.
Another one's linear programming problems.
That's another very famous and broad class
of problems and the common parent of
these two, which is a lot broader and
it's, well, it's what this class is about.
Is convex optimization problems, right?
So, that's that's the common parent of
these.
And these are problems where, they can be
solved efficiently and and
reliably, right?
And so, I mean, and when you start getting
into some details, there's,
there's a lot of exceptions there and
things, qualifications, but
roughly speaking this is correct.
So, lets look at least squares just to
look at what one of
these things looks like.
It's a very simple problem.
Looks like this, it says, minimize the two
norms squared of ax minus b.
The variable is x, by the way, that's part
of the,
you have to say what the variable is.
And then a and b are data or parameters,
meaning that they are the ones that tell
you what a problem instance looks like.
And you have to instantiate a and b or
specify them before then you have a
problem instance and then you solve it.
Okay, so that's that I'm,
I'm assuming that everyone here have seen
least squares in probably I would hope,
in multiple classes because it comes up in
tons of classes or it should.
It might not look exactly like this in
those classes, right?
so, all right,
well this problem, I mean I'm assuming,
assuming no pathologies here.
I mean a is for example, a tall and full
rank.
Then, this is just, this is an analytical
solution to it.
It's just a transpose a inverse a
transpose b, right?
So, that's a good chunk of what we did in
EE263.
And I might add, many other classes,
right?
In statistics this is called regression,
okay?
Its got lots of names.
Alright, analytical solution oh which, by
the way, doesn't mean a whole lot, right?
There plenty of things that have
analytical solutions that
so-called analytical solutions that are
impossible to actually compute.
And actually, this whole course is about
lots of problems where there are no
analytical solutions, and they're very
easy to compute.
That's kind of what this class is.
okay, so more than simply being an
analytical solution, there
are reliable and efficient algorithms in
software to solve least squares problems.
By the way, it's not trivial and, and
not one of them uses the analytical
solution directly.
In another word, you, I'll tell you that
you don't do, what you don't do is
form a transpose a then form its inverse
multiply it by a transposed and
multiply by b.
You do, that's not how it's done.
I mean, obviously it's not done a whole
lot difference from that because it
just evaluating this but still, okay.
And the computation time is proportional
to n squared k,
n is the size of x here and k is the
number of rows.
So, it is a regression problem or
let, something like that, you'd say that,
that k is the number of examples or
something like that, or data measurements
or data elements, something like that.
And then n is the number of you know,
features or regressors, or
something like that, right?
And so the computation times proportional
to n squared, k.
That's if everything is dense.
If a is sparse it's a whole lot less than
that, right?
So, and I mean, this is absolutely
amazing.
You can solve problems that are really
quite large.
And with total and utter reliability.
Meaning you will compute in this case as
assuming there are no pathologies here,
if there's actually a unique x that
minimizes that and
you'll actually compute the, that point.
To very high accuracy very quickly, right?
So, okay.
So, I would say least squares is a mature
technology.
Right?
It's kind of cool,
it goes back about 200 years.
Because Gauss wrote a, a, wrote a paper
about least squares in Latin.
Right around 180 something or other.
Right in there.
So, so
a little bit more than 200 years old, I,
anyway, so, and
it's been, it's been used like,
everywhere.
Right, so, which I'm sure all of you know.
Okay, so how do use least squares?
Well, there's no, there, you can't even
ask this question like, is your,
is this a least squares problem.
It's just not that hard, right?
See, here's, you ready?
Let's, let's figure out, how do you test
that a problem is a least squares problem?
You first have to find, is the objective,
are you being asked to minimize the norm,
the two norm squared of something which is
an affine function of x.
Affine is linear plus a constant.
And if the answer is, yes then you say,
yes it's least squares.
If its no then you say no, it's not.
Okay, so there.
That, that was the, so you don't even talk
about this I mean, what does it mean?
So, instead, what least squares, the way
you should learn about least squares.
And, I mean to some extent you get this
maybe better in
the statistics courses than some other
ones.
But you know, you learn a couple of
tricks, for least squares.
Where upon, you are very effective.
One is the idea of weighting, so you, you
know, you have a bunch of measurements and
you, you can weight some more than others,
that's weighted least squares.
And then the idea of adding
regularization.
And we're going to talk about these things
later in the course but,
you know those two things and you are now
very effective.
And in fact you can even say a giant pile
of engineering, statistics,
all sorts of stuff, data analysis has been
done exactly this way, right?
So, planes fly because of this, basically.
So, now they'll fly better when more
people know the topic of
this class [LAUGH] but
we really have to say this [INAUDIBLE]
least squares you can do a lot with it.
So, okay, Alright so, linear programming
that's this problem.
You minimize a linear function of a
variable subject to
some constraints which are of a linear
function less than a budget, okay?
So, we'll talk about this in great detail
later in the course, that's a,
that's a linear program.
This is also not new, by the way.
This was al, this for example Fourier
wrote a paper about this, I don't know,
1820 something like that, long time ago.
So, but the modern area, era really traces
to about 1948,1950 and
by the way, has a Stanford connection.
Right?
because it's George Dantzig who
popularized it worldwide.
It actually more honestly, it has a Moscow
connection because that's where it
was really done first in the 30s but,
anyway this is linear programming, we'll
talk a lot about later.
But here's the interesting thing.
There's actually, except in completely
trivial cases,
there's no analytical formula for the
solution.
'Kay, there's nothing like a transpose a
inverse a transpose b.
I mean there are for, you know, completely
trivial special cases, right?
But, in general no, there's not.
Here too, there's reliable and efficient
algorithms and software to
solve linear programming problems and it,
it's just as reliable as least squares.
Well, maybe not just, but it's very
reliable, and it's used everywhere,
in all mathematics, almost all
mathematically sophisticated fields.
By the way,
there's still a few kind of backward
fields where it hasn't penetrated yet.
It's coming.
If you know anyone in one of those, if you
have a friend in one of those fields,
just, tell them what, you know, they bring
linear programming into, well we'll see,
we'll get to that later.
Okay, so now the computation time, this is
very interesting.
It's just like least squares [LAUGH]
right?
It's the same,
it's the number of variables squared times
the number of inequalities.
And the number of inequalities has to be
bigger than actually doesn't have to be
but typically is bigger than the number of
variables, right?
So, same sort of thing.
It's it's a small dimension squared times
a big one.
We're going to come back to that later in
the class.
If you remember nothing from the end of
this class,
it's it's small squared times big, but
we'll get to that later, much later.
Okay, so, this is a mature,
it turns out this is also I would say a
mature technology.
Linear programming.
I mean it basically, it works.
It's like least squares.
What's interesting about,
linear programming, is that there are many
problems that don't look like,
linear programming.
But they can be transformed to linear
programs.
And we'll, we'll see a lot of that, in in,
in the course as well, right?
But that's good and bad news, right?
The, the, the good news is it means that
something that looks pre,
like a pretty restrained problem, like
it,,
the only thing it ever refers to is linear
functions.
But almost any interesting thing you could
think of, they are non linear
functions involved and then you say, well,
this must have very limited practical use.
And that's going to turn out to be false,
for the reason I just mentioned.
But there are a lot of problems that can
be transformed to linear programming.
That's the, the good news.
Now, I don't know if it's bad news.
I don't know.
Maybe it's also good news.
The good news is, then, is you have to
know what problems can be transformed, and
how to transform them.
And that's also going to be part of this
course.
Okay, so that's linear programming, and
we'll go over this in great detail later.
This gets us to, well, convex
optimization.
So, I'll say what it is now.
Of course, we'll come back later and do
tons of,
you know, go over this in great detail.
So for now we're going to say it looks
like this.
It's a problem where you minimize an
objective with constraint functions.
And in all of these, these functions have
to be convex and
that just means that this inequality holds
here it says that if
you take a weighted average of after of f
and of, of x and y.
And you evaluate the function there that's
less than the same weighted average of
the function values and that's basically a
picture that looks like this, right?
It says that, it says that if you take x
here, and y here, and
if you take some combination like alpha's
0.25, beta's 0.75.
And you go here,
then it says that if you evaluate it at
that combination that mixture the function
is less than the just the same mixture of
the function values, right?
Or, to put it in classical language, you'd
say something like this.
The cord lies above the graph.
Linear programming and least squares
problems are special cases, right?
Because the graph of norm ax minus b
squared is like a bowl shaped thing.
I mean, if you slice it,
you get ellipsoids and it kind of goes
down like that, right?
So, I mean it's, we'll see later, it's
going to satisfy this.
And affine functions actually satisfy this
always, right?
In fact, affine functions satisfy this,
this const, this inequality here with
equality, right?
So, or another way say it, is a convex
function and
we'll talk about this in great detail in
the next two, three weeks.
Convex functions have non negative
curvature.
They curve up right?
Affine function linear plus constant, they
have zero curvature they are on
the boundary between well not convex and
convex right?
So, linearly programming is sort of like
the extreme case of
convex optimization because all the
functions involved are just barely convex.
Right?
Or something like that, right, they're
right on the boundary.
Okay, alright, now, in general there's no
analytical solution for convex, except for
of course you know, a handful of sort of
trivial cases.
And we'll look at some of those, and some
of those are useful, but
that, that's kind of not the focus of this
course.
But there are reliable and efficient
algorithms.
And the computation time, its roughly the
same as something like least square.
It depends though on various things and
we will have a much more nuanced picture
of this later in the class.
But its something like n squared m would
come up, right?
Depending on the sizes of various things.
But in general it would look, it would
degenerate to this something like, for
example, for linear programming it would
degenerate to the numbers I gave.
And the same for least squares, right?
So, that, that's what it would look like
something like that.
And it's related to, the number of,
of variables that's n cubed number of
constraints m.
And, and capital F is something, the cost
of evaluating all the functions and
their first and secondary, something like
that.
Okay now then the question is, you know,
how do you use convex optimization?
Well here is, I mean here is
the first thing that's actually kind of
interesting is this.
It's actually not easy to recognize convex
options.
And in fact, that's where you're going to
spend the first three weeks getting up to
speed on that.
And in fact, not just the first three
weeks, because we'll do it for
three weeks, and we'll be all overwhelmed
and stuff like that.
But then for the next seven after that, in
practical context,
we'll be doing absolutely nothing but
recognizing convex functions.
Nothing.
I mean,
that's, that's basically what the class is
about, 'Kay?
So, and it's, it's just, it's just not
that, it's not obvious.
We'll get in, we'll see some we'll see
what that looks like later.
Okay, and there are some tricks.
There are some tricks we will see a bunch
of them where for
example, problem might not be convex in
its original form.
But then it turns out you do some
transformation and now it's convex.
And the implication is now it's easy to
solve.
A good example is that circuit design that
we talked about.
It's not convex in the lengths and widths,
but those are what you're supposed to,
that's what you're supposed to optimize,
so what do you do?
And it turns out, and this is not at all
obvious.
It is convex if you work, instead of with
the widths and
the lengths, you work with the log of the
lengths and the log of the widths.
That's weird.
Although actually if you talk to circuit
designer, it's complete, they,
they would say well duh, or something like
that.
And I would say well yea, why do you say
that?
And their like it's obvious.
There's, I don't know anyway.
I actually, I actually trust them.
I, I believe they know that, right?
It's actually and also interesting if you
look at sort of like,sometimes the widths
and lengths are discretized and they look
like things like this.
It'll be like 1, 1.4, 2, 2.8.
Anyone know these numbers?
4.
So they're geometrically spaced, hinting
that somebody knew clearly that what
mattered was actually the log of these
things, of these widths.
And not the actual values or subjects.
So, okay.
Another thing it's true is that that's
another focus of the class is
that it turns out that lots of problems
can be solved via convex optimization.
so, that's, that's also that's also part
of this class, so
we are going to look at a lot of them.
By the way, a whole, a whole lot more
cannot be but that's another story and
we'll talk about that several times.
Okay, let's look at an example, so
here I have a bunch of lamps, that's,
these, are these the lamp positions and
I have some surface down here which is
[UNKNOWN] linear.
And the lamps, I can choose a power at
each lamp and
then that gives you an illumination on
each surface.
And the mapping from power to illumination
is linear.
Right?
So, this is not, this is not coherent
light, it's incoherent and
the power is add, okay?
And you just get some geometry factors.
The geometry factors would be inverse
square the farther you are away.
And then you have a shading or I think
some people call it the cosine factor.
Right?
So, that if you shine light from here and
it goes down you know, you get cosine
theta is the effective power or
illumination so, okay.
And the zero, says that if the surface is
like this,
this is the surface you are illuminating
and
the source is there, you get zero because
it's under it, right, so, okay.
And you can make much more sophisticated
models, that would look the same, for
example, you could add mirrors and weird
other objects and stuff like that.
And it'd still be linear, but
it'd be a super pain in the ass to figure
out what these coefficients are.
Now the question, you're going to choose
the lamp powers.
The lamp powers by the way have to be
between zero and some maximum power.
And what you want is to des,
is to, achieve some constant desired
illumination on the bottom.
And we're going to measure that, by log,
by percentage deviation, in fact by
maximum percentage deviation, right?
So, we're going to take the log of,
of the, the actual illumination, subtract
that from the log of the desired one and
we'll take the max from that, that's
basically the mini-max percentage error.
That's the correct interpretation of the
objective, right?
So, okay, alright.
So, how would you do it?
Well, and I'll just trace you through what
I think would be a reasonable way to
solve a problem like that.
By the way I'm, I'm, this is someone who
actually wants to do this.
This is not a theoretical analysis or
something like that.
So, it's, you might do the following, just
to get a feel for
the problem, you might do this.
You might set all the lamps at constant
power and then vary that power level, and,
and, and plot the objective.
And find, at least the,
find out what constant power level would
give, would do the best that way.
Okay, you might use least squares.
So, you might do something like this, you
might say,
well, I'll, I'll the idea is to make i
desired, ik equal to i desired, right?
I really want to make it equal in a
mini-max percentage error.
But you know, screw it.
I mean, one measure of being close is,
is gotta look like something like another
one, so
I'll use least squares for which I have
technology, okay?
So, I'll use least squares.
Now the problem with this is if you do
this,
it's pretty much guaranteed that some of
the powers are going to come out negative.
And in fact, you're going to do, it's
likely that you'll do really well.
That you'll have, you'll really do well.
Many of the ik's will be very close to the
desired one, and
the way you'll do that is something like
this.
When, when you go back here you know,
these things will put out some power, and
then to adjust it, like this guy in the
middle will spray some negative power.
It will spray darkness on to the, on to
the the patches, right?
And it'll just kind of adjust everything.
You'll do really well.
But, but it, it's not relevant that you do
well, because it's, doesn't work.
It, it violates the constraints.
Okay, so, then you would go into some
weird mode where you start,
you would do things like this.
You'd say, okay, I'll do least squares and
get some lamp powers, and
then if the p that's being called for
in least squares is negative, I'll clip it
off, I make it zero.
I'll turn that lamb off, okay?
And if pj is bigger than my maximum
allowed power.
My maximum allowed power is 10 kilowatts
and
it comes out as 20 kilowatts, I just clip
it to 10, I'll so as much as I can, right?
And you know, if you're lucky, something
like this might work, right?
But if you want to do something a little
more sophisticated,
you would then come up with something like
this, you'd say, well, I'll, I'll keep
this here because that's what I really
want, it's not what I really want, sorry.
This is already a surrogate for
what you really want, which is the
mini-max percentage error, okay.
And you'll add something like this, this
is,
this is standard trick in least squares.
You add, you augment the objective by
adding in this, this says,
I want my lamp powers to be right smack in
the middle of the interval.
That they're allowed to be in, which is
zero p max, right?
And so the point is here,
weight, these are like weights, these are
little, that's a little knob I can turn.
And if I crank up a wj super high, what
happens?
Pj gets to p max over two, I mean narrowly
right?
Okay, but in particular some way as I'm
turning that knob at some point pj gets in
the acceptable interval, right?
So, for these ws high enough you get
feasible,
now of course that's part of the
objective.
Meanwhile this is getting bigger and so
now you could think of some methods for
automatically adjusting these weights, and
weight twiddling and all that kind of, you
could do some stuff.
And something would probably work, maybe
kind of.
Something would happen.
It would work.
This is, I mean, by the way, this is how
stuff is actually done, right?
So, okay.
By the way, you're in statistics, you're
machine learning and you're making, and
you're snickering right now?
You shouldn't be.
because there?
Same thing, it's just, it's these are
just, these are just regularization.
Right?
Although I guess cross validation is
pretty good, pretty that, that,
that no one can argue with, so that's
fine, okay, alright.
Or you might say, well no, I know about
linear programming and
I can actually solve this problem.
And it, this is, now you're getting real
close to the real problem, right,
because look at this, you can handle in
linear programming these inequalities.
And you can handle the, the max of an
absolute value.
So, you're getting pretty close now to, to
what you want.
The difference is, this is the mini-max
error, but
what you want is in fact not the mini-max
error, but the mini-max fractional error.
So, you're getting close.
This would get you pretty close,
especially by the way, if the opt,
if the solution comes out, and it's only
like plus, minus 5%.
You're done.
Why?
Because, you know, between 0.95 and
1.05, log log 1 [INAUDIBLE].
You know, log x looks like, you know, x
minus 1, period.
So, you're done, right?
Now, if it comes out plus minus 50%
something like that,
that's not true anymore.
but, okay.
Now all of these are kind of,
these are not solutions, these are
approximations, right?
But it turns out it's a convex problem,
right?
And it's convex I'll say why in a minute,
but
it's convex because what you're really
minimizing if you take the x of it is,
this thing h is something like the
fractional error, right?
So, it looks like this.
If, if you're above your target one,
right, then it's just linear in it right?
And if you're below it it's one over it,
because it's something like that.
So, in other words plus or minus two would
tell you something,
that's the 50% point and indeed it would
be the interval one half to two.
Right?
So, that's how that works.
And we'll see later that a sum, a convex
function is convex and so
is a max and all that kind of stuff.
So, that would tell you this function is
this problem is convex and
you solve it exactly.
And not only that, actually with tools
that you will learn in
this course this would be completely, you
could, I mean by the fifth, fourth week or
something like that this would be a joke
for you.
It would be insulting to ask you to solve
a problem like that and you could
actually write a script that's about four
lines long that would solve it, right?
By the eighth week of the class, you could
write your own,
you could roll your own for this, right?
You could write your own, solve for it,
stuff like that.
So, oh and by the way,
the computational complexity is a modest
factor times least squares, right?
So, like, 20, maybe 10.
Right?
So, what that tells you is
that if you do more than ten weight
twiddle, you know,
if you twiddle around with the weights
like ten times, and fiddling around.
Then it would, it would be faster just to
solve it exactly.
That's what it comes down to.
Okay.
[COUGH] But let's see, let's add some more
constraints, and see what happens.
So, we'll add, we'll think about adding
one of, you know, two constraints.
Here's one, no more than half of the total
power is in any 10 lamps.
I have no idea why you'd have a constraint
like that, but
let's suppose you did, right?
Something like that, right?
Okay?
So, or
no more than half the lamps are on, right?
So, suppose these are your two these,
these are your these,
these are two constraints.
At first, they sound like they're about
the same.
And certainly if you parse them in English
they sound kind of similar, right?
They, they don't sound that different,
right?
And it turns out this, this constraint is
convex, and
that means it's immediately easy to solve,
exactly.
This one is actually extremely difficult
to solve exactly,
by the way there's very good heuristics
for solving the second one.
Sorry approximately solving the second
one.
Very good heuristics for it but they're
just heuristics.
Okay?
I mean, heuristics are, can be, very
useful, right?
But they're not, you're not solving the
problem, right?
And, what's interesting about this things
like this.
There are lots of other examples like
this.
is, it turns out that sort of, you know,
your basic intuition about whether
a problem is easy or hard especially if
you're not trained about say convexity.
And we're talking about continuous
optimization problems right?
If you're not trained in recognizing
convexity,
then basically your intuition is mostly
just wrong.
This is wrong, right?
The, the kind of things that you either
got explicitly or
implicitly from your 19th century
mathematics training, right?
Which is like, small problems are easier
than big ones, I don't know, you know.
These, they move the smoother things they,
that things are, the, the easier they are.
All of these are just re, they're just
false, they're just not true, right?
They're not, and worse than that they're
not useful, right?
So, okay.
That's actually one of the things we'll,
we'll, we'll see in this, in this class as
we move forward, they'll be lots of,
examples of this kind of stuff.
So, let me say a little bit about what the
course is about.
So, the goals are well,
basically to get you all up to speed in
recognizing these, these problems, right?
So, how, how can you if someone has a
problem, in a practical context, and
the question is, how do you recognize it
as convex, formulate it.
Or in the,
in these more advance settings it, it's
kind of a second tier, or whatever.
You would do something like this instead
of saying that's convex or
not, you would say, that's not convex, but
if we work with, and
then you name some sick change of
variable, it is convex.
Right?
So, we, we'll get to plenty of those, too.
And by this a bunch of those, they, they
occur in all sort of things.
Actually people trained in statistics and
machine learning would already know this
and the case of exponential family, right?
Turns out, the correct thing to estimate
is not the co-variance, that's wrong.
Turns out, the correct parameter to
estimate is the inverse co-variance.
Even sicker, the correct thing to estimate
is not the mean of a bunch of vectors.
It's the co-variance inverse times the
mean.
Okay?
So, you will, you will see all sorts of
little cool things like that.
You've already heard two from this, from
today's overview.
Right?
Okay so we'll also at least in principal
in fact not even just in principle but
we'll actually have you write up some
simple code, and that's simple code for
solving problems like, like these.
You'll know how it's done you won't, we
won't focus a lot on,
on that, that's silly.
Because well, there's quite good software
done by
people who know a lot more than you will
know at that point.
Actually a lot more than I know about some
of these things.
And they've spent a lot of time doing it.
So, so it's not to replicate it.
It's actually to demystify it.
To be able to characterize the solution, a
solution.
Right?
And say what does it look like.
You could say it's no better than this,
and things like that.
We'll see that.
So, okay, so
the main topics of the class then are for
the first couple of weeks we're going to
look at convex sets and
function I, I'm going to warn you now it's
going to be dry.
And what can I say?
Too bad.
It's all for a a grander purpose because I
don't know somewhere around week three or
four it will actually then start getting
interesting.
And by five, six, seven, eight, we, we'll
hit, we'll have hit our stride.
And by then, by week six, my claim is
you'll have been paid back for
what happened to you during the first, the
second and third weeks.
we'll, we'll look at a whole bunch along
the way of examples and applications.
Sometimes they'll be along, along the way,
just to illustrate something which is
a theoretical thing or sometimes it'll
just be fun by itself.
We'll just spend whole lectures looking at
thing like a statistical models and
things like that.
We'll hold lectures looking at various
things.
And we'll also do, then do a section at
the end which is on algorithms.
And algorithms, yeah, how do you actually
solve these things.
And again, that's mostly to demystify
these things, because they're not,
they're not that, they're not that hard.
Okay.
So, I do want to say a little bit about
non-linear optimization.
And so this is the traditional, these are
traditional techniques for
general non-convex op, eh, problems.
And they involve compromises.
By the way this is also called NLP,
which I know clashes with natural language
programming, but you know.
They actually had the acronym first for
the record but that's NLP, it's non linear
programming, and
by the way, that's the kind of, very much
the western view of the world, right?
The, as, as, as all the stuff was
developed in the 50s, 60s, 70s in the US,
it was mostly, oh and, you know, and
Britain and various other places.
It was LP vs NLP.
So, linear programming versus non-linear
programming and
that was the conceptual view, and that's
how people identified you know,
that's, that's who you would hang out
with, and things like that.
There were a few others, it was was ILP,
that was Integer Linear Programming.
And they mostly didn't hang out with each
other.
Anyway, we'll move on.
okay, so here people use local
optimization methods and the idea is, is,
at, at, at the very least,
you find a point that minimizes [UNKNOWN]
zero among feasible points near it.
Right?
So, at least you find,
if you come up with a circuit design and
you say, and
they say, what's the power distribution,
you say it's 82 milliwatts.
And they go, hm that's pretty good
because, you know, last week it was 122.
And then, then you'd say, well, you know,
if you, and the idea is this,
if you we're to search around your design
space near that current solution,
the power would always either go up or
you'd become infeasible.
Right?
You move in one direction and
you'd, you'd no longer meet your timing
requirements but
you move in another direction, you meet
your timing requirements.
And everything else but unfortunately the
power goes out, right?
Or something like that, so that, that's a
local solution.
Okay, and
this, this is extremely successful, I mean
this can handle large problems.
It can do all sorts of stuff, it can be
fast.
Unfortunately, what it, what it requires
is an initial guess a good guess, right?
So, that's how that's done.
And it kind of really turns it into an art
not really a science but,
which is great so it's an art.
And of course, when you do this you're
never really quite sure whether or
not this is the best you can do, because
you don't know.
Now you may not care because, you know, if
you're taping out in ten days and someone
just reduced the power of some some sub
circuit by some significant amount.
Your primary thought is not my God, do you
think there's another design that's like
a little bit better or something like
that, you're like, this is great.
So, so this is fine.
I, I mean in, in some applications, it's.
In many applications, this is just fine.
Okay, now the other compromise is to give
up on speed,
you don't give up on solving, right?
So, another way to say this is, in local
optimization, you kind of give up,
you redefine solve to mean not solve,
right?
It's kind of a best effort thing, right?
By the way, you can always do anything
because you take a heuristic and
you round it, you round, at the end before
you return the solution, you check if
what you require that someone pass in an
initial design or an initial point.
And if after you've done some you time
out, you do whatever the hell you,
it doesn't make any of yous quit and
you check if you what you have produced is
better than what they had.
If it's not, you just, you return what
they gave you, right?
So, then you can do no harm, right?
So, then it's fine, I guess.
alright, now the other opt, the other goal
is,
the other option is to do this, you
actually solve the problem.
You get the absolute best, but you, but
now you're willing and
you will have to sometimes accept very
long computation times, right?
And in this case,
the worst case complexity in theory grows
exponentially with problem size and
sometimes in practice actually fairly
often in, in practice.
This is where you actually get the
absolute best you get, you, you, you get,
you get something to absolutely minimizes
the objective, right?
Now, it turns out in both of these well,
certainly in global optimization, almost
every method for
global optimization is based on convex
optimization as a subroutine right?
So, and we'll see bits and pieces of that
as we go through the course.
So, let me let me finish up with just a
brief history of convex optimization.
So, bits and pieces of course trace much
earlier than this in mathematics, right?
well, linear programming you know,
is 200 years old easily least squares is
whatever 200 years old maybe older.
But the theory of it you know, was pretty
well developed actually by about 1950 and
by 1970 it was really quite well
developed.
I guess in math it's called convex
analysis.
That's the mathematics of, convexity
mathematics of convex optimization.
Yeah, it's kind of, and that was basically
like, kind of done in 1970, roughly.
Now algorithms for solving it there have
been lots, but
I'll just mention some of the highlights.
So the one is this simplex method for
linear programming.
And this is George Dantzig, who was
actually at Stanford.
So this is from the 40s this is also done
in Moscow in the 30s I should add.
This is simplex method for linear
programming and, and
actually the date is really interesting
because it tells you something.
It's basically coincident with the
development of
the modern digital computer.
And that, that's what sort of make this
entere, I mean,
this was in 1940 all the material we're
going to cover in this class,
what we couldn't have covered any of the
applications.
But all of the material will be super
interesting.
Very interesting mathematics, right?
What, but, when you throw computation, the
ability to do computation and
actually do stuff that has real
algorithmic teeth,
where you're not just writing down silly
formulas.
And or searching for silly formulas in
vain, or
something like that, then it gets really
interesting.
And so, it's not an accident that, that,
that this is about the right time.
It came at the right time.
It's a very simple method called, simplex,
it was propagated and
used everywhere in the world.
It's used in, all over to this day.
Okay now, part of something interesting in
this class is
in the 60s there were some early, early
attempts at, at interior point methods.
We are going to study those in maybe the
seventh, eighth week of the class or
eighth or ninth, something like that.
There were early attempts at these.
So, a lot of the stuff that we are
going to look at is not new.
By the way some, is very new.
So, some of the applications and things
like that are very new, some is new.
But, a lot of it is, not new.
Those traces to the 60s.
In the 70s, there was work out of, out of
Soviet Union on,
methods called ellipsoid methods and
sub-gradient methods.
We're actually not going to cover those in
this class, but
just its another I think a very important
milestone.
A big one was in the 80s and in the 1980s
you may
even heard about this I guess AT&T was
being broken up or something like that.
Bell Lab was, was being pulled, was, was,
was going out on its own.
And somebody knew something,
somebody who knew somebody else who knew
somebody else and, and an algorithm for
linear programming ended up on the front
page of the New York Times.
Right, not, not, not front, the sci, not
the science section.
Front page.
I mean okay, maybe it was a slow news day
okay, still.
>> [LAUGH].
>> But still, still it was the front page.
And sometime in the late 80s to now there
was just a whole bunch of
things came together in the right way.
And there are people in the Soviet Union
working on solving general convex
problems, people looking at applications
and
this all kind of came together, and and it
was great.
So, and, and things worked out.
So, the most interesting part is something
like this,
is before about 1990 there, there were
plenty of applications.
It was almost all linear programming,
right and they were,
they were generally not, I mean, some were
in engineering, but
mostly they were in areas like finance
management.
These types of areas and so they were in
operations research departments.
What were happened in the 90s was that
more and more areas in engineering started
using these things by the way, a similar
thing happened in statistics.
I would say that up until 19 you know,
90 it was still like you're doing you know
Fisher and analysis of variants and
basically in least squares and things like
that.
And it's somewhere between 1990 and like
ten years ago,
the idea that you would actually solve
some problem to come up with a statistical
estimate sort of became mainstream and has
propagated very widely now.
We'll talk about that in great detail.
But since then there's been this huge
explosion in lots of areas, in engineering
but also in statistics, machine learning
and lots of other areas so.