The second section of course of course was
on a applications in
geometry in approximations statistics
areas like that.
And this last section in the course is on.
Numerics and algorithms how do you
actually solve these problems?
Now, you have been solving in these
problems more well for
the last two parts of the course you have
been solving these problems.
But presumably at this point you don't
know how it's done and
the main goal of this section, the whole
section of the course is to demystify.
How it is that we solve these convex
problems, right.
So that's that's the idea.
Now, most of you are not going to write
your own solvers.
Right.
Actually, some of you might have to,
if you solve, if you go into areas where
the problems are absolutely gigantic,
you know, something like CVX is not
going to work,
you're going to have to develop your own
solver.
Or if you go into like real time systems
where you need to be able to
solve optimization problems in micro
seconds.
Again something like cvx is not going to
work for you and
you're going to really have to known how
its done.
I should say a couple more things about
that.
I still believe strongly, its not just a
question of demystifying it but
I believe its very important for everyone
to know a little bit
About how these problems are solved and
specifically what you want to
know is the link between problem structure
and how fast we can solve it.
So that's really, if there was one take
away for
the entire last part of this course, it's
to understand that.
That one thing.
You should be able to look at that problem
and say "Ooh!
That's got a hundred thousand variables,
but I can solve that super fast, because I
recognize the structure." So that's what
this whole section of the course is about.
Now we are going to go back today and
start, well, at the very beginning.
We are going to talk a little about
numerical algebra.
Some of you probably know this, others of
you probably don't.
People who have used things like...
Matlab have certainly been using this as a
user,
as a consumer but you may not know
actually how it's done.
And what we'll do today is just look at
the basics and
I should also say how it fits into the big
picture.
So the big picture is, this lecture,
we're going to talk about How do you solve
a linear equation.
So that's fine.
And there's a finite algorithm for that
and we'll look at how that's done, and
we'll we'll see we'll see how it's done.
It's gaussian elimination.
You've been doing this since high school I
assume.
Okay then I'll tell you how this fits into
the rest of the course.
Right?
So in the rest of the course we'll see how
do you minimize, we'll start by talking
how do you minimize a smooth function.
well, with start with how do you,
we'll start with how do you minimize a
quadratic function.
Well, you set the gradient equal to 0.
But the grading of a quadratic fuction is
a linear function, and
so, minimizing a quadratic function,
solving linear equations.
So if you like, you can think of this
whole stuff we're going to look at now,
how do you solve linear equations, as how
do you minimize a quadratic funtion.
So, that's the optimization connection.
Okay so, we will first start by talking
matrix structure and algorithm complexity.
Matrix structure is, you know, somethings
are obvious like what is, you know,
diagonal matrices, identity matrices
sparse matrices.
We'll talk about that.
Then we'll talk about the dominant method
used to solve linear equations.
And that's using factored matrices.
So you'll factor a matrix and
then solve, do a sequence of solves, with
the factored, with the factors.
We'll talk about some very famous
factorizations, the so called LU,
that's going to be for lower triangular,
upper triangular,
the Cholesky factorization and something
called the LDL transpose
factorization where L is lower triangular,
D is diagonal and L is upper triangular.
Actually we will see in some cases D is
block diagram.
Then, we'll look at a general construction
called block elimination in the matice
inversion lemma and this is something that
shows you how it
is that you can solve sometimes absolutely
enormous sets of linear equations.
Very efficeintly by explointing some
structure that's present.
And the last thing we'll talk about,
though very briefly is solving
undetermined equations.
So first let's just start with solving Ax
equals b.
Where A is n by n.
Okay?
And in fact let's say on
that laptop right there, that's not mine,
but I know the, I know the number.
I wa, I want to ask you all,
how long do you think it takes to solve
the equation Ax equals b?
Where x is size 1,000.
Before you say anything, I want to point a
few things out.
That's solving 1,000 equations, for 1,000
variables.
The size of A, is a million coefficients.
Everybody got it?
Okay?
And now what I
want to know is how fast can I solve it?
The answer is 30 milliseconds.
Okay, and I happen to know the number on
that thing is about ten.
So actually, this is an amazing thing, and
it's actually worthwhile for
all of us to sit and think how
unbelievably amazing that is, right.
I mean that is ridiculous.
Right?
That's something that
takes like a billion, we'll see it takes,
generic methods take a billion operations.
It's ten, fifteen miliseconds on that.
Okay?
It's got multiple cores,
does all sort of things are happening to
make that number.
But just the idea actually that it's less
than a second is unbelievably impressive.
Okay?
So well we'll get to that.
So it, so it basically for general methods
right?
The general methods means you, you're
exploiting nothing in the matrix a,
absolutely none, right?
All the entries are assumed to be non-zero
there's no particular structure.
The structure would be something like a
might be A discreet foray transform or
a discreet cosine transform.
In which case, of course, you can solve it
faster than n cubed.
You can solve it in like n log n.
Okay so that would be structure.
Other structure would be sparsity.
Right, that would be that A has a lot of
zeroes.
Right, one definition of sparsity goes
something like this: it's.
A matrix that has enough zeros that it's
worth your while to take advantage of it.
That's 1967; I mean it's a perfectly good
definition, right?
So, okay.
So general methods, it says that these
things grow, like N cubed.
oh, so for fun, how long would it take
that laptop there to solve?
Say a hundred, hundred equations,ah and
a hundred variables that's 10 thousand
coefficients in the matrix.
So the answer was what 30?
>> Micro seconds
>> Micros seconds, thank you, okay.
So I mean that's ridiculous,
by the way this also hints Why you should
know about all those things, right.
These numbers are so ridiculous that it
means these things can now be embedded on
all, it means the amount of computation
you can do can now, is unbelievable.
You can put stuff, you can actually embed,
all of these things can be embedded.
They can, and things that would normally
take like seconds to run.
>> Can run in milliseconds.
They can be embedded in things.
I mean, crazy stuff can happen.
So, OK.
All right.
So, basically for
general, these are the generic methods.
This grows as N cubed.
And I'll, I mean I'll tell you what the
generic methods are, shortly.
what, what they are.
And this is, this is the part that I
think.
I want everybody to know.
When A is structured, and we'll talk about
all sorts of structure, it's way faster.
Or generally, substantially faster than n
cubed.
Okay, and structured is stuff like banded.
A banded matrix is 1 Where, basically, a i
j is zero,
if the difference between i and j is big
enough.
Bigger than some thresh hold.
Right, systems like that can actually be
solved in linear time, okay.
So, I mean these are just things you did,
you wouldn't I mean unless you knew this,
it's not obvious right, so what that say
is I can solve a million variables with
a million equations on that laptop,
actually I can do that on my phone but
on that,that laptop I solve a system of a
million equations,a million variables.
If, if it's banded with a bandwidth of
like five.
Right?
And not only that, it can solve, I mean,
unbelievably fast.
I won't do the calculation now but it'll
be shocking.
OK?
And if you didn't know that, you'd think
well that's,
that's a big hard problem or something.
You multiply it by n cubed.
Okay.
so, what are the basic ideas?
Well this goes back to the 60s.
It's still sort of relevant.
It's less relevant that it was.
I'll say a little bit about that.
But, it's still not a bad indicator.
so, basic concept is a FLOP, that's
supposed to be a Floating Point Operation.
And roughly, it's something like an
addition, a subtraction,
a multiplication, division of 2 floating
point numbers.
Now, there's some older definitions where.
It's an addition plus a multiply and
you might include things like square roots
in there.
All of that is nonsense because square
roots cost like 50 times more.
A division is something like, cost you 20
times more than an add.
So for all of these things, the,
the key idea now is just to not to take
the numbers too seriously, right?
They're to be considered to be within a
factor of ten.
Right?
And that, that, that's the right number.
these, the flop was invented sort of when,
you know,
main CPUs didn't do floating point
arithmetic, you know.
Then basically had to like send a message
over to some giant board that
was like your floating point board.
And all sorts of stuff happen.
And then when that multiplying was
finished.
Right?
Something would come back.
Everybody, you know, and
so in that setting, sure, counting the
number of flops made total sense.
It's ridiculous now right because, you
know it, with the number of,
I mean there's all sorts of things you
could do there not even getting into like
minor details but you can do crazy stuff
all in parallel and stuff like that.
So, okay.
>> All right.
So, the, the, the idea, and
this traces to the 60s and is still
actually somewhat relevant.
It goes something like this.
To estimate the complexity of an [UNKNOWN]
what you do,
is you'd express the number FLOPs.
It usually, it's a polynomial.
It's a polynomial function of the problem
dimensions.
And then what you do is you drop.
All but the leading terms, right?
So, you know, if it's something like, you
know, 1/2 n cubed plus 2 n
squared plus blah, blah, blah - something
like that - you just say, well, it's one.
The complexity's 1/3 n cubed.
And honestly, these days, the 1/3 doesn't
make any difference at all.
Because you're not shooting for - you
know, factor of 2 is ridiculous.
You could not predict using these methods,
right?
Factor of 10 is the right, the right
amount.
Now you know this is not an accurate
predictor of
computation on modern computers.
Right.
It, you can get it within a factor of ten
if, if thing you know in the absence of
certain bad things and
actually if things are done really well
right like it's optimized code it once
again becomes a reasonable predictor.
So it's kind of an interesting thing.
but, you know it's still, it's, it's very
useful as a rough estimate of complexity.
It's still, it's still gives you that,
right?
but, you know, do not come along and say
oh, you know, this one is
half the number of flops therefore, it
must run faster or something.
I mean things like your, your access
pattern and, and,
and Locality of reference and memory are
way more important than factors of to and
flop counts, and things like that, so,
okay.
I mean another nice thing is that a lot of
these things are done for
us by people who know what they're doing,
namely those who write like compilage and
things like that, so that, that's the good
news.
Okay, so.
Let's look at some, operations and this is
a conceptual division.
It's a vector-vector, matrix-vector,
matrix-matrix product.
And I should say this is something you
should probably all know about.
There's no reason not to.
There's something called BLAS and it
traces to the 60s, 70s.
It's called it, it stands for Basic Linear
Algebra Subroutines.
Right?
And believe it or
not, the, the standards of these are
written in I, well four tran.
That gives you a rough idea.
OK?
And by the way still.
So, and then they have of course,
these are re implimented in all sorts of
real languages actually.
So anyway this is basic linear and they
call these things,
this is called blass- Level one, this is
blast two, and that's blast three.
Right.
You don't need to know that, but actually
that's not true.
An educated person just knows these
things.
You don't have to know the details of
these things.
But you should know but there's blast
level one, blast level two, and
blast level three.
And I'll say a little bit about what,
what they mean and what why it's important
to know about.
Okay.
So vector-vector operations this would be
something like, you know, calculating an
inner product, right?
You calculate an inner product, yeah, you
can count the number of flops.
It's like 2n minus 1 flops, 2n if n is
large, right?
So that's something like that.
So you'd say it's order 2n or something
like that.
Another one would be like a sum.
Something, something like that.
By the way if you're taking an inner
product it, it what,
would also depend if, if the vectors are
sparse.
Then, needless to say this could be way
faster.
And it actually depends, I mean, quite a
bit on You know,
the data structure used to describe sparse
vectors and things like that.
So.
Okay.
The other thing let's just say about an
inner product,
I mean just to give a hint, sort of, about
modern stuff,
is something like an inner product, is, is
easily paralyzable.
Right so so on a modern on on some modern
platform it'd be divided up
if you do an inter plot of 2 million long
vectors they have multiple threads and
each one would be taking inner product in
chunks and
then those would be added together in
things like that so.
That's.
I'm just saying.
That's by the way how you get the 20
millisecond, 30 millisecond numbers to
solve a thousand equations on that laptop.
Okay?
So, but it's not bad.
If you want to think of something serially
stepping through like,
please get me the next x i.
Please get me the next y i.
Please multiply them together.
And then, plus equals that on some, some,
you know,
you're inner product plus equals x i y i.
If you want to think of that.
Go ahead, it doesn't hurt.
It's charming, it's simple.
But, you should understand that's not how
it works.
I mean, unless you write the code right
like that, right?
In which, in which case it'll run,
whatever, 10 times slower, like so.
Okay.
All right.
Next one is matrix vector product.
That's y equals a x.
So here you multiply a matrix by a vector
and what is it?
Well, you know there's many ways to think
of it.
But, one way if you're just counting
FLOPs, it doesn't matter,
is that it's basically, you take the inner
product of each row of A with x.
Okay?
So, it's basically calculating M inner
products in our N.
And that's something like 2 MM.
Right?
And you forget the 2.
This is like, that's a joke.
Right?
It's order M, N.
Right.
So, it's the number,
it's vaguely number entries in A.
Now if A is sparse, this is obviously a
whole lot less.
Right?
And but actually, [INAUDIBLE] how fast it
is, is quite a complicated topic and
depends on exactly what data structure's
used to represent the sparse matrix and
all sorts of stuff like that.
Right?
But Again, it's not easy at least at a,
without looking, getting into the details
to realize that,
if a matrix is a million by a million,
with maybe 10 million non-zero entries,
you only have to multiply it by the 10
million non-zero entries, right?
So, okay.
And it can be less, it's a structure.
so, for example, here's one.
If I gave you the matrix A.
As a, a low rank product, right?
So if I gave you the matrix A.
Let's suppose a is million by million.
But I give it to you as a million by ten.
Multiply it by ten by million, right?
So it's what you would get if you ran pca,
or sbd, or
something like the low rank approximation.
>> Number 1, you'd actually be able to
store it.
You can't store a million by million
matrix, right?
So, but you could store it this way.
And the multiply would certainly not be a
million squared.
It would be way less.
It's order of a million.
In fact, it's like 20 million times that
because, 10 by 10.
Everybody got this?
Right.
So, okay any of BLAS level three.
These are matrix matrix products.
So, that means multiply two matrices.
I mean that's the canonical one, is
multiply two matrices.
And here, it's actually the product of the
dimensions, basically, right?
If these are like m by n, m by p.
It'd be, it's mnp.
So it's the product of the, of the
dimensions.
Okay.
That are sparse, it's much less and
you get different things if if they're
symmetric, you can divide things by two,
I mean, that typically doesn't matter but
that's, that's the idea.
And now, this is probably where I, I mean,
again, we, these are now things We're not
going into these details, but
I'll just say a little bit about it so
that you appreciate it, right.
So, everybody here knows how to multiply
two matrices, right.
I mean it is, you could write a five-line
C program that would do this,
every here could, right.
It can be truly trivial.
It could be like how do you get C i k?
Why, you, you walk along A and
you walk along B and multiply the, the
associated entries.
And then add it all up.
right?
So, you could write a five line C program.
Right?
It'd be a bunch of fours and
wouldn't even be five lines, probably.
It'd be 5 lines with a lot of commenting
but, okay and you can compile it.
And, of course, it would do, like you know
whatever.
Two MNP FLOPs by the time it runs.
In fact.
If you were to do, if you were to use
LAPACK, that,
that's the, again, this is just for
cultural background.
You do not need to know this although it's
not bad to know it, okay?
So, LAPACK is just, this is an open source
package of linear algebra routines.
and, you know, multiplying two matrices.
This I mean doesn't seem like there be any
if you don't think about this doesn't seem
to be any subtlety there right we all know
what CIK is, its sum over J, AIJ be JK
right I mean it don't look like a whole
lot of room for optimizing there right.
I can give you something a little more
complicated like sorting or
something like that or finding the
shortest path But
then you can imagine somebody smart could
do something better.
Everybody, everybody see what I'm saying
here?
I mean, come on, calculating the product
of two matrices?
You know, one person's implementation, you
can beat a naive one by a factor of 100?
That doesn't seem right.
Does anyone know, by the way, how that's
done, and why?
Its actually kind of interesting.
I mean, this is just for cultural
background, but its good to know.
Here's how you multiply two thousand by
thousand matrices.
Here's how you do it if you use this
package.
What happens is, thousand by thousand
matrices are broken down into things like
ten by ten block matrices with blocks that
are hundred by hundred.
Everybody following this?
Now, matrix multiplication you can do
block wise.
Right.
So, what that says is you end up
multiplying 200 by 100 matrices
by blocking them and then each block you
do 100 by 100 multiply.
Okay.
Now the 100 by,
how do you do 100 by 100 multiply?
It's blocked down to 10.
So each of those is a ten by ten matrix of
ten by ten matrices.
Everybody got this?
And then so what's really happening is
you're doing giant piles of
ten by ten multiplicates, and
by the way the parameters of ten I made up
are totally made up and it would differ.
Depends on your architecture.
Alright?
Okay, so that's called blocking.
And the idea behind blocking is you can
arrange it if you do it just right.
If the block's in the right sizes like
that ten by ten multiplied might hap,
might happen in, you know, the ten by ten
multiplied might happen with registers or
something, right.
And then the hundred by hundred might fit
in L, might just fit in L1, right?
And stuff like that.
So if you do this right, if you do your
blocking right.
>> Then, you, and not only that.
You could do part of it in parallel and
stuff like that.
If you have multiple cores, you know,
somebody's multiplying these.
Somebody's multiplying these.
You exploit all this stuff.
And that's actually how matrices get
multiplied.
OK?
On, at, at least on a,
you know, on sort of a modern processor.
Right?
So, that, that, that's the idea.
And, and if you wa, and
the memory access pattern is such that
there are never [UNKNOWN].
And by the way, how do they, how do they
choose the block sizes?
That's they have something called atlas,
right?
That's [LAUGH] really kind of cool.
I mean, you don't need to know any of
these things, right?
But it's sort of fun.
That's automatically tuned linear algebra
software.
This all open source stuff.
And what it does, it takes your computer
and it just said, I try 10, right?
And it does it, and
it factors matrices for a while and it's
say I'll try blocking it as 9 by 9.
It tries 9, it tries 11, it tries 12, and
it just does bisection or
just tries a bunch of them and then half
an hour later.
It's decided on your architecture what the
right cash,
what the right blocking sizes are.
Okay, completely imperdible, everybody got
this?
So, and when you see these curves their
absolutely amazing.
It would be things like, you would see
something going like,
here's, here's a function of n.
And say it would be, it would be looking
like that.
That's a log, log plot.
Then all of a sudden you would see this.
[LAUGH] Right, and, and you'd say, and by
the way, what would this be?
Yeah, so this is something that's just
barely fitting in some cache, right?
And this is something that, that.
This is called bad blocking.
This is, this is where your block sizes
were exactly You know a handful of
things to big to fit in some cache.
So basically it's a disaster, something
like that.
In fact this can even go down that's the
cool part.
This can be nonmonotonic but any way okay.
So that's more than you need to know about
all of this but it is good to know.
Actually it is good to know even if you're
interests are quite theoritical or
mathematical.
This is good to know beacuse if you do
theorical or
very mathematical things You know, here's,
this is how it hits the road.
It hits the road right here, in, in LA
Pack in most cases.
Well, except in giant sparse things, but
we'll talk about that.
But a lot of times, you do some cool
statistics,
you do any you do [UNKNOWN], it's this.
Now we're going to talk about solving
linear equations,
and The one way to do it.
We'll first talk about classes.
classes, of, of, matrices.
Where solving Ax equals b is easy.
And then there's a simple trick that puts
it all together.
So, one would be this.
Diagonal matrices.
Right, so if A is diagonal then solving a
equals b.
Is simple.
oh, by the way, one interesting thing is
people will,
when people write A inverse b,
mathematically it's what you mean.
That's what x is.
But it is universally understood, even if
people write it
in an algorithm statement that it doesn't,
that you do not parse it this way.
A inverse times b because that would
suggest code like, you know,
a.in, you know, times b and eh, eh,
except in extremely rare cases you would
never compute it that way.
But,.so, a inverse be is sort of like a,
a phrase that when someone describes an
algorithm you should see.
And it doesn't mean form inverse and
multiply by b Mathematically it's the
same.
The semantics is identical.
But you should understand that this is so
common so, and people will even say things
like inverting that matrix is easy and
they don't mean inverting the matrix.
They mean solving the equation.
Okay, so this is just, so, okay.
So here, you know, computing a inverse b.
If, if A is diagonal.
It's incredibly easy.
It's just you divide.
It's N FLOPs.
You know, roughly.
Whatever it is.
OK?
The next one is interesting.
Right?
It says that a matrix is lower triangular.
And so, that says, you know it looks like
this.
A11, A21, A22, you know, something like
that.
Okay?
And you're multiplying this by, you know
x1 up to xn and that's supposed to be,
you know b1 up to bn.
Okay?
And yeah, how do you, how do you do this?
You look at the first row.
The first row says a1, 1, x1 equals b1, so
x1 is, is obviously a b1 array 1, 1.
Right?
Oh, and by the way, what exception do you
throw if a1, 1 is zero?
What if we have a divide by 0 exception?
Yeah.
You throw a message back which
is like A singular.
So, so I'm not going to calculate a A
inverse b for you.
Right, so okay.
So once you know x1, right?
And there's lots of ways to think of this.
Once you know x1, the second row says A21
x1 plus A22 x2 equals b two right?
But you know x one so
you just plug in that value subtract it on
the right and then divide it by A22.
So the algorithim looks osmething like
this an dyou
can sort of calculate the number of flops.
I mean it doesn't matter but you can
kind of get a rough idea what it is.
>> This thing is kind of growing.
the, oh this, and it's got a, a great
name.
This is forward substitution.
And the reason it's called forward
substitution is you calculate XI.
And then XI, from then on, you substitute
that value into the equation.
Right?
And so, you can see, you do kind of like.
Length 1, length 2, length 3, length 4,
and it's growing.
And you know that the sum of
those numbers is something like the square
over 2, right?
And if you do it exactly right, it's just
like n squared, right?
You count blocks, that doesn't matter.
It's n squared blocks.
Okay, and that's called forward
substitution.
And there's a, a similar one, if a matrix
is upper-triangular.
And what do you imagine it would be, you
know, the same thing.
It's like called, it's backwards
substitution.
Right?
You start by getting XN first and
going backwards.
Okay?
So these are, and these are,
just completely simple.
There's nothing complicated here.
This is really interesting when A is
sparse.
Because when you have a lower triangular
sparse matrix.
I don't know.
Go ahead and give me a rough number.
So for a sparse matrix.
1, and a very important attribute is
number of non zeros,
sometimes written NNZ, okay?
So I just roughly, if I have, in terms of
the number of non zeroes.
How many FLOPS does it take to do forward
or
backward substitution with a lower
triangular, upper triangular matrix?
That's sparse, in terms of the number of
[INAUDIBLE] zeros.
What is it?
Yeah, it's winning.
In fact it equals, kind of, to the n and
z.
Everybody got that?
Because, basically each of these
coefficiants appears once.
Right?
And so, it's about linear.
So, that means if I
have a million by million matrice Right?
With let's say 50 million non zeros,
that's you know on average of 50 per non
zeros per row or column.
That's 50 million, 50 million flops.
How fast can I do it on there?
This rough order magnitude.
You can assume that's between 1 and 10
gig, gig gigaflops something like that.
So the answer is milliseconds.
Another one would be orthogonal.
So if a matrix is orthogonal then in fact
solving,
well computing a inverse b is the same as
well a transpose b.
Right?
So its just a matrix vector multiplied,
its ordered n squared in general but
it turns out it actually depends how the
orthogonal matrix is stored.
There are other data structures.
Here's a very famous one.
And it looks like this.
That's, that's called, that's a
reflection.
Right?
That's, that's an orthoganol matrix.
And you can see it is an identity minus a
rank one matrix.
Right?
We're going to
talk a lot about that later today.
But so there that can be done in order n
flops.
Right, so very fast.
Right.
So, so for example, one, I mean, it's not
completely standard, but it, you would
occur often is one data structure for
representing an orthogonal matrix is as a
product these things,
these reflections here.
And you would actually give them, you
would give the u , u1, u2, u3,
u4 and you can see the multiple, multiple
actually would be the same to multiply,
multiply by the transpose which is the
inverse,
each of those would simply be linear in
that in that data structure,
right and if I now want this permutation
matrix so permutation matrix.
Well, it's kind of silly.
Right?
If I solve, you know, P x equals b, all I
do is permute the interest, right?
And actually by this 1960's version of
things.
When you say, how many flops is that, the
answer is zero.
There's no floating point in just doing,
you're copying.
You're copying I, I guess you, all you're
doing is you're copying, you know,
whatever it is eight bytes or, how many
bytes is a, a double?
Eight?
So
you're copying [UNKNOWN] eight bytes from
here to there and around like that.
So, and oh, by the way, if that's a
hundred million long vector, and
their access pattern is completely random
or whatever This could, you could
end up with, this could be not, it could
be 0 flops and actually take some time.
Okay?
[COUGH] Alright okay, so alright and
now we get to, how do you solve Ax equals
b?
and, it's a general method.
It's, it's, it's, it's a high level, It's,
it's, it's factor solved.
And there are some very important things
that actually to know about it.
And some, if you hadn't seen these stuff
before,
you'll learn something shortly and it'll
be quite real I mean,
it'll be something you should know, and
it's not expected.
So the idea is this, there's two steps,
there's factor and
there's solve And factor says you take
your coefficent matrix and
you factor it as a product of simple
matrices.
By the way, you've seen tons of things
like that.
Like SVD, eigon decomposition, eigen
vector,
you know, you've seen lots of these
things.
Right?
QR factorization.
Alright, so what you do is you factor it
as a product of simple matrices.
Sometimes it's two,
it just it could be as few as two and it
could be as many as four or five, right.
Actually sometimes it can be a variable
number where some of those things have
exotic data structures, like it could be
these products of reflections, right.
OK.
So well, one example is you can actually
understand the fft this way.
I don't knwo if people know.
If you know what the fft is, great and
I'll say what it is.
It's a specific matrix.
It's the dfd matrix, the discreet
[UNKNOWN] transform.
It's a Vandermon matrix with a bunch of
complex numbeers in it.
Do you know what I'm talking about?
Fine.
It basically calculates a discreet
[UNKNOWN] transform.
And there's an interesting thing where you
take an order n, matrix like that, and
you can factor it into a product of log
and
matrices, which have very specific
sparsity patterns.
Okay, and it turns out, if you do this and
then exploit some of the structure,
you get an N log N factorization.
Okay, so, alright, let, let's move on.
So, these are things like, you know,
diagonal, upper, lower, triangular, and
so on.
And then I mean this is totally obvious.
>> What is A inverse B?
Well, I mean, the inverse of a product is
just the product of the inverse.
It's in the other order, like this.
And then you parse it.
This is extremely important this way,
remembering that you're never computing
any of these inverse.
Right?
You're, you parse it this way.
So, you should actually think of
that as a method.
A1 inverse that you call on B.
so.
That, that's what happened.
So, it, you just un, you just, you unwind,
right?
So you write A as a product, calc,
calculate inverse B,
you call the inverse methods from
backwards, right?
And you just unwind everything.
So it looks like, that's the idea, right?
So, so that's the idea.
Now this immediately has some.
Pretty cool implications.
It says the following, and this, this is
like very important.
It says that suppose you need to sol, had
solve a bunch of
equations with the same coefficient matrix
but with different right hand sides.
Okay, that comes up in tons of places,
right?
I mean Void, tons.
Right?
So suppose that's your problem.
And what you, by the way,
you'll see tons of cases where this comes
up.
Okay.
Then, what it says is, you factor the
matrix.
That typically costs more we'll talk about
that in a minute, then the,
then the solve.
Right?
So you factor it and you cash the
factorization.
Now what that means is it says that if you
want, if you have, if you
want to do multiple right hand sides you
get one factorization, here, and m solves.
Okay?
So, for
the most common methods by the way,
solving linear equations,
the factor plus n cubed, the factor steps.
And the back solves cost n squared the
solve steps.
Okay, and now I'm going to ask you a
question.
To solve 1000 linear equations with 1000
variables
on that machine is, I'll just make up a
number.
We'll fix it as, I like your number.
30 miliseconds.
It's 30 milliseconds,
and I want to know how much time does it
take to solve two equations.
AX equals B1, AX equals B2, with the same
A.
It's 30 milliseconds to do one.
How many is it to do two?
By the way, the naive method just calls,
solve AB twice.
And the answer is, what did we say, 30
millisecond?
60 milliseconds.
And what is the correct answer?
30.
It's studen, is 30.
OK?
All right?
How many does it.
So, by the way, that's pretty weird.
Everyone got that, that the cost of
solving two linear equations, if you,
if you, if you cash the factorization, is
actually the same as one.
And I don't think this is obvious,
frankly.
It is not obvious unless you knew this,
right?
It, it's an absolutely real phenomenon and
it's, it's the key to tons of things.
Okay?
Because of things being sort of
either viable or not.
Right?
How much would it cost me to solve, let's
say, 25 linear equations.
25 different righthand side same A on that
laptop.
I'm doing 25 times more work.
And time is the same.
The answer is yes because the
factorization dominates everything.
Once you factor you can it simply.
If whatever your background is, you didn't
know it, this can actually have
a huge impact on all sorts of stuff So
let's look at some factorizations.
By the way, I'm not going to cover
factorizations here so
that's an entirely different topic and
they're not that hard actually to,
to work out how these factorizations go.
It's a whole world in itself.
But this just so you know at the highest
level.
We can't go into the details of
factorizations.
So.
Here's the most famous one.
Is LU factorization and
by the way it's completely equivalent to
gaussian elimination.
It says any nonsingular matrix you can
factor as PLU.
Where P is a permutation matrix, L is
lower triangular,
U is upper triangular and obviously L and
U have to have non-zeros on
their diagonals cause if there was zero on
the diagonal of L or U, what would happen?
Yeah.
It's non-invertible.
The determinant is zero and so you have no
right solving Ax equals b, okay?
So, okay.
So, and this factorization, we're not
going to go into it
although it is just Gaussian elimination,
the cost is order n cubed, FLOPs.
Right?
So, that, that's how that works.
Okay?
And so, here it is.
Here's how you solve a set of linear
equations by LU factorizations.
So, you're given A and B.
The first thing you do is you factor A as
PLU.
That's N cubed FLOPs.
You then, then how do you solve?
Well, you go backwards, right?
So, you solve PZ one equals B, that's like
zero flops or
whatever, I mean, whatever you like.
It's, you premuting the entries of B.
Right, then you do forward substitution
back substitution, and
you can see this is like two N squared.
Right.
And so, I mean the numbers don't really
matter here but
the point is n is typically big enough.
N would have to be tiny, before like 10 or
something, then all of this is off anyway.
But n would have to be, so if n is any
reasonable number 10, 100,
1000 or something like that, then the n
cubed thing is bigger, right?
And so that's the idea.
And so it's basically about n cubed,
right?
It's, it's, it's the, it's, it's the
complexity, okay?
So that, that, and that's LU
factorization.
The back solve, notice it's order n
squared.
So, in fact, you would say the following.
the, let's see, how shall I put it.
Okay, here's a good way to conceptualize
it.
One way to think of solving a x equals b
for
different right hand sides, is something
like this.
The first time you solve it, it costs you
n cubed.
Thereafter At, after you ca, you factor A
and
cash it, you get a discount by an or, by a
factor n.
Everybody got that?
Right?
So, so
the first one might take you half a second
and
then the next one is going to take you
submillisecond, right?
I mean, so these are actually very
important things to know about.
Okay.
now, sparse LU factorization.
This is quite interesting.
And I'm not going to get into the details,
but
this is actually very good stuff to know
about.
If any, if you have a sparse matrix A,
the most common factorization method is to
factor it into a product of four matrices.
And you know by the way they have other
names for
these you know p1 and p 2 were sometimes
called you know row and
column permutations or something but that
is what they do.
That is you factor it into a product of
four things a permination LUP okay.
Now the fact is mathematically you only
need
one of those permutations to ensure the
existence of a factorization.
Right.
That's the mathematically because it
follows from the previous one.
Right, the reason you'd use two and
reason you would use a permutation both on
the left and
on the right is that the L that's actually
happening here is this.
As P1 transpose A P2 transpose Right is L
U.
So what you're really doing is permuting
the rows and
columns of A, and then calling an
unpermuted L U factorization on it.
Okay?
Now, by the way,
if you choose P1 and P2 wrong, L U
factorization doesn't exist, right?
So let's assume you've chosen them
correctly and they work.
It turns out that A is sparse.
The sparsity pattern of l and u is,
depends on the permutations.
Okay so if you pick a good permutation l
and u are quite sparse.
And that, of course, is going to affect
your solve time.
Because, your what, your solve time.
We've already looked at that.
Back and forward substitutions.
Basically n and z.
On L, and then Z on U.
Alright.
That's the number of flops.
So the point is, if I pick 1 permutation
P1 and P2,
so that, L has a milion non zeroes and
I pick another one so that L has a hundred
million non zeroes.
Right.
It's not just a memory issue but
also a run time.
Everybody see this?
So okay, this is actually quite
fascinating It turns out that when
you do an LU factorization on a matrix,
right?
Then the permutation can have a huge
effect on the sparsity of the result.
How do you choose P1 and P2?
Well, you can ask lots of questions.
For example, obvious question would be,
how do you choose row and
column permutations of a sparse maker so
that it's, it's LU factorization has the
fewest numbers of non-zeros.
It's a totally natural question and it's
mp heart.
Okay?
So, fine.
So what do people do?
Well, it's, it means everything, these are
all heuristics.
Okay?
And, actually,
they're more than heuristics, right?
it's, they're even, they're very stringent
requirements, right?
Because what people do who worked on
sparse matrices is the following.
If you want to, so what happens is,
something like this.
Well, you choose these entries using
various methods, right?
One of the methods depends on the sparsity
pattern,
it also depends on the values of A, right?
As you're going along you might choose,
the P is actually built up while you're
doing the factorization.
Okay?
So that, that that's how this works.
And, and I'm not going to go into any
details, but that's sort of the idea.
And it's, it's worth knowing about this.
Okay.
And, what's the cost?
Well it's usually, way less than n cubed.
Right.
By the way,
if it gets even close to n cubed It means
you have implemented an extremely
inefficient method when you should have
just called a,a dense LU pack routine,
right, which would've blocked everything
nicely for you.
That's, that's all it means, right?
But, but this is a big deal.
So you know, if you're lucky this is
>> This is actually I'd, a,
a, a very big give, by the way, everyone
here is a beneficiary of this.
I can tell you that right now.
so, and the reason is very simple.
CVX, for example, calls SDPT3 or SEDUMI.
All of these things use sparse matrix
methods to actually do the heavy lifting.
That's if you profile any of these
solvers, that's all they're doing.
The only thing they're doing is solving
linear equations.
So, there's nothing else.
Linear, And they're literally solving a x
equals b.
Now a is symmetric, but that's another
story, it doesn't matter.
Same idea goes, right.
And they're all spa, and, and they're
exploiting sparsity very heavily.
Okay, now they, what's at,
there's a little, I mean it's a bit funny,
right, because.
You know, if someone comes along over your
shoulder,
when you're plot feeling with CVX, and
somebody says, what are you doing.
Well, I'm doing convex optimization, and
they go, well, you know,
how do you know it works, and you go,
that's the whole point.
It's just like, it's, it's tractable.
I mean, we can do that, I mean, you know,
had a whole course, and
that, that was the whole point.
There's other problems you can't solve,
but these you can really solve.
The, as a practicle matter the only reason
you can solve them, as a practicle matter,
is because the euristics of choosing the
permentations for
solving linear systems of equations are so
good.
Everybody got that?
Don't, but do not tell anyone outside this
class that.
Right?
This is a secret we keep together here.
So, if anyone asks you, what, why does
that work?
Is that heuristic?
You say absolutely not.
This is not a heuristic.
And in theory it's not, right.
If, the worse thing that can happen is
your permutation fails spectacularly and
you avert to n cubed.
That is not good.
[INAUDIBLE] 10,000 or 50,000.
So, but now you know.
This is why, roughly speaking, you can
solve equations.
10,000 variables, 100,000 variables, a
million variables.
Million by million.
You can, kind of, solve, sparse equations.
And, so, the correct way to say it is if
the gods, god or
gods, who control The [UNKNOWN]
of permutations used in sparse
factorization are smiling on you, and
that depends on the offerings you have
made to them likely.
If they are smiling on you then you can
solve equations that would just
otherwise be completely and totally out of
question, everybody got this right but
there are some sparsity [UNKNOWN] Where
you don't have to rely on
the gods of heuristic, sparse permutation
selection algorithms.
And we'll talk about some of, well I'll
tell you one right now.
If the matrix is banded, you don't need to
make any offerings at all.
That's, it's really going to work.
Always, m'kay.
But you know for general sparse matrices
this is not true, okay, so.
Now this is very good stuff to know about
even if you, if you're more interested in
sort of more theoretical stuff, this is
very good stuff to know about.
So now, well we're going to encounter
more,
I mean what we're going to encounter are
some things that are generally not
just square, but you actually have sine
structure.
There's the Cholesky factorization.
If you have a positive definite matrix,
A, then you can factor it as it LL
transfer \g, but it's not.
What it says is, it's an LU factorization,
with L = U.
Well kind of duh, or aesthetics tells you
that right.
because what's a matrix that's symmetric.
Well it's transposes the same, or you swap
rows and columns, the same thing.
So, of course, the U and the L, sh, that's
all this is, okay.
And L is lower triangular And
in fact, generally people require just to
normalize that.
That the entries are positive.
One very interesting fact about Cholesky
factorization, is a numerical one.
It actually is stable.
Again we're not really talking about that.
It means you do not have to permute, you,
you can say immediately, that if you
calculate that in double precision.
You aren't, you're not going to have any,
any trouble, right.
That your er, you can bind the error in L.
And stuff like that.
As a, as a practical matter, it just
works.
In this case, and the cost is 1/3 n cubed.
And, you know?
Again, the difference between 2/3 and
1/3 is, like, zippo in, in current things,
right?
Where cache, cache misses is way more
important than some factor of two.
But, you know?
You get the, rough.
[INAUDIBLE] , I mean, this, you save
because.
Well, you don't have to calculate
separately in an L and a U, right?
You're just calculating one L.
Okay.
So, how do you solve things by Cholesky
factorization.
By the way, this would come up in least
squares, right?
That's your most, that's your most basic
convex optimization problem,
least squares.
You can do it by Cholesky factorization.
So.
Here, you'd factor A, as l l transpose,
and you do forward and
backward substitution, and the cost is
about 1 3rd n, cubed.
Okay, so that's, that's the, that's the
idea, that's Cholesky factorization.
Now sparse Cholesky factorization.
It looks just like sparce LU, but there's
actually a very critical difference, and
I'm going to say what it is.
And you probably don't need to know it at
this level, but
these are good things to know about.
So here, here it is.
As before, there's P one and P 2, you do
pre- and post-multiply.
Or, if you like, you can say that what
you, another way to write this Is,
is to say just to think of it this way
first you permute A then call
a Cholesky factorization on their
perumuted version right so
that, that, that's a a good way to think
of it.
Oh and by the way.
Everybody has a different thing, you know.
Sometimes it's lower triangular, sometimes
it's upper triangular.
The permutation either goes like here, or
there.
So you always, anytime you actually look,
use something that does a factorization.
You have to look at what, exactly what
they mean by it.
And it'll probably be different from these
notes.
Right, so, but.
That's, this is too bad.
There's no standards.
Okay, now here you always have a Cholesky
factorization.
But the, the permutation can have a huge
effect on the sparsity of L,
and therefore on the memory required to
carry this out, and second, and of course,
it also has, since the number of nonzeros
in L is basically the flop count.
That's going to affect the run time.
Okay.
Now, unlike the sparse LU factorization
where you're actually choosing P1 and
P2 as you go, as you factor the matrix.
Right?
Because you actually looking at
entries and you want to, you don't,
want to avoid numbers.
They're too small.
If you wanted to, if you're going to
divide by something.
Here it turns out that P can actually be
chosen
entirely on the basis of the sparsity
pattern of A.
Okay?
So, in other words, all that mat-, you
take the sparsity pattern of A,
you don't even have to know what the
entries, the numbers are going to be,
Right, if you can make a graph out of it
that's a very common thing, and
then you chose an elimination ordering
right but you do this once right.
So, that says if you are going to do
something like solve ax equals b with
different values of A multiple times.
When A is sparse definite, you can
actually cash the permutation.
I don't know if you got that but this will
be,
this will, the usefulness will be clear in
about two weeks.
You can cash the factorization.
And that's the idea.
anyway, so the cost is usually you know,
way less than and and
all that kind of stuff.
So that's, that's how that works.
okay, another factorization we going to
see is the so
called LDL transpose factorization and
that's this if you
have a symmetric matrix not necessarily
not necessarily a positive definite
you can factor it as LDL transpose right
and D.
P is permutation matrix.
L is lower triangular unit, so you have l
i equal 0, d is block diagonal, and
it's either got 1 by 1 blocks or 2 by 2 to
blocks, right?
So and you get sort of the same thing,
right?
So this would be kind of one,
this would be one of the methods of, of
sort of choice.
Oh, and I think I, I can give you a rough
idea of what
>> What backslash doesn't MatLab.
I mean, just roughly.
It's something like this.
When you type A backslash B, I think it
looks at the diagonal of, of A.
And if they're positive, or it looks, it
quickly looks.
It compares some entries quickly to see
if,
if it's possible that A is positive
symmetric positive definite.
Right?
So, it guesses that.
Then, it attempts the Cholesky factor.
If it finds that it is, if it,
if there's some evidence that A is
symmetric, and positive definite, like,
for example, it has a negative on the
diagonal, it doesn't do this.
It's all over.
It's not positive definite.
So, it attempts to do a Choloesky
factorization because it's numerically
stable and fast.
Okay?
But, if it turns out A wasn't, then the
Cholesky fails.
Then, it falls back and does something
like an LU or something like that.
I mean this is roughly what it does.
Right?
So, okay.
And it won't a sparse factorization unless
A is like
explicitly stored flagged as sparse.
Okay.
Now we're going to talk about something.
It's about an elimination method, but it
actually ties to a whole bunch of stuff.
And it turns out it's actually kind of the
same as selecting the permutation, but
we'll get to that.
So what we'll do is let's just take x
equals b and block it.
So, all we're going to do is we're
going to,
we're going to write it as blocks.
We're going to partition x that'll
partition b,
and we're going to write it that way.
So, it's just two sets of equations.
It's a1 1x 1 plus a1 2x 2 equals b1,
and then a2 1x 1 plus a2 2x 2 equals b2,
right?
So that's, that's it.
On this block, you know.
And let's see what happens.
What you do is from the first equation,
basically, is a one one,
x one plus a one two, x two equals b one.
And what you do is assumingn a one one is
non singular, right?
You put this over there then premultiply
the a one one and that,
that says that you can write x one.
As a function of X2 and you get this,
okay.
And so the idea is now we're going to
eliminate X1 from the system of equations,
right.
So, all we do, is we plug this value of X1
into this, right.
By the way, this is, this is actually
just, sort of,
like you know, this, this substitution
stuff.
And with, but with matrices, blocks,
right?
So, what happens is, if you plug this
equation into that, right.
You get A 2 1 times this thing, plus A 2 2
times x 2 equals b 2.
And when the smoke clears, that's a set of
equations for x 2.
And you get.
This equation right here okay.
So this just you've just elim and
you would say things like you have
eliminated X1 okay.
This matrix you have seen before that's
the shirt compliment okay and
you've seen it in any legitimate class
you've taken.
Because a legitimate class uses linear
algebra, and then,
you can't use linear algebra and not see
that, right?
So you take probability class, that's
conditional, that's conditional, you know,
covariance or some, that's the conditional
variance, covariance matrix, right?
You take other things.
Take circuits, mechanics, anything,
physics.
This comes up.
Okay, so that's the sure compliment.
So what it says is that when you eleminate
variable, a block or variables, or
a block of variables from a set of linear
equations.
You're left with a set,
with a linear equation that involves the
sure compliment, okay?
So actually, that's, I mean that's good
thing to know about, okay.
So, by the way you would form this matrix,
you'd solve X2 and
then you would recover X1 using that
formula, okay.
And so, here's a completely generic,
completely generic algorithm for
solving this block equation.
And it says this It says, yeah I mean
you're going to form,
you're going to form this matrix.
That's the sure his thing compliment, it's
called S here.
Right, so you, you form this thing, a 1 1
inverse a 1 2.
Now, by the way, that can be formed lots
of different Wait oh, let me ask that.
How would you if there were no structure
in a11 and
a11 was let's say a 1000 by 1000, and
suppose a12 was 1000 by 10.
Please tell me how you would form a 11
inverse, a 12.
What would you do?
So A 1 1.
Thousand by thousand.
Inverse times, A 1 2 is a thousand by 10.
How do you, how do you calculate that
product?
It li-, it's a product.
How do you do it?
A 1 1 cash.
And do 10 back solves.
Done.
Perfect.
Okay?
So.
All right.
So, but, you just write,
people just write stuff like form A11
inverse A12.
Okay.
And assuming you know what you're doing.
so, you form this, your compliment.
Then you solve this, your compliment
equation, and
then, you use this equation to reconstruct
X1.
Okay?
So, that's the method.
All right?
And, you know let's, let's, let's figure
out how much it costs.
And the answer is, it's F plus N2S.
That's the cost of factoring A11.
And S is the solve step.
Right?
These are the back solves.
As you, as you said,
that there's one factorization and some
solves.
Step 2 cost this.
And what we're going to do here is
we're just going to assume on the second
step as dense.
I mean, because you could work it out,
when it's not Right and then the the the
last step
is a something that's again we're going to
just assume its dense generic nothing and
we'll just do we'll just solve that
equation and that's going to be a N,
N, N two cubed right so the total thing
looks something like this.
Now.
Here's what happens.
If, if you apply this method now, to a
matrix
that has no structure whatsoever, then f
equals this, and s equals that.
And you plug it into this formula, and you
get back, actually, exactly.
The fact you get, there's no savings what
so ever okay?
So that was a completely silly thing to
do.
I mean, it doesn't matter that's how you
do it right.
Actually, it's interesting because it
shows you,
it shows you what blocking is right?
because there is, this is blocking 2 by 2
now you can imagine what blocking 10 by
10 looks like, it's just this.
Okay, so that's it.
Here is where it's useful.
>> When A11, has structure, right?
So, the factor, with the factor cost and
the solve cost on A11 is low,
then, this delivers, this delivers big
savings.
Here's an example.
Suppose that A11 was diagonal.
Right?
That means the factor cost is zero and the
solve cost is n1.
That's just, just divide.
Right?
Then the number of flops is this, and this
is absolutely amazing, so
this is that if you see a set of linear
equations that look like this.
Right?
So, It looks like that.
I'm going to, I'm going to draw the,
non-zeroes.
Right?
Oh sometimes people call this a spy
diagram, I have absolutely no idea why,
but anyway, whatever.
I, it doesn't matter.
I'm just showing you the non-zeroes.
Okay?
Now there's many other ways to understand
this, and and I'll,
I'll show A, a couple and the once the way
they are purely mathematical you probably
have seen before, OK.
So and also introduces a very interesting
idea so you what that is.
So lets , lets takes this one suppose you
wanted to solve A plus BC and
the idea here is that B is like you know
it, its so this is low rank.
Looks like that.
And here's, and here's a.
And let's assume a has structure.
So let's make a banded.
You know?
That's, 'cuz it's pretty,
and it has structure.
So, there's your, your sparsity pattern.
That's a plus bc, okay?
It could be anything else.
It could be sparse.
It could be.
Forty eight, you know, DFT, it could be
anything, you know,
it could be something that you have a fast
transformer for.
It could be some wave lit thing or
something, I don't care, right?
And then so the people would call this is
like structured plus low rank.
That's what this is.
So it could be sparse plus low rank matrix
or something.
Okay.
Now the dif, the sparsity pattern of A
plus BC is generally full.
Severy, you know, cause, you take an
outer, you just take B and
C to be columns.
Or, you know, B is a column and C is a row
vector.
Then it's just an outer product, it sprays
entrys all over the place.
Right, so, so then, a generic, a generic
method there will be no sparsity, nothing.
So, how you can solve these is very
clever, and
in fact the first step, there's a name for
it.
It's actually called unelimination.
So elimination means you take your
variables and
you look at one block and you say,
I'm going to express that in terms of the
others and then get rid of it.
Unelimination means that you're going to
introduce a new, a new one.
So what you do is you look at (A + BC)x =
b, you write that as A + By.
>> Right?
Equals B.
Y is actually CX.
Everybody got that?
That's just, of course, they're the same
thing.
They're identical.
But, you rewrite these equations like
that.
Right?
So, there's, there's, and , and, here, so,
you've, i mean you've done unelimiation.
You've introduced new variables and new
equations.
Everybody got this?
And you see this.
Now, you're not trained yet but you will
be.
And it, once you're trained, what your
eye, what you're searching for
is the following: easily inverted matrices
on the diagonal.
And your eye should, once you're trained,
go immediately to that minus I.
You will go, it will go immediately there.
Because in the world of easily inverted
matrices, I is up there and
-I is up there.
Okay?
Everybody cool?
Alright, now.
I need, see, I just have this fantastic, I
just learned about block elimination.
There's a, I'm going to elimi- I eliminate
that block.
Now if you eliminate that block you're
eliminating y and where do you end up?
Right back here.
Everybody got it?
So, well duh, I mean you un eliminated and
then eliminated the thing you had just
introduced right?
OK.
Fine.
So the key, is to, is to control.
>> Your urge.
Primal matrix structure factorization
urge, to eliminate that minus I.
And instead, you take the system and you
eliminate A.
And, in fact, that's not a bad idea
because the assumption here is that A is
easy to invert.
Right?
So, A is 48 transform or
some wave lifting.
I don't know what it is.
It doesn't matter what it is.
Right?
So, that's what it is.
OK.
If you eliminate A, so, if you
uneliminate.
If you go from this.
To this, and then you eliminate a.
Not the minus i.
You get this equation.
And you will recognize that as the Schur
complement here, right?
It's like, you now, this thing minus that
times the inverse of that times that.
OK.
Or other way around.
Some, that's that's Schur complement.
OK?
And you get this.
Now, then you solve for ax, and you can,
once you get y, you get x, okay?
And you can actually write this out, just
purely mathematically, and
it comes out to be this.
A plus b, c inverse, is a inverse minus,
and then this big old thing over here.
Okay, it's a very thing, it's got all
sorts of names.
Matrix inversion lemma I think is a nice
one,
and you'll just do a quick example and
then, and then we'll quit for today.
So if A were diagonal and B and
C were debts then that's a beautiful
example, right?
So that's called a diagonal plus low rank
Matrix, right?
Perfect, perfect example of this
structure, right?
Then it says you can actually solve it in
here if you,
you do the dumb method it's like n cubed.
If you'd used this method which is an
un-elimination and
an elimination it actually ends up it goes
from cubic in n to linear in n.
OK?
So my claim is, you just,
these are not small differences, right,
these are not theoretical things, right?
The difference between knowing this and
not knowing it means you can look at
something, and it could be a million by
million set of equations.
But if it's diagonal plus low right, now
you know.
I can solve that in probably in like
sub-millisecond.
But you have to know what you're doing.