What I want to do is just talk, a little
bit, very briefly about sort of
the main ideas of the course and just a
couple of other things.
So, some of this is kind of obvious but
it's probably worth saying now.
So when we talk about modeling, that's
kind of the focus of the course is on,
is on, is on modeling.
Right?
Yeah it is, look.
A lot of problems in things like
engineering design, statistics,
machine learning economics.
Management, you know, goes on in signal
processing.
You know?
All of these kinds of things.
You can express them as mathematical
optimization problems, right?
So, I mean, this is kind of obvious,
right?
But, actually, you'd be shocked at how few
people, make it over that step.
And this business of yeah I mean real
problems are really multi objective but
once you know about optimization, it's not
a big deal to, to look at, you know,
to have something, be a constrain or a
trade off between three things or
something like that I mean.
So, that's fine.
Now, we focus on a canonical form, where
we identify one objective as
infinitely soft and all others as
infinitely hard.
I mean, that's, that's fine, but
everyone should know that real problems,
there's a trade off among some of them.
I mean, some are really non-negotiable,
right?
You know, like covariances should
definitely be positive semi-definite,
for example, right?
Powers?
Definitely should be bigger and equal to
0.
These are non negotiable, but a lot of the
others are.
Are, are, are.
Not, and the main point is something like
this,
that roughly speaking, the tractable
problems are the ones that are convex.
And, you know, that's kind of rough.
And, I mean you could even go more than,
you could make the radical assertion is
that, that's not a rough statement.
That's just true and the or if you wanted
to push the radical statement I,
I'm not sure I believe the radical
statement and
I'm not sure if it has any implications
even if you did.
So I'm not sure it matters.
You would argue that all the polynomially
type,
that all the polynomial time solvable
prob, discreet problems they all work
because say, some convex relaxation
actually has zero duality gap, right.
So you'd look at all this or, you know,
minimum you know,
find the shortest path between two points
in a weighted graph.
Right?
Okay.
Well,
you would say the convex relaxation of
that has zero duality gap.
Right?
I mean that's a bit silly because it,
then you ask the question, well great,
now that I know this, should I be solving,
you know, minimum distance and
graph, you know, shortest path problems
that way and the answer is no.
Go back and use the same method you were
using before.
So it doesn't really say anything.
The other source of non trivial problems
that would appear to be non convex.
And yet you can solve.
And they are solved all the time, are
obvious.
They are singular values, eigenvalues,
PCA.
There are obvious, right?
It turns out there, there is also a kind
of a weird connection to convexity.
For those problems.
The dual, actually is the semi-definite
product, problem, semi-definite program.
And it has zero duality gap.
There's zero duality gap for those, right?
So you could even argue.
I mean, that's a bit weird and extreme, to
walk up to someone, and say,
what are you doing in PCA or something.
And you say, how do you know it works?
And you go, well.
I mean, you know?
I'm, sure I'm getting the best whatever
rank 12 fit, or something like that.
By the way, that's not the one we just
looked at, the example, right?
Sure, I'm getting, how do you know, well
it's the global solution and so
on, it really doesn't help to say, oh I
can tell you why.
It's because of some result in algebraic
geometry that the semi
definite programming dual of your PCA
problem, has zero duality gap.
That doesn't seem to me to be
illuminating.
It is true.
But it's not, doesn't seem to me to be
illuminating.
Okay, so, alright.
Now if you have a non convex problem, in
general.
You have [INAUDIBLE] , you have two
choices.
And these are the two extremes.
Actually, there's everything in between.
And here they are.
One is to give up on, is to actually
replace solution with solution.
And then a little asterisk, and then a
footnote that says.
Maybe, right?
Or not really, right?
And it's just you're looking for a local
solution, and this is,
these are extremely useful with lots of
cases where this is very useful.
I mean engineering design, something like
that.
You really don't care if that is the,
is the lowest power design that meets all
your specification.
Right?
If it's, if it's low enough power, or
it's a 20% improvement over what you had
ten days ago, that's fantastic!
And you're, and you don't sit around and
worry about whether it's the global
solution.
Okay, so, very useful.
And these all have the same running time
as convex problems, right?
Now, at the other extreme, you have global
optimization.
And these will have exponential worse care
run time.
By the way, in a lot of practical cases,
they don't have exponential I mean, well,
I don't know what means.
Sorry.
In a lot of practical instances you can
actually solve these to completion, and
it's not so bad.
Right?
So.
And in fact what really happens is
anywhere where people actually do this,
they have a timeout and they run something
for a couple of minutes and they quit.
And you're really getting something in
between.
So.
Oh, one thing that's interesting is and
this is something that has come up you
know, in the last, like 20, 25 years.
It's been a slow thing if you accept
linear programming,
right, possibly quadratic programming
then.
You know, it was, it's, what's, this, it's
just been the last 25 years,
people have discovered a lot of problems
that actually are convex.
Or can be transformed to be convex, right?
And that, this was not, I mean, it's not
obvious.
Although I have some advice to give you.
So this is serious advice now.
So,.
Long time ago, I use to give a talk on, on
control, and I would say,
look, here are some problems in control
that you can reduce to convex problems.
And I'd show one, and another, and
everything.
I thought, well, it would be good, I
should show one that cannot be.
So, I showed one that I thought could not
be.
I said, here's one, and actually,
fortunately in the slides it said that
probably cannot be reduced to a con.
And it was something involving, you know,
finding a Lyapunov function and
the state feedback gain at the same time.
And I, I gave even a very good argument
for it, I said look they get
multiplied together and that's never good
for convexity, we know that, right.
I mean so they just, it wasn't looking
good.
Everybody following this?
And this is just in the spirit of, I just
showed you five things that can be
reduced to convex problems, I should show
one that cannot.
Okay.
So I gave the talk ten, fifteen times.
After the fifteenth time, somebody, Eddy
Packard at Berkley comes up to
me quietly and he goes, can I show you
something?
And I said, oh sure.
And he takes out a piece of paper and
he fills like about four lines at the top
of it.
And guess what?
The problem I had just, not just then but
15 earlier times, to large audiences, said
was non convex.
He did some sick change of variables,
right,
that no normal person should ever have
thought of.
[LAUGH] But there it was, guess what, it
was convex, it was four lines, right.
And then I, so, I, I, you know, I started
getting, you know, hyperventilating and
like, so I looked, I quickly looked back
at my slides.
And, sure enough, I was so lucky.
The, the top of it said a problem that
probably cannot be,
cannot be solved using convex
optimization.
And then I even had a footnote that said,
you know, as far as I know.
So, so anyway.
So, okay, so let me tell you what the
moral of that story is.
If you're, you know,
if you're with friends, it's informal, say
whatever you like.
Okay?
But, if you're out in some other place,
you should not,
don't look at something and say here are
the things that seem to be reasonable for
you to say in a semi-public setting.
Here are the things you can say.
You can say.
That problem is convex or
can be transformed or solved or, by convex
optimization.
That's okay, but I mean, if you know it's
true.
The second thing you can, if that problem
has not been shown to be mp hard,
you should be quite, quiet in, in, in
public or even semi public.
Kay?
So, that's my advice because I've been
I've been a victim of this.
So, alright.
Everybody got this?
So, okay.
Alright, so, what are the theoretical
consequences of convexity.
Well, you know, the simplest one is like,
you know,
if you have a local optimum, it's global,
right?
And so that's, and but by the way, that's
a very,
shallow idea of why this all works because
a lot, you explain this to someone,
a lot of people go, oh yeah, yeah, sure,
that makes total sense sure.
It turns out that's not right, for
example,
their optimization problems where.
All local optima are global and they are
hard.
Right.
So, this is not quite fair.
This is okay if it's just you know,
if you want to give a 20 second version of
why this.
This is why.
By the way local optima global,
that goes back to something very early on
in the class.
One interesting question is.
How can you conclude that from convexity,
right, and
the answer is really simple, in what
convexity allows you to do,
is it allows you to go from a local
statement to a global one, right.
If I know the gradient of a function at a
point,
I can produce a global lower bound, that.
If someone says, oh, wait a minute.
How could you possibly know that, that's
the best you could do?
That's ridiculous.
R100 is a big place.
R1000 is a lot bigger.
And the, that's the answer.
And you say, the answer is because of the
mathematical properties of
the functions involved, I can extrapolate
from here.
And know something globally about it.
I mean, then you get duality and all and
it gets more complicated but
that's basically where it comes from.
So there's an extensive duality theory.
What is that?
Well, lots of ways to think of it.
One way is to say,
it's just a very systematic way to derive
lower bounds on optimal value.
That's what it is right, by the way that
alone is a very good met, you know,
you have a problem.
And now you say well, I mean if you can't
solve it or
something like that even if, especially if
it's not convexed,
it's even interesting, then you say, here
are some lower bounds.
If you come up with things that satisfy
these and
that should be something you should be
able to do then you'd say,
then this is a lower bound, right that's
actually very valuable often.
and, in the case of convex,
you get necessary insufficient conditions
for optimality.
And you get cool things like certificates
of infeasibility and math,
and theorem of alternatives for
inequalities.
Right?
And for a set.
That, that's also, that, that's the basis
of lots of things like, for
example, economics.
Right?
Just to name one.
So, because everything's based on
absence of arbitrage.
Right?
So, it's lots of other things like that.
And of course as a practical matter you
get something unbelievably useful which is
sensitivity analysis.
Right?
So, when you solve a problem for
free you get to find out how sensitive is
that problem?
How sensitive is the optimal way of that
solution to any change in parameters.
Right?
If you're
doing engineering design that's
unbelievably useful.
Because it tells you how much, for
example that power constraint is really
limiting you.
Or your phase margin constraint.
This will tell you exactly.
I mean, at least in a protobational sense,
it'll tell you how much that is costing
you.
Right?
In statistics, in fitting, this is also
unbelievably useful right?
Because you say, well I'm assuming my
parameters are non negative.
Why?
Because I think that the greater this
feature is.
I have prior knowledge saying that it must
be the case that the probability of
this classifier being one, should
increase, right.
That's a non negativity.
If some of those things turn out to be
zero,
with a large lagrange multiplier, that's
telling you something.
That's basically saying, guess what, if I,
if I could actually take that coefficient
negative.
I could get a way, I could really reduce
the the negative log likelihood.
Everybody see what I'm saying?
So, okay.
And you have solution methods that have
polynomial worst-case complexity theory.
That's with self-concordance and, and it
kind of varies, as you know,
between sort of the practical and the
theoretical analysis.
Okay.
Now, the practical consequences are
[COUGH] for medium scale problems,
you can solve a problem like 20 to 80
steps, roughly.
Right?
Each of
those steps is basically least squares
problem of the same size.
Right?
So, if you like, it's hilarious.
We've come all the way back to 1802 or
whatever it is and someone says, what are
you doing?
I'm solving a problem.
How are you doing it, least squares?
And you say, well actually 20 or 30.
I'm doing solving 30 of these squares
problems.
Right?
But in this case,
it's a, it's a different thing.
Instead of like, tweaking parameters and
tuning stuff in an ad hoc way, you
actually say what you want.
Like I want this thing to be positive.
I want this thing to be in that range.
And that tweaking of parameters is done in
a very sophisticated way.
Okay.
So I'll, I'll move on.
I should say that for people solving, you
know, much larger problems, and that's
basically anyone in machine learning,
interior point methods are, are not used.
They are, these are small things and, you
know, there's a whole
world of problems that, methods that can
be used in, in those regimes.
And, there, there's actually several
places where you can learn about that.
So.
Okay.
So let me say a little bit about you know,
how do you use it.
And this is just my idea and
it diff, actually it differs markedly from
some other people who actually.
Whose opinions I, very much respect, I'll
say a little bit what that is in a minute.
So, here's one idea, and it's, you know,
has to do with the kind of problems I
would look at, something like that.
But it goes like this.
The idea is you should use rapid
prototypes in
approximate modelling, right.
You start with simple models, small
problem instances and
some inefficient solution method.
And you see.
If it's promising.
If it's not promising, then there's no
need for
you to worry about how to scale it.
I mean, that's actually in a way, that's a
good, that's a good outcome.
Right?
Because you don't have
to worry about scaling it.
You can always do things like work out and
simplify and
interpret the optimality conditions and,
and,
and give an interpretation of the dual.
That's always interesting.
At the least.
And sometimes even useful.
Another thing although we didn't, we
talked only a little bit about it.
We had a few problems involving integer,
variables and things like that and
there were hints of this.
But my feeling is you should first learn
convex optimization.
Once you're fully certified in convex
optimization which you
will all be by the end of this coming
weekend.
But once you're fully certified.
Then it's okay.
Then you get more relaxed about it, and in
fact you can solve lot,
there's lots of non convex problems.
You can, you can solve extremely
effectively knowing these tools so
I should say a little bit about this.
So, this is actually quite, this idea, if
you start with small simple models and
then ramp up, that's very different than
for example, what people do with Google.
Right?
So, there,
they have this big deal which is
youprototype@scale.
You don't write some little, tiny thing
and, you know,
on your laptop or something.
It's like the first thing you write.
Runs on a data center.
Okay, and the, and the argument for that
and I think it's actually correct is a lot
of things they're looking for don't emerge
until you get to scale, right?
And in that case of course it's completely
correct.
You don't sit around and type something
into CVX and say, oh hey look at this, and
then say, oh now all I have to do is map
it to I mean not to mention, Matlab and
CBX are not real things.
But but even the analog of that, so, so
there, that makes perfect sense.
And I think that's just a different set of
applications and stuff like that.
And I respect that as well.
But just so you know, that this seems very
obvious, but
there's plenty of people who completely
reject it, and I think.
For what they want to do.
Completely correctly.
So.
Okay.
So I'll say a little bit about a few
things and then we'll I'll just wrap up.
so, things we didn't' cover are, you know,
methods for large scale problems.
Right?
And there are tons of these.
These will be covered in EE364B.
Related to that is, is, is a whole,
there's a whole set of mathematics we did
not cover, which is sub gradient analysis
and, and, and a bunch of convex analysis.
And these are, these are related.
Actually these are all related and
in fact so is this distributed convex
optimization, right, so, how do
you solve these problems on you know,
distributed machines and things like that?