So now we'll move on to another section.
It's going to be a whirlwind tour of some
interesting problems in
statistical estimation.
As with these other lectures, there's
actually much more in the book.
We expect you to read all of it.
Skim it all.
Homework will cover other things.
But we'll look at [COUGH] some of the big,
big picture questions here, and
we'll look at some interesting examples.
So we'll start with the idea of of
parametric distribution estimation.
So, and I mean this is at the absolute
core of statistics.
so, with, so, so if you have, I mean, well
there's several.
We won't look at the non-parametric case,
we'll look at the parametric case.
The, the parametric case is this, is that
you have a,
you have a observed a variable.
An outcome, of a random variable.
But it came, you don't know which
distribution it came from, and
you have a parameterized set of
distributions.
So this is kind of the basic starting
point in standard,
classical frequentist statistics.
So, this is the idea.
So, you have a parameterized family of
distributions and
it's paramaterized well the parameter
we'll call x, okay?
So, yeah ,this notation does not exactly
conform to standard statistics notation.
I guess it'll be theta or something like
this, right?
But that's fine, okay.
Now, an absolutely standard method for
estimating which distribution generated
the actual observed outcome y.
Is maximum likelihood estimation, and what
that says is,
you take, you take your observation,
that's y.
You plug this into the density, it
doesn't, I mean it can also be,a,
a discrete probability but density,
whatever you like, right, here.
And you consider this function as a
function of the parameter, the just,
that parameterizes the family of
distribution, right?
And that, that's called the likelihood
function.
And in fact, we'll take,
usually people take a log it doesn't
matter if you're maximizing.
And so, if you choose x by solving this
problem,
that's maximum likelihood estimation,
right?
So, and if you take a statistics course
you'll hear all about why this is
a good idea, and, you know, in some cases
asymptotically optimal, and
all that kind of stuff.
so, this is, l of x, that's going to be
the log likelihood function, and
you can add constraints on, on that.
And a lot of times, they're implicit, you
know, for example x,
the parameter might include something like
a covariance matrix, right?
Because your, your, for example, your
family might be Gaussians or
something like that.
And so the mean and covariance might be
the parameter that, that characterizes it.
And there of course, the parameter that
corresponds to the covariance obviously
has to be positive definite, right?
So these could, and these could be then
what you do is,
that's, that's the domain of the
likelihood function.
And you would simply make some, one,
one simple way is to say that this is
zero, there.
Because then log of it is minus infinity,
right?
So, and that's infinitely bad if you're
maximizing, right, so that's one.
Okay, now, the maximum likelihood
estimation problem, that's convex.
If the log likelihood is concave.
That, but this is, by the way this is
different from a log con,
log concave distribution which we've
looked at before.
This is, this is
log concave in the parameters that
describe the family of distributions.
Now if you know about exponential
families, then these two coincide.
Because it's actually only an inner,
they're both,
involve in an exponent of an inner
product, and then a normalizing constant.
So if, if you know what I'm talking about
fine,
if you don't, don't worry about it, okay?
But it's a different concept, the concept
here is, is the log likelihood function
concave, in the parameters that describe
the distribution.
Actually something very interesting's
going to happen,
in a lot of cases you'll have the, you'll,
you'll sort of have what you think are the
natural parameters for distribution.
And sure enough, it will be log concave in
those perameters.
We're going to see examples very shortly,
right?
But actually, in other cases, something
really cool is going to happen.
You'll look at the, the log likelihood
function,
as a function of what you though were the
natural perameters.
And guess what, it won't be concave, it
just won't be.
Here's an example.
Let's estimate the mean and covariance of
a Gaussian, that generated, a sample.
What could be simpler, 'kay?
Well does that log likelihood function in
sigma, and mu, it's not concave.
But it's going to turn out, you just do a
change of variables, and it will be.
Now, if you, have had, you know, enough
machine learning and statistics You'll
understand that the correct, it, it will
not be a shock to you.
That the correct parameters there are like
sigma inverse, and sigma inverse mu, okay?
These are actually more natural, right?
Than sigma, and mu, and
again, I'm, I'm, this is a bit more
advanced than I want to be at this point.
But I just, just to mention to those
people who know about those things, right?
And it turns out those are precisely the
parameters in an, in an exponential model.
So, okay.
Okay, so, oh and I should say that all of
this material, I, I,
you know, your, our goal here is just to
go over some interesting things.
If you've never seen this stuff before,
some of this stuff we're going to be
talking about is going to be super simple
and completely accessable.
But if you've had you know, some PhD level
courses in statistics or
machine learning, then there'll be a
little bit added stuff.
And I'm going to mention of that stuff
like I just did,
some of the more advanced stuff for fun.
Okay, so let's start with a very simple
setup.
Let's do linear measurement models.
So here x is a vector of unknown
parameters and
we have linear measurements.
So, we have yi, is a, its a scalar, its a
linear function of x plus a noise, right?
And so and by the way this is a good point
to stop and
talk about sort of just, I mean its, it
doesn't make any difference at all.
But sort of the philosophical way you
would regard the set up, right?
So if you are in something like signal
processing or something like that you
would say, this says, I mean your view of
the world is you know.
This gives you the ideal measurement if
your measurements were perfect.
They're not perfect and vi is sort of like
an added noise, right?
So this is your corrupted or real or
whatever you like to call it measurement,
okay?
And that would be the view from someone
who does signal processing or
something like that, right?
If you were to, if you were to do
something like get a perfect sensor, and
run this experiment at like you know, 0 or
0.01 degree Kelvin, right?
So there's no thermal noise or whatever
else that comes from.
Then in fact, you get yi equals ai
transposed x, right?
You don't, since you don't do those
things, vi is a noise, right?
So a statistician would say the following.
They would look at that and
they would say, x is a y comes from a
distribution, right?
It's a distribution, because that's a
random variable right there, the vi,
those are random variables.
They'd say so y comes from a distribution
and you'd say well what distribution does
it come from, and the answer is well it
depends on what x is.
So, x is here is a parameter that descri,
that tells you which distribution
generated y, right?
So I dunno if this is making, at the end
of the day,
you end up doing the same things with
this.
But it is actually just interesting to sit
for a minute and
think about the different views of what y
equals ax plus v can mean.
Okay, so, alright, so,
there's nothing deep in this, I'm just
saying these are the two views.
Okay, now, what you, what you do here is,
is this is y has and
I am going to assume that the vi or rid
here with some density p of z.
If you, if you if x has the value of x or
if the parameter has the value of x
then the distribution the density of y is
this, right?
Its the product because they are
independent and, and
yi minus ai transpose x, is, well that's
exactly vi, right?
So, and then, that, these, that, that's
the value that vi had, and
you simply take the product of the, of the
densities.
Because it's independent, to get the, the
density of of, of y, the vector, right?
So that's, that's the idea, by the way,
other people would call, something like
this, the residual.
And the residual here, is in fact nothing
but the noise, right?
So that's another way to, to, to think of
to think of this.
Okay, so the maximum likelihood solution
says,
here if you want to estimate x by maximum
likelihood.
What you do, is we'll form, the, we'll
max,
we'll maximize the log of this product,
but that's the sum right?
And this tells, gives you a hint as to why
the log is going to come up often, right?
So, you maximize the sum of the log of the
density of the residual, okay?
Now, by the way, if the residuals are,
have a density that, that is sort of
centered around zero, right?
And, and it'd be kind of, if they don't by
the way that means that it's sort of
a known offset and it's a bit silly,
right?
But if, if they do what that says is,
you know, these are functions that are
kind of centered.
This function is sort of centered around
zero and then it kind of goes off, right?
It, it's a concave function that tails off
after that.
That's actually quite interesting because
this is, this is actually a penalty.
This is penalty approximation, right?
Is exactly minimizing a sum, of a
function, of,
which which we previously called
penalties.
It's a penalty approximation method, but
here the penalty is specifically,
the negative log likelihood, if you
convert this to a minimization problem.
Already got this?
So, so in other words where you might just
say that's the penalty.
And then give a story about your penalty
function in terms of how much it irritates
you to have a big residual, small
residual, you know medium size residual.
All of this kind of stuff, negative,
positive residual that would be
your discussion of why you are using a
certain penalty.
It says that all of that can be transposed
perfectly to a statistics framework and
there instead of saying something like, it
irritates me to
have a positive residual is more
irritating than a negative residual.
What you're really saying is something
about the distribution,
the density of a noise, okay?
So, let's look at some examples.
Here's one, suppose these noises are
Gaussian.
Well then, if I take the negative log
likelihood, I get this, right?
So that, that, that, sorry that's the log
likelihood.
And it's this, that's a constant, and when
I'm maximizing over x, it doesn't matter.
Here, this constant's totally irrelevant.
And I'm maximizing this thing, well
there's a negative sign there, so
I can just minimize this thing, that
doesn't matter.
That, because it's a positive constant.
And so I minimize, hey, that's just least
squares, okay?
So, now you know, least squares is
nothing, but it is exactly maximum
likelihood estimation under the assumption
that the noises are Gaussian.
If you say, you have a square, and you say
what does that mean,
you say well it means if a residual is
small, I mean that's fine with me.
Because it's sort of small squared, but if
it's big that's not so good.
What this says is,
that corresponds exactly to a statistical
model, with Gaussian noise.
Because if you have Gaussian noise, and
you say well, if something's less than
like one sigma or
something, you'd say, fine, okay, nope,
that's, that's entirely plausible, right?
Whereas if something were like six sigma
or eight sigma, you'd look at that and
you'd say, hmm, that's, that's I mean, I
can't say it's impossible.
But it seems very strange, that, that my
fit here, or my estimation, is telling me
that the parameter, that what I've
observed was an eight sima event.
Everybody see what I'm saying here?
So, okay, let's look at Laplacian noise.
Now that's noise with a density that is a
double-sided exponential like that.
And it's actually a little bit interesting
to look at that distribution.
Compared to a Gaussian, what can you say
about the tails of
a Laplacian distribution compared to
Gaussian?
Much heavier, right?
Because this is like, e to the minus you
know, z squared, this is e to the minus z.
Okay, so it's way bigger tails.
What that says is that the likelihood of a
big outlier is,
well I mean it's going down, right?
It's e to the minus z.
But it's way bigger than for a Gaussian,
everybody following this?
And then, this is a bit of a weird thing
here, right?
This, you have that point there.
And it even says that something like this,
I mean that, that's going to tell you,
that, the probability, of having, of being
a little bit off.
Actually is substantially reduced from
being right at zero.
Everybody, and
that, that's comes now just from
probability from that, kink, right there.
Okay, so, this turns into, guess what, L1.
And it makes perfect sense.
Because now if you look at L1 you get both
of those things about what happends for
large residuals and small residuals.
For large residuals L1 charges you
linearly,
where as least squares charges you
quadratically.
So, it's not like you like, it's not like
you expect to have large residuals but
you don't go nuts as if it were quadratic
or worse, right?
And, at the, then you focus on small
things, small residuals, and
this says, it actually keeps up the, it,
it keeps up the incentive to drive a
residual to zero, right?
And you can see that exactly here, right?
So, so it's actually kind of interesting
that both,
both of these could be it can be, you can
interpret both.
But as from an intuitive description of a
penalty function, abstract penalty
function or from the probability, the
implied probably distribution of the resi,
of, of, of the noise in the additive noise
model.
Let's do Uniform noise, right?
Well, if you have Uniform noise then the
log likelihood function is well, it's,
it's actually just a constant.
And if basically it's constant, doesn't
matter what constant it is,
actually provided you are consistent with
with the measurement, right?
And so, there, you simply solve a
feasibility problem and, and
their multiple maximum likelihood
solutions and
you simply choose one that satisfies this,
this condition.
And all of those are maximum likelihood
estimates, right?
By the way, there's statistical properties
where maximum likelihood has been used for
maybe like a 100 years or something like
that now.
Is, most of that theory assumes things
like, that this log likelihood function
has a, a unique maximum, or something like
that, roughly.
Right, so, and that's not the case here.
Okay, oh, let's, let me mention just one
other thing.
So here what this says is that, you can
actually go backwards,
you can start from probability
distribution and find the penalty.
Because you just take the negative log of
the distribution.
But you can also go backwards, right?
So for example if, if you decided,
if you discussed with someone in some
fitting problem what they want, and
it's determined that what they want is
something that looks like this.
You know, that's quadratic and then this
rises steeply.
You know, I don't know how this would come
up but it would.
You'd talk, you'd talk to them, you'd say
what do you feel about under fitting?
And they'd say oh that, that's, that's
bad.
That is not good Right?
And you'd say, how about if you underfit
just a little bit?
No, that's, that's, that is not good.
And they'd say, but what about if you
underfit a lot?
And you'd say look, because the data's got
weird outliers and stuff like that, if
there has to be, if I have to underfit on
a couple of my, my points, it, so be it.
I don't want to go nuts over it, 'kay?
And that discussion, generates that.
And then you'd say, what if you over fit
and you say,
well the fact is if you over fit a little
bi, it doesn't make any difference at all.
And you'd say, well what about over
fitting more, and
then they would say well, I don't know.
So anyway, anyway, doesn't matter.
You end up with a story like this, right?
We all know this now.
You can translate a little of the story
and
description into this, okay, what this
says is the following.
It says, then if a statistician walks into
the room, and you say what are you doing?
And they don't want to hear a story about
your feelings about, overfitting and
underfitting and things like, they don't
want to hear that.
So, what you say to them is,
you say, oh excuse me, I'm doing maximum
likelihood estimation, right?
This implies a distribution, and the
distribution is very simple.
It's e to the minus this, of course you
have to normalize it but that's it.
So you'd say to them, you say I'm doing
maximum likeliest estimation.
And for this problem, we can even say what
it is.
How would you describe this distribution?
Somebody describe it to me, I mean in
words.
So it's some weird Frankenstein
distribution on the left.
It's got some weird exponential, right?
On the right, it's Gaussian.
And in the middle it's got some uniform
phase.
Now they would think you were weird.
But you'd, then you'd turn to the
statistician, and say, no, no, no, we've
been, we've been doing this for years, and
we know, this, this, it looks like this.
Okay, everybody, everybody got this?
So the, it's actually very interesting
that you can justify these from
different points of view.
And you get, you end up with the same
conclusion.
Okay, so, alright, now these things here,
by the way,
are things that are kind of obvious.
These are things we talked about in
approximation.
Linear approximation, they're kind of, in
some ways they are penalty problems with
an affine function, you know, ax minus b
or something like that.
I mean that's what this is, but actually
what's interesting is,
in maximum likelihood, you end up with all
sorts of interesting things.
Where you do not end up with a, an affine
function, a norm, or
a penalty function of an affine function.
And so these are actually quite
interesting, so
we'll look at a couple of these.
So, first is logistic regression.
So the I, so this is a distribution
actually on, so
the outcomes are zero, one, Boolean
outcomes.
And the probability, that you get a one is
the logistic function.
So it's, it's e to the a transpose u plus
b divided by one plus a transpose u
plus b.
And the probability that y equals 0 is 1
minus this, right?
Which in, of course, is one over one plus
e to the, a transpose u plus b, okay?
So that's the idea.
Now here, the idea is that u, are here.
These are observable explanatory
variables, right?
So I mean, I can tell you all sorts of
things about them, this would be,
let's say a patient made it to a hospital
eventually develops sepsis.
That, that's what we're looking at, okay?
So, and then you, here would be all sorts
of medically relevant variables, right?
Could, could be basic that you know also
to basic things were is
scores given to them.
Various anyway, it doesn't,
doesn't matter that's the whole bunch of
things like that.
By the way somebody's could be Boolean to,
that would be very often a case, right?
So, it be so called categorical variables,
right?
And so model like this and this model is
instantiated by fixing A and B
then gives you a model of the probability
someone developing Sepsis, right?
When they're admitted to the hospital,
right?
So that, because you just simply take
their, their u, you evaluate this
function, and, if it is 0.05, that's good,
and if it's 0.87, that's not good, okay?
So that's the idea.
All right, so the estimation problem is to
estimate a, these parameters a and
b from observations, right?
So that's, that's, that would be your,
that's what we're going to do.
So we're going to work out the log
likelihood function.
and, and then we going to maximize it,
right and it,
I guess it wouldn't be in this class if it
didn't turn out to be concave.
So, lets, okay, so lets take a look at
that so what we'll do is so
you, you've been given a bunch of
observations.
And basically what these are, these are
previous patients, right?
Could be from the last year, from the
region, doesn't matter, so
you just get a whole bunch of data, okay?
And the y's are, are just zero one, right?
So I guess you, you'd call these maybe
labels in, in machine learning.
Alright, so what does, we'll just make it
simple and reorder them, so
that all the ones that actually develop
sepsis are first.
That's k of them, and all the rest did
not, right?
Just for simplicity.
Then, the log likelihood function well its
very simple its simply the, you,
you take this for the, over the ones were
y was one.
So that's, that's, that's these terms,
right?
And then for, for
the case were y was zero that's one minus
this which is exactly that.
And so that, that's the log likelihood
function and this is a function of a and
b, okay?
Well, if you worked what this is well you
can see all sorts of bits.
This is log of the probability of x.
But that's just this thing, right?
And then you get minus, and then here,
there's this thing on the bottom, you
just, you sum over, over the all of it.
That's log sum x, but we all know, we all
recognize log sum x is convex.
And so, now we do this in, in discipline
convex programming or CVX style.
We just walk from inside of the Expression
Tree out, and
you say that's affine of, by the way you
don't then say x is convex.
That would be a false move.
You recognize log of one plus x as log of
e to the zero plus e to the a transpose u
plus bi.
And you say log sum x is convex, log sum x
of affine is convex,
sum convex minus concave, done.
Everybody got this?
Okay, so what this says is if we have a
bunch of data,
you simply maximize this function here,
and that will give you a and b.
That'll give you parameters a and b and
now you have a model.
You have a model that will predict predict
probabilities for new and
unseen values of new instances, right?
That's the idea, so, this is of course
extremely widely used.
And depending on your background and I can
speak for my own.
So if your background is you know,
from a sort of traditional EE type things
with signal processing.
You probably won't have seen this which is
sort of a pity, right?
You've seen a lot of stuff involving
linear things and stuff like that, but
you probably won't have seen this.
So, okay, so, here is an example, but
this is an example where you hardly need
anything fancy, right?
But, just so we can draw it.
So, the example here as n equals one,
is one explanatory feature, it's kind of
dumb, that's u, that's here.
And variance between zero and 10 and
what, what are plotted here are bunch of
samples, right?
And so, ignore this curve for
the moment, we just take a look at it, we
would say things like this.
Look, it's kind of, I mean, you don't need
anything fancy for u equals one.
You look at this and you say, yeah, look,
I mean if, if u is like, two or,
I don't know, two or three, below three.
It's quite likely, but
not, it's quite likely that the, that the
outcome y will be zero.
It's, but it is not one, because look at
this guy up here.
Okay, sorry, it's not probability, it's
not,
the probability that your zero is not one,
right?
Because there are exceptions.
On the other hand, if you say, if u is
bigger than about six,
it's, it's quite likely, that the outcome
is going to be one.
But, it is absolutely not certain, because
look at that, okay?
So what this shows here is the logistic
fit, right?
And so, and it, I mean it certainly seems
about right and it has all the weight of
statistics behind it, so it can be
justified at great length.
And, and so the use of this would go
something like this,
the new sample will come along and you
would be too.
And you would say well I think the
probability is about 8%.
That it's one, right?
U comes along, it's eight and you'd say
its about 94%.
Now, and u would come along and it's five
and you'd say I don't know.
Okay?
[BLANK_AUDIO].
So, we'll move to a completely different
thing.
Which is this hypothesis testing.
Actually these are all related.
Because in fact maximum likelihood
estimation, with,
parameter that is continuous, is something
like hypothesis testing, right?
Because you're sort of, you're testing one
value of x versus another.
And in fact, we're going to see that
maximum likelihood is basically, it, it,
it's the thing that would win in a binary
hypothesis,
hypothesis test against any other value.
But okay, so
here it is, this is its absolutely, most
basic form, goes like this.
And it's the most basic form, actually,
of, well, I guess, statistics.
It's this, what you have, is you have two
hypotheses,
that you have a variable that was
generated either from one distribution.
This is finite value, it's got n possible
values.
It's either generated from one
distribution or
another, period, that's it.
So, that it can't get anymore basic than
this.
I guess you could have like, two, [LAUGH]
something here, but okay.
So you have two distributions, and you see
a sample, and
what you want to say is you want to say
something intelligent, about whether or
not, which distribution it came from.
That, that's it, that's the most basic
one.
Okay, you know some things would be
obvious here, right?
That if one distribution you know, looked
like this, you know 0.9, you know 0.100.
Or something like that and
the other looked like, you know, 0.05, you
know 0.05.
You know, 0.8 and 0.1, then, you know,
it's, I mean, you could guess, right,
that if the, if, if in fact what you
observed was, say, this one.
Then you can say with absolute and
total certainty that it was this
distribution that generated it, right?
If it turned out to be, If your
observation was one, capital X equals one,
you could say with very good confidence.
That in fact it was generated by the first
distribution.
Everybody see this?
Right?
So, and
in fact the whole idea here is as the two
distributions get closer together,
this gets harder to do Okay, and so now
we're just going to look at what's a,
what's a, what is a good and, principled
way, to make this choice, okay?
So we're going to look at randomized
detectors.
so, a randomized detector, that's a
matrix,
it's going to look like this, it's two by
n.
These are the outcomes, here, over here,
so
we write the outcomes here, and then this
is something like one and two.
And what it is is that each column is
going to be,
is going to tell you what you should do,
when the outcome, is if it's column four,
if the outcome is capital X equals four,
right?
So if you look over here, you might have
0.9 and point 0.1 that's pretty weird.
Because what it says is something like
this its says when capital x
equals four you should say actually its
going to be a randomized detector.
So you are going to say with probability
0.9,
you are going to say that it was generated
from distribution one.
And in probability 0.1, you are going to
say is generated from distribution two.
So, we'll talk about why you might do this
in a minute.
Now, much more natural would be things
like this, okay?
And that says that if capital X equals
seven, you simply say, well it was,
it was outcome two.
It was distribution two that it came from,
okay?
So this is the idea.
Why you would want these aa randomize
detector, we'll talk about in a minute.
Actually, it's interesting, you can also
think of it as a relaxation, right?
Of an estimator.
Okay, oh, and if all the elements are zero
or
one, it's called a deterministic detector,
so that's the idea.
Alright, so, how do you choose that,
detector?
Well, if you simply multiply you, you take
a,
there's a detection matrix, and the
detection matrix is,
you simply multiply t by you multiply t on
the left by p and q.
And you get a two by two matrix, and
the entries, can be interpreted in, in a
very, very interesting way.
They're, basically, the probability of,
error/g, so this gives you, this is if,
if p is the true distribution, q is the
true distribution.
And then this tells you sort of the
probability of selecting,
the correct one, right?
So, these entries,
tell you something about the probabilities
here of being right, right?
Being right means capital X came from
distribution one and
you would announce that it came from
distribution one.
And you could swap one with two and that's
being right.
Being wrong, is the distribution came
from, the sample came from
distribution one, but you announce that it
was distribution two, right?
And these have names like you know, false
positive and false negative.
And you know, that means one of these
things here, anyway, so
that's the idea, right?
So, this is the, this is the idea, okay,
so
Pfp that's the probability of selecting
hypothesis two if x
is generated by distribution one and
that's a false positive.
So you're saying it's from distribution
two but
in fact it was from distribution one.
And of course what you like is you want
both of these things to be zero,
I mean you want this matrix to be I, the
identity, right?
Oh, there is another name for
this, I think some people call it a
confusion matrix, I think.
alright, so, we basically have a
multi-criterion formulation, right?
Because what you would really like, oh,
by the way, how would you make a false
positive rate zero?
That you can do.
You never want to select hypothesis two if
it was generated by, what?
Yeah, just cli, make everything negative.
Just, and then, the great news there is
that your false positive rate is as low as
it can get, zero, okay?
So that's one, and so, I mean it's a real
trade off here, right?
Alright, so if we make this a bi-criterion
problem it juts looks likes this.
It's a very simple one.
and, the natural thing to do is scalarize.
So if you scalarize, right,
this will give you the pareto curve
actually, it won't in this case.
You'll see exactly what it does get you.
Because the piece, the, the pareto curve
in this case is piece wise linear and
it gives you verteses on it.
So we'll, we'll see that in a minute.
So you minimize this, but in fact, that,
this is,
this is completely trivial to solve.
For one thing, it, the whole problem
splits across the columns of t, right?
Because the constraint's only involved to
tell you that the columns are,
have sum up to one, right?
And the objective is linear, so it's
completely separable.
So, this thing splits you can decide each
one, and
then this is completely trivial to work
out what the answer is.
And the answer is simply this, this is
very interesting.
It says here at lambda remember is
actually, and
lambda has a very beautiful
interpretation.
Lambda is our,
is remember something that translates, I
think it's the false positive.
I think it's the false positive, rate,
irritation at false positive, versus,
irritation for false negative, right.
So it's the exchange rate, between the two
things that you want small.
That's the interpretation from duality or
multi-criterion.
So, and the answer to this is really
simple.
It's this It, you, you get a deterministic
detector, and
you should choose one if P is bigger than
lambda Q.
And this is sometimes written this way,
like that, right?
And the other one is written of course
this way, and
then this is called a likelihood threshold
test, a likelihood ratio test, right?
So you simply have a threshold and so all
you do now is
you simply take one distribution and the
other one, you take the ratio.
And then, all you're doing is your setting
a threshold.
And then, for any given threshold you
choose which ever which ever one has
the higher value or something like that,
right?
Or you sort these and then, choose those,
anyway, and
as you vary lambda here the ratio.
Then what you are getting are a trade off,
you are trading off false positives, false
positive and false negative, okay?
So, now another one you could do is
minimax detector, that's very interesting.
So minimax detector says no, no, I care
about false positive and false negative
equally, please minimize, in fact this
says please minimize probability of error.
But, I want to minimize probability of
error.
Then you get this thing, and actually
that's a real l,
that's an honest lp, and the solution is
generally not deterministic, right?
It's generally something where the
detector has entries that are not zero,
one, one, zero, okay?
So, let's look at an example, you know,
obviously you don't need all this heavy
stuff for this kind of thing, right?
So here's an example, here's, so, here's
two distributions I guess that's p and
that's q.
And you know some things are obvious,
right?
If the outcome is one,
it looks rather, looks like a pretty good
bet that distribution p generated it.
If the outcome is three, it looks like a
[COUGH] quite good bet, rather good bet
that distribution, the second distribution
q, generated the data, right?
Just, just, just lookin' at it.
And let's see.
Now, if the outcome is two or four, it's
maybe less obvious, right?
As to which one generated it, right?
So here is the trade off curve um,
[COUGH], so
this trade off curve it's piece wise
linear, and
this is showing you these various this, so
this,this is the actual trade off curve.
These actually are the points you get from
the likelihood ratio test,
right these well I guess you get these two
because those the two
we've talked about before Which is how,
how can you get zero false positive or
something like that, so you get something
like this, so you see the idea.
Oh, by the way, this picture, when invert,
I think if you turn it,
you just flip it top to bottom.
It, it's got a name called ROC, which is
receiver operating characteristic.
But the minimax one, that's four, right?
This line here is line of equal error.
A false, false positive and false negative
and its right here, right?
So that's the, that's the idea so, so
its a bit strange, by the way this is one
of those cases were.
Well as a, as a big picture we, we will
and we have talked about these and
we will talk about it more were you
want to solve a problem.
And you end up doing something like a
relaxation, right?
So, if someone comes up to you and says,
fine, these are the two distributions.
I want you to estimate, repeated, what's
going to happen,
repeatedly is you're going to see samples,
outcomes.
And I want you to guess which distribution
it came from and
I want you to absolutely minimize being
wrong, right?
Simple, you have to use the minimax
detector.
What's weird about it is you're not
consistent, right?
Because you'd say things like x equals
three.
And you go, yeah, that came for outcome
one, yeah, and
then, later they say x equals three.
You go, mm-hm, sorry, that came from
distribution Q,
sorry first it came from distribution P
then Q.
So, you're not consistent, it's a, it is a
It's a non-deterministic detector, right?
But, that is the, that is actually the
only way that you can actually minimize
the probability of being wrong.
So, okay, so,
that's that, by the way, it's not very
interesting with two distributions, right?
This actually is already very interesting,
when I have let's say ten distributions,
they're bigger, and things like that, it's
already way interesting.
And I should add something there you can,
you can actually get really interesting
problems.
If I show you 10 distributions on lets say
a 1000 outcomes or 10,000 outcomes it, its
actually there your confusion matrix or I
think we called it the detector matrix.
What do we call it, fine, the detection
probability matrix of
the confusion matrix, it's got a lot of
entries in it, right?
Like for example it's got 100, okay?
And you think of all sorts of interesting
convex problems you could do.
You could say things like, you say, you
know what?
I, I absolutely do not, the probability
that you think, that you say, that you
estimate it came from distribution seven
when it really came from distribution six.
That absolutely can't exceed 10%, okay?
Everyone understood what we just said?
That's just simply a linear inequality on
one entry in that matrix.
You see what I'm saying, right?
And you can go on and add all sorts of
penal convex constraints and
things like that.
You'd say, the probability of being wrong
when the distribution come,
is actually generated from distribution
three.
I want the probability of being wrong, to
be no more than 10%.
What would that be, what I just said?
What kind of constraint on d would that
be?
That's it, that's, nothing more, right?
Yeah, either the, either the diagonal
element Is bigger than 0.9,
that's just fine.
Or, actually, the sum of the off-diagonals
is less than the number, but
that's the same because they all add up
to, yeah.
Okay, everybody, everybody got this?
So, by the way, a lot of these problems
are not, I don't think,
taught in standard statistics-type things
or machine learning.
I mean, I think there is, they have a loss
function for all of these things and
so on.
But you can now do interesting things,
just because you know about linear
programming, for example.
Okay, we're going to go to our last sample
here of topics.
It's actually very interesting ones.
It's experiment design, right?
So, and I, it's in a very specific
setting,
it's in a setting where you get a simple
problem.
But, it's, actually, quite interesting,
it's very good to know about, and
it's extremely useful, so it's this.
We're going to have m linear measurements,
so
I have a bunch of measurements yi is ai
transpose x plus wi.
And what we're going to do is,
we're going to normalize things to have
all these noises N, 01, right?
So, I, so, for example, if the noise
actually had a smaller variance, or
something like that, I would scale it up,
and that would actually just, make,
I'd scale a and y would scale and all that
kind of stuff, right?
So that's the idea, so
all the noises are normalized to have
variance one, standard deviation one.
Okay, and so, if you want to, I mean, we
can talk about various things here, x is,
x is a parameter we want to estimate, y is
a measurement.
And you should interpret the size of a now
as something like a signal to
noise ratio, right?
Because if a is big, if a3 is big, that
means, that's a,
that's a clean sensor measurement.
If a3 is small, that's a crappy sensor
measurement.
[SOUND].
Everybody got this?
Right?
So, because the bigger a3 is,
the bigger this chunk is compared to the
noise which is on the order of one, okay?
So norm of a being big is,
is good, that's, something like a signal
to noise ratio.
Okay, now,
if I estimate this, well the least squares
estimate, is just that, right?
It's just, whatever it is.
A transpose A inverse A transponse B, and
that's this, and we write it this way.
And what you see here Is it's a sum, of
the outer products of the ai's, and
then inverse times, the, this sum, okay?
So that, that's simple enough.
Okay, now, the error, that's x hat minus
x, is zero mean, and
has a co-variance matrix, which is
actually just this thing here.
So that, that's the co-variance matrix,
okay?
And, and notice that this kind of makes
sense, right?
Because look at this, if, that's, now
that's a co-variance matrix, so
it's, it's a positive semi-definite
matrix.
what's, int, actually a positive definite
matrix,
what's interesting about it is this, if ai
is bigger, this thing gets smaller.
I mean if they're all bigger, right?
Because we'll just look at it.
This, this matrix is monotone, in the
matrix sense, in ai.
I mean, that sounds weird, but you know
what I mean.
It means that, if, if you were to double
a,
you know, a seven that dyad, contribution
would be bigger in the matrix sense.
This matrix would be bigger, and then you
take the inverse, that would switch it,
it'd be smaller, so you do, you'd get
better estimation.
Okay, so, it all makes sense.
Okay, and so, for
example, if you wanted to get a confidence
ellipsoid that would be related this way.
It would be [COUGH] something like this,
you'd have x hat,
that's your, that's your estimate from
here.
And you'd select beta de, de, depending on
the confidence level you want,
you know, depending on some chi-squared
distribution or something like that.
That would give you the confidence level.
And, so, experiment design, says, the
following, so
all of this is basic, experiment design is
the following problem.
you, can choose from a palate of
measurements that are possible.
In other words, you have something like p,
possible measurements, here.
They're going to be denoted v1 through vp.
And you are allowed, to choose, like from,
for each m you choose one of those, right?
So for example you might say something
like this.
I want all my measurements to be v1,
that's why.
Why?
Because it's the best sensor, okay,
something like that.
Or you might say I want to do this, I
want to, I want,
I want to start with v1 and then v2.
Then I'll do a v7, then I'll come back
with another v1, then a v,
everybody following this?
So this is what you have to choose, okay?
Now some things are kind of obvious here.
For example, this is a sum of dyads,
right, so
it actually doesn't matter what order you
do them in right?
And, in fact, the only thing you really
have to, say here,
to specify an experiment design is to say,
I want to do 22 of experiment one.
12 of experiment two, zero of experiment
three, and so
on, and those integers have to add up to
m.
Which is the total number of experiments
you're going to do.
Everybody got that?
So, and, you can imagine also it's a
variations to where you add cost for
the experiments, and time or money or
something like that.
You can imagine all sorts of things, but
we're going to stick with the simple one
at first.
Okay, so we end up with a problem that
looks like this, and, and
this'll, this looks like a good time for
me to say something.
It's a general thing, that we can talk
about, and it's fun, okay.
So, you end up with a problem that looks,
looks like this.
Choose a bunch of integers, m1 through mp,
they add up to m.
In fact, what you're really doing is
you're allocating a set of m
experiments across, p possible
experiments.
So you're just, that's, it's an allocation
problem, but
notice it's an integer allocation problem,
okay?
And you want to do that, to minimize, this
covariance matrix.
Now, of course, that's a vector
optimization problem, right?
Because it doesn't,
it makes absolutely no sense to stay
minimize a covariance matrix, right?
So, it's pretty optimal and many ways to
do that.
You could scalarize, you could do all
sorts of things, right?
There's many ways to talk about a,
minimizing a covariance matrix, right?
So, or if you like, this has been geomet,
if you like thinking geometrically, buy me
the smallest confidence ellipsoid, right?
By the way, there is no such thing, so you
want to say something like this.
Find me a small confidence ellipsoid, and
let's translate it to mean find the[
pareto optimal one.
So pareto optimal, in that sense means,
find me a confidence,
a choice of these m's, so the, the
confidence ellipsoid you get.
There's no smaller confidence ellipsoid,
that you can get all,
by another allocation of experiments,
right?
That's what that means.
Okay, so, but
we all know that because that's what
multi-criterion optimization is.
Okay, now the variables are a bunch of
integers, that should be lighting up,
a big warning sign.
So the amber light, in your convex
optimization conceptual,
center should be blinking when you hear
integers.
And in fact, this problem is difficult in
general, right?
I mean that's the, right thing to say
whenever you see integers.
Actually, in some cases it's false, of
course there are plenty of
integer problems which, actually, are
solvable, but In, in general they're not.
Okay, so instead, what we're going to do
is relaxed experiment design.
So relaxed experiment design says this,
hm, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
rewrite it this way.
I'm going to work with the fractions of
the experiments of each type I do, and so
I'm going to get,
I'm going to work with a lambda, and, I'll
have one transposed lambda as zero.
And, if I added one more constraint, if I
added simply this, m lambda is in z.
Then, this problem would be identical to
that problem, right?
This says that the Lambdas are integer
multiples of one over m.
So if I added this constraint, this is
identical to that one, and
now, you want to see what, want to see how
convex relaxation is done?
Everybody know this now, you know what
convex relaxation is, right?
Watch very carefully, convex relaxation is
this.
You write down an optimization problem.
There are a few constraints that you don't
know how to handle, comment them out.
That's what it is, okay?
What are some common scalarizations,
you can minimize the log of the
determinate that's a convex.
Well sorry concave, increasing function
and
therefore will produce a pareto optimal
point.
You can take the traits the maximum
eigenvalue, all sorts of crazy stuff.
You know, you can add all sorts of
constraints now to it [COUGH], sorry.
for, for this thing, okay, so, and these
have names, right?
So, [COUGH] when you minimize the log
determinant of the inverse,
it's beautiful interpretation.
That's exactly, you are minimizing the
volume of the confidence ellipsoid, right?
And you end up with this problem that is
convex, right?
So you solve that.
And then, you know, depending on what, if
you were successful in convincing someone
that was more sophisticated to solve the
relaxed problem, you're done.
If you haven't then you round, and
you hold up the optimal value, of the
relaxed problem, as a lower map.
Okay, let's take a look at that.
I'm not going to go into the details here,
I'm not going to argue everything over the
dual but it's actually quite interesting.
So the dual problem of this can be
messaged, I should say a dual problem.
And that means that you have to allow me
to do a few little manipulations before,
and a few after but you get it into a real
form that looks like this.
Maximizes log det W, plus a constant that
is totally irrelevant.
Subject to [COUGH], vk transpose W vk less
than or
equal to one and this has a beautiful
interpretation geometrically.
It turns out this says, find me the
minimum volume ellipsoid centered at
the origin, that includes all the test
vectors.
Um, [COUGH], and it turns out, that, the
Lagrange multipliers on these constraints
are precisely the fractions the optimal
fractions that you should use, right?
So, this is beautiful, so you get this
connection between, an experiment design
problem and a geometric problem, which is
going to be our next topic, right?
And so the picture is something like this.
well, this is the picture, right?
The picture is this.
We have 20 test vectors.
That's the origin and here's a bunch of
things, tests you can do,
potential tests and here's a bunch, okay?
And I'm going to, before you even look at
what the optimal design is,
I'm going to ask you some questions about
it.
Okay, so let me ask you.
Please explain, intuitively, why you would
never choose that experiment?
Well let's suppose that experiment's
number 11,
why would you not choose experiment 11?
[COUGH] You can say.
And don't say anything about convex
optimization or log [UNKNOWN] or
anything else.
Just, you tell me why would you not choose
that experiment.
Well what, what is this experiment here?
It's basically, it gives the, it,
it's the negative of that experiment, but
it's about twice as big.
So in other words,
it's a completely equivalent measurement
with one half the noise.
Twice the signal to noise ratio, right?
So, if I give you a set of, a palette, of
20 experiments you can carry out, one is
basically a copy of another, but twice as
bad, then why would you ever use it?
You would not, okay?
So, I'm just, I'm just saying, all of this
is kind of intuitive, right?
You want to use experiments that are
spread apart.
Now, roughly speaking, you don't choose
any of these.
Because these, well not quite because they
don't go up here, but
these measurements here are kind of like
those.
I mean there's got some minus signs but
who cares.
It actually goes away immediately when you
form that dyad.
The vk, vk transpose goes away instantly.
So what happens is, you're, you're not
going to choose, any of these,
because these sort of stand in for them
and have higher signal-noise ratio.
And sure enough, look what it does,
it picks the two [COUGH] which have kind
of highest angle.
The two measurements which are most
independent, if you want to say that, or
something like that, have the highest
angle.
And it concentrates at 50 50 on them,
okay?
So, by the way, stupid thing in R too, you
don't need this, right?
But, if you're making, if you're
estimating 10 or
100 parameters, these things are not
obvious at all, right?
Not at all, right?
You have a thousand possible experiments
to do, and so on.